<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6137984</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ery266</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ery266</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Plant&#x02014;Environment Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Conserved and differential transcriptional responses of peroxisome associated pathways to drought, dehydration and ABA</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ebeed</surname><given-names>Heba T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>hebeed@du.edu.eg</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>Sean R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn-0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cuming</surname><given-names>Andrew C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>Alison</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>a.baker@leeds.ac.uk</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Botany and Microbiology Department, Faculty of Science, Damietta University, Damietta, Egypt</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Centre for Plant Sciences, University of Leeds, Leeds, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence: <email>hebeed@du.edu.eg</email>; <email>a.baker@leeds.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="fn-0001"><p>Present address: Department of Plant Sciences, University of Cambridge, Downing Street, Cambridge CB2 3EA.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-07-19"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>69</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>4971</fpage><lpage>4985</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ery266.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Peroxisome biogenesis, peroxisome &#x003b2;-oxidation and antioxidant enzymes show conserved upregulation in response to ABA and water deficit-inducing treatments, highlighting an overlooked role for peroxisomes in response to drought.</p></abstract><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Plant peroxisomes are important components of cellular antioxidant networks, dealing with ROS generated by multiple metabolic pathways. Peroxisomes respond to environmental and cellular conditions by changing their size, number, and proteomic content. To investigate the role of peroxisomes in response to drought, dehydration and ABA treatment we took an evolutionary and comparative genomics approach. Colonisation of land required evolution of dehydration tolerance in the absence of subsequent anatomical adaptations. Therefore, the model bryophyte <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic>, the model dicot <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and wheat (<italic>Tricitcum aestivum</italic>), a globally important cereal crop were compared. Three sets of genes namely &#x02018;<italic>PTS1</italic> genes&#x02019; (a proxy for genes encoding peroxisome targeted proteins), <italic>PEX</italic> genes (involved in peroxisome biogenesis) and genes involved in plant antioxidant networks were identified in all 3 species and their expression compared under drought (dehydration) and ABA treatment. Genes encoding enzymes of &#x003b2;-oxidation and gluconeogenesis, antioxidant enzymes including catalase and glutathione reductase and <italic>PEX3</italic> and <italic>PEX11</italic> isoforms showed conserved up-regulation, and peroxisome proliferation was induced by ABA in moss. Interestingly, expression of some of these genes differed between drought sensitive and resistant genotypes of wheat in line with measured photosynthetic and biochemical differences. These results point to an underappreciated role for peroxisomes in drought response.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>ABA</kwd><kwd>antioxidant</kwd><kwd>bioinformatics</kwd><kwd>drought</kwd><kwd>moss</kwd><kwd>peroxisome</kwd><kwd>PEX</kwd><kwd><italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic></kwd><kwd>wheat</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Water deficiency is a severe constraint on crop production world-wide (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Boyer, 1982</xref>). For example drought regularly limits wheat production in almost 50% of the cropped area. This issue is of increasing concern and is amplified by climate change, population growth and urbanization, impacting on water availability for agriculture and therefore global food security (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Godfray <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Consequently new insights into the molecular mechanisms of response to drought is an important but challenging goal for improvement of drought tolerant plant varieties (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Claeys and Inz&#x000e9;, 2013</xref>)</p><p>Abscisic Acid (ABA) is a major player in coordinating the adaptation of plants to adverse conditions as well as functioning in many plant developmental processes (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Leung and Giraudat, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Fujita <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">Stevenson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). ABA mediates physiological processes such as stomatal closure, osmolyte accumulation, and the synthesis of stress-related proteins, as well as compounds associated with the scavenging of reactive oxygen species that are implicated in desiccation related membrane damage (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Ingram and Bartels, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Hoekstra <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). ABA is required for the induction of genes as a response to dehydration stress (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Nakashima <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Moreover, exogenous application of ABA induces a number of genes that respond to dehydration and cold stress (<xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr">Zhu, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">Shinozaki <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Cuming <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) However, not all genes that are induced by dehydration and cold stress respond to the exogenous application of ABA (<xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr">Zhu, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0073" ref-type="bibr">Yamaguchi-Shinozaki and Shinozaki, 2006</xref>). This suggests the existence of ABA-independent and ABA-dependent signal transduction pathways that convert the initial stress signal into cellular responses (<xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr">Zhu, 2002</xref>).</p><p>The recruitment of ABA to regulate responses to water stress emerged with the evolution of land plants, which are monophyletic in origin, descending from a single successful colonisation of terrestrial habitats by a charophyte algal ancestor <italic>ca</italic>. 470Ma (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Delwiche and Cooper, 2015</xref>). The conquest of land necessarily required adaptations enabling these ancestral plants to survive the highly variable conditions characteristic of the terrestrial habitats, most notably exposure to ultraviolet radiation, salinity, dehydration and temperature variation. Lacking the anatomic adaptations characteristic of extant tracheophytes, survival of the earliest colonisers must have been cellular and biochemical in nature. A common cellular consequence of these environmental stresses is the formation of reactive oxygen species (ROS). Consequently, possession of antioxidant mechanisms must have ranked highly in the suite of adaptations that supported the transition from aquatic to terrestrial habitats, enabling both ROS signaling and defence against ROS toxicity. Such adaptations remain important today, being widespread and highly conserved in nature among all classes of land plant and central to many environmental stress responses (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Mittler <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Noctor <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).</p><p>Peroxisomes are both major sources of ROS and sites of important anti-oxidant defences (<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Noctor <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). They contain antioxidant molecules such as ascorbate and glutathione, and some antioxidant enzymes, including ascorbate peroxidase, dehydro- and monodehydroascorbate reductase, glutathione reductase and catalase. Changes in activities of these enzymes are regulated by various stress conditions (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">del Rio <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>). Accordingly, peroxisomes have been suggested to play important roles in defence against abiotic and biotic stress in plants (<xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">Willekens <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">del Rio <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>). They are involved in lipid mobilization through &#x003b2;-oxidation and the glyoxylate cycle, photorespiration, nitrogen metabolism, synthesis and metabolism of plant hormones (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Hu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Peroxisomes import membrane and soluble proteins from the cytosol to maintain and modulate their functions (review (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Cross <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).The biogenesis of peroxisomes requires a group of protein factors referred to as peroxins encoded by <italic>PEX</italic> genes (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Distel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>). Two types of targeting signals have been identified for peroxisomal matrix enzymes: PTS1, a C-terminal tripeptide and PTS2, an N-terminal nonapeptide (<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Reumann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Peroxisome membrane proteins are inserted post translationally by the action of chaperone/receptor PEX19 and its docking factor PEX3. Some membrane proteins may also be targeted to peroxisomes via the ER in a process that also requires PEX3 (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Cross <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p><p>Peroxisomes are remarkably dynamic, responding to environmental and cellular cues by alterations in size, number, and proteomic content. As well as importing proteins from the cytosol, peroxisomes proliferate by division in a process dependent upon the PEX11 family (<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Orth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Kamisugi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Plant peroxisome proliferation has been reported in response to hydrogen peroxide, pathogens or ozone (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Morr&#x000e9; <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Lopez-Huertas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Oksanen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), and during senescence (<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Pastori and Del Rio, 1997</xref>).</p><p>To investigate the evolving roles of peroxisomes in perception and response to abiotic stress we focused on drought and its consequences: dehydration stress, ABA production and ROS metabolism. We have taken a genome wide cross species approach, utilising information gained from a modern angiosperm and from a bryophyte&#x02014;the most ancient group of land plants&#x02014;to compare transcriptional responses of PTS1 targeted peroxisome proteins, antioxidants and <italic>PEX</italic> genes. We benefit from the plethora of genomic resources available for the well characterised angiosperm and bryophyte models, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> and extend these studies to the globally preeminent crop species, wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>), for which comparable resources are only now being developed (<xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">Uauy, 2017</xref>). Due to its large hexaploid genome wheat is a much more challenging species to study than haploid <italic>Physcomitrella</italic> and diploid <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, therefore we used the rich data and extensive information from these two model species to demonstrate that genes encoding peroxisome targeted proteins are disproportionally upregulated and that upregulation of peroxisomal &#x003b2;-oxidation is a conserved response to drought, dehydration and ABA. Additionally peroxisome biogenesis appears to be upregulated with increased expression of isoforms of <italic>PEX3</italic> and <italic>PEX11</italic> seen in both moss and wheat with clear differences between drought sensitive and drought tolerant cultivars. Interestingly increased expression of glyoxylate cycle enzymes ICL and MS is seen in moss and wheat but not in Arabidopsis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Compiling Arabidopsis peroxisomal genes and identification of homologs in moss and wheat</title><p>Arabidopsis proteins predicted to be targeted to peroxisomes were retrieved from AraPerox 1.2 (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Reumann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). The antioxidant genes, their description and localization information were compiled manually from The Arabidopsis Information Resource (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org">www.arabidopsis.org</ext-link>). Those Arabidopsis antioxidant enzymes annotated as peroxisomal were used to identify non-peroxisomal isoenzymes and some additional known non-peroxisomal components of the anti-oxidant network from Arabidopsis were also added. This resulted in a list of 51 Arabidopsis proteins, representing 10 families.</p><p>To identify homologs for genes encoding PTS1-containing proteins, <italic>PEX</italic> proteins, and antioxidant enzymes (&#x02018;<italic>PTS1</italic>, <italic>PEX</italic> and <italic>Antox</italic>&#x02019; genes respectively) in <italic>P. patens</italic> and wheat, the whole protein sequence content of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> was obtained from TAIR and Arabidopsis proteins were used to search the <italic>Physcomitrella</italic> and wheat genomes at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/">http://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/</ext-link> (E-value&#x0003c;1e-10 and &#x0003c;1e-5, respectively) by TBLASTN to identify homologs. Then, all the sequences of unique hits in wheat or moss were used for reciprocal BLASTP search of the Arabidopsis proteome. Due to the large hexaploid wheat genome, wheat homologs for PTS1-containing proteins and antioxidant enzymes were obtained by separate queries using BioMart (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gramene.org/">http://www.gramene.org/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Gupta <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), and the TAIR Arabidopsis dataset. Data were filtered to obtain corresponding homologs in <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>, then gene stable IDs were converted to corresponding Ensembl gene ID manually by TBlastN analysis of protein sequences against the wheat genome at Phytozome (<italic>E</italic>-value&#x0003c;1e-5) to identify the best blast match for each locus. PredPlantPTS1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ppp.gobics.de/">http://ppp.gobics.de/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Reumann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) was used for the prediction of PTS1 signals in moss and wheat homologs of genes of putative PTS1 proteins. All candidate homologs were verified with the help of CDD and Expasy databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.expasy.org/">https://www.expasy.org/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Gasteiger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>) to confirm the presence of expected conserved domains. All the moss and wheat proteins identified from BLAST searches were accepted only if they contained the corresponding Arabidopsis domains; then multiple sequence alignments were used to confirm the conserved domains of identified sequences. Retrieved sequences in wheat were corrected when a portion of protein was missing due to incorrect gene model prediction. Sequences showing large truncations and that could not be completed by further BLAST searches were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Peroxisomal gene expression in moss under ABA, dehydration and mannitol</title><p>The gene expression profiles of the <italic>Physcomitrella</italic> peroxisomal (<italic>PTS1</italic>, <italic>PEX</italic>) and <italic>Antox</italic> genes responding to ABA, osmotic- and dehydration- stress were obtained using the RNA-seq data deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus database under accession number GSE72583 and then to the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (accession number SRP063055; BioProject PRJNA294412) (<xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">Stevenson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). To assess statistical significance, hypergeometric probabilities were evaluated for the number of genes in the data set of interest (eg. <italic>PTS</italic>1, <italic>PEX</italic> or <italic>Antox</italic>) up-regulated &#x02265;2-fold change (FC) by the experimental treatment compared to the total number of genes up-regulated &#x02265;2 FC in the entire gene set for that treatment. The heatmaps were drawn using the Morpheus software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clue.io/morpheus/">https://clue.io/morpheus/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Minguet <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Peroxisomal gene expression in Arabidopsis in response to ABA treatment</title><p>Arabidopsis RNAseq expression data were downloaded from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) (GEO accession number: GSE65739 and SRA accession number: SRP053346) and 4 samples, two biological replicates of 10-day-old Arabidopsis seedlings mock treated (GSM1603932 GSM1603936) or treated with 50 &#x003bc;M ABA, (GSM1603933, , GSM1603937) (<xref rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr">Weng <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) were selected to study expression of our candidate genes. Processed data files were downloaded.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Peroxisomal gene expression in <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> under drought stress</title><p>Wheat transcriptome profiling and gene expression data were retrieved from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) (GEO accession number: GSE30436) (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Kadam <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Twelve samples were selected to study expression of candidate genes in two bulked populations of wheat recombinant inbred lines which differed in their susceptibility to drought &#x02018;drought sensitive Bulk&#x02019; and &#x02018;drought tolerant Bulk&#x02019;. The sample accession numbers are as follows: GSM754878, GSM754879, GSM754880, GSM754884, GSM754885, GSM754886, GSM754890, GSM754891, GSM754892, GSM754896, GSM754897, GSM754898, three samples were used as a biological replicate for each treatment. CEL files were downloaded and processed data values for the selected samples were used to calculate FC in tolerant and sensitive genotypes. Probesets corresponding to <italic>PTS1, PEX</italic> and <italic>Antox</italic> genes were searched using an online PLEXdb Blast tool available at Affymetrix (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.affymetrix.com/">http://www.affymetrix.com/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title><p>The Egyptian wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) variety, Giza 168 was obtained from the Agricultural Research Centre; ARC, Giza, Egypt. The British variety Oakley was obtained from KWS, UK, Ltd. To test osmotic tolerance, seeds were exposed to 20% (w/v) PEG-6000 as an osmotic-stress inducing medium. Thirty seeds were germinated on filter paper in petri dishes wetted with 7 ml of distilled water or 20% PEG solution using three replicates for each variety and treatment, then the number of germinated seeds was counted to calculate germination percentage (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Germination was scored when radicles reached 5mm in length.</p><p>To analyse ABA responses of wheat plants seeds were germinated in pots containing compost in a growth chamber at 20 &#x000b0;C, 16 h photoperiod, 60% RH and watered twice per week. ABA (100 &#x000b5;M) was applied as foliar sprays at 9 days after sowing (DAS). Gas exchange parameters were determined for control and ABA-treated plants 24 h following ABA application using a commercial, open-flow gas exchange measurement system (LI-6400P, LI-COR Inc., Lincoln, NE). Biochemical methods were used for measuring osmolyte concentrations one week after ABA treatment as follows: soluble sugars were extracted according to (<xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Schortemeyer <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>) and determined according to (<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">Schl&#x000fc;ter and Crawford, 2001</xref>), proline was determined according to (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Bates <italic>et al.</italic>, 1973</xref>), glycine-betaine was determined according to (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Grieve and Grattan, 1983</xref>) and amino acids concentrations were determined according to (<xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">Sircelj <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p><p>For moss, WT protonemal tissue was sub-cultured at weekly intervals on cellophane overlays on solid BCD medium containing 5mM diammonium tartrate and trace elements (BCDAT) (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Knight <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). ABA-treated (BCDAT supplemented with 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> M ABA, 1 h). Tissue was harvested and squeezed dry before freezing in liquid nitrogen and storage at &#x02013;70 &#x000b0;C before RNA isolation. Protonemal tissue from a line expressing a peroxisomal targeted mRFP (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Kamisugi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) was sub-cultured on cellophane overlays on solid BCD medium containing 1mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> 5 mM diammonium tartrate. Seven days old protonemal tissue on the cellophane discs was transferred to petri dishes containing BCDAT with or without 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> M ABA for 6 h before counting peroxisomes by fluorescence microcopy. The number of peroxisomes per cell was determined for at least 23 randomly selected cells. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed to identify significant differences between the treatments with a level of significance of a <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05. For determining the significant effects between the treatments, comparison was made using the least significant difference (LSD) test with a <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>RNA extraction and qPCR</title><p>About 0.1g wheat leaf tissue was harvested 24h after ABA treatment and homogenized with liquid nitrogen and total RNA was extracted using an RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen) and treated with RNase-Free DNase (Qiagen) following the instruction protocol. For moss samples, RNA was extracted according to (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Knight <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). For rt-PCR, RNA (10 &#x000b5;g) was digested with 1 unit of RQ1 DNase (Promega) for 10 min at room temperature and purified by phenol-chloroform extraction and ethanol precipitation. RNA for all samples was quantified by nanodrop spectrophotometry then the purity and integrity of total RNA was assessed by Agilent BioAnalyzer. Complementary DNA was synthesized from 1 &#x000b5;g of RNA using the BioRad iscript select cDNA synthesis kit. The reaction mixture was diluted 30-fold with water, and 2 &#x000b5;l aliquots were used for PCR amplification. Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) was performed with the diluted cDNA samples in a 20 &#x003bc;l reaction mixture containing 10 &#x000b5;l BioRad iQ SYBR 2X mix and 300 nM PCR primers. PCR was performed using a BioRad Cfx Manager as follows: denaturation for 2 m at 95 &#x000b0;C, followed by 40 cycles of 10 s at 95 &#x000b0;C, and 30 s at 60 &#x000b0;C. The PCR amplification efficiency was determined for each primer combination automatically calculated by the BioRad CFX Manager software using the input information of standard concentrations and dilutions used into the program. The standard curve was 5 serial dilutions of a mixture of all sample cDNAs. The PCR efficiencies ranged from 87 to 110%. Three biological replicates and three technical replicates were used for each treatment. No signals were detected in any reaction without template that had been used as a negative control (NTC). The relative transcript levels were calculated using the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x02206;&#x02206;Ct</sup> method, with the wheat glyceraldehyde3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) and moss Clathrin Coat Assembly Protein AP50 (CAP50: Pp3c27_2250V3.1) genes as internal controls. Primer pairs are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Results</title><sec id="s10"><title>Identification of peroxisome associated genes in wheat and moss</title><p>Three sets of genes associated with peroxisome biogenesis and function were identified in wheat and moss using the corresponding Arabidopsis proteins as queries. These 3 gene sets coded for i) proteins carrying a predicted peroxisome targeting signal type 1 (PTS1) sequence at the C-terminus (&#x02018;genes of putative PTS1 proteins&#x02019;) ii) enzymes involved in the cellular antioxidant network that had been described as peroxisomal, their non-peroxisomal homologs and some additional non-peroxisomal antioxidant enzymes (&#x02018;<italic>Antox</italic> proteins&#x02019;) and iii) <italic>PEX</italic> genes involved in peroxisome biogenesis. <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarises the number of genes in these gene sets in Arabidopsis and their corresponding homologs in moss and wheat. In total 340 genes of putative PTS1 proteins from Arabidopsis, identified 1052 homologs in wheat and 282 homologs in moss. Some of these homologs were present in multiple copies and only 185 gene products were predicted to contain PTS1 in wheat and 108 in moss <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Tables S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">S3</xref> show the identified genes of putative PTS1 proteins in moss and wheat respectively.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Numbers of genes studied in Arabidopsis included in this study and the numbers of their corresponding homologs in moss and wheat</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arabidopsis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moss</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>PTS1</italic></bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">337 predicted as PTS1<break/>3 non-canonical PTS1 (Catalase)<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185* (of 65 <italic>A. thaliana PTS1</italic> genes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (of 63 <italic>A. thaliana PTS1</italic> genes)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number of homologs identified</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1052 (of 85 <italic>A. thaliana PTS1</italic> genes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282 (of 146 <italic>A. thaliana PTS1</italic> genes)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Number of homologs predicted to contain PTS1</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">228 (of 64 <italic>A. thaliana PTS1</italic> genes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (of 60 <italic>A. thaliana PTS1</italic> genes)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 paralogs for 1 catalase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 paralogs for 3 catalase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Antioxidant enzymes</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (of 27 <italic>A. thaliana</italic> genes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (of 26 <italic>A. thaliana</italic> genes)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PEX</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-1001"><p>*For 46 PTS1 proteins of Arabidopsis the corresponding homologs in wheat could not identified due to major differences in protein sequences in Gramene and phytozome databases as described in the Methods.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0002"><p>
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>Catalase (<italic>CAT</italic>) genes are included in the antioxidant genes set but they also possess a non-canonical PTS1 which although functional deviates from the PTS1 consensus</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The 51 &#x02018;Antox&#x02019; genes from Arabidopsis identified 94 homologs in wheat and 49 in moss (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). For the Arabidopsis proteins the known/predicted location according to SUBA (the subcellular localization database of Arabidopsis proteins (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Hooper <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>) and for the identified moss and wheat homologues the favoured subcellular location predicted using Plant-mPloc (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Chou and Shen, 2010</xref>) is given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Tables S4 and S5</xref> respectively. The <italic>PEX</italic> gene complement of wheat and moss has been described (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Cross <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Antioxidant homologous gene numbers in Arabidopsis, moss and wheat</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>A. thaliana</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P. patens</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>T. aestivum</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalase (<italic>CAT</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascorbate Peroxidase (<italic>APX</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monodehydroascorbate reductase (<italic>MDAR</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione reductase (<italic>GR</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isocitrate dehydrogenase (<italic>ICDH</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-Phosphogluconolactonase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione peroxidase (<italic>GPX</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-ascorbate oxidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dehydroascorbate reductase (<italic>DHAR</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total counts</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Expression of peroxisome related genes in moss in response to ABA, osmotic stress and dehydration</title><p>In order to investigate the response of peroxisome related pathways under ABA and drought stress conditions in moss we analyzed the changes in expression of the putative <italic>PTS1</italic>, <italic>Antox</italic> and <italic>PEX</italic> genes listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Tables S2 and S4</xref> and (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Cross <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) in the <italic>Physcomitrella</italic> RNAseq datasets. The genes upregulated by &#x0003e;2-fold change for each of these gene sets under conditions of 10 &#x000b5;M ABA treatment, osmotic stress (10% mannitol) or dehydration (70% loss of fresh-weight) are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> and gene identification numbers of each set are indicated in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S6</xref>. While there are commonalities, each stress has its own distinct signature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). The numbers of up- and down-regulated genes under the 3 conditions is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>. Using hypergeometric probability, statistically significant numbers of genes of putative PTS1 proteins were up-regulated &#x0003e;2FC in response to ABA, dehydration and mannitol compared to the total number of up-regulated genes in the whole dataset under each condition, whereas the number of up-regulated <italic>Antox</italic> genes and <italic>PEX</italic> genes were statistically significant only under osmotic stress by mannitol.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Numbers of differentially regulated genes in <italic>P. patens</italic> in response to 10 &#x000b5;M ABA, 70% dehydration and osmotic stress (10% (w/v) mannitol treatment) conditions. <bold>A:</bold> peroxisomal genes expression under control, ABA, dehydration and mannitol. Red colour indicates a higher expression level and blue colour indicates a lower expression level, white indicates unexpressed gene. Each row is normalized to control. <bold>B:</bold> Total numbers of differentially regulated <italic>PTS1</italic>, <italic>Antox</italic> and <italic>PEX</italic> genes Black bars indicate up-regulated genes, pale grey bars indicate down-regulated genes. <bold>C:</bold> Numbers of genes up-regulated &#x02265;2FC in response to ABA, osmotic stress and dehydration in wild-type protonemal tissue of <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic>. Star symbol indicates significant hypergeometric probability at <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05, two stars for <italic>P</italic> value&#x02264;2.3E-02.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery26601"/></fig><p>Nine genes of putative PTS1 proteins were upregulated under all 3 conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). These were two copper amine oxidases (Pp3c14_14330 and Pp3c17_5710), two acyl adenylate activating enzymes (<italic>AAE17</italic> and <italic>4CL1</italic>; Pp3c1_12140 and Pp3c26_11730 respectively), an <italic>AIM1</italic> homologue which is a multifunctional protein of the &#x003b2;-oxidation pathway (Pp3c1_580) and <italic>ECH1a</italic> which is an enoyl CoA hydratase also potentially associated with &#x003b2;-oxidation (Pp3c23_900). Two isoforms of isocitrate lyase (<italic>ICL</italic>; Pp3c7_2440and Pp3c7_2470), and one isoform of malate synthase (<italic>MS</italic>; Pp3c20_22510) the unique enzymes of the glyoxylate cycle which convert acetyl CoA into malate for gluconeogenesis were also upregulated. <italic>Antox</italic> genes upregulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>) were two catalase isoforms (Pp3c18_13590 and Pp3c19_6540) and isocitrate dehydrogenase (<italic>ICDH</italic>; Pp3c20_22810). It was noteworthy that this isoform is predicted to contain a PTS1 motif &#x02013;SKL. Two enzymes associated with the ascorbate-glutathione cycle; dehydroascorbate reductase (<italic>DHAR2</italic>; Pp3c15_21480), glutathione reductase (<italic>GR2</italic>; Pp3c4_17890), probably plastid isoforms, were also upregulated. Two <italic>PEX3</italic> genes (Pp3c8_16550 and Pp3c20_5170) and one <italic>PEX11</italic> gene (PEX11-6, Pp3c3_15780) were upregulated under all treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). The metabolic interrelationships of the proteins encoded by these genes is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Diagram showing metabolic relationships between selected peroxisomal proteins and enzymes upregulated by drought or ABA. Protein names are shown in black typeface and metabolites in green. 4CL1 and AAE17 activate (unknown) substrates for &#x003b2;-oxidation, which utilizes enzymes acylCoA oxidase (ACX)1 and multifunctional proteins MFP2 and/or AIM1. ECH1a is a poorly characterized member of the enoylCoA hydratase/isomerase family. ACX (and other peroxisomal enzymes) produce hydrogen peroxide that is broken down by catalase (CAT). Acetyl CoA produced can enter the glyoxylate pathway; malate synthase (MLS) and isocitrate lyase (ICL) are the unique enzymes of this pathway which produces malate that is exported as a substrate for gluconeogenesis. Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (PEPCK) is the first committed step of this pathway, leading to production of sucrose and/or compatible osmolytes. Succinate produced by the ICL reaction is exported to mitochondria for further metabolism. In Arabidopsis, citrate can be exported directly for respiration (not shown). On the right hand side of the diagram a simplified representation of the ascorbate glutathione cycle is shown. Asc; ascorbate; DHA dehydroascorbate; GSH reduced glutathione; GSSG; oxidized glutathione. DHAR dehydroascorbate reductase. GR1 glutathione reductase; ICDH NADP+ dependent isocitrate dehydrogenase. Ascorbate peroxidase (APX) and monodehydroascorbate reductase (MDAR) are membrane bound proteins that participate in removal of hydrogen peroxide and regeneration of ascorbate. PEX3 is involved in import of peroxisome membrane proteins (including the components of the import machinery for matrix proteins) and PEX11 is involved in peroxisome division.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery26602"/></fig><p>To validate the effect of ABA treatment on gene expression, rt-QPCR was carried out. Catalase was upregulated more than three orders of magnitude upon ABA treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Acyl CoA oxidase 1 (<italic>ACX1</italic>) and <italic>AIM1</italic>, markers for the &#x003b2;-oxidation pathway, were upregulated ~3-fold and &#x0003e;20-fold respectively. Malate synthase, marker for the glyoxylate cycle was upregulated &#x0003e;5-fold by ABA treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Induction of marker genes for &#x003b2;- oxidation and glyoxylate cycle by ABA treatment in <italic>P. patens</italic>. Quantitative gene expression for catalase (<italic>CAT</italic>), Pp3c19_6540; abnormal inflorescence meristem 1, fatty acid multifunctional protein (<italic>AIM1</italic>), Pp3c1_580; Malate synthase (<italic>MS</italic>), Pp3c20_22510; Acyl-CoA oxidase Pp3c14_14860. Data are expressed as fold change in expression (y-axis) relative to ABA untreated control. Three biological replicates and three technical replicates were used for each treatment. Bars represent the standard error. *Data are significant at <italic>P&#x02264;</italic>0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery26603"/></fig></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Induction of peroxisome biogenesis in <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> by ABA</title><p>
<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> shows expression of the 3 members of the <italic>PEX3</italic> gene family and 5 members of the <italic>PEX11</italic> family in response to ABA treatment. <italic>PEX3-3</italic> was the most highly induced showing ~10-fold increase in transcript level although both <italic>PEX3-1</italic> and <italic>PEX3-2</italic> showed an increase in transcript level in response to ABA. The <italic>PEX11</italic> family members showed strikingly different responses to ABA. PEX11-1 was unresponsive, <italic>PEX11-3</italic> and <italic>PEX11-4</italic> are down-regulated whilst <italic>PEX11-5</italic> and <italic>PEX11-6</italic> were upregulated ~5 and ~2.5-fold respectively, consistent with the RNA-seq data. As PEX3 and PEX11 both have roles in peroxisome proliferation/division, peroxisomes were counted in <italic>P. patens</italic> chloronemata expressing a peroxisomal targeted RFP that had been ABA-treated for 6 hours (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">B</xref>). The mean peroxisome number per cell in ABA-treated samples was 24 compared to 16 in untreated cells which was significant at the <italic>P</italic>=0.05 level (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5C</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Quantitative real time-PCR analysis of <italic>PEX3</italic> and <italic>PEX11</italic> gene families in <italic>P. patens</italic> in response to ABA. <italic>PEX3-1</italic>, Pp3c24_12050; <italic>PEX3-2</italic>, Pp3c8_16550; <italic>PEX3-3</italic>, Pp3c20_5170; <italic>PEX11-1</italic>, Pp3c19_20730V3.1; <italic>PEX11-3</italic>, Pp3c19_20730; <italic>PEX11-4</italic>, Pp3c24_12360; <italic>PEX11-5</italic>, Pp3c2_11370; <italic>PEX11-6</italic>, Pp3c3_15780. Data are expressed as fold change in expression (y-axis) relative to ABA untreated control. Three biological replicates were used and three technical replicates for each treatment. Bars represent the standard error. *Data are significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery26604"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Increased peroxisome biogenesis by ABA in <italic>P. patens</italic> chloronemata. <bold>A</bold>: control, <bold>B</bold>: ABA-treated, <bold>C</bold>: peroxisome number&#x000b1;SE, 23 cells were used to count the peroxisomes and analysis of variance (ANOVA) with a level of significance of a <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05 to identify significant differences between the treatments. For determining the significant effects between the treatments, comparison was made using the least significant difference (LSD) test with a <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery26605"/></fig></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Expression of peroxisome related genes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> in response to ABA</title><p>For comparison with the ABA responses seen in moss, RNAseq data for ABA-treated 10-day old Arabidopsis seedlings was examined. The results for <italic>PTS1</italic>, antioxidant and <italic>PEX</italic> gene sets are summarised in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Tables S7, S8</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">S9</xref> respectively). Genes which showed upregulation by all 3 treatments in moss (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S6</xref> at <italic>JXB</italic> online) and which are also upregulated &#x0003e;2FC by ABA in Arabidopsis are listed in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. These include two adenylate activating enzymes (<italic>AAE17;</italic> At5g23050 and <italic>AAE12</italic>; At1g65890) and the &#x003b2;-oxidation enzyme <italic>ACX1</italic> (At4g16760). A glutathione reductase <italic>(GR1</italic> At3g24170) and a dehydroascorbate reductase (<italic>DHAR1</italic> At1g19570) associated with the peroxisomal ascorbate-glutathione cycle also showed up-regulation of &#x0003e;2FC. However, unlike moss, glyoxylate cycle genes (<italic>ICL</italic> and <italic>MS</italic>) were not upregulated by ABA in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S7</xref> and <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).Of the <italic>PEX11</italic> family only <italic>PEX11d</italic> (At3g61070) showed up-regulation &#x0003e;2FC under ABA treatment.</p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Common up-regulated genes in moss, Arabidopsis and wheat. Moss genes up-regulated by ABA, dehydration and mannitol &#x0003e;2FC. Expression of these genes in Arabidopsis by ABA (<xref rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr">Weng et al., 2016</xref>) or in wheat by drought (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Kadam et al., 2012</xref>)</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Moss genes up-reg &#x0003e;2FC (ABA, Man &#x00026; deh)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>A. thaliana</italic> (ABA)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic>T. aestivum</italic> (drought)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tolerant</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">sensitive</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Genes of putative PTS1 proteins:</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Copper amine oxidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Acyl activating enzyme, <italic>AAE</italic></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">AAE17</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">AAE7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAE7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">AAE10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAE12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>4-Coumarate:CoA ligase, 4CL1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isocitrate lyase, <italic>ICL</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malate synthase, <italic>MS</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal inflorescence meristem 1, fatty acid multifunctional protein, <italic>AIM1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enoyl-CoA hydratase like protein a<italic>, ECHIa</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acyl-CoA oxidase 1, <italic>ACX1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Enzymes involved in the cellular antioxidant network</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalase, <italic>CAT</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione reductase, <italic>GR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isocitrate dehydrogenase, <italic>ICDH</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dehydroascorbate reductase, <italic>DHAR2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0221a;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>PEX genes</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>PEX3</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>PEX11</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>PEX11D</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>PEX11D</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>PEX11D PEX11A</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0003"><p>ND = not detected. ND means that this gene is not found in the array or seq-data.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0004"><p>&#x0221a; and X means shares up-regulation (&#x02265;2) with moss or not, respectively.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0005"><p>
<italic>AAE17</italic>, 12, 7 and 10 and <italic>PEX11D</italic> and E: are <italic>AAE</italic> and <italic>PEX</italic> family members respectively, expressed in Arabidopsis and wheat.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Expression of peroxisome related genes in <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> in drought tolerant and sensitive genotypes under drought stress</title><p>To extend the comparison of peroxisomal responses to wheat, homologs for PTS1, antioxidant enzymes and PEX proteins were identified using the corresponding Affymetrix probe ID (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Tables S10, S11</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">S12</xref> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). A microarray data set of two sets of bulked recombinant inbred lines which differed in their drought tolerance (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Kadam <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) were analysed for differences in expression of these 3 sets of genes. The values of FC calculated for treated samples compared to control samples are presented <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>. Of the upregulated genes of putative PTS1 proteins 9 are shared, 3 are unique to the tolerant and 14 unique to the sensitive genotype (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A</xref>). A total of 23 genes of putative PTS1 proteins were significantly up-regulated &#x02265;2FC in the drought sensitive genotype with hypergeometric probability of 0.01 and 8 genes were down-regulated (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6B</xref>). In the drought tolerant genotype 12 genes of putative PTS1 proteins were up-regulated and 7 were down-regulated. It was notable that <italic>ICL</italic> and <italic>MS</italic> and <italic>AAE</italic> were commonly up-regulated in sensitive and tolerant genotypes but with a higher FC in the sensitive genotype although the tolerant genotype had a higher level of expression under the control condition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S10</xref> and <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Out of 34 Affymetrix wheat probes for <italic>Antox</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S11</xref>), 3 genes were up-regulated in the tolerant samples (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A</xref>). <italic>APX5</italic> and <italic>CAT</italic> were the common up-regulated <italic>Antox</italic> genes under drought conditions in both cultivars. The wheat array contained only 17 probes for <italic>PEX</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S12</xref>). Only <italic>PEX11d</italic> was up-regulated &#x02265;2FC in the drought tolerant wheat while <italic>PEX11a</italic> and <italic>PEX11d</italic> were upregulated in the sensitive cultivar. No <italic>PEX</italic> genes were down-regulated &#x02265;2FC in either cultivar (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6B</xref>). <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the genes in wheat that are upregulated by drought where homologues are also up-regulated by ABA in Arabidopsis and by ABA, dehydration and mannitol in moss.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Differentially regulated peroxisomal genes in wheat in response to drought stress in sensitive and tolerant cultivars in GEO dataset GSE30436. <bold>A:</bold> Numbers of <italic>PTS1</italic>, <italic>Antox</italic> and <italic>PEX</italic> genes up-regulated &#x02265;2FC in response to drought stress in sensitive and tolerant wheat cultivars. <bold>B:</bold> Total numbers of differentially regulated genes of <italic>PTS1</italic>, <italic>Antox</italic> and <italic>PEX</italic> genes. Black bars indicate up-regulated genes, pale grey bars indicate down-regulated genes. Star symbol indicates significant hypergeometric probability at <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.01). <bold>C:</bold> Peroxisomal gene expression under drought stress in sensitive and tolerant cultivars. Blue colour indicates a lower expression level and red colour indicates a higher expression level. Each row normalized to control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery26606"/></fig></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Gene expression of peroxisome related genes in drought tolerant and sensitive cultivars of wheat in response to ABA</title><p>To further explore the relationship between expression of peroxisome related genes in response to drought tolerance, two wheat genotypes differing in their performance under drought stress were selected based on a germination tolerance test using PEG-6000 and calculating water content percentage (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). These data suggest Giza is less tolerant to drought than Oakley. Carbon dioxide assimilation was measured in both cultivars with and without 100 &#x000b5;M ABA treatment after 24 hours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>). In both cultivars, CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation decreased as a result of closure of stomata by ABA, and this is reflected by the decrease in stomatal conductance and transpiration in both cultivars. However, both cultivars maintained stable levels of internal carbon. Giza, the more sensitive variety, is the most affected in terms of CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>). Osmolyte accumulation after 7 days in both cultivars showed variation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>). Soluble sugars significantly decreased in Giza upon ABA treatment, presumably as a result of decreased photosynthesis. However, in Oakley the soluble sugars did not significantly change compared to the untreated control. Proline and glycine betaine accumulated in both cultivars in response to ABA. Free amino acids were elevated in response to ABA in Giza which may reflect proteolysis; however this response was much less marked in Oakley (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>Physiological and biochemical performance of two wheat cultivars Giza and Oakley in response to ABA treatment. <bold>A:</bold> Photosynthesis parameters in 10 days old seedlings after 24 hours of 100&#x000b5;M ABA treatment. <bold>B:</bold> Osmoprotectant compounds analysis in two wheat cultivars Giza and Oakley after 7 days of 100 &#x000b5;M ABA treatment. Data are means of 3 replicates&#x000b1;SE. Bars labelled with different letters are significantly different at <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery26607"/></fig><p>Expression of <italic>PEX3</italic> and the <italic>PEX11</italic> family was studied in these leaf samples 24 hours after ABA treatment by rtQPCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). <italic>PEX3</italic> (the conserved region in 3 <italic>PEX3</italic> genes; Traes_5DS_BB388ED7C, Traes_5AS_6B30155C7 and Traes_5BS_8560EC011) was strongly upregulated by ABA treatment in the tolerant variety Oakley but not in the sensitive cultivar Giza. Three <italic>PEX11d</italic> isoforms d-1; Traes_4AL_D9FFAAA1A, d-3; Traes_7AS_D51B7852F and 4; Traes_7DS_DA11E7020 were also upregulated in Oakley but not Giza. Giza showed significant up-regulation of <italic>PEX11b</italic>; Traes_2AL_FB2B6601D and slight increase in <italic>PEX11d-2; Traes_4BL_DD7569D22</italic>.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p>Quantitative real time-PCR analysis of <italic>PEX3</italic> and <italic>PEX11</italic> in two cultivars of <italic>T. aestivum</italic>, Giza168 and Oakley in response to 100 &#x000b5;M ABA after 24 hours. Data are expressed as fold change in expression (y-axis) relative to ABA untreated control. Three biological replicates were used and three technical replicates for each treatment. Bars represent the standard error. Star symbols indicate significance of t-test for control and treated samples. *Data are significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery26608"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study has collated an inventory of predicted peroxisomal PTS1 targeted proteins (genes of putative PTS1 proteins) from moss and wheat. It has also collated information on the network of anti-oxidant enzymes (<italic>Antox</italic> genes) from these species, both probable peroxisome isoforms and their non-peroxisomal homologues. Using this information, along with previously collated information on the <italic>PEX</italic> gene complement of these species we have examined transcriptional responses of these gene sets to drought, dehydration and ABA response with the intention of identifying evolutionary conserved responses</p><sec id="s17"><title>The peroxisome proteome of moss and wheat</title><p>The results summarized in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> show that not all PTS1 proteins in Arabidopsis have obvious homologues in wheat and moss, whilst among the homologous proteins identified in these two species, some appear to lack a PTS1. In some cases this could be due to a false positive prediction of peroxisome targeting of the corresponding Arabidopsis protein, as not all have been experimentally validated. Also possible is potential false negative predictions arising from yet unknown variation in PTS1 usage in moss and wheat, and the potential for &#x02018;piggy back import&#x02019; (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Kataya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) where a protein lacking a PTS1 can be co-imported with a partner that has a PTS1. Nevertheless despite these caveats the data suggest that the peroxisome proteome is quite variable between organisms. This fits with the proposal that peroxisome targeting by the PTS1 pathway can evolve relatively rapidly through alternative splicing, point mutation and stop codon read through (<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Reumann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). The overrepresentation of <italic>PTS1</italic> gene transcripts amongst those upregulated across species points to the importance of peroxisome processes in response to drought and ABA.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Evidence for conserved upregulation of peroxisomal &#x003b2;-oxidation</title><p>Members of the acyl adenylate activating family of enzymes were upregulated in all 3 species. These enzymes activate diverse substrates for entry into &#x003b2;-oxidation. <italic>AAE17</italic> in Arabidopsis is the closest relative of <italic>AAE18</italic> which activates the synthetic pro hormone 2,4-dichlorophenoxy butyric acid (2,4DB) for &#x003b2;-oxidation but the natural substrates are not known for either enzyme (<xref rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr">Wiszniewski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). rtQPCR confirmed significant induction of <italic>ACX1</italic> and <italic>AIM1</italic> by ABA treatment in moss (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). <italic>ACX1</italic> is also induced by ABA in Arabidopsis (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S7</xref> and <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> at <italic>JXB</italic> online) and by wounding, dehydration and Jasmonic acid (JA) (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Castillo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>).</p><p>Jasmonates have been reported to interact with ABA signaling in drought stress (see (<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Riemann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) for recent review). As drought is proposed to lead to a block in OPDA conversion to JA, and OPDA is an important signal for guard cell closure which regulates guard cell aperture both co-operatively with, and independently of, ABA (<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">Savchenko <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), it therefore seems unlikely that ABA increases JA production via upregulation of peroxisomal &#x003b2;-oxidation. Neither <italic>OPR3</italic> or <italic>OPCL1</italic>, which are key enzymes in the pathway, change in Arabidopsis on ABA treatment (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S7</xref> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> is reported to contain cyclopentanones (OPDA) but not jasmonates (<xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">Stumpe <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Why then should peroxisomal &#x003b2;-oxidation be upregulated? Stress responses trigger lipid dependent signaling (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Hou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) and peroxisomal &#x003b2;-oxidation could be involved in turnover of some of these molecules or in degradation of peroxidated membrane lipids formed as a result of oxidative stress. Metabolism of the yet unknown substrates activated by the AAEs may also be important signals or mitigators of stress responses.</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>The glyoxylate cycle&#x02014;upregulation for production of carbohydrates?</title><p>Fatty acid breakdown produces acetyl CoA which can enter the glyoxylate cycle (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Eastmond <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Eastmond and Graham, 2001</xref>). Induction of isocitrate lyase and malate synthase, provides a route for synthesis of malate which can be converted to oxaloacetate, the starting point for gluconeogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Consistent with this hypothesis, the moss gene Pp3c4_25090 encoding a PEP carboxykinase (the first committed step of gluconeogenesis) was upregulated 3.2, 4.4 and 2.7-fold under ABA, mannitol and dehydration treatment. Gluconeogenesis can provide soluble sugars for respiration or osmotic balance under water deficit conditions, and sucrose accumulates to high levels in <italic>P. patens</italic> following ABA treatment (<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Oldenhof <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Strikingly, the glyoxylate cycle enzymes were not induced upon drought or ABA treatment in Arabidopsis ((<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Li and Hu, 2015</xref>) and see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Table S7</xref> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Non coordinate induction of &#x003b2;-oxidation and glyoxylate cycle was seen during starvation or senescence in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Charlton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005<italic>a</italic></xref>) supporting the notion that lipid is broken down and respired (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Pracharoenwattana <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) in contrast to other species where it feeds into the glyoxylate cycle.</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Branched chain amino acid metabolism</title><p>Another source of substrates for &#x003b2;-oxidation in non-lipid storing tissue is degradation of branched chain amino acids (BCAAs). The expression of <italic>BCAT5</italic>&#x02014;the first key enzyme in degrading BCAAs&#x02014;and <italic>IVDH</italic> (Isovaleryl-CoA-Dehydrogenase), the enzyme that converts acyl CoA to enoyl CoA (two copies of <italic>BCAT5</italic> and two copies of <italic>IVDH</italic> in moss), both show strong upregulation under ABA, dehydration and mannitol treatment, as does <italic>ECH1a</italic>, an enoylCoA dehydratase. In Arabidopsis the pathway for degradation of BCAAs is predominantly mitochondrial (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Binder, 2010</xref>) but at least one step of valine degradation catalyzed by hydroxyisobutryl CoA hydrolase (encoded by the <italic>CHY1</italic> gene) is peroxisomal (<xref rid="CIT0075" ref-type="bibr">Zolman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Intriguingly <italic>chy1</italic> mutants are defective in cold responses, are more sensitive to dark induced damage and accumulate ROS; phenotypes which can be suppressed by exogenous application of sucrose suggesting a role in osmoprotection and/or maintenance of carbohydrate levels (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Dong <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>A role for peroxisomes in stomatal movement</title><p>An early response to water stress is stomatal closure and recent data points to a role for peroxisome metabolism in guard cells in regulating stomatal movement. Peroxisomal &#x003b2;-oxidation of stored lipids contributes to ATP production for stomatal opening in both Arabidopsis and the lycophyte <italic>Selaginella</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">McLachlan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Furthermore, an Arabidopsis mutant defective in peroxisomal NADP+ dependent isocitrate dehydrogenase showed deficiency in stomatal opening which was rescued by ascorbate. This led to the proposal that loss of peroxisomal NADP<sup>+</sup> dependent ICDH activity impacts the ascorbate glutathione cycle leading to increased cytosolic H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Leterrier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). An ICDH isoform (Pp3c20_22810) with a putative PTS1 sequence was upregulated by all treatments in moss.</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>Peroxisomes and ROS</title><p>Increased photorespiration as a result of stomatal closure under water deficit leads to increased production of hydrogen peroxide as a consequence of increased photorespiratory flux. Interestingly though, none of the candidate glycolate oxidases were upregulated &#x0003e;2-fold. Antioxidant responses are complex and sometimes contradictory (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Noctor <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). One significant complication is the likely compartment-specific production of ROS and antioxidants; spatial information which is lost upon biochemical extraction. In the current study, focusing on the response of likely peroxisomal targeted enzymes provides an alternative approach to looking at a compartment specific response. Considering the genes commonly upregulated across the 3 stress treatments in moss, Acyl CoA oxidase and the copper amine oxidases generate H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2.</sub> Copper-containing amine oxidases (CuAOs) are involved in oxidative de-amination of polyamines, ubiquitous polycationic compounds involved in crucial events in the life of the cell (<xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">Tavladoraki <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Two catalase isoforms and virtually the complete ascorbate glutathione cycle was upregulated. Glutathione reductase 1 in Arabidopsis is dual targeted to the cytosol and peroxisomes (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Kataya and Reumann, 2010</xref>), and a peroxisomal isoform of NADP<sup>+</sup> dependent isocitrate dehydrogenase contributes to the ascorbate glutathione cycle in peroxisomes (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Jimenez <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Reumann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Measurement of changes in organelle redox using roGFP showed drought primarily affected chloroplast and mitochondrial redox potential whereas peroxisome redox potential was more affected in the dark and was exacerbated by 3-amino triazole treatment which inhibits catalase (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Bratt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). This suggests an effective peroxisomal antioxidant defence under drought conditions. Upregulation of catalase was seen in moss and wheat under all conditions whilst upregulation of <italic>ACX1</italic>, <italic>GR</italic> and <italic>DHAR2</italic> showed common upregulation between moss and Arabidopsis (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Wheat (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Ford <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) and moss (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Cui <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) proteomic studies also support upregulation of antioxidants and polyamine biosynthesis (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cheng <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) under drought stress.</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title>Peroxisome biogenesis</title><p>Peroxisomes multiply by division of preexisting peroxisomes in a process requiring the PEX11 family of membrane proteins and may also form <italic>de novo</italic> from the ER in a pathway that requires PEX3. PEX3 in addition recruits peroxisomal membrane proteins including membrane bound enzymes and components of the import machinery for peroxisome matrix proteins All three <italic>PEX3</italic> genes in moss were upregulated by ABA treatment, and different members of the <italic>PEX11</italic> gene family were differentially expressed suggesting specialization of function. Consistent with this, ABA triggered peroxisome proliferation in protonemal tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p><p>In Arabidopsis <italic>PEX11b</italic>, <italic>c</italic> and <italic>d</italic> are upregulated under hypoxia and biotic stress and only <italic>PEX11b</italic> and <italic>PEX11d</italic> are upregulated by ABA whereas <italic>PEX11c</italic> is down regulated (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Li and Hu, 2015</xref>). <italic>PEX11e</italic> induction in response to salt stress requires components of the ABA signaling pathway (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Charlton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005<italic>b</italic></xref>). Salt stress, like drought, imposes a dehydration stress but also an ionic stress and triggers peroxisome proliferation (<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Mitsuya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Arabidopsis <italic>PEX11b</italic> stimulates peroxisome proliferation in response to light (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Desai and Hu, 2008</xref>). High light, drought, salt and ABA all trigger ROS production which transcriptionally activates some <italic>PEX</italic> genes (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Lopez-Huertas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Exogenous application leads to formation of peroxules, and <italic>PEX11a</italic> is involved in this process (<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Serrano <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). In wheat, striking differences were seen between drought sensitive cultivar Giza and drought tolerant cultivar Oakley with respect to <italic>PEX</italic> gene expression. <italic>PEX3</italic> and <italic>PEX11d1, d3</italic> and <italic>d4</italic> were strongly upregulated by ABA in the resistant cultivar but not in the sensitive one. Conversely <italic>PEX11b</italic> was upregulated in the sensitive cultivar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s24"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Peroxisome biogenesis and genes of putative PTS1 proteins are upregulated in response to drought, dehydration and ABA across evolutionary distant plant species. While the specifics of the responses differ, core pathways of PEX3/11 and &#x003b2;-oxidation are conserved. This suggests an important and evolutionarily ancient role for peroxisomes in stress perception and response. As differential regulation of <italic>PEX3</italic> and <italic>PEX11</italic> family members is correlated with better drought tolerance, the accumulation of multiple gene copies has perhaps allowed elaboration in the control of peroxisomal biogenesis in response to stress. Collectively our findings give new insights into the role of peroxisomes and peroxisome associated processes in response to drought and ABA across a wide evolutionary distance and suggest that the role of peroxisomes in perceiving and responding to drought stress is worthy of further investigation.</p></sec><sec id="s25"><title>Supplementary Data</title><p>Supplementary data are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p><p>Supplementary Fig. S1. Germination % of two wheat varieties, Giza 168 and Oakley under 20% PEG-6000.</p><p>Supplementary Table S1. Primer sequences used in this study.</p><p>Supplementary Table S2. List of <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> homologues of proven and predicted Arabidopsis PTS1 proteins.</p><p>Supplementary Table S3. List of wheat homologues of proven and predicted Arabidopsis PTS1proteins.</p><p>Supplementary Table S4. List of Arabidopsis antioxidant gene homologues in <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic>.</p><p>Supplementary Table S5. List of Arabidopsis antioxidant gene homologues in wheat.</p><p>Supplementary Table S6. List of <italic>P.patens</italic> differentially regulated genes under ABA, mannitol and dehydration.</p><p>Supplementary Table S7. Microarray-based expression data for Arabidopsis genes of putative PTS1 proteins under ABA treatment, GSE65739.</p><p>Supplementary Table S8. Microarray based-expression data for Arabidopsis antioxidant genes under ABA treatment, GSE65739.</p><p>Supplementary Table S9. Microarray based-expression data for Arabidopsis <italic>PEX</italic> genes under ABA treatment, GSE65739.</p><p>Supplementary Table S10. Microarray based-expression data for wheat genes of putative PTS1 proteins under drought, GSE30436.</p><p>Supplementary Table S11. Microarray based-expression data for wheat antioxidant genes under drought, GSE30436.</p><p>Supplementary Table S12. Microarray based-expression data for wheat <italic>PEX</italic> genes under drought, GSE30436.</p></sec><sec id="s26"><title>Author contributions</title><p>H.T.E.: Designed and performed wheat experiments and moss peroxisome proliferation experiment, identified peroxisomal homologs of moss and wheat, analysed Arabidopsis and wheat RNA-seq and microarray data, and performed real-time QPCR. S.S.: Provided moss cDNA samples, provided help in the bioinformatic analysis and performed some analysis of moss RNA-seq data. A.C.C.: Provided reagents and training for the moss work, designed and supervised moss work. A.B.: Conceived the project with H.T.E. and A.C.C., designed, supervised and coordinated the study and prepared the paper with H.T.E. All authors saw and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Figure S1</label><media xlink:href="ery266_suppl_supplementary_figure_s1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup2"><label>Supplementary Tables</label><media xlink:href="ery266_suppl_supplementary_tables.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Prof. Dr Christine Foyer for providing lab facilities for measuring photosynthesis, James Cooper from C.F. lab for his help with LI-COR gas exchange system, Dr Rupesh Paudyal for help with fluorescent microscopy, Dr Wanjun Qi for help in qPCR, ARC; Giza, Egypt and KWS; UK for providing wheat seeds. This work was supported by post-doctoral Fellowship from the Egyptian Mission Sector, Ministry of Higher Education, Egypt awarded to H.T.E., 2014 and research facilities were provided from University of Leeds, UK and Damietta University, Egypt.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waldren</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teare</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1973</year>
<article-title>Rapid determination of free proline for water-stress studies</article-title>. <source>Plant and Soil</source>&#x000a0;<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Branched-chain amino acid metabolism in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>The Arabidopsis Book</source>&#x000a0;<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e0137</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22303262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1982</year>
<article-title>Plant productivity and environment</article-title>. <source>Science</source>&#x000a0;<volume>218</volume>, <fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>448</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17808529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bratt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenwasser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fluhr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Organelle redox autonomy during environmental stress</article-title>. <source>Plant, Cell &#x00026; Environment</source>&#x000a0;<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1909</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1919</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz Castillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>M&#x000e9;traux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Gene-specific involvement of beta-oxidation in wound-activated responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlton</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005a</year>
<article-title>Non-coordinate expression of peroxisome biogenesis, beta-oxidation and glyoxylate cycle genes in mature Arabidopsis plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Reports</source>&#x000a0;<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>653</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15449020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlton</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohme-Takagi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005b</year>
<article-title>Salt-induced expression of peroxisome-associated genes requires components of the ethylene, jasmonate and abscisic acid signalling pathways</article-title>. <source>Plant, Cell &#x00026; Environment</source>&#x000a0;<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>524</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Identification of leaf proteins differentially accumulated between wheat cultivars distinct in their levels of drought tolerance</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>&#x000a0;<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e0125302</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25984726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Plant-mPLoc: a top-down strategy to augment the power for predicting plant protein subcellular localization</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>&#x000a0;<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e11335</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20596258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Claeys</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inz&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The agony of choice: how plants balance growth and survival under water-limiting conditions</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>162</volume>, <fpage>1768</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1779</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23766368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebeed</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Peroxisome biogenesis, protein targeting mechanisms and PEX gene functions in plants</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - Molecular Cell Research</source>&#x000a0;<volume>1863</volume>, <fpage>850</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>862</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26408938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Proteome analysis of <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> exposed to progressive dehydration and rehydration</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>&#x000a0;<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>726</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21994173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuming</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamisugi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quatrano</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Microarray analysis of transcriptional responses to abscisic acid and osmotic, salt, and drought stress in the moss, <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic></article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>&#x000a0;<volume>176</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17696978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>del Rio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pastori</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandalio</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sevilla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corpas</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Huertas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>The activated oxygen role of peroxisomes in senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>1195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9536035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delwiche</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The evolutionary origin of a terrestrial flora</article-title>. <source>Current Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>R899</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>R910</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26439353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Light induces peroxisome proliferation in Arabidopsis seedlings through the photoreceptor phytochrome A, the transcription factor HY5 HOMOLOG, and the peroxisomal protein PEROXIN11b</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>146</volume>, <fpage>1117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1127</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18203870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Distel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>A unified nomenclature for peroxisome biogenesis factors</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8858157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zolman</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>disruption of <italic>Arabidopsis CHY1</italic> reveals an important role of metabolic status in plant cold stress signaling</article-title>. <source>Molecular Plant</source>&#x000a0;<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19529827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastmond</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bryce</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Postgerminative growth and lipid catabolism in oilseeds lacking the glyoxylate cycle</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>&#x000a0;<volume>97</volume>, <fpage>5669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5674</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastmond</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Re-examining the role of the glyoxylate cycle in oilseeds</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>&#x000a0;<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11173291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cassin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bacic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Quantitative proteomic analysis of wheat cultivars with differing drought stress tolerance</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source>&#x000a0;<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>44</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22639595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>ABA-mediated transcriptional regulation in response to osmotic stress in plants</article-title>. <source>Journal of Plant Research</source>&#x000a0;<volume>124</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>525</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21416314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasteiger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gattiker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoogland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanyi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>ExPASy: the proteomics server for in-depth protein knowledge and analysis</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>&#x000a0;<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>3784</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3788</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beddington</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crute</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pretty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toulmin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Food security: the challenge of feeding 9 billion people</article-title>. <source>Science</source>&#x000a0;<volume>327</volume>, <fpage>812</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>818</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grieve</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grattan</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year>
<article-title>Rapid assay for determination of water soluble quaternary ammonium compounds</article-title>. <source>Plant and Soil</source>&#x000a0;<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naithani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tello-Ruiz</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Gramene database: navigating plant comparative genomics resources</article-title>. <source>Current Plant Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>7-8</volume>, <fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28713666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golovina</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buitink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Mechanisms of plant desiccation tolerance</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>&#x000a0;<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castleden</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanz</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aryamanesh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>SUBA4: the interactive data analysis centre for Arabidopsis subcellular protein locations</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>&#x000a0;<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>D1064</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D1074</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27899614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ufer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Lipid signalling in plant responses to abiotic stress</article-title>. <source>Plant, Cell &#x00026; Environment</source>&#x000a0;<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1029</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1048</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zolman</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Plant peroxisomes: biogenesis and function</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>&#x000a0;<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>2279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22669882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>The molecular basis of dehydration tolerance in plants</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>403</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Del Rio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sevilla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Evidence for the presence of the ascorbate-glutathione cycle in mitochondria and peroxisomes of pea leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>114</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>284</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vikram</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pawar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaikwad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khanna-Chopra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Genomic associations for drought tolerance on the short arm of wheat chromosome 4B</article-title>. <source>Functional &#x00026; Integrative Genomics</source>&#x000a0;<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>464</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22476619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamisugi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsuya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuming</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Giant peroxisomes in a moss (<italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic>) peroxisomal biogenesis factor 11 mutant</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>&#x000a0;<volume>209</volume>, <fpage>576</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>589</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26542980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kataya</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heidari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kommedal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slupphaug</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lillo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Protein phosphatase 2A holoenzyme is targeted to peroxisomes by piggybacking and positively affects peroxisomal &#x003b2;-oxidation</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>167</volume>, <fpage>493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>506</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25489022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kataya</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Arabidopsis glutathione reductase 1 is dually targeted to peroxisomes and the cytosol</article-title>. <source>Plant Signaling &#x00026; Behavior</source>&#x000a0;<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20038819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuming</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quatrano</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Moss gene technology</article-title>. <source>Molecular Plant Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leterrier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barroso</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Begara-Morales</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Calvo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luque</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vi&#x000f1;egla</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corpas</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Peroxisomal NADP-isocitrate dehydrogenase is required for Arabidopsis stomatal movement</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>&#x000a0;<volume>253</volume>, <fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>415</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25894616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giraudat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Abscisic acid signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Using co-expression analysis and stress-based screens to uncover arabidopsis peroxisomal proteins involved in drought response</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>&#x000a0;<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e0137762</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26368942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Huertas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charlton</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Stress induces peroxisome biogenesis genes</article-title>. <source>The EMBO Journal</source>&#x000a0;<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>6770</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6777</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11118212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLachlan</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geilfus</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The breakdown of stored triacylglycerols is required during light-induced stomatal opening</article-title>. <source>Current Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>712</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26898465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Minguet</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Segard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charavay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parcy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>MORPHEUS, a webtool for transcription factor binding analysis using position weight matrices with dependency</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>&#x000a0;<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e0135586</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26285209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsuya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sparkes</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charlton</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lousa</surname><given-names>Cde M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Salt stress causes peroxisome proliferation, but inducing peroxisome proliferation does not improve NaCl tolerance in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>&#x000a0;<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e9408</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20195524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderauwera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tognetti</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vandepoele</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gollery</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shulaev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Breusegem</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>ROS signaling: the new wave</article-title>?<source>Trends in Plant Science</source>&#x000a0;<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>300</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21482172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selld&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ojanper&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandelius</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalko</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalko</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Peroxisome proliferation in Norway spruce induced by ozone</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>&#x000a0;<volume>155</volume>, <fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional regulatory networks in response to abiotic stresses in Arabidopsis and grasses</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>149</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19126699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noctor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mhamdi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The roles of reactive oxygen metabolism in drought: not so cut and dried</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>164</volume>, <fpage>1636</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1648</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24715539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noctor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veljovic-Jovanovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novitskaya</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Drought and oxidative load in the leaves of C3 plants: a predominant role for photorespiration</article-title>?<source>Annals of Botany</source>&#x000a0;<volume>89 Spec No</volume>, <fpage>841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>850</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12102510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oksanen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e4;iki&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sober</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karnosky</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Ozone-induced H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation in field-grown aspen and birch is linked to foliar ultrastructure and peroxisomal activity</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>&#x000a0;<volume>161</volume>, <fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>799</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oldenhof</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolkers</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tablin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Freezing and desiccation tolerance in the moss <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic>: an in situ Fourier transform infrared spectroscopic study</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - General Subjects</source>&#x000a0;<volume>1760</volume>, <fpage>1226</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1234</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740364</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The PEROXIN11 protein family controls peroxisome proliferation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>&#x000a0;<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>350</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17220199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastori</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Del Rio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Natural senescence of pea leaves (an activated oxygen-mediated function for peroxisomes)</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>113</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pracharoenwattana</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornah</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> peroxisomal citrate synthase is required for fatty acid respiration and seed germination</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>&#x000a0;<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>2037</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2048</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15923350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babujee</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wienkoop</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siemsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antonicelli</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rasche</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000fc;der</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weckwerth</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Proteome analysis of Arabidopsis leaf peroxisomes reveals novel targeting peptides, metabolic pathways, and defense mechanisms</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>&#x000a0;<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>3170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3193</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchwald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lingner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>PredPlantPTS1: a web server for the prediction of plant peroxisomal proteins</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source>&#x000a0;<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>194</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22969783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhary</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lingner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Characterization, prediction and evolution of plant peroxisomal targeting signals type 1 (PTS1s)</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - Molecular Cell Research</source>&#x000a0;<volume>1863</volume>, <fpage>790</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>803</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26772785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dhakarey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hazman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Exploring Jasmonates in the hormonal network of drought and salinity responses</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source>&#x000a0;<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1077</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26648959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Serrano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romero-Puertas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanz-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandalio</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Peroxisomes extend peroxules in a fast response to stress via a reactive oxygen species-mediated induction of the peroxin <italic>PEX11A</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>171</volume>, <fpage>1665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1674</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27208303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savchenko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolla</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nasafi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phadungchob</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chehab</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Froehlich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dehesh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Functional convergence of oxylipin and abscisic acid pathways controls stomatal closure in response to drought</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>164</volume>, <fpage>1151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1160</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24429214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schl&#x000fc;ter</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Long-term anoxia tolerance in leaves of <italic>Acorus calamus</italic> L. and <italic>Iris pseudacorus</italic> L</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>&#x000a0;<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>2213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11604461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schortemeyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stamp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>BOY</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Ammonium tolerance and carbohydrate status in maize cultivars</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source>&#x000a0;<volume>79</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Regulatory network of gene expression in the drought and cold stress responses</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>410</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>417</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12972040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sircelj</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tausz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grill</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Batic</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Biochemical responses in leaves of two apple tree cultivars subjected to progressing drought</article-title>. <source>Journal of Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>162</volume>, <fpage>1308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1318</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16425449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamisugi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trinh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genetic analysis of <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> identifies <italic>ABSCISIC ACID NON-RESPONSIVE</italic>, a regulator of ABA responses unique to basal land plants and required for desiccation tolerance</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>&#x000a0;<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1327</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27194706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stumpe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>G&#x000f6;bel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faltin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The moss <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> contains cyclopentenones but no jasmonates: mutations in allene oxide cyclase lead to reduced fertility and altered sporophyte morphology</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>&#x000a0;<volume>188</volume>, <fpage>740</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>749</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20704658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavladoraki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cona</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Federico</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tempera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viceconte</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saccoccio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toninello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agostinelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Polyamine catabolism: target for antiproliferative therapies in animals and stress tolerance strategies in plants</article-title>. <source>Amino Acids</source>&#x000a0;<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>426</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21874532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0068"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uauy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Wheat genomics comes of age</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28346895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0069"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Exploring the mechanism of <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> desiccation tolerance through a proteomic strategy</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>149</volume>, <fpage>1739</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1750</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19211702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0070"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Co-evolution of hormone metabolism and signaling networks expands plant adaptive plasticity</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>&#x000a0;<volume>166</volume>, <fpage>881</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>893</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27518563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0071"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willekens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chamnongpol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schraudner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langebartels</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Montagu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inz&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Camp</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Catalase is a sink for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and is indispensable for stress defence in C3 plants</article-title>. <source>The EMBO Journal</source>&#x000a0;<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>4806</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4816</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9305623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0072"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiszniewski</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bussell</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Identification of two Arabidopsis genes encoding a peroxisomal oxidoreductase-like protein and an acyl-CoA synthetase-like protein that are required for responses to pro-auxins</article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19043666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0073"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional regulatory networks in cellular responses and tolerance to dehydration and cold stresses</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>803</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0074"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Salt and drought stress signal transduction in plants</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source>&#x000a0;<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>273</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0075"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zolman</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monroe-Augustus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krukenberg</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>chy1, an Arabidopsis mutant with impaired beta-oxidation, is defective in a peroxisomal beta-hydroxyisobutyryl-CoA hydrolase</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>&#x000a0;<volume>276</volume>, <fpage>31037</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31046</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11404361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>