<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6305195</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ery346</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ery346</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Growth and Development</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
<italic>HEADLESS</italic>, a <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> homolog, uncovers novel aspects of shoot meristem regulation and leaf blade development in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Yingying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn-0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Huan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn-0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn-0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Ye</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Butuo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Zuoyi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Yaling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Pengcheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Jiangqi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Hongshan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0005">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mysore</surname><given-names>Kirankumar S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Jianghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>Million</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Lifang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>niulifang@caas.cn</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>linhao@caas.cn</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Biotechnology Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Department of Plant and Soil Sciences, Institute for Agricultural Biosciences, Oklahoma State University, Sam Noble Parkway, Ardmore, OK, USA</aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>Key Laboratory of Tropical Plant Resources and Sustainable Use, CAS Center for Excellence in Molecular Plant Sciences, Xishuangbanna Tropical Botanical Garden, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, Yunnan Province, China</aff><aff id="AF0004"><label>4</label>Noble Research Institute, LLC, Sam Noble Parkway, Ardmore, OK, USA</aff><aff id="AF0005"><label>5</label>Lanzhou Institute of Husbandry and Pharmaceutical Sciences, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Lanzhou, Gansu Province, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence: <email>linhao@caas.cn</email> or <email>niulifang@caas.cn</email></corresp><fn id="fn-0001"><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-09-29"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>70</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2018. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ery346.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The WOX family transcription factor HEADLESS exhibits a repressive activity and performs conserved and novel functions in the regulation of shoot meristems and leaf shape in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic>.</p></abstract><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The formation and maintenance of the shoot apical meristem (SAM) are critical for plant development. However, the underlying molecular mechanism of regulating meristematic cell activity is poorly understood in the model legume <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic>. Using forward genetic approaches, we identified <italic>HEADLESS</italic> (<italic>HDL</italic>), a homolog of Arabidopsis <italic>WUSCHEL</italic>, required for SAM maintenance and leaf development in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>. Disruption of <italic>HDL</italic> led to disorganized specification and arrest of the SAM and axillary meristems, resulting in the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant being locked in the vegetative phase without apparent stem elongation. <italic>hdl</italic> mutant leaves are shorter in the proximal&#x02013;distal axis due to reduced leaf length elongation, which resulted in a higher blade width/length ratio and altered leaf shape, uncovering novel phenotypes undescribed in the Arabidopsis <italic>wus</italic> mutant. HDL functions as a transcriptional repressor by recruiting MtTPL through its conserved WUS-box and EAR-like motif. Further genetic analysis revealed that <italic>HDL</italic> and <italic>STENOFOLIA</italic> (<italic>STF</italic>), a key regulator of <italic>M. truncatula</italic> lamina outgrowth, act independently in leaf development although HDL could recruit MtTPL in the same manner as STF does. Our results indicate that HDL has conserved and novel functions in regulating shoot meristems and leaf shape in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, providing new avenues for understanding meristem biology and plant development.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>HEADLESS</italic></kwd><kwd>leaf development</kwd><kwd><italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></kwd><kwd>SAM maintenance</kwd><kwd>transcriptional repressor</kwd><kwd><italic>WUSCHEL</italic> homolog</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The shoot apical meristem (SAM) is made of pluripotent stem cells located at the shoot apex, which is responsible for self-maintenance and producing lateral organ primordia that develop into post-embryonic aerial organs (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Barton, 2010</xref>). The SAM provides an environment for maintenance of meristematic cell activity and is regarded as a plant stem cell niche (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Busch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Several key regulators of stem cell control in the SAM have previously been identified through genetic approaches. The homeobox gene, <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> (<italic>WUS</italic>), which is specifically expressed in the organizing center of the SAM, plays a central role in shoot stem cell identity and is required for non-cell-autonomous induction and maintenance of stem cell fate in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Mayer <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Lenhard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">Yadav <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). In Arabidopsis <italic>wus-1</italic> mutant plants, the defect is exhibited at all developmental stages, and the shoot stem cells are misspecified, resulting in the premature termination of SAMs and floral meristems, and leading to an aberrant flat morphology (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Mayer <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). The CLE peptide CLAVATA3 (CLV3) acts as a negative signal for shoot stem cell proliferation (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Fletcher <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Kondo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Ohyama <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Several receptor-like protein kinases, including CLV1, RECEPTOR-LIKE PROTEIN KINASE 2 (RPK2), and CLAVATA3 INSENSITIVE RECEPTOR KINASES (CIKs), the receptor-like protein CLV2, and the pseudokinase CORYNE (CRN) are required for the perception of the CLV3 signal to repress <italic>WUS</italic> expression (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Clark <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Kayes and Clark, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000fc;ller <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Ogawa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Kinoshita <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Hu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). In turn, <italic>WUS</italic> directly activates <italic>CLV3</italic> expression within the central zone, indicating that SAM maintenance is controlled by a complex <italic>WUSCHEL</italic>&#x02013;<italic>CLAVATA</italic> feedback loop (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Brand <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Schoof <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Somssich <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Recent studies in Arabidopsis using computational and experimental approaches revealed that WUS activates <italic>CLV3</italic> only in the absence of HAIRY MERISTEM (HAM) proteins, and an apical&#x02013;basal gradient of HAM defines the expression pattern of <italic>CLV3</italic> in the initiating meristems (<xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p><p>The phytohormone cytokinin is essential for maintenance of the shoot meristem activity and cell proliferation (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Riou-Khamlichi <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">Werner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). It has been shown that the WUS protein is linked to cytokinin signaling through direct transcriptional repression of type-A <italic>Arabidopsis Response Regulator</italic> (<italic>ARR</italic>) genes (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Leibfried <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), which are negative regulators of cytokinin signaling. In Arabidopsis, the expression of the closely related type-A response regulator genes including <italic>ARR</italic>5, <italic>ARR6</italic>, <italic>ARR7</italic>, and <italic>ARR15</italic> is repressed by WUS in the center of the SAM. Ectopic expression of an active phosphorylated form of <italic>ARR7</italic> causes the formation of an aberrant SAM, indicating that WUS controls meristem function by directly regulating cytokinin-inducible response regulators (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Leibfried <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). WUS mainly functions as a transcriptional repressor in SAM maintenance and interacts with TOPLESS (TPL) and TPL-related (TPR) transcriptional co-repressors, which are recruited via their conserved WUS-box (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Kieffer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Causier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Dolzblasz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p><p>The plant specific <italic>WUSCHEL</italic>-related homeobox (WOX) family genes, of which <italic>WUS</italic> is the founding member, fulfill specialized functions in several key developmental processes such as embryonic patterning, vascular patterning, and lateral organ development (<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">van der Graaff <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Costanzo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). It has been reported that WOX transcription factors play essential roles in leaf development in various species, including both monocots and eudicots. In monocots, two maize <italic>WOX3</italic>/<italic>PRS</italic> homologs, <italic>NARROW SHEATH1</italic> and <italic>NARROW SHEATH2</italic> (<italic>NS1</italic> and <italic>NS2</italic>), redundantly regulate leaf blade outgrowth, as demonstrated by the <italic>ns1 ns2</italic> double mutant with a severe narrow leaf phenotype (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Scanlon <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Nardmann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Similarly, simultaneous mutations in <italic>NS</italic> homologous genes, <italic>NARROW LEAF2</italic> and <italic>NARROW LEAF3</italic> (<italic>NAL2</italic> and <italic>NAL3</italic>), also result in a narrow leaf blade phenotype in rice (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Cho <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Ishiwata <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). In eudicots, the Arabidopsis <italic>WOX3</italic>, called <italic>PRESSED FLOWER</italic> (<italic>PRS</italic>), specifically regulates the lateral axis-dependent development of flowers (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Matsumoto and Okada, 2001</xref>), while combining <italic>prs</italic> with <italic>wox1</italic> in the <italic>wox1 prs</italic> double mutant leads to a narrow leaf blade defect indicating that <italic>WOX1</italic> and <italic>PRS</italic> play functionally redundant roles in regulating leaf blade development in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Vandenbussche <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Nakata <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In the model legume <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> and woodland tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana sylvestris</italic>), loss of function in the <italic>WOX1</italic> homolog <italic>STENOFOLIA</italic> (<italic>STF</italic>) and <italic>LAMINALESS1</italic> (<italic>LAM1</italic>), respectively, is sufficient to arrest lateral leaf blade outgrowth, leading to severe defects in leaf width, as well as vein patterning (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Tadege <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Similarly, other homologs <italic>MAEWEST</italic> (<italic>MAW</italic>) in petunia and <italic>LATHYROIDES</italic> (<italic>LATH</italic>) in pea are also involved in controlling leaf blade development and petal fusion (<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Vandenbussche <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">Zhuang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). STF promotes leaf blade outgrowth by activating cell proliferation at the adaxial&#x02013;abaxial juxtaposition of the leaf margin with a transcriptional repression mechanism (Lin <italic>et al</italic>, 2013; <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>, 2014</xref>). This repression requires MtTPL in a manner analogous to WUS function in the SAM (<xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>, 2014</xref>). In fact, this function can be substituted by WUS.</p><p>Expression of Arabidopsis WUS under control of the <italic>M. truncatula STF</italic> promoter can complement both the <italic>stf</italic> and <italic>lam1</italic> mutant phenotypes, indicating that a WUS-like function might be required for cell proliferation in the determinate leaf blade tissue in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> and <italic>N. sylvestris</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Tadege <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). <italic>WUS</italic> can also complement the <italic>prs</italic> and <italic>wox5</italic> mutant phenotypes if expressed under the control of appropriate promoters (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Shimizu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), suggesting a common mechanism in the function of repressive <italic>WOX</italic> genes. Nevertheless, <italic>WOX</italic> genes have very specific and restricted expression patterns, and <italic>WUS</italic> expression outside of the vegetative SAM has been reported in the monocots rice and maize (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Nardmann and Werr, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Lu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), and recent studies revealed that <italic>WUS</italic> expression could also be activated in the leaf axil to promote axillary meristem initiation in Arabidopsis (J. <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Several reports described the genetic manipulation and characterization of <italic>WUS</italic> in several species but, in eudicots, <italic>wus</italic> loss-of-function genetic mutants have so far been reported in Arabidopsis, Petunia, and <italic>Antirrhinum</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Stuurman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Kieffer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), where phenotypes are characterized by a &#x02018;stop-and-go&#x02019; type of growth habit (organogenesis and termination are constantly reiterated in mutant plants) with aberrant vegetative and inflorescence meristems (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Stuurman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Kieffer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; J. <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Importantly, the molecular function of the <italic>WUS</italic> homolog in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> is poorly understood.</p><p>Here, we report the isolation and characterization of <italic>headless</italic> (<italic>hdl</italic>) from <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, which is defective in SAM development. We show that <italic>HDL</italic> is the homolog of <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> in Arabidopsis and is required for maintaining shoot meristem activity and leaf shape in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>. Unlike the <italic>wus</italic> mutant, the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant is stemless and never flowers, but, like WUS, HDL exhibits a repressive activity and represses the expression of several type-A response regulators in the <italic>M. truncatula</italic> shoot apex.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title><p>
<italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> ecotype R108 was used for all experiments described in this study. <italic>hdl-1</italic> (NF11982), <italic>hdl-2</italic> (NF3119), and <italic>hdl-3</italic> (NF2389) alleles were identified from the <italic>Tnt1</italic> retrotransposon-tagged mutant collection of <italic>M. truncatula</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Tadege <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Scarified <italic>M. truncatula</italic> seeds were germinated overnight on moist Petri dishes, and placed at 4 &#x000b0;C for 1 week, except for the 12 h germinated seeds for SEM analyses. Plants were grown at 25 &#x000b0;C day/23 &#x000b0;C night temperature, 16 h day/8 h night photoperiod, 60&#x02013;70% relative humidity, and 150 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> light intensity.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Plasmid constructs and plant transformation</title><p>To make the complementation construct, the <italic>HDL</italic> genomic DNA containing a 2713 bp upstream sequence, the entire <italic>HDL</italic> gene, and a 1366 bp downstream region was cloned into the binary vector pCAMBIA2300 using HDL-pro-<italic>Kpn</italic>I-iF and HDL-1366ASC-<italic>Pst</italic>I-iR primers (Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S1</xref> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). The destination construct was introduced into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> by chemical transformation. <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciences</italic> strain AGL1 was used for <italic>M. truncatula</italic> transformation as previously described (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Meng <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>RNA extraction and quantitative RT&#x02013;PCR</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from shoot apices or unexpanded young leaf tissues of corresponding <italic>M. truncatula</italic> plants by using TRIzol<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> reagent (Invitrogen). cDNA was generated by reverse transcription with SuperScript III (Invitrogen). Quantitative reverse transcription&#x02013;PCR (RT&#x02013;PCR) was performed as previously described (H. <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>) with at least three biological and three technical replicates for both samples and controls. <italic>MtActin</italic> was used as the internal control. All primers used in this study are listed in Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Table S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Subcellular localization and confocal microscopy</title><p>For subcellular localization of HDL, <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain GV2260 containing <italic>pMDC83-HDL</italic> and the nuclear marker plasmid <italic>p35S::mRFP-AHL22</italic> or <italic>pMDC32-GFP</italic> and <italic>p35S::mRFP-AHL22</italic> were simultaneously infiltrated into 3- to 4-week-old <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> leaves. The <italic>pMDC32-GFP</italic> was used as the control. P19 from <italic>Tomato bushy stunt virus</italic> was used to inhibit transgenic silencing. The fluorescence signal was observed with a confocal microscope (Zeiss LSM700) 48&#x02013;60 h after infiltration.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Histological analysis and <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization</title><p>Tissues of <italic>M. truncatula</italic> were &#x0fb01;xed and embedded as previously described (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Lin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013<italic>a</italic></xref>). The tissues were sliced into 8&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;m sections with a Leica RM2265 microtome, af&#x0fb01;xed to microscope slides, and stained with toluidine blue. Images were obtained with a digital camera mounted on the Olympus BX-51 compound microscope.</p><p>RNA <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization was performed essentially as described previously (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). RNA antisense and sense probes were generated with the T7 and SP6 polymerases, respectively, using a 909 bp HDL cDNA template. Sections from shoot apices of 4-week-old wild-type R108 plants were processed and hybridized with digoxigenin-labeled sense and antisense probes. Slides were observed under bright field through an Olympus BX63 microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>SEM analysis</title><p>For SEM, fresh <italic>M. truncatula</italic> shoot tissues were fixed with 3.0% glutaraldehyde in 25 mM phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) for 2 d, then plant tissues were further fixed with 1.0% osmium tetroxide in 25 mM phosphate buffer for 2 h and subsequently dehydrated in a graded ethanol series. The desiccated tissues were critical-point dried in liquid CO<sub>2</sub>, mounted on aluminum stubs, and sputter coated with gold. Specimens were then observed using a JSM-8404 microscope (S3400N; Hitachi Ltd).</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Y2H and BiFC assays</title><p>The yeast two-hybrid (Y2H) assay was performed according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (ProQuest two-hybrid system with Gateway technology; Invitrogen). The mutations in <italic>HDL</italic> (<italic>HDLm1</italic>, <italic>HDLm2</italic>, <italic>HDLm1m2</italic>, <italic>HDLmAD</italic>, <italic>HDLmADm1</italic>, <italic>HDLmADm2</italic>, and <italic>HDLmADm1m2</italic>) were introduced by PCR site-directed mutagenesis using appropriate primers as previously described (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Lin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013<italic>a</italic></xref>). For Y2H assay, the coding sequences of <italic>HDL</italic> and the mutant derivatives of <italic>HDL</italic>, <italic>HDLm1</italic>, <italic>HDLm2</italic>, <italic>HDLm1m2</italic>, <italic>HDLmAD</italic>, <italic>HDLmADm1</italic>, <italic>HDLmADm2</italic>, and <italic>HDLmADm1m2</italic> were cloned into pGADT7-GW (AD), and the coding sequences of <italic>MtTPL</italic> were cloned into pGBKT7-GW (BD) using the Gateway system (Invitrogen). The bait and prey plasmids were co-transformed into the Y2H gold yeast strain (Clontech). For the auxotrophic assay, yeast colonies were patched onto SD/-Leu/-Trp (DDO) and SD/-Trp/-Leu/-His/-Ade (QDO) plates, and grown in darkness at 28 &#x000b0;C for 3 d.</p><p>Bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) assays were conducted as described (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Lu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Briefly, <italic>HDL</italic>, <italic>HDLm1</italic>, <italic>HDLm2</italic>, <italic>HDLm1m2</italic>, <italic>HDLmAD</italic>, <italic>HDLmADm1</italic>, <italic>HDLmADm2</italic>, and <italic>HDLmADm1m2</italic> were cloned into pEARLEYGATE201-YN, while <italic>MtTPL</italic> and <italic>HDL</italic> were cloned into pEARLEYGATE202-YC by the LR reaction. HDL-YN, HDLm1-YN, HDLm2-YN, HDLm1m2-YN, HDLmAD-YN, HDLmADm1-YN, HDLmADm2-YN, HDLmADm1m2-YN, and MtTPL-YC, as well as HDL-YN and HDL-YC were introduced into <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain GV2260. Combinations of plasmids were simultaneously infiltrated into 3- to 4-week-old <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves. P19 was used to inhibit transgenic silencing. The fluorescence signal was observed with a confocal microscope (Zeiss LSM700) 48&#x02013;60 h after infiltration.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Transient luciferase expression assay</title><p>Construction of the reporter GAL4-LUC plasmid was described previously (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Lin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013<italic>a</italic></xref>). For effector plasmids, the coding sequences of <italic>HDL</italic> or <italic>HDL-VP64</italic> were first cloned into pGBKT7. Then the coding regions of the BD fusion were amplified using specific primers and cloned into p2GW7 using the Gateway system (Invitrogen) to yield effector plasmids. The transient expression assay was performed with Arabidopsis protoplasts as previously described (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Asai <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). For each transformation, 5 &#x000b5;g of reporter plasmid and 4 &#x000b5;g of effector plasmid were used. For normalization of the activity of the reporter gene, 0.5 &#x000b5;g of plasmid pRLC (<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>) was used as the internal control.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis</title><p>Amino acid sequences of HDL, ARRs, and homologs were aligned using Clustal W, and a Neighbor&#x02013;Joining phylogenetic tree was constructed using MEGA 4 software. The most parsimonious trees with bootstrap values from 1000 trials are shown.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Accession numbers or gene identifiers used in this study</title><p>Sequence data used in this study were retrieved from GenBank and can be found under the following accession numbers: <italic>HDL</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Medtr5g021930">Medtr5g021930</ext-link>), <italic>MtTPL</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Medtr4g009840">Medtr4g009840</ext-link>), <italic>STF</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Medtr8g107210">Medtr8g107210</ext-link>), <italic>LFL</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Medtr7g060630">Medtr7g060630</ext-link>), <italic>WUS</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At2g17950">At2g17950</ext-link>), <italic>WOX1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At3g18010">At3g18010</ext-link>), <italic>WOX2</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At5g59340">At5g59340</ext-link>), <italic>WOX3/PRS</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At2g28610">At2g28610</ext-link>), <italic>WOX4</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At1g46480">At1g46480</ext-link>), <italic>WOX5</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At3g11260">At3g11260</ext-link>), <italic>WOX6/PFS</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At2g01500">At2g01500</ext-link>), <italic>WOX7</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At5g05770">At5g05770</ext-link>), <italic>WOX8</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At5g45980">At5g45980</ext-link>), <italic>WOX9</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At2g33880">At2g33880</ext-link>), <italic>WOX10</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At1g20710">At1g20710</ext-link>), <italic>WOX11</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At3g03660">At3g03660</ext-link>), <italic>WOX12</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At5g17810">At5g17810</ext-link>), <italic>WOX13</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At4g35550">At4g35550</ext-link>), <italic>WOX14</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At1g20700">At1g20700</ext-link>), <italic>ARR3</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At1g59940">At1g59940</ext-link>), <italic>ARR4</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At1g10470">At1g10470</ext-link>), <italic>ARR5</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At3g48100">At3g48100</ext-link>), <italic>ARR6</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At5g62920">At5g62920</ext-link>), <italic>ARR7</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At1g19050">At1g19050</ext-link>), <italic>ARR9</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At3g57040">At3g57040</ext-link>), <italic>ARR15</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At1g74890">At1g74890</ext-link>), <italic>ARR16</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At2g40670">At2g40670</ext-link>), <italic>ARR17</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At3g56380">At3g56380</ext-link>), and <italic>ARR22</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://At3g04280">At3g04280</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Results</title><sec id="s14"><title>Identification and characterization of the <italic>M. truncatula headless</italic> mutant</title><p>To understand the molecular mechanisms that determine the development of the SAM in legumes, three identical SAM-defective mutants named <italic>headless</italic> (<italic>hdl-1</italic>, <italic>hdl-2</italic>, and <italic>hdl-3</italic>) with stemless and bushy phenotypes were identified from forward genetic screens of <italic>Tnt1</italic> retrotransposon-tagged lines of <italic>M. truncatula</italic> genotype R108 (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Tadege <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The <italic>hdl</italic> mutant never bolts in at least 2 years and continuously produces only leaves. In contrast, the wild-type R108 produces the first metamer within the first week of growth after germination, and takes ~6 weeks to form the first flowers. The <italic>hdl</italic> mutant plants show a range of obvious defects in meristem maintenance and leaf formation at the early seedling stage, which become apparent at the simple (unifoliate) leaf stage. <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> produces trifoliate leaves but the first true leaf, which probably has an embryonic origin, is always simple. In <italic>hdl</italic> mutants, the unifoliate leaf is either absent or significantly delayed in appearance compared with wild-type R108 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A&#x02013;D</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figs S1, S2A, B</xref>). Histological analysis showed that <italic>hdl</italic> mutants initiate a defective SAM that is essentially flat at the early stage of seedling development, leading to retarded growth compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E</xref>, F, 2A&#x02013;J). At a later stage, several leaf primordia are initiated ectopically from the abnormal shoot meristems on the flat apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2K</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">L</xref>). Gradually, more and more leaves start to form from the axil of cotyledons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S2A&#x02013;D</xref>) and axils of mutant leaves, but there is no apparent stem elongation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1G&#x02013;J</xref>). Moreover, dome-shaped structures (presumably ectopic meristems) are formed at the petiole base of older <italic>hdl</italic> leaves, and multiple leaves are initiated from these apical domes in a disorganized manner (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S2E</xref>). In addition, <italic>hdl</italic> mutants also show defects in axillary mersitem development which usually produce up to three leaves before the meristematic activity terminates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2M</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">N</xref>). Eventually the <italic>hdl</italic> mutants remain bushy and dwarf, being locked at the vegetative phase without any bolting or stem elongation throughout their life, appearing forever young at least for the 2 years that we tested, suggesting severe compromise in SAM organization and maintenance. Both the Arabidopsis <italic>wus-1</italic> and Petunia <italic>terminator</italic> (<italic>ter</italic>) mutants exhibit premature termination of the vegetative and floral meristems but display reiteration of ectopic meristems and leaves in a &#x02018;stop-and-go&#x02019; type of growth with stems and inflorescences (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Stuurman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). In addition, <italic>hdl</italic> mutant leaves lack leaf elongation in the longitudinal direction, leading to a reduced leaf tip and a heart-shaped blade morphology with increased width/length ratio compared with R108 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1K</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">L</xref>). Occasionally, the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant leaves show defects in the initiation of more than three leaflets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). These leaf phenotypes indicate that <italic>HDL</italic> may function in the determinate leaf primordia. These novel and conserved phenotypes of <italic>hdl</italic> mutants show that <italic>HDL</italic> function is highly relevant to SAM maintenance and regulation of leaf blade development in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Morphological comparison between the wild type and <italic>hdl</italic> plants. (A, B) Phenotype of the wild type (A) and <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant (B) at 3 days after germination (DAG). Scale bars=1 mm. (C, D) Phenotype comparison of the wild type (C) and <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant (D) at 8 DAG. The inset shows magnification of the shoot apex in <italic>hdl-1</italic>. Scale bars=1 cm. (E, F) Longitudinal sections of the wild type (E) and <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant (F) shoot apices at 3 DAG. Scale bars=100 &#x000b5;m. (G, H) Five-week-old wild-type (G) and <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant (H) plants. Scale bars=5 cm. (I, J) Close-up views of the basal part of wild-type (I) and <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant (J) plants in (G, H). Scale bars=1 cm. (K) Dissected leaves of the wild type and <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant. Scale bars=1 cm. (L) Comparison of leaf width/length ratio in the wild type and <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant. Bars represent means &#x000b1;SE (<italic>n</italic>=30 plants). The asterisks indicate significant differences (** <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01, Student <italic>t</italic>-test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34601"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Shoot meristem phenotypes of the <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant. (A&#x02013;D) Scanning electron micrographs of the wild-type (A) and <italic>hdl-1</italic> apices after germination for 12 h (B&#x02013;D). Scale bars=100 &#x000b5;m. (E&#x02013;H) Shoot apices of 4-day-old wild type (E) and <italic>hdl-1</italic> (F&#x02013;H). The red arrow points to the shoot apical meristem. Scale bars=100 &#x000b5;m. (I&#x02013;L) Shoot apices from 35-day-old wild-type (I) and <italic>hdl-1</italic> (J&#x02013;L) plants. Red arrows point to the shoot apical meristem, and white arrows indicate leaf primordia. Scale bars=100 &#x000b5;m. (M, N) Axillary buds from 35-day-old wild-type (M) and <italic>hdl-1</italic> (N) plants. Red arrows point to the axillary meristem. Scale bars=100 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34602"/></fig></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Molecular cloning and expression pattern of the <italic>HDL</italic> gene</title><p>We cloned the <italic>HDL</italic> gene by PCR-based genotyping of flanking sequence tags (FSTs) in segregating populations. Flanking sequence analysis of <italic>Tnt1</italic> retrotransposon in the <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant revealed that FST 17 segregated with the mutant phenotype. The <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant phenotype is determined by a single recessive gene, and all mutant plants genotyped homozygous for FST 17 show the phenotype representing the <italic>hdl</italic> locus. The genomic sequence of FST 17 (<italic>HDL</italic>) contains three exons, and the <italic>Tnt1</italic> retrotransposon is inserted at the beginning of exon 1, 19 bp downstream of the translational start in the <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). We further confirmed by PCR analysis that the other two identical phenotype mutants, <italic>hdl-2</italic> and <italic>hdl-3</italic>, are allelic to <italic>hdl-1</italic>, and found that both have <italic>Tnt1</italic> insertions at the same position in exon 3 of <italic>HDL</italic>, 1151 bp downstream of the translational start, even though <italic>hdl-2</italic> and <italic>hdl-3</italic> were identified from independent <italic>Tnt1</italic>-tagged lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). RT&#x02013;PCR analysis of the transcript in mutant seedlings revealed that the transcription of the full-length coding sequence of <italic>HDL</italic> is abolished in all three <italic>hdl</italic> mutants, while expression was clearly detected in the R108 control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). To confirm further that the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant phenotype is caused by the disruption of this locus, we crossed heterozygous <italic>hdl-1</italic> and <italic>hdl-2</italic> plants and generated <italic>hdl-1</italic>/<italic>+ hdl-2</italic>/<italic>+</italic> F<sub>1</sub> progeny, which displayed identical stemless phenotypes to <italic>hdl-1</italic> and <italic>hdl-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>), indicating that <italic>hdl-2</italic> and <italic>hdl-3</italic> are allelic to <italic>hdl-1</italic>. The identity of <italic>HDL</italic> was further confirmed by a mutant complementation test. The plasmid <italic>pHDL::HDL gDNA</italic> containing a 5.4 kb genomic DNA fragment consisting of a 2713 bp upstream sequence, the entire 1346 bp <italic>HDL</italic> gene including three exons and two introns, and a 1366 bp downstream region was introduced into the <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant. We also transformed the <italic>hdl-1</italic> line with the <italic>p35S::HDL</italic> (CDS) construct. Phenotypic examination of transgenic plants showed that the <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant is complemented by the <italic>pHDL::HDL</italic> construct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C&#x02013;J</xref>), while it is poorly rescued by the <italic>p35S::HDL</italic> construct. The <italic>p35S::HDL</italic> transgenic plants show partial recovery of bolting, but the leaf shape is even more poorly restored compared with the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S5</xref>), suggesting that HDL function is orchestrated by its specific spatiotemporal expression pattern.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Molecular cloning of the <italic>HDL</italic> gene. (A) Schematic representation of the gene structure of <italic>HDL</italic> showing the <italic>Tnt1</italic> insertion sites in <italic>hdl</italic> mutants. (B) RT&#x02013;PCR analysis of <italic>HDL</italic> transcripts in the wild-type (WT) and <italic>hdl</italic> alleles. (C&#x02013;E) Phenotypes of wild-type (C), <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant (D), and T<sub>1</sub> transgenic seedlings of <italic>hdl-1</italic> complemented with <italic>pHDL::HDL</italic> (E). Scale bars=5 cm. (F, G) Magnification of the indicated region in (C, E), respectively. Scale bar=1 cm. (H&#x02013;J) Dissected leaves of wild-type (H), <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant (I), and T<sub>1</sub> transgenic seedlings of <italic>hdl-1</italic> complemented with <italic>pHDL::HDL</italic> (J). Scale bars=0.5 cm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34603"/></fig><p>Sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis revealed that <italic>HDL</italic> encodes a 302 amino acid WOX family homeodomain transcriptional regulator with 40% amino acid identity to Arabidopsis WUS (Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Fig. S6</xref>). The predicted HDL protein contains the highly conserved homeodomain near the N-terminus, an identical WUS-box, as well as an EAR-like motif and acidic region at the C-terminal region (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>) similar to WUS. RNA <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization in the vegetative shoot apex of wild-type R108 revealed that <italic>HDL</italic> is specifically expressed in the central region of the SAM and the axillary meristem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">B</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S8</xref>), which is consistent with previous reports (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Kurdyukov <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Interestingly, <italic>HDL</italic> expression is also detected in the central/joint region of leaf primordia at the P3 stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). In the older primordia stage P4, <italic>HDL</italic> is expressed in the proximal&#x02013;distal axis of the leaf blade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>) and at the joint region of the leaflets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">D</xref>). These specific expression patterns of <italic>HDL</italic> are consistent with its function in regulating SAM maintenance and leaf blade development during <italic>M. truncatula</italic> shoot morphogenesis.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Expression pattern of <italic>HDL</italic> and subcellular localization of the HDL protein. (A) <italic>HDL</italic> expression by mRNA <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization in 4-week-old vegetative shoot apex viewed in longitudinal sections. SAM, shoot apical meristem; AM, axillary meristem. P1&#x02013;P4 indicate different leaf primordia stages. Arrowheads point to signals. Scale bar=50 &#x003bc;m. (B) <italic>In situ</italic> hybridization of <italic>HDL</italic> in the cross-section of the vegetative shoot apex. SAM, shoot apical meristem; TL, terminal leaflet; LL, lateral leaflet; St, stipule. P3&#x02013;P5 indicate different leaf primordia stages. Arrowheads point to signals. Scale bar=50 &#x003bc;m. (C) <italic>In situ</italic> hybridization of <italic>HDL</italic> in the longitudinal section of P4 leaf primordia. TL, terminal leaflet. P2 and P4 indicate different leaf primordia stages. Arrowheads point to signals. Scale bar=50 &#x003bc;m. (D) <italic>In situ</italic> hybridization of <italic>HDL</italic> in the cross-section of P4 leaf primordia. TL, terminal leaflet; LL, lateral leaflet; St, stipule. Arrowheads point to signals. Scale bar=50 &#x003bc;m. (E) Subcellular localization of <italic>35S::GFP</italic> and <italic>35S::HDL-GFP</italic> in tobacco epidermal cells. Nuclear protein AHL22 was used as a nuclear localization marker. Scale bars=50 &#x000b5;m. (F) BiFC assay showing that HDL could form a homodimer. YN indicates the N-terminal half of YFP and YC indicates the C-terminal half of YFP. Nuclear protein AHL22 was used as a nuclear localization marker. Scale bars=50 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34604"/></fig></sec><sec id="s16"><title>
<italic>HDL</italic> encodes a nuclear-localized transcriptional repressor</title><p>To determine the subcellular localization of the HDL protein, we fused the C-terminus of HDL with green fluorescent protein (GFP) under the control of the <italic>Cauliflower mosaic virus</italic> (CaMV) 35S promoter, and the construct was transferred into tobacco (<italic>N. benthamiana</italic>) leaf epidermal cells by the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> infiltration method. In contrast to the GFP control, which is localized to both the cytoplasm and nucleus of epidermal cells, the HDL&#x02013;GFP fusion protein was localized in the nucleus (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4E</xref>). In addition, we found that HDL could form a homodimer in the nucleus through BiFC analysis using split yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4F</xref>), which is consistent with previous reports that WUS homodimerization is possibly important for its regulation of stem cell activity (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Daum <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).</p><p>To investigate whether HDL functions as a transcriptional activator or repressor, we examined its transcriptional activity by dual luciferase transient expression assay in Arabidopsis protoplasts. The effector plasmid was constructed by fusing the GAL4 DNA-binding domain to the N-terminus of HDL, and the reporter plasmid contained the luciferase (<italic>LUC</italic>) gene fused to a 5&#x000d7;GAL4-binding site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>). Bioluminescence measurements showed that luciferase activity is reduced by ~2-fold in the presence of HDL effector protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>), indicating its strong repressive activity. These results are consistent with previous findings that Arabidopsis <italic>WUS</italic> encodes a nuclear-localized transcriptional repressor (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Kieffer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>HDL exhibits transcriptional repressive activity. (A) Schematic representation of reporter and effector constructs used in the transient expression assay. (B) Relative luciferase activities measured as bioluminescence in Arabidopsis protoplasts. Error bars represent the SE of three replicate assays. The asterisks indicate significant differences (**<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01, Student <italic>t</italic>-test). (C&#x02013;H) Phenotypes of wild-type (C, E, G) and <italic>p35S::HDL-VP64</italic> transgenic plants (D, F, H). (G) and (H) are magnifications of the indicated regions in (E) and (F), respectively. Scale bars=5 cm in (C&#x02013;F), 1 cm in (G, H).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34605"/></fig><p>To confirm the repressive function of HDL in the regulation of SAM maintenance and leaf blade development, we fused the exogenous activation domain VP64 to the C-terminus of HDL, which reduces its repressive activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">B</xref>), under the control of the 35S promoter and transformed this construct into <italic>M. truncatula</italic> ecotype R108. We found that 16 of 21 <italic>p35S::HDL-VP64</italic> transgenic plants exhibited reduced apical dominance as well as heart-shaped blade morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C&#x02013;H</xref>), which partially mimic phenotypes of the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant, indicating a dominant negative effect of the chimeric HDL&#x02013;VP64 in SAM and leaf development. This is not caused by co-suppression as the endogenous <italic>HDL</italic> transcript level is not altered (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S9</xref>), but by the antagonistic activation activity of VP64. Taken together, these results indicate that HDL may mainly act as a transcriptional repressor in regulating <italic>M. truncatula</italic> SAM maintenance and leaf development.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>HDL physically interacts with the co-repressor MtTPL protein using its conserved WUS-box and EAR-like motif</title><p>Since there is a conserved WUS-box and EAR-like motif in the C-terminus of HDL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>; Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Fig. S7</xref>), we examined the interaction between HDL and the co-repressor MtTPL by performing Y2H and BiFC assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">C</xref>). We found that HDL interacts with MtTPL in the nucleus reconstituting the yellow fluorescence when both HDL-YN and MtTPL-YC proteins are transiently expressed in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaf epidermal cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>). This interaction between HDL and MtTPL in split YFP is consistent with the Y2H analysis in quadruple drop-out medium (QDO) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>). Moreover, we found that either substitution of acidic amino acids in the acidic region (mAD) or mutation of leucine residues in the WUS-box and the EAR-like motif alone does not obviously reduce its interaction with MtTPL, but combined mutations in both the WUS-box and EAR-like motif abolish the interaction with Mt-TPL in Y2H assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>). This finding was further verified by BiFC assay, in which the HDLm1m2-YN coupled with MtTPL-YC fails to generate YFP signals despite both proteins being stably expressed in tobacco cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S10</xref>), demonstrating that both the WUS-box and EAR-like motif are required for the HDL interaction with MtTPL.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>HDL physically interacts with the co-repressor MtTPL through its conserved WUS-box and EAR-like motif. (A) Sequence of the acidic region, WUS-box, and C-terminal EAR-like motif in the HDL protein. Mutations introduced into the acidic region (mAD), WUS-box (m1), and EAR-like motif (m2) are indicated by red fonts. (B, C) Identification of HDL domains required for interaction with MtTPL by the yeast two-hybrid system and BiFC assay. DDO indicates SD/-Leu/-Trp; QDO indicates SD/-Trp/-Leu/-His/-Ade; YN indicates the N-terminal half of YFP, and YC indicates the C-terminal half of YFP. Nuclear protein AHL22 was used as a nuclear localization marker. Scale bars=50 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34606"/></fig></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Transcript abundance of A-type cytokinin-responsive genes in shoot apices of the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant</title><p>The <italic>ARR</italic> genes have been reported to be direct targets of WUS, and the transcript of several A-type cytokinin-responsive genes including <italic>ARR5</italic>, <italic>ARR6</italic>, <italic>ARR7</italic>, and <italic>ARR15</italic> is up-regulated in the Arabidopsis <italic>wus</italic> mutant (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Leibfried <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Because HDL functions similarly to WUS in regulating shoot meristem development, we wondered whether this would be the case in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> as well. A total of 11 putative A-type cytokinin response regulators were isolated using the Arabidopsis A-type ARR proteins as a BLAST query in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) and J. Craig Venter Institute (JCVI) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>). We found that the expression levels of 4 out of 11 type-A ARR family members are considerably increased in <italic>hdl-1</italic> shoot apices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig.7B</xref>). Among them, from the phylogenic analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>), it was found that Medtr4g106590 and Medtr3g078613 are close to ARR7 and ARR15, while Medtr3g015490 and Medtr8g038620 group together with ARR9. The up-regulation of ARR7 and ARR15 homologs in <italic>hdl</italic> is consistent with the finding in the Arabidopsis <italic>wus-1</italic> mutant (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Leibfried <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) and suggests that HDL may modulate the cytokinin response for its function in meristem maintenance. We also found that 3 out of 11 type-A ARR family members, Medtr1g049100, Medtr5g036480, and Medtr4g051330, are slightly down-regulated in <italic>hdl-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>), suggesting that <italic>HDL</italic> has a complex relationship with these cytokinin signaling response regulators.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>Transcript abundance of A-type cytokinin-responsive genes in the <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant. (A) Phylogenetic analysis of A-type cytokinin-responsive regulators in Arabidopsis and <italic>M. truncatula</italic>. (B) Transcript levels of A-type cytokinin-responsive genes in shoot apices of the <italic>hdl-1</italic> mutant. Error bars represent the SE of three replicate experiments. The asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01, Student <italic>t</italic>-test) compared with the wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34607"/></fig></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Genetic analysis of <italic>HDL</italic> and <italic>STF</italic> in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> leaf development</title><p>We previously reported that the <italic>M. truncatula</italic> WOX gene <italic>STF</italic> mainly functions as a transcriptional repressor in regulating leaf blade outgrowth (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Tadege <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Lin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013<italic>a</italic></xref>). The obvious leaf phenotype of <italic>hdl</italic> and the fact that both HDL and STF act as transcriptional repressors by interacting with the co-repressor MtTPL prompted us to test the genetic relationship between <italic>HDL</italic> and <italic>STF</italic> in regulating leaf development in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>. We generated the <italic>hdl-1 stf</italic> double mutant using heterozygotes and compared the phenotypes of single and double mutants <italic>hdl-1</italic>, <italic>stf</italic>, and <italic>hdl-1 stf</italic>. Compared with the single mutants, the <italic>hdl-1 stf</italic> double mutant shows an additive effect combining the <italic>hdl</italic> stemless phenotype and the <italic>stf</italic> narrow leaf phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>). In the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant, the elongation of the leaf tip is reduced, leading to a heart-shaped leaf with an increased width/length ratio. In the <italic>stf</italic> mutant, the leaf length elongation is virtually unaffected and the distal leaf tip is characteristically pointed due to absence of lateral expansion, but in the <italic>hdl-1 stf</italic> double mutant, leaves show a combination of the narrow blade, distorted margin, and pointed tip of <italic>stf</italic>, and the reduced blade length of <italic>hdl</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>), suggesting that HDL and STF may function in independent genetic pathways in leaf development. In agreement with this genetic analysis, quantitative RT&#x02013;PCR analysis showed that the expression level of <italic>STF</italic> is not significantly changed in the young leaves of <italic>hdl</italic> compared with the wild type, and vice versa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">C</xref>). As <italic>STF</italic> regulates leaf lateral extension by partially repressing the expression of the adaxial polarity factor <italic>ASYMMETRIC LEAVES2</italic> (<italic>AS2</italic>) through its interaction with MtTPL in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, the expression of <italic>MtAS2</italic> was further compared in <italic>hdl-1</italic>, <italic>stf</italic>, and <italic>hdl-1 stf</italic>. Quantitative RT&#x02013;PCR results showed that there is no obvious change of <italic>MtAS2</italic> expression in <italic>hdl-1</italic> young leaves compared with the wild type, and expression of <italic>MtAS2</italic> in the <italic>hdl-1 stf</italic> double mutant is similar to that in <italic>stf</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8D</xref>). These results suggest that HDL and STF have distinct functions in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> leaf blade development.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p>Genetic analysis of <italic>HDL</italic> and <italic>STF</italic> in regulating leaf development. (A) Phenotype analysis of the wild type, <italic>hdl-1</italic>, <italic>stf</italic>, and the <italic>hdl-1 stf</italic> double mutant. Scale bars=1 cm. (B&#x02013;D) Transcript levels of <italic>HDL</italic> (B), <italic>STF</italic> (C), and <italic>MtAS2</italic> (D) in young leaves of the wild type, <italic>hdl-1</italic>, <italic>stf</italic>, and the <italic>hdl-1 stf</italic> double mutant. Error bars represent the SE of three replicate experiments. The asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, Student <italic>t</italic>-test) compared with the wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34608"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Discussion</title><p>
<italic>WUSCHEL</italic> is the founding member of the WOX family and plays an essential role in maintaining stem cell identity in the SAM of plants (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Mayer <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">van der Graaff <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Although this key stem cell regulator has been isolated and to some extent characterized from several plant species, its actual function is described by a genetic mutation only in a couple of cases apart from Arabidopsis, which are not necessarily telling the same story. In this study, we described an <italic>M. truncatula</italic> stemless and bushy mutant named <italic>headless</italic> (<italic>hdl</italic>), in which shoot meristem maintenance is disrupted by <italic>Tnt1</italic> retrotransposon insertion in the exons of the <italic>HDL</italic> gene. <italic>HDL</italic> encodes a nuclear-localized homeodomain transcription factor closely related to Arabidopsis WUS. Loss of <italic>HDL</italic> function led to arrested and disorganized shoot meristem development including the SAM and any axillary meristems, resulting in a stemless phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1G&#x02013;J</xref>). The only visible above-ground structures in the mutant are leaves and stipules at all stages of development, but the leaves also show a characteristic heart shape compared with the more oval-shaped blade in the wild-type R108, unlike any of the reported <italic>wus-1</italic>, <italic>ter</italic>, and <italic>roa</italic> mutants (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Stuurman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Kieffer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Wild-type <italic>M. truncatula</italic> shows a trailing type of growth (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Bucciarelli <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) in which the SAM first produces a single unifoliate leaf after germination, followed by establishment of a central growth axis. The central growth axis then produces four trifoliate leaves in close succession and at the axils of each leaf is an axillary meristem (the fourth leaf of which is the SAM), which develop into growing units called metamers (main stems), each with elongating internodes, trifoliate leaves, and axillary buds (meristems). These axillary meristems have the potential to grow into secondary metamers and may branch out until terminated later with the development of the inflorescence meristem, giving rise to a prostrate habit. The <italic>hdl</italic> mutant partially fails in the formation of the unifoliate leaf as some of the mutant plants skip this first leaf altogether, and completely fails in the proper establishment of the central growth axis. The <italic>hdl</italic> SAM appears essentially flat 3 d after germination, while the wild type has a clear apical dome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">F</xref>). Gradually, a disorganized SAM starts to form in <italic>hdl</italic> with fewer cells, producing fewer trifoliate leaves (two or three) around it, but perhaps all the meristematic cells are consumed in making the leaves, and the SAM is unable to replenish itself to maintain a central axis with a rib meristem. However, unorganized ectopic meristems are formed at the leaf axils, reminiscent of axillary meristems in the wild type, but again these end up forming only leaves instead of metamers, and the cycle continues with indefinite proliferation of leaves, giving the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant a bushy and &#x02018;forever young&#x02019; appearance. These results indicate that <italic>HDL</italic> is a key regulator required for organization and maintenance of the SAM and axillary meristems in <italic>M. truncatula.</italic> Recent studies also showed that Arabidopsis <italic>WUS</italic> is not only necessary for SAM maintenance but is also required for AM initiation. Nevertheless, the <italic>hdl</italic> meristem phenotypes appear to be stronger than the Arabidopsis <italic>wus-1</italic> and the equivalent Petunia <italic>ter</italic> phenotypes. Both the <italic>wus-1</italic> and <italic>ter</italic> SAMs are correctly specified at the beginning, and mutants are indistinguishable at the early seedling stage from their corresponding wild-type seedlings, but the meristem terminates prematurely (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Stuurman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), and that is where the phenotypes become obvious. Not only that, but the SAM re-establishes itself and resumes growth in both cases, producing vegetative and inflorescence stems in a &#x02018;stop-and-go&#x02019; type of growth (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Stuurman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). In addition, ectopic meristems in <italic>wus-1</italic> mutants form aerial rosettes and inflorescences, reiterating growth (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>). For this reason, WUS is thought to be neither necessary nor sufficient for stem cell specification (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Green <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Our results highlight that <italic>M. truncatula HDL</italic> is necessary for both correct specification and maintenance of the SAM and axillary meristems since all shoot meristems are completely abrogated in the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant, uncovering novel insights in meristem biology. In rice, the ortholog of <italic>WUS</italic>, <italic>MONOCULM 3</italic> (<italic>MOC3</italic>)/<italic>TILLERS ABSENT1</italic> (<italic>TAB1</italic>), has been shown to be required for the maintenance of the pre-meristem zone and the formation of axillary meristem instead of the SAM (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Lu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Disruption of <italic>MOC3</italic>/<italic>TAB1</italic> leads to axillary meristem arrest, resulting in a monoculm phenotype with a normal culm (primary stem) (<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), suggesting diversification of <italic>WUS</italic> functions in regulating the stem cell niche in monocot species.</p><p>In Arabidopsis, the WUS protein acts mainly as a repressor in stem cell regulation, and the WUS-box is the essential repressive domain (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Sequence alignment reveals that the HDL protein contains a conserved WUS-box and EAR-like motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>; Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Fig. S7</xref>). We found that HDL exhibits a strong repressive activity and physically interacts with the transcriptional co-repressor MtTPL using the conserved WUS-box and EAR-like motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">C</xref>), suggesting that HDL is also primarily a transcriptional repressor. This is consistent with the proposal that all WUS/modern clade WOX members with the conserved WUS-box may primarily function as transcriptional repressors through forming a WOX&#x02013;TPL repressor complex shown for WOX1 and WOX3 homologs, STF and LFL (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Lin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Niu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). This WOX&#x02013;TPL interaction was also recently reported to be important for WOX5 function in the Arabidopsis root apical meristem, suggesting a role in columella stem cell maintenance (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Pi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Moreover, we found that the HDL protein could form a homodimer, which is consistent with the previous report that the formation of WUS dimers might contribute to the regulation of shoot apical stem cell activity (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Daum <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).</p><p>The phytohormone cytokinin plays an essential role in regulating plant developmental programs including meristem function. A previous report showed that disruption of the <italic>LONELY GUY</italic> (<italic>LOG</italic>) gene, which encodes a cytokinin-activating enzyme, causes the arrest of SAM activity in rice (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Kurakawa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). In maize, mutation of the cytokinin-inducible gene <italic>ABPHYL1</italic> (<italic>ABPH1</italic>) leads to increased meristem size. ABPH1 is homologous to two-component response regulators and is proposed to play a role in negative regulation of cytokinin response (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Giulini <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). In the Arabidopsis shoot meristem, <italic>KNOX</italic> and <italic>WUS</italic> promote meristem activity in part through activating cytokinin signaling (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Jasinski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Shani <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Cytokinin signaling activates <italic>WUS</italic> transcription (<xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>; H. <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), and <italic>WUS</italic> in turn activates direct repression of type-A ARR negative regulators of cytokinin signaling (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Leibfried <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Our results showed that four genes related to <italic>ARR7</italic>, <italic>ARR9</italic>, and <italic>ARR15</italic> are significantly up-regulated in the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant shoot apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>, B), suggesting that <italic>HDL</italic> is required for repressing type-A <italic>ARR</italic> genes in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> shoot meristems. It is likely that <italic>WUS</italic> and <italic>HDL</italic> share this conserved mechanism to modulate cytokinin signaling for stem cell maintenance in their respective SAMs. However, we also noted that other type-A response regulators including <italic>Medtr1g049100</italic>, <italic>Medtr5g036480</italic>, and <italic>Medtr4g051330</italic>, related to <italic>ARR3</italic>, <italic>ARR4</italic>, and <italic>ARR9</italic>, respectively, are down-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>, B), necessitating further characterization of these genes in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>. Whether species-specific sensitivity variation in the cytokinin signal or the diversity of cytokinin response regulators and their effect in modulating the cytokinin signal, or others factors unrelated to cytokinin signaling, contribute to the complete arrest of the SAM and axillary meristems in <italic>hdl</italic> mutants compared with <italic>wus-1</italic> mutants is unknown at this stage. The mechanism by which <italic>HDL</italic> regulates leaf shape in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> also remains to be elucidated.</p><p>It has been reported that <italic>WOX1</italic>, <italic>WOX3</italic>, and their orthologs are major regulators in controlling lateral leaf blade outgrowth in diverse eudicot and monocot plants (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Scanlon <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Nardmann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Vandenbussche <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Tadege <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Nakata <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">Zhuang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Cho <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Ishiwata <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Although the primary function of <italic>WUS</italic> is regulating the maintenance of vegetative and inflorescence meristems (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Laux <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Mayer <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), it is also involved in ovule development and floral patterning in the differentiated floral organs (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Lohmann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Other clues also implicate that the founding member of the WOX family may be involved in leaf blade development. We previously showed that the leaf blade phenotypes of <italic>stf</italic> in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> and <italic>lam1</italic> in <italic>N. sylvestris</italic> could be fully restored by expressing Arabidopsis <italic>WUS</italic> under the control of the <italic>STF</italic> promoter (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Tadege <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Lin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013<italic>a</italic></xref>), suggesting that <italic>WUS</italic> can function in determinate leaf primordia, and the leaf and shoot apical meristems might share a common mechanism. It is even likely that WUS has a redundant function in leaf blade development with other <italic>WOX</italic> genes. The <italic>wox1 prs wus</italic> triple mutant exhibits a noticeably narrower leaf blade compared with the <italic>wox1 prs</italic> double mutant, implicating that <italic>WUS</italic> might function in regulating leaf lateral blade outgrowth in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Tadege, 2015</xref>), although this has not been investigated in detail. However, in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, the mutation of <italic>HDL</italic> results in clearly altered leaf shape, changing from a more or less oval shape in R108 to heart-shaped blades in the mutant, suggesting that <italic>HDL</italic> may regulate leaf development in the proximal&#x02013;distal axis in contrast to the role of <italic>STF</italic> in regulating blade outgrowth in the medial&#x02013;lateral axis. We found that the <italic>stf hdl</italic> double mutant leaf phenotypes are additive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>), suggesting independent genetic pathways for leaf width and length growth in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>. It is possible that the <italic>WUS/HDL</italic> function in stem cell maintenance or lateral organ patterning may depend on dosage, targets, and the microenvironment. Identification of downstream targets of <italic>HDL</italic> responsible for leaf development will shed light on understanding the underlying molecular mechanism of HDL function in leaf length regulation and any commonalities that exist with its major function in meristem maintenance.</p><p>A potential problem in the recruitment of leaf primordia founder initial cells was seen at the early seedling stage where establishment of the unifoliate leaf is significantly delayed or sometimes blocked. However, once the first true leaves are formed, this problem appears to dissipate and the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant leaves maintain their trifoliate identity, suggesting that the <italic>hdl</italic> leaf shape phenotype is unlikely to be caused by defects in the recruitment of leaf primordia founder initials from the SAM. Occasionally, leaves may acquire extra leaflets but, in most cases, trifoliate leaves are continuously formed from the <italic>hdl</italic> SAM and axillary meristems. However, in doing so, the stem cells are fully consumed and unable to replenish themselves. Similar to <italic>WUS</italic>, <italic>HDL</italic> may not be required for SAM initiation (<xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>) but, unlike the <italic>wus-1</italic> mutant, normal SAM function is never observed in the extended life of the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant, suggesting that the central zone and the rib zone of the SAM are probably defective from the outset. These observations suggest that <italic>M. truncatula HDL</italic> is required for both shoot meristem organization and stem cell maintenance, as well as for leaf elongation in the length direction but not for allocation of leaf founder cells from the stem cell pool, uncovering novel aspects of meristem biology.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s21"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>Supplementary data are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p><p>Fig. S1. The <italic>hdl</italic> mutant shows a defect in leaf outgrowth.</p><p>Fig. S2. The <italic>hdl</italic> mutant exhibits a loss of apical dominance phenotype.</p><p>Fig. S3. The <italic>hdl</italic> mutant plants occasionally show defects in the initiation of leaflets.</p><p>Fig. S4. Genetic analysis of <italic>hdl-1</italic> and <italic>hdl-2</italic> mutants.</p><p>Fig. S5. Complementation of the <italic>hdl</italic> mutant with <italic>p35S::HDL.</italic></p><p>Fig. S6. Phylogenetic analysis of WOX family proteins in Arabidopsis and <italic>M. truncatula</italic>.</p><p>Fig. S7. Sequence alignment of HDL and Arabidopsis WUSCHEL.</p><p>Fig. S8. <italic>In situ</italic> hybridization analysis using the control sense <italic>HDL</italic> probe.</p><p>Fig. S9. Transcript abundance of endogenous <italic>HDL</italic> and exogenous <italic>HDL-VP64</italic> in <italic>p35S::HDL-VP64</italic> transgenic plants.</p><p>Fig. S10. Subcellular localization of the mutated HDL proteins.</p><p>Table S1. Primers used in this study.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Figures S1-S10 and Table S1</label><media xlink:href="ery346_suppl_supplementary_figures_s1-s10_table_s1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Professor Richard Dixon for providing p2GW7 and pRLC plasmids. This work was supported by grants from Ministry of Science and Technology of the People&#x02019;s Republic of China (2016YFD0101001 and 2015CB150103), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31570309 and 31770347), Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Non-profit Scientific Institution (Y2018LM04), Xinjiang Key R&#x00026;D Program (2018B01006-3 and 2018E02053), and the Capital Science and Beijing Municipal Science and Technology Commission (lj201812). Development of <italic>M. truncatula Tnt1</italic> insertion lines and forward genetic screenings were supported by the National Science Foundation, USA (DBI 0703285 and IOS-1127155) and The Noble Research Institute. The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></ack><sec id="s22"><title>Author contributions</title><p>YM, LN, and HL conceived and designed the research. YM, HL, HW, YL, BZ, ZW, YH, PZ, and HY performed the experiments. YM, HL, HW, MT, LN, and HL analyzed the data. JW, KM, JC, and MT contributed analytical tools. YM, LN, MT, and HL wrote the manuscript. This work has not been submitted elsewhere for publication, and all authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tena</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plotnikova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willmann</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Gomez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>MAP kinase signalling cascade in Arabidopsis innate immunity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>415</volume>, <fpage>977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>983</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11875555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Twenty years on: the inner workings of the shoot apical meristem, a developmental dynamo</article-title>. <source>Developmental Biology</source><volume>341</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19961843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hobe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Dependence of stem cell fate in Arabidopsis on a feedback loop regulated by <italic>CLV3</italic> activity</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>289</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>619</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10915624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucciarelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmquist</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>A standardized method for analysis of <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> phenotypic development</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>142</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16877701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miotk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ariel</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional control of a plant stem cell niche</article-title>. <source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>18</volume>, <fpage>849</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>861</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20493817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Causier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The TOPLESS interactome: a framework for gene repression in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>158</volume>, <fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22065421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Conserved genetic determinant of motor organ identity in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> and related legumes</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>109</volume>, <fpage>11723</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11728</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurdyukov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kereszt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gresshoff</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>The association of homeobox gene expression with stem cell formation and morphogenesis in cultured <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>230</volume>, <fpage>827</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>840</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19639337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandeya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The rice <italic>narrow leaf2</italic> and <italic>narrow leaf3</italic> loci encode WUSCHEL-related homeobox 3A (OsWOX3A) and function in leaf, spikelet, tiller and lateral root development</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source><volume>198</volume>, <fpage>1071</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1084</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23551229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>The <italic>CLAVATA1</italic> gene encodes a putative receptor kinase that controls shoot and floral meristem size in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>89</volume>, <fpage>575</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>585</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9160749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costanzo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trehin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenbussche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The role of WOX genes in flower development</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>114</volume>, <fpage>1545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1553</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24973416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daum</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medzihradszky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>A mechanistic framework for noncell autonomous stem cell induction in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>111</volume>, <fpage>14619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14624</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolzblasz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nardmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clerici</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Causier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Graaff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Stem cell regulation by Arabidopsis WOX genes</article-title>. <source>Molecular Plant</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1028</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1039</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27109605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Running</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Signaling of cell fate decisions by <italic>CLAVATA3</italic> in Arabidopsis shoot meristems</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>283</volume>, <fpage>1911</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1914</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10082464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prigge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katzman</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title><italic>CORONA</italic>, a member of the class III homeodomain leucine zipper gene family in Arabidopsis, regulates stem cell specification and organogenesis</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>17</volume>, <fpage>691</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>704</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15705957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giulini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Control of phyllotaxy by the cytokinin-inducible response regulator homologue <italic>ABPHYL1</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>430</volume>, <fpage>1031</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1034</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15329722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>A group of receptor kinases are essential for CLAVATA signalling to maintain stem cell homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Nature Plants</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29581511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohme-Takagi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Arabidopsis WUSCHEL is a bifunctional transcription factor that acts as a repressor in stem cell regulation and as an activator in floral patterning</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>21</volume>, <fpage>3493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3505</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishiwata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Two <italic>WUSCHEL</italic>-related homeobox genes, <italic>narrow leaf2</italic> and <italic>narrow leaf3</italic>, control leaf width in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant &#x00026; Cell Physiology</source><volume>54</volume>, <fpage>779</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>792</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23420902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jasinski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piazza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craft</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woolley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rieu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsiantis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title><italic>KNOX</italic> action in Arabidopsis is mediated by coordinate regulation of cytokinin and gibberellin activities</article-title>. <source>Current Biology</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1560</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1565</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16139211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kayes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title><italic>CLAVATA2</italic>, a regulator of meristem and organ development in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source><volume>125</volume>, <fpage>3843</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3851</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9729492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clerici</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maulbetsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Analysis of the transcription factor WUSCHEL and its functional homologue in Antirrhinum reveals a potential mechanism for their roles in meristem maintenance</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>18</volume>, <fpage>560</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>573</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16461579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Betsuyaku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osakabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>RPK2 is an essential receptor-like kinase that transmits the <italic>CLV3</italic> signal in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source><volume>137</volume>, <fpage>3911</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3920</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20978082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kakimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakagami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>A plant peptide encoded by <italic>CLV3</italic> identified by in situ MALDI-TOF MS analysis</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>313</volume>, <fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>848</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16902141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kyozuka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Direct control of shoot meristem activity by a cytokinin-activating enzyme</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>445</volume>, <fpage>652</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>655</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17287810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurdyukov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheahan</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional regulation of early embryo development in the model legume <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Reports</source><volume>33</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24258241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>J&#x000fc;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>The <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> gene is required for shoot and floral meristem integrity in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source><volume>122</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8565856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leibfried</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>To</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stehling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kehle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kieber</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title><italic>WUSCHEL</italic> controls meristem function by direct regulation of cytokinin-inducible response regulators</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>438</volume>, <fpage>1172</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16372013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>J&#x000fc;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Termination of stem cell maintenance in Arabidopsis floral meristems by interactions between <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> and <italic>AGAMOUS</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>105</volume>, <fpage>805</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>814</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11440722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McHale</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohme-Takagi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mysore</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year><italic>a</italic>
<article-title>Evolutionarily conserved repressive activity of WOX proteins mediates leaf blade outgrowth and floral organ development in plants</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>110</volume>, <fpage>366</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>371</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year><italic>b</italic>
<article-title>STENOFOLIA acts as a repressor in regulating leaf blade outgrowth</article-title>. <source>Plant Signaling &#x00026; Behavior</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e24464</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23603965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hobe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parcy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>A molecular link between stem cell regulation and floral patterning in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>105</volume>, <fpage>793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>803</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11440721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Arabidopsis homolog of the yeast TREX-2 mRNA export complex: components and anchoring nucleoporin</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>61</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>270</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19843313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title><italic>MONOCULM 3</italic>, an ortholog of <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> in rice, is required for tiller bud formation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Genetics and Genomics</source><volume>42</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25697101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>A homeobox gene, <italic>PRESSED FLOWER</italic>, regulates lateral axis-dependent development of Arabidopsis flowers</article-title>. <source>Genes &#x00026; Development</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>3355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3364</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoof</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haecker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>J&#x000fc;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Role of <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> in regulating stem cell fate in the Arabidopsis shoot meristem</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>95</volume>, <fpage>805</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>815</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9865698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Targeted mutagenesis by CRISPR/Cas9 system in the model legume <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Reports</source><volume>36</volume>, <fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27834007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bleckmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The receptor kinase CORYNE of Arabidopsis transmits the stem cell-limiting signal <italic>CLAVATA3</italic> independently of <italic>CLAVATA1</italic></article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>20</volume>, <fpage>934</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>946</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18381924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsugeki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rikirsch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Roles of the middle domain-specific <italic>WUSCHEL-RELATED HOMEOBOX</italic> genes in early development of leaves in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>24</volume>, <fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22374393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scanlon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The maize duplicate <italic>genes narrow sheath1</italic> and <italic>narrow sheath2</italic> encode a conserved homeobox gene function in a lateral domain of shoot apical meristems</article-title>. <source>Development</source><volume>131</volume>, <fpage>2827</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2839</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15169755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The shoot stem cell niche in angiosperms: expression patterns of <italic>WUS</italic> orthologues in rice and maize imply major modifications in the course of mono- and dicot evolution</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2492</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2504</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16987950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watira</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mysore</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title><italic>LOOSE FLOWER</italic>, a <italic>WUSCHEL</italic>-like homeobox gene, is required for lateral fusion of floral organs in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>81</volume>, <fpage>480</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25492397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakagami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Arabidopsis CLV3 peptide directly binds CLV1 ectodomain</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>319</volume>, <fpage>294</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18202283</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa-Ohnishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>A glycopeptide regulating stem cell fate in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature Chemical Biology</source><volume>5</volume>, <fpage>578</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19525968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aichinger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Graaff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Llavata-Peris</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weijers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hennig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Organizer-derived <italic>WOX5</italic> signal maintains root columella stem cells through chromatin-mediated repression of <italic>CDF4</italic> expression</article-title>. <source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>33</volume>, <fpage>576</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>588</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26028217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riou-Khamlichi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacqmard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Cytokinin activation of Arabidopsis cell division through a D-type cyclin</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>283</volume>, <fpage>1541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1544</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10066178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luijten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heidstra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Conserved factors regulate signalling in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> shoot and root stem cell organizers</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>446</volume>, <fpage>811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>814</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17429400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scanlon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneeberger</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>The maize mutant <italic>narrow sheath</italic> fails to establish leaf margin identity in a meristematic domain</article-title>. <source>Development</source><volume>122</volume>, <fpage>1683</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1691</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8674408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoof</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haecker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>J&#x000fc;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The stem cell population of Arabidopsis shoot meristems in maintained by a regulatory loop between the <italic>CLAVATA</italic> and <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> genes</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>100</volume>, <fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>644</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10761929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The role of hormones in shoot apical meristem function</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>484</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>489</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16877025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelsey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohtsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schnable</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scanlon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Tissue specificity and evolution of meristematic <italic>WOX3</italic> function</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>149</volume>, <fpage>841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>850</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19073779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Somssich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Je</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title><italic>CLAVATA&#x02013;WUSCHEL</italic> signaling in the shoot meristem</article-title>. <source>Development</source><volume>143</volume>, <fpage>3238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27624829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuurman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>J&#x000e4;ggi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhlemeier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Shoot meristem maintenance is controlled by a GRAS-gene mediated signal from differentiating cells</article-title>. <source>Genes &#x00026; Development</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>2213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2218</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12208843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mysore</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Control of vegetative to reproductive phase transition improves biomass yield and simultaneously reduces lignin content in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title>. <source>Bioenergy Research</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>857</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>867</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bedair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title><italic>STENOFOLIA</italic> regulates blade outgrowth and leaf vascular patterning in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> and <italic>Nicotiana sylvestris</italic></article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21719692</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Large-scale insertional mutagenesis using the <italic>Tnt1</italic> retrotransposon in the model legume <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>54</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>347</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18208518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohmori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ushijima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsusaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumamaru</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Axillary meristem formation in rice requires the <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> ortholog <italic>TILLERS ABSENT1</italic></article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1184</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25841039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenbussche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horstman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zethof</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rijpkema</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerats</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Differential recruitment of WOX transcription factors for lateral development and organ fusion in Petunia and Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2283</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19717616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Graaff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rensing</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>The WUS homeobox-containing (WOX) protein family</article-title>. <source>Genome Biology</source><volume>10</volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20067590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avci</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Mutation of WRKY transcription factors initiates pith secondary wall formation and increases stem biomass in dicotyledonous plants</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>107</volume>, <fpage>22338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22343</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Overexpression of the WOX gene <italic>STENOFOLIA</italic> improves biomass yield and sugar release in transgenic grasses and display altered cytokinin homeostasis</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genetics</source><volume>13</volume>, <fpage>e1006649</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28264034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>TQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Cytokinin signaling activates <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> expression during axillary meristem initiation</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1387</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28576845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Motyka</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laucou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smets</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Onckelen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schm&#x000fc;lling</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Cytokinin-deficient transgenic Arabidopsis plants show multiple developmental alterations indicating opposite functions of cytokinins in the regulation of shoot and root meristem activity</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>2532</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2550</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tavakkoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title><italic>WUSCHEL</italic> mediates stem cell homeostasis by regulating stem cell number and patterns of cell division and differentiation of stem cell progenitors</article-title>. <source>Development</source><volume>137</volume>, <fpage>3581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3589</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20876644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Repression of <italic>AS2</italic> by WOX family transcription factors is required for leaf development in Medicago and Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Signaling &#x00026; Behavior</source><volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e993291</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25807065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>STENOFOLIA recruits TOPLESS to repress <italic>ASYMMETRIC LEAVES2</italic> at the leaf margin and promote leaf blade outgrowth in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>26</volume>, <fpage>650</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>664</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24585835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>A molecular framework for the embryonic initiation of shoot meristem stem cells</article-title>. <source>Developmental Cell</source><volume>40</volume>, <fpage>264</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>277.e4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28171749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0068"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>HAIRY MERISTEM with WUSCHEL confines <italic>CLAVATA3</italic> expression to the outer apical meristem layers</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>361</volume>, <fpage>502</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>506</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30072538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0069"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rameau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title><italic>LATHYROIDES</italic>, encoding a WUSCHEL-related Homeobox1 transcription factor, controls organ lateral growth, and regulates tendril and dorsal petal identities in garden pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Plant</source><volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22888154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>