<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Physiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Physiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-042X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5816349</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2018.00091</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fluid Metabolism in Athletes Running Seven Marathons in Seven Consecutive Days</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chl&#x000ed;bkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Daniela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/410200/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nikolaidis</surname><given-names>Pantelis T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/194718/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosemann</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/182731/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>Beat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/338472/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bedn&#x000e1;&#x00159;</surname><given-names>Josef</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/433030/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Centre of Sports Activities, Brno University of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Brno</addr-line>, <country>Czechia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Exercise Physiology Laboratory</institution>, <addr-line>Nikaia</addr-line>, <country>Greece</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Institute of Primary Care, University of Zurich</institution>, <addr-line>Zurich</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Medbase St. Gallen Am Vadianplatz</institution>, <addr-line>St. Gallen</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Faculty of Mechanical Engineering, Brno University of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Brno</addr-line>, <country>Czechia</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Luca Paolo Ardig&#x000f2;, University of Verona, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Martin D. Hoffman, University of California, Davis, United States; Hassane Zouhal, University of Rennes 2 &#x02013; Upper Brittany, France</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Beat Knechtle <email xlink:type="simple">beat.knechtle@hispeed.ch</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Exercise Physiology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Physiology</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>&#x02020;These authors have contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>91</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Chl&#x000ed;bkov&#x000e1;, Nikolaidis, Rosemann, Knechtle and Bedn&#x000e1;&#x00159;.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chl&#x000ed;bkov&#x000e1;, Nikolaidis, Rosemann, Knechtle and Bedn&#x000e1;&#x00159;</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><bold>Purpose:</bold> Hypohydration and hyperhydration are significant disorders of fluid metabolism in endurance performance; however, little relevant data exist regarding multi-stage endurance activities. The aim of the present study was to examine the effect of running seven marathons in 7 consecutive days on selected anthropometric, hematological and biochemical characteristics with an emphasis on hydration status.</p><p><bold>Methods:</bold> Participants included 6 women and 20 men (age 42.6 &#x000b1; 6.2 years). Data was collected before day 1 (B<sub>1</sub>) and after day 1 (A<sub>1</sub>), 4 (A<sub>4</sub>), and 7 (A<sub>7</sub>).</p><p><bold>Results:</bold> The average marathon race time was 4:44 h:min (ranging from 3:09 &#x02013; 6:19 h:min). Plasma sodium, plasma potassium and urine sodium were maintained during the race. Body mass (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.501), body fat (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.572) and hematocrit (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.358) decreased. Plasma osmolality (Posm) (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.416), urine osmolality (Uosm) (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.465), urine potassium (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.507), urine specific gravity (Usg) (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.540), plasma urea (PUN) (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.586), urine urea (UUN) (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.532) and transtubular potassium gradient (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.560) increased at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, and A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>. Posm correlated with PUN at A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.59, <italic>p</italic> = 0.001) and A<sub>4</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.58, <italic>p</italic> = 0.002). The reported post-race fluid intake was 0.5 &#x000b1; 0.2 L/h and it correlated negatively with plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.42, <italic>p</italic> = 0.007) at A<sub>4</sub> and (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.50, <italic>p</italic> = 0.009) at A<sub>7</sub>. Uosm was associated with UUN at A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.80, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), at A<sub>4</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.81, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and at A<sub>7</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.86, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and with Usg (<italic>r</italic> = 0.71, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) at A<sub>1</sub>, (<italic>r</italic> = 0.52, <italic>p</italic> = 0.006) at A<sub>4</sub> and (<italic>r</italic> = 0.46, <italic>p</italic> = 0.02) at A<sub>7</sub>.</p><p><bold>Conclusions:</bold> Despite the decrease in body mass, fluid and electrolyte balance was maintained with no decrease in plasma volume after running seven marathons in seven consecutive days. Current findings support the hypothesis that body mass changes do not reflect changes in the hydration status during prolonged exercise.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>multi-stage marathon</kwd><kwd>endurance</kwd><kwd>running</kwd><kwd>hydration status</kwd><kwd>sodium</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="61"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="9045"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Hypohydration and hyperhydration are significant disorders of fluid metabolism in endurance performance (Hew-Butler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Ultramarathon running races, generally performed on a variety of off-road terrains, are good models for the study of physiological responses to extreme stress (Millet and Millet, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), as they alter normal physiological processes and often result in fluid and electrolyte imbalance (Noakes et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>).</p><p>Altered hydration status has not been well studied in multi-stage races (Krabak et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In a multi-stage ultramarathon, athletes often compete for several days (Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>), run at a slow pace (Costa et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and are at an increased risk of fluid overload (R&#x000fc;st et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In case of excess fluid consumption, an increase in body mass, total body water and a decrease in plasma sodium [Na<sup>+</sup>] (Hew-Butler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) can be expected. Exercise-associated hyponatremia (EAH) is a common occurrence among endurance athletes (Hew-Butler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and the incidence of EAH in multi-stage marathons is similar to its incidence in marathons and single-stage ultramarathons (Krabak et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). EAH occurred during multi-stage races with both increased and stable levels of total body water (Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>; R&#x000fc;st et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Costa et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>By contrast, anecdotal evidence suggests that multi-stage ultra-runners do not consume sufficient fluid to maintain euhydration, especially in hot ambient conditions (Costa et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). During multi-stage races, body mass often decreases (Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2008a</xref>,<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2012b</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Zouhal et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; R&#x000fc;st et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Costa et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Hue et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Krabak et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) or remains unchanged (Knechtle and Kohler, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2008c</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2010b</xref>). The decrease in body mass and the increase in urine specific gravity can indicate dehydration (Kavouras, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Hypohydration from an athlete's perspective represents 2&#x02013;5% body mass (volume) deficit (McDermott et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Nevertheless, recent studies suggest that body mass loss for the maintenance of euhydration is 3%, or even 4%, depending on exercise duration (Noakes et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Hoffman and Stuempfle, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), as body mass is ~1% higher at the race start than the day before (Hoffman et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013a</xref>; Hoffman and Stuempfle, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Therefore, it seems that body mass is not an accurate surrogate for body fluid volume in prolonged endurance races (Hew-Butler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Hoffman et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) and body mass losses of 1.9&#x02013;5% are required in order to maintain euhydration during prolonged exercise (Hoffman et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). It is worth mentioning that that the appropriate body mass loss depends on the exercise duration. Multistage ultramarathon runners were most likely dehydrated after the last and longest stage of the race in a prospective observational cohort study (Krabak et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) though with the highest EAH prevalence. Contributing factors to body mass losses can be excessive distances, limited access to fluids and gastrointestinal problems (Hew-Butler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p><p>In multi-stage races, plasma volume increases (Fellmann et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>; Costa et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) or remains stable (Zouhal et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; R&#x000fc;st et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Despite an increase in plasma volume, plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] (Wade et al., <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>; Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; R&#x000fc;st et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Costa et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Hue et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and urinary [Na<sup>+</sup>] volumes (Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>) often remain unchanged. The activity of aldosterone and antidiuretic hormone (ADH) is presumably the reason for maintained fluid homeostasis in athletes competing in multi-stage races (Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>; R&#x000fc;st et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>To date, multi-stage races with distances longer or shorter than the marathon in at least one stage have been examined (Fellmann et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Knechtle and Kohler, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2008a</xref>,<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">c</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, we have not found any study investigating the effect of a multi-stage race&#x02014;in which athletes are required to run one marathon per day for seven consecutive days&#x02014;on the parameters of fluid metabolism using multiple hydration assessment techniques. Only one recent case study mentioned a recreational female runner who completed a multi-day endurance running event consisting of 26 marathon distances in 26 consecutive days (McManus et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) and the paper specifically focused on nutrition education. Although this case study has improved our understanding of fluid metabolism in ultra-endurance activities, there was only one subject, and thus, further research is needed. Recent studies (Maughan et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Hoffman et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) suggest that changes in body mass do not reflect changes in the hydration status of those who participate in prolonged exercise. By contrast, hydration guidelines indicate that it is necessary to avoid body mass loss of more than 2% during exercise (American College of Sports Medicine et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Therefore, the aim of the present study was to examine the effect of running seven marathons in seven consecutive days on selected anthropometric, hematological and biochemical characteristics with an emphasis on fluid metabolism. Based upon previous findings from studies investigating multi-stage ultramarathons, we hypothesized that body mass would decrease and our aim was then to examine if body mass changes while running marathons for several consecutive days reflect changes in the hydration status of the runners.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>The approval to conduct the study was obtained from the local institutional ethics committee at the Centre of Sports Activities, Brno University of Technology, Brno, Czechia. The athletes were encouraged to participate through links on the website. In addition, they were contacted via e-mail 3 months before the race and asked to participate in our investigation. Participation requirements for these competitions stipulate that the athletes have to be at least 18 years of age. No other inclusion/exclusion criteria were used, except that they finish the race. Thirty amateur ultra-runners who registered for the &#x0201c;Moravian Ultra Marathon&#x0201d; of 2015 volunteered to participate in the study. However, four of them did not complete all marathon races and were excluded from all analyses, resulting in a final sample of 26 runners (6 women and 20 men, age 42.6 &#x000b1; 6.2 years). All volunteers provided written informed consent after the risks and benefits of the study were carefully explained to them.</p><sec><title>The race</title><p>The study was performed at the 2015 &#x0201c;Moravian Ultra Marathon,&#x0201d; an international running multi-stage race, which consists of seven marathons in seven consecutive days. It is considered the longest and most difficult multi-stage race in Czechia. The race was held in Lomnice from 28 June to 4 July 2015. For stage 1, all runners start at the same time&#x02014;at 2:00 pm. Based on the results from stage 1, participants with a performance under 4:30 h start at 3:00 p.m. on the second day, while the others start at 2:00 p.m. For the last stage (stage 7), the runners have individual starting times, beginning at 8:00 and based on their average performance during the week (the previous results from each stage). The final time is measured individually, from the starting time of each participant. The winner is the athlete with the lowest total time from all stages. Stages are point-to-point distance, with a different route every day. Stages 1 and 7 started and finished in Lomnice, while stages 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 each started at a different location. The racers were taken by bus prior to the start, and each stage finished in Lomnice. Each stage has the approximate length of a classical marathon (42.2&#x02013;43.0 km) and runs through very rugged terrain, with an average ascent of 900 m, which makes it certainly more challenging than other races organized in Czechia. The route took place on an asphalt surface, through both light traffic and fields and woods. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> shows ascents and descents and general weather conditions during all the stages of the &#x0201c;Moravian Ultra Marathon.&#x0201d; The temperature rose gradually from stage to stage, and increased by 12 degrees during stage 7. Each stage had six refreshment stations where food and beverages, such as water, sports drinks, tea, soup, caffeinated drinks, mineral water, fresh, and dry fruit, cheese, salty and sweet biscuits, salty crisps, peanuts and chocolate (until it melted in the heat), were available. Runners could also use their own refreshments.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Stages of the &#x0201c;Moravian ultra marathon&#x0201d;: ascents, descents and general weather conditions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stage</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ascent (m)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Descent (m)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>General weather conditions</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Temperature range (&#x000b0;C)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Humidity (%)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">830</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">830</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sun, wind</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02013;20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">830</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">862</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sun, wind</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02013;20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">830</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">734</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sun</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#x02013;25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">900</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">787</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sun</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#x02013;26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">760</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">948</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sun</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#x02013;30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">911</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,055</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sun</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#x02013;26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">740</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">740</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sun</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#x02013;30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Measurements and calculations</title><p>Participants recorded the amount of fluids with which they started the race. Then, at each fluid station, there were assistants marking the number of cups consumed by the athletes. Fluids that were part of a meal or snack were not recorded. Immediately after each stage, during post-race measurements, the total fluid intake was estimated based on the data from the athletes and assistants. The athletes did not report solid food intake. We are aware of the fact that fluids from the fluid station could sometimes be used for other purposes than drinking (cooling, etc.). However, we assume that this was done predominantly near the fluid station, and the assistants were asked to mark the number of actually consumed cups. The organizer did not provide the athletes with any special advice on the website regarding what or how much they should drink during the race.</p><p>Blood and urine samples were collected before stage 1 (B<sub>1</sub>). Due to the demanding conditions of the 7-day race and limitations related to performing research at a competitive event, we decided to perform further sampling during the race only after stage 1 (A<sub>1</sub>), 4 (A<sub>4</sub>), and 7 (A<sub>7</sub>). Standardization of the sitting position prior to blood collection was respected. The measurement included a mid-flow urine sample prior to body mass measurements. Blood and urine samples were immediately transported to the laboratory and analyzed within 6 h. After venipuncture of the antecubital vein, two Sarstedt S-Monovettes (plasma gel, 7.5 mL) for chemical analysis and one Sarstedt S-Monovette (EDTA, 2.7 mL) (Sarstedt, N&#x000fc;mbrecht) for hematological analysis were drawn. Hematocrit was determined using Sysmex XE 2100 (Sysmex Corporation, Japan) (Imeri et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>); plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>], plasma [K<sup>+</sup>] and plasma urea were determined using the Modula SWA biochemical analyzer, Modul P + ISE (Hitachi High Technologies Corporation, Japan, Roche Diagnostic) (Stockmann et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>); and plasma osmolality was determined using Arkray Osmotation (Arkray Factory, Inc., Japan). Urine samples were collected in Sarstedt Urine Monovette (10 mL) and sent to the laboratory. Urine [Na<sup>+</sup>], urine [K<sup>+</sup>], and urine urea were determined using the Modula SWA biochemical analyzer, Modul P + ISE (Hitachi High Technologies Corporation, Japan, Roche Diagnostic). Urine specific gravity was determined using Au Max-4030 (Arkray Factory, Inc., Japan), and urine osmolality was determined using Arkray Osmostation OM-650 (Arkray Factory, Inc., Japan) (Zanchi et al., <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio in urine was calculated. Transtubular potassium gradient was calculated using the equation: Transtubular potassium gradient = [urine [K<sup>+</sup>] &#x000d7; plasma osmolality/(plasma [K<sup>+</sup>] &#x000d7; urine osmolality), according to West et al. (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>). Percentage change in plasma volume was determined in accordance with Van Beaumont (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">1972</xref>).</p><p>Blood samples are examined in clinical laboratories and strenuous exercise may have a profound effect on laboratory parameters (Kratz et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Kratz et al. (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) therefore provided a table of modified reference ranges for basic biochemical and hematological laboratory parameters derived from marathon runners. We compared these modified reference ranges with the values of hematocrit observed in our study. The modified reference ranges without sex difference include pre-race (39&#x02013;49%) and post-race (38&#x02013;48%) hematocrit values and post-race plasma osmolality values (273&#x02013;318 mOsm) (Kratz et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Plasma osmolality clinical reference range was 280&#x02013;303 mOsmol/kg (Fischback and Dunning, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Individual post-race urine specific gravity samples were compared with the values provided by Armstrong et al. (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>), i.e., urine specific gravity within the range of 1.013&#x02013;1.029 g/mL is considered normal, values over 1.030 indicate significant dehydration and values below 1.012 g/mL indicate hyperhydration.</p><p>Anthropometric characteristics were determined in order to estimate fat-free mass, fat mass and percent body fat at B<sub>1</sub> and at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, and A<sub>7</sub>. Body mass was measured to the nearest 0.1 kg using a commercial scale (Beurer BF 15, Beurer GmbH, Ulm, Germany). Hydration status was assessed according to the criteria proposed by Noakes et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) with overhydration classified as any weight gain above the initial body mass, euhydration as a decrease in body mass of 0.01&#x02013;3.0%, and dehydration as any decrease in body mass greater than 3.0%. Skinfold measurements were taken on the right side of the body at eight sites (pectoralis, axillar, triceps, subscapular, abdomen, suprailiac, front thigh, and medial calf) using a skinfold caliper (Harpenden skinfold caliper, Baty International Ltd) and recorded to the nearest 0.2 mm. Fat-free mass (kg) was estimated using an equation for male (Stewart and Hannan, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>) and female (Warner et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) athletes. Fat mass (kg) was calculated by subtracting fat-free mass from total body mass. Percent body fat was estimated using a specific equation for men (Ball et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2004a</xref>) and women (Ball et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2004b</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All variables were expressed as mean and standard deviation. The data was tested for normality using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Since most variables were normally distributed, parametric statistics was used for all variables to be comparable. Pearson's correlation coefficient r was used to examine relationships between the variables. The magnitude of correlation coefficients was considered trivial if <italic>r</italic> &#x02264; 0.10, small if 0.10 &#x02264; <italic>r</italic> &#x0003c; 0.30, moderate if 0.30 &#x02264; <italic>r</italic> &#x0003c; 0.50, great if 0.50 &#x02264; <italic>r</italic> &#x0003c; 0.70, very great if 0.70 &#x02264; <italic>r</italic> 0.90, nearly perfect if &#x02265; 0.90 and perfect if <italic>r</italic> = 1.00 (Batterham and Hopkins, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). A between-within subjects analysis of variance (ANOVA) examined pre- and post-race differences. The magnitude of the differences was examined with eta squared (&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup>), which was classified as small (0.010 &#x0003c; &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> &#x02264; 0.059), moderate (0.059 &#x0003c; &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> &#x02264; 0.138) and great (&#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> &#x0003e; 0.138). The significance was set at alpha = 0.05. All statistical analyses were performed using MINITAB (Version 17.2; Minitab, Inc., USA) and SPSS software.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 197 ultra-athletes entered the race and 53 (27%) finished all seven stages. Twenty-six runners (twenty men and six women) (87%) of the 30 who volunteered to participate in our study finished the whole race. Four athletes dropped out due to injuries or total fatigue. Pre-race training, average running speed and race time per day of each finisher are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Pre-race experience, training, running speed of the finishers and race time per stage.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6 (6.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years as an active runner (years)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of finished ultra-marathons (n)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 (10.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean weekly training volume in running (km)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.6 (26.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longest weekly run (km)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.2 (30.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average racing speed (km/h) (stage 1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.34 (6.55&#x02013;13.60)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average racing speed (km/h) (stage 4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.25 (7.47&#x02013;12.78)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average racing speed (km/h) (stage 7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.01 (6.53&#x02013;13.16)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average race time (h:min) per stage 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4:43 (3:09&#x02013;6:55)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average race time (h:min) per stage 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4:43 (3:21&#x02013;5:45)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average race time (h:min) per stage 7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4:46 (3:11&#x02013;6:25)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>&#x02020;</label><p><italic>During the 3 months before the event. Data are expressed as mean (SD) or mean (range)</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title>Body mass and body fat</title><p>On average, body mass decreased significantly at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) and A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>4</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.501) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Ultra-runners were distributed by their hydration status based on body mass changes in accordance with the study by Noakes et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). There were 12% overhydrated, 61% euhydrated and 27% dehydrated athletes at A<sub>1</sub>; 27% overhydrated, 31% euhydrated and 42% dehydrated runners at A<sub>4</sub>, and 15% overhydrated, 31% euhydrated and 54% dehydrated runners at A<sub>7</sub>. Body fat decreased significantly at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>; A<sub>4</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) and A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.572) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). A scatterplot of percentage change in body mass vs. percentage body fat change is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. Body mass change was not associated with plasma osmolality or urine specific gravity (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Results of selected body composition and blood and urine parameters of runners along multistage marathon competition.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Parameter</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>B<sub>1</sub></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>A<sub>1</sub></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Absolute change (A<sub>1</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>A<sub>4</sub></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Absolute change (A<sub>4</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>A<sub>7</sub></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Absolute change (A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass (kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.3(9.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.8(9.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.5(1.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.9(9.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.4(1.6)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.3(9.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.0(1.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body fat (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5(3.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4(4.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1(1.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2(4.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.3(1.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2(4.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.3(1.5)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematocrit (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.8(2.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8(3.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0(2.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8(4.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.0(3.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5(4.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.3(3.5)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma sodium (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.3(2.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.3(3.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0(2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.4(3.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1(3.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.5(4.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.8(4.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma potassium (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3(0.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4(0.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1(0.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4(0.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1(0.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3(0.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0(0.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma osmolality (mOsm/kg H<sub>2</sub>O)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286.7(5.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295.6(5.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9(7.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">294.9(7.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2(7.1)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">293.8(8.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1(8.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma urea (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1(1.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3(1.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2(1.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3(2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2(2.3)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7(1.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6(1.8)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine sodium (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.6(53.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1(26.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;31.5(53.6)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.8(50.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16.8(81.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.2(130.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.4(139.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine potassium (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9(31.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.6(27.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7(35.0)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.3(20.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.4(31.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.5(20.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6(32.8)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine osmolality (mOsm/kg H<sub>2</sub>O)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">404.5(246.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">534.0(196.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.5(291.1)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">735.6 (214.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">331.1(252.9)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">715.9(206.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311.4(273.4)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine urea (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143.5(107.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229.7(128.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.2(110.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">347.3(115.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203.8(115.0)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">327.9(122.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184.4(144.9)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine specific gravity (g/mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.015(0.007)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.022(0.006)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007(0.009)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.027 (0.007)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012(0.008)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.029(0.005)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014(0.010)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio in urine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5(0.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7(0.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2(0.9)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8(1.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3(1.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6(1.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1(1.6)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transtubular potassium gradient</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3(19.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4(19.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1 (25.5)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5(23.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2(24.4)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.2(22.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9(27.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Mean (SD)</italic>.</p><fn id="TN2"><label>*</label><p>p &#x02264; 0.05 and</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>**</label><p><italic>p &#x0003c; 0.01 changes after stage 1, 4, and 7 vs. before stage 1. B<sub>1</sub>, before stage 1; A<sub>1</sub>, after stage 1; A<sub>4</sub>, after stage 4; A<sub>7</sub>, after stage 7</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Body composition, blood and urine data and their changes. Symbol # denotes difference from day 0 = B<sub>1</sub> (before stage 1) at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01. Symbols &#x02020; and &#x02021; denote differences between two days at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 and <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphys-09-00091-g0001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>BM, body mass; BF, body fat. A scatterplot of body mass change vs. body fat change at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, and A<sub>7</sub>. Body mass change was associated with body fat change (<italic>r</italic> = 0.52, <italic>p</italic> = 0.007) at A<sub>1</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.42, <italic>p</italic> = 0.03) at A<sub>4</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.42, <italic>p</italic> = 0.03); at A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphys-09-00091-g0002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>], plasma [K<sup>+</sup>], reported fluid intake</title><p>No change was observed in plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] (<italic>p</italic> = 0.326, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.044) and [K<sup>+</sup>] <bold>(</bold><italic>p</italic> = 0.900, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.005) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] of &#x0003c; 135 mmol/L was found in one male athlete who finished the competition with plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] of 135 mmol/L (A<sub>1</sub>), 134 mmol/L (A<sub>4</sub>) and 130 mmol/L (A<sub>7</sub>). However, this athlete was already hyponatremic at pre-race testing (132 mmol/L) and plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] concentration was higher after two of the three stages.</p><p>The average reported fluid intake during stages 1, 4, and 7 was 0.5 (0.4) L/h. That is 6.1 (2.2) mL/kg/h during stage 1; 7.0 (2.6) mL/kg/h during stage 4, and 7.5 (3.2) mL/kg/h during stage 7. Fluid intake during stage 4 was negatively correlated with plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.42, <italic>p</italic> = 0.007) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) and plasma [K<sup>+</sup>] (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.43, <italic>p</italic> = 0.03) at A<sub>4</sub>. Fluid intake during stage 7 was negatively associated with plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.50, <italic>p</italic> = 0.009) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) and plasma osmolality (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.53, <italic>p</italic> = 0.005) at A<sub>7</sub>. Fluid intake during the stages was not associated with body mass or percentage plasma volume change at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, and A<sub>7</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>A scatterplot of plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] vs. reported fluid intake at A<sub>4</sub> and A<sub>7</sub>. Fluid intake &#x02013; fluid intake during the stage. Fluid intake during stage 4 was negatively correlated with plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.42, <italic>p</italic> = 0.007) at A<sub>4</sub>. Fluid intake during stage 7 was negatively associated with plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.50, <italic>p</italic> = 0.009) at A<sub>7</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphys-09-00091-g0003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Plasma osmolality, plasma urea</title><p>Plasma osmolality was within the modified reference range for marathoners proposed by Kratz et al. (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Plasma osmolality significantly increased at A<sub>1</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub> vs. B1 and A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.416) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>); but remained stable at A<sub>4</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>4</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub>. Plasma urea significantly increased at A<sub>1</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>), A<sub>4</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> = 0.01) and A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>4</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.586). Absolute plasma osmolality and plasma urea changes are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. A scatterplot of plasma osmolality vs. plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] and plasma urea is detailed in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>A scatterplot of plasma osmolality vs. plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] and plasma urea at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, and A<sub>7</sub>. Plasma osmolality was associated with plasma [Na<sup>+</sup>] (<italic>r</italic> = 0.69, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) at A<sub>1</sub>, (<italic>r</italic> = 0.64, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) at A<sub>4</sub> and (<italic>r</italic> = 0.42, <italic>p</italic> = 0.03) at A<sub>7</sub>. Plasma osmolality was correlated with plasma urea at A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.59, <italic>p</italic> = 0.001) and at A<sub>4</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.58, <italic>p</italic> = 0.002); at A<sub>7</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphys-09-00091-g0004"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Hematocrit, plasma volume</title><p>Pre-race hematocrit values ranged from 38.5 to 49%, and were within the modified reference ranges established for marathon runners (Kratz et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Post-race hematocrit values (38&#x02013;48%) were achieved by all the finishers at A<sub>1</sub>, whereas 12% of the athletes (2 men and 1 woman) showed lower values at A<sub>4</sub>, and 12% (1 man and 2 women) at A<sub>7</sub>, i.e., they were anemic (Kratz et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Hematocrit significantly decreased at A<sub>1</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>), A<sub>4</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> and at A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.358) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Percentage change in plasma volume was 2.1(7.7)% at A<sub>1</sub>, 12.4(11.1)% at A<sub>4</sub> and 13.3(13.7)% at A<sub>7</sub>, calculated according to Van Beaumont (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">1972</xref>). Percentage change in plasma volume at A<sub>4</sub> and A<sub>7</sub> was significantly higher than the value at A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> = 0.001, <italic>p</italic> = 0.002, respectively). Percentage change in plasma volume was not correlated with plasma or urine osmolality change (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05).</p></sec><sec><title>Urine [Na<sup>+</sup>] and [K<sup>+</sup>], K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio in urine, transtubular potassium gradient</title><p>There was no change in urine [Na<sup>+</sup>] (<italic>p</italic> = 0.386, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.036) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Urine [K<sup>+</sup>] increased at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>), and at A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.507) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio in urine significantly increased at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.430) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Transtubular potassium gradient significantly increased at A<sub>1</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>), A<sub>4</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.560) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Urine osmolality, urine urea, urine specific gravity</title><p>Urine osmolality significantly increased at A<sub>1</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>; A<sub>4</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>), A<sub>4</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.465) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Urine urea significantly increased at A<sub>1</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>), A<sub>4</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.532) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Urine specific gravity significantly increased at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>), A<sub>7</sub> vs. A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.540) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). There were 4% hyperhydrated and 12% dehydrated athletes at A<sub>1</sub>; 4% hyperhydrated and 50% dehydrated at A<sub>4</sub>, and 0% hyperhydrated and 65% dehydrated at A<sub>7</sub> based on the athletes' individual post-race urine specific gravity samples. A matrix plot of urine osmolality, urine specific gravity and urine urea at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, and A<sub>7</sub> is detailed in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>A matrix plot of urine osmolality, urine urea and urine specific gravity at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub> and A<sub>7</sub>. Usg &#x02013; urine specific gravity. Urine osmolality was significantly associated with urine specific gravity (<italic>r</italic> = 0.71, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) at A<sub>1</sub>, (<italic>r</italic> = 0.52, <italic>p</italic> = 0.006) at A<sub>4</sub> and (<italic>r</italic> = 0.46, <italic>p</italic> = 0.02) at A<sub>7</sub>. Urine osmolality was significantly associated with urine urea at A<sub>1</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.80, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), at A<sub>4</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.81, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and at A<sub>7</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.86, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Urine specific gravity was associated with urine urea (<italic>r</italic> = 0.39, <italic>p</italic> = 0.05) at A<sub>1</sub>. Other correlations were not significant (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphys-09-00091-g0005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>We investigated the effect of a multi-stage race in which athletes have to run one marathon per day on the parameters of fluid metabolism. Running one marathon per day led to a body mass decrease without any disturbance of fluid homeostasis. Plasma sodium, plasma potassium and urine sodium remained stable at pre-race (baseline) levels at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, and A<sub>7</sub> vs. B<sub>1</sub>. We have confirmed the hypothesis that body mass changes do not reflect changes in the hydration status of runners. Also of note is the finding of a negative relationship between the reported fluid intake and plasma sodium at A<sub>4</sub> and A<sub>7</sub>.</p><sec><title>Body mass and body fat decrease</title><p>The average body mass loss was 2.9%, which is relatively low compared to the studies conducted by Zouhal et al. (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) during a 7-day, self-sufficient, multi-stage running race across the desert, and Hue et al. (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) during a 6-day, 142-km trail running race, both in hot environments (~30 or ~25&#x000b0;C, respectively). By contrast, body mass loss was higher than in the 5-day, self-sufficient multi-stage ultramarathon in a hot ambient environment (~36&#x000b0;C) in the study by Costa et al. (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), during the longest 7-day multi-stage mountain ultramarathon in Europe called the &#x0201c;Swiss Jura Marathon&#x0201d; with temperatures ranging from 8 to 14&#x000b0;C in the study by Knechtle et al. (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>), and during a 5-day multi-stage ultra-endurance run where athletes had to run 338 km in 5 days with temperatures ranging from 19 to 22&#x000b0;C (Knechtle and Kohler, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). The strenuous conditions of a 7-day, multi-stage marathon run also led to a significant decrease in body fat. A decrease in body mass is often the consequence of body fat decrease (Helge et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Bircher et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). A decrease in fat mass is expected and the ability to use body fat as fuel is important in such ultra-endurance athletes (Raschka and Plath, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>). When considering body mass and body fat changes, it should be recognized that, in contrast to continuous events, the athletes had time between the stages for fluid and nutritional restoration. Therefore, although there may be some minor cumulative mass loss, the main loss of mass probably occurred during each stage. The decrease in body mass and the increase in urine specific gravity after each observed stage in comparison with pre-race values might also be due to dehydration (Armstrong et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). Although sweat rate was not assessed, the temperature rose gradually from stage to stage (~24&#x000b0;C) and increased by 12 degrees during the seventh stage. The highest number of dehydrated athletes based on their body mass changes (Noakes et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) was found at A<sub>7</sub>. A similar number of athletes were probably dehydrated after a multi-stage ultramarathon in the study of Krabak et al. (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Nevertheless, the present runners had a significantly higher percentage change in plasma volume than after A<sub>1</sub> and no relationship between the change in plasma volume and plasma osmolality or fluid intake was found. Moreover, body mass changes were not associated with urine specific gravity changes in these ultramarathoners and the loss of body mass is an imperfect predictor of total body volume (Hew-Butler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). A recent study of a 161-km ultramarathon by Hoffman and Stuempfle (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) defines dehydration as a decrease in body mass greater than 4%, which would mean that in our study, 15% of the athletes were dehydrated at A<sub>1</sub>, 15% at A<sub>4</sub> and 27% at A<sub>7</sub>&#x02013;much less than with the original calculations defined by Noakes et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The number of dehydrated athletes might vary depending on the definition of dehydration based on race distance (Noakes et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Hoffman and Stuempfle, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). It has been estimated that ~3&#x02013;4% body mass should be lost during prolonged exercise in order to maintain euhydration (Noakes et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Hoffman and Stuempfle, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and 1% of body mass loss could be due to fat utilization in prolonged races (Stuempfle et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). During prolonged exercise, body mass loss does not exactly reflect body water loss, due to the effects of change in body mass by the release of water bound with muscle and liver glycogen, substrate use and production of water during substrate metabolism (Hoffman et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Notwithstanding, we found a positive relationship between urine specific gravity changes and urine urea changes, most likely as a result of increased protein catabolism (Noakes and Carter, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>; Warburton et al., <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). During endurance activities, the body primarily aims at maintaining sodium and plasma osmolality, but not body mass (Tam et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Plasma sodium, plasma potassium, reported fluid intake</title><p>Overall, the ultramarathoners in our study maintained plasma sodium and potassium levels. Blood sodium levels are not affected by sodium losses during exercise, but by the associated changes in body water content (Noakes, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Sodium and potassium remained within the normal range, similarly as after a 142-km trail running race in tropical conditions (~30&#x000b0;C) (Hue et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Post-race serum sodium concentrations did not differ among the five stages of a 225-km multi-stage ultramarathon (~36&#x000b0;C) (Costa et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Similarly, plasma sodium and potassium remained unchanged during a 7-day multi-stage mountain ultramarathon (~17&#x000b0;C) (Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>).</p><p>We would expect an association between the reported fluid intake and post-race plasma sodium, and indeed, runners with a lower fluid intake showed higher plasma sodium levels at A<sub>4</sub> and A<sub>7</sub>. Nevertheless, the runners in current study showed no occurrence of EAH. We have to take into consideration the fact that the reported amount of fluids could be under- or overestimated by the athletes or assistants at fluid stations. In any case, the reported average intake of 0.5 L/h was probably appropriate to maintain body water despite the body mass loss.</p></sec><sec><title>Plasma osmolality, plasma urea</title><p>Plasma osmolality increased similarly as in the studies by Knechtle et al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>) or Costa et al. (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and was related to plasma sodium. Aldosterone increases sodium reabsorption and raises plasma osmolality by increasing the excretion of potassium from the body; increased plasma osmolality stimulates ADH production until plasma osmolality is restored to normal levels (Noakes, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Plasma osmolality was within the normal clinical reference range (Fischback and Dunning, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) in all the ultramarathoners before the start and at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub> and A<sub>7</sub>, except for three male runners at A<sub>7</sub> (above normal clinical range) and one male finisher with plasma osmolality level below the normal clinical range pre-race and at A<sub>7.</sub> Moreover, plasma osmolality was not related to percentage change in plasma volume and plasma sodium remained stable post-race. Appropriate hydration probably preserved plasma osmolality within the normal range and maintained intracellular volume and homeostasis in the present multi-stage marathon run. By contrast, plasma osmolality was associated with plasma urea at A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>4</sub> in similarity to the studies by Knechtle et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>). An increase in plasma urea suggests increased metabolic activity; however, it can also indicate decreased renal functions (Rama et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>) attributable to skeletal muscle damage and protein catabolism. An increase in plasma urea concentration (+52%) provides indirect evidence of the breakdown of proteins in the body (Dressendorfer and Wade, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>). Higher post-race plasma urea occurs in a high percentage of ultramarathon runners who most likely finish faster and have greater body mass losses (Hoffman and Weiss, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). We assume that the increase in plasma urea concentrations induced the increase in plasma osmolality.</p></sec><sec><title>Hematocrit, plasma volume</title><p>The decrease in hematocrit was similar to that observed in the literature on multi-stage endurance ultra-running races (Raschka and Plath, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Zouhal et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>; R&#x000fc;st et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Rama et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Hemodilution might be caused by sodium retention and potassium secretion due to increased aldosterone activity, as well as due to the increased secretion of ADH with fluid conservation (Dressendorfer and Wade, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Noakes, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). An increase in plasma volume with hemodilution and decreased hematocrit is often observed after prolonged exercise of moderate intensity over several consecutive days (Fellmann et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>; Costa et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). During prolonged exercise, plasma volume tends to remain constant or increase due to the movement of water from the intracellular to the extracellular compartment (Fellmann et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Zouhal et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Plasma volume increase is also represented by the production of metabolic water from the oxidation of fatty acids and carbohydrates and glycogen degradation in muscles and in the liver (Pastene et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>). It is necessary to mention that the missing correction of blood parameters prior to stage 4 and 7 according to the change of plasma volume throughout the race week may have confounded the results and the conclusions of the study. In any case, considering &#x0201c;pseudoanemia&#x0201d; as a response to prolonged strenuous endurance exercise as well as the possibility of intravascular hemolysis from mechanical trauma and oxidative injury of red blood cells reflects the impact of physical exertion of an ultramarathon (Rama et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Urine osmolality, urine specific gravity, urine urea</title><p>Urine osmolality increased and was associated with increased urine specific gravity which was related to increased urine urea. Increased urine osmolality was also reported by Costa et al. (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) during and after a five-stage 225 km ultramarathon and by Knechtle et al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>) after a 7-day multi-stage ultramarathon. Increased urine osmolality and its high levels are a common feature of exercise-heat stress and can indicate a state of water conservation (Armstrong, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). By contrast, it seems that urine osmolality did not reflect body water content during a multi-stage ultra-race in the heat reported by Costa et al. (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Runners in their study had urine osmolality above the reference range and showed an increased plasma volume, just as the runners in the present study. Similarly, percentage plasma volume change was not associated with urine osmolality change in the present ultramarathoners. According to Costa et al. (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), urine measure of hydration is insufficient in monitoring hydration status. Catabolic products of protein metabolism could also lead to increased urine osmolality, which limits its potential usefulness for the assessment of dehydration (Cheuvront et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). An increase in urine urea may be related to increased protein catabolism, secondary to the reduction in renal blood flow, all of which may occur after prolonged strenuous exercise (Noakes and Carter, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Potassium/sodium ratio in urine, transtubular potassium gradient</title><p>The potassium/sodium (K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup>) ratio in urine was &#x0003c; 1 before B<sub>1</sub>, increased and was &#x0003e; 1 at A<sub>1</sub>, A<sub>4</sub>, and A<sub>7</sub> in the present study. Sodium and potassium concentrations are indirect markers of aldosterone and ADH secretion (Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>). The K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio in urine was &#x0003c; 1 before the multi-stage ultra-endurance race and was &#x0003e; 1 after each stage in the case study by Knechtle et al. (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>). The K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio also increased in the study focusing on multi-stage ultra-endurance triathletes (Knechtle et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2012b</xref>). The limitation was that we did not observe the K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio in urine at B<sub>4</sub> and B<sub>7</sub>. Nevertheless, the urine K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio &#x0003e; 1 may reflect contraction of the extracellular volume leading to hyperreninemic hyperaldosteronemia and could be interpreted as a reaction to the stimulation of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone-system (RAAS) (Wade et al., <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>); however, we did not measure the RAAS. Transtubular potassium gradient also increased and reached values &#x0003e; 10, indicating an increased aldosterone activity (Gault et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>). It is important to note that there is a limitation to the transtubular potassium gradient calculation, as it requires urine sodium &#x0003e; 25 mmol/L (Choi and Ziyadehm, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) so that sodium delivery to the cells is not rate-limiting for potassium secretion. 15% of the present runners did not reach this level at A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>4</sub> and 35% at A<sub>7</sub>. Nevertheless, the present findings suggest that a positive K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio in urine was influenced by increased aldosterone activity and more potassium than sodium was excreted by the kidneys during the stages. Increased aldosterone is a physiological reaction in multi-stage ultra-runners according to Wade et al. (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>). The RAAS increases transtubular potassium ratio during the race to preserve plasma sodium. This may also explain why plasma sodium remained stable at the finish of the multi-stage marathon despite body mass losses.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>This study has a few limitations worth noting. Water intake was calculated based on information reported by the competitors and assistants at fluid stations; it was not analyzed through dietary analysis software and water in solid food was not recorded. The absence of data on renal hormone responses, urine losses, metabolic water gain, respiratory water and sweat losses may limit the present study. Another limitation is the missing differentiation between sexes that are considered of importance regarding the risk profile for exercise associated dysnatremia. Notwithstanding, we believe our findings provide a foundation for future studies because our methodology is the same as previous well-established studies of marathon and single-stage races (Noakes et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Hoffman et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2013b</xref>) and multi-stage races (Krabak et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) although they investigated larger numbers of participants. Finally, limited blood and urine samplings only on day 4 and 7 could mask some potential relationships. The main reason noted were a lack of time to collect and process the blood and urine samples prior to all stages, the sake of the athletes' comfort and the runners' inability to prepare for the start in time. After the stage at the finish the participants were more able and willing to take part in laboratory measurements.</p></sec><sec><title>Practical applications</title><p>The findings of the present study support the hypothesis that body mass changes do not reflect changes in the hydration status during prolonged exercise of several hours. As hydration status is a major concern for ultra-endurance runners and professionals working with them, future hydration guidelines should consider these findings in order to help coaches, trainers, sport nutritionists and doctors develop tailored nutritional strategies during a race.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Fluid and electrolyte balance was maintained without any decrease in plasma volume at the finish of a 7-day multi-stage marathon run. We presume that the decrease in body mass could be the result of the metabolic breakdown of fuel, which includes body fat loss, endogenous substrate use, sweat loss, respiratory and urinary losses, and/or fecal body mass loss during running. The lack of change in body fluid balance may be due to the distance of a marathon.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>DC: designed the study, collected all data and drafted the manuscript, PN, TR, and BK helped in designing the study and drafting the manuscript, JB performed the statistical analyses.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the athletes for their splendid cooperation without which this study could not have been done. We thank the organizers of the &#x0201c;Moravian Ultra Marathon&#x0201d; for their generous support. Finally, special thanks go to the laboratory staff of the University Hospital &#x0201c;U Svat&#x000e9; Anny&#x0201d; in Brno, Czechia, for assisting with measurements and analyzing hematological and biochemical samples. We thank Alena &#x0017d;&#x000e1;kovsk&#x000e1; and her students from the Institute of Experimental Biology at Masaryk University, Brno, Czechia, for their assistance with the measurement and collection of biological samples and their transport to the hospital for processing. We also thank Patricia Villiger for her help in English editing.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American College of Sports Medicine</collab><name><surname>Sawka</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichner</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maughan</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montain</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>American college of sports medicine position stand. exercise and fluid replacement</article-title>. <source>Med. Sci. Sports Exerc</source>. <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>390</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/mss.0b013e31802ca597</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17277604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17277604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Assesing hydration status: the elusive gold standard</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Coll. Nutr</source>. <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>575S</fpage>&#x02212;<lpage>584S</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17921468?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17921468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soto</surname><given-names>J. A. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hacker</surname><given-names>F. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casa</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavouras</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maresh</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Urinary indices during dehydration, exercise and rehydration</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Sport Nutr</source>. <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>355</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijsn.8.4.345</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9841955?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9841955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batterham</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>W. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Making meaningful inferences about magnitudes</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Sports Physiol. Perform.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.1.1.50</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19114737?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19114737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altena</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stan</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004a</year>). <article-title>Comparison of anthropometry to DXA: a new prediction equation for men</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Clin. Nutr.</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1531</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15162135?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15162135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desimone</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004b</year>). <article-title>Accuracy of anthropometry compared to dual energy X-ray absorptiometry. A new generalizable equation for women</article-title>. <source>Res. Q. Exerc. Sport</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>258</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02701367.2004.10609158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15487289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bircher</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Enggist</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jehle</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Effects of an extreme endurance race on energy balance and body composition &#x02013; a case study</article-title>. <source>J. Sports Sci. Med</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 24198693?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24198693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheuvront</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenefick</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Charkoudian</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawka</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Physiologic basis for understanding quantitative dehydration</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Clin. Nutr</source>. <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>462</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/ajcn.112.044172</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23343973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23343973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziyadehm</surname><given-names>F. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The utility of the transtubular potassium gradient in the evaluation of hyperkalemia</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Soc. Nephro</source>. <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>424</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>426</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1681/ASN.2007091017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18216310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>R. J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixera</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rama</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swancott</surname><given-names>A. J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Water and sodium intake habits and status of ultra-endurance runners during a multistage ultra-marathon conducted in a hot ambient environment: an observational field based study</article-title>. <source>Nutr. J.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2891-12-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23282226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dressendorfer</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Effects of a 15-d race on plasma steroid levels and leg muscle fitness in runners</article-title>. <source>Med. Sci. Sports Exerc.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>954</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>958</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/00005768-199108000-00012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1956271?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1956271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fellmann</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeyre</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaufr&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dela&#x000ee;tre</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coudert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Intracellular hyperhydration induced by a 7-day endurance race</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol. Occup. Physiol</source>. <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>359</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004210050603</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10483806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10483806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischback</surname><given-names>F. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunning</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>A Manual of Laboratory and Diagnostic Tests 7th edn</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lipincott Williams and Wilkins</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gault</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Longerich</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harnett</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weslowski</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Predicting glomerular function from adjusted serum creatinine</article-title>. <source>Nephron</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1436333?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1436333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helge</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langfort</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messonnier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacho</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Skiing across the greenland icecap: divergent effect on limb muscle adaptations and substrate oxidation</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Biol</source>. <volume>206</volume>, <fpage>1075</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1083</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.00218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12582149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hew-Butler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowkes-Godek</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Statement of the third international exercise-associated hyponatremia consensus development conference, carlsbad, California</article-title>. <source>Clin. J. Sport Med</source>. <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>320</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JSM.0000000000000221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26102445?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26102445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulet</surname><given-names>E. D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maughan</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Considerations in the use of body mass change to estimate change in hydration status during a 161-kilometer ultramarathon running competition</article-title>. <source>Sports Med.</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>250</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-017-0782-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28895063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28895063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hew-Butler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuempfle</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013b</year>). <article-title>Exercise-associated hyponatremia and hydration status in 161-km ultramarathoners</article-title>. <source>Med. Sci. Sports Exerc.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>784</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>791</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0b013e31827985a8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23135369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23135369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuempfle</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Hydration strategies, weight change and performance in a 161 km ultramarathon. Res</article-title>. <source>Sports Med.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15438627.2014.915838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuempfle</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Is sodium supplementation necessary to avoid dehydration during prolonged exercise in the heat?</article-title>
<source>J. Strength Cond. Res</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>620</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1519/JSC.0000000000001138</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26907835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26907835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuempfle</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fogard</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hew-Butler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013a</year>). <article-title>Urine dipstick analysis for identification of runners susceptible to acute kidney injury following an ultramarathon</article-title>. <source>J. Sports Sci.</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2012.720705</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23035796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23035796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Does acute kidney injury from an ultramarathon increase the risk for greater subsequent injury?</article-title>
<source>Clin. J. Sport Med.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>422</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JSM.0000000000000277</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26657822?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26657822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hue</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baillot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinnapah</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzel</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Thermoregulation, hydration and performance over 6 days of trail running in the tropics</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Sports Med</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>906</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>911</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0033-1361186</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24841838?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24841838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imeri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herklotz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Risch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbetsleitner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerlauth</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Risch</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Stability of hematological analytes depends on the hematology analyser used: a stability study with Bayer Advia 120, Beckman Coulter LH 750 and Sysmex XE 2100</article-title>. <source>Clin. Chim. Acta</source>. <volume>397</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cca.2008.07.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18706900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18706900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kavouras</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Assessing hydration status</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Clin. Nutr. Metab. Care</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>524</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00075197-200209000-00010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12172475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12172475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008c</year>). <article-title>A multi-stage ultra-endurance run over 1,200 km leads to a continuous accumulation of total body water</article-title>. <source>J. Sports Sci. Med</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Enggist</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jehle</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Energy turnover at the Race Across America (RAAM) &#x02013; a case report</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Sports Med.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>499</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>503</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2004-821136</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16037895?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16037895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gn&#x000e4;dinger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imoberdorf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballmer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of exercise-associated hyponatremia in male ultraendurance athletes</article-title>. <source>Clin. J. Sport Med</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>226</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>232</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JSM.0b013e31820cb021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21427567?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21427567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiouplidis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imoberdorf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballmer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010a</year>). <article-title>Does a multi-stage ultra-endurance run cause de- or hyperhydration?</article-title>
<source>J. Hum. Sport Exerc</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4100/jhse.2010.51.07</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosemann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010b</year>). <article-title>A triple iron triathlon leads to a decrease in total body mass but not to dehydration</article-title>. <source>Res. Q. Exerc. Sport</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>327</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02701367.2010.10599680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000fc;st</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gn&#x000e4;dinger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imoberdorf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012a</year>). <article-title>Regulation of electrolyte and fluid metabolism in multi-stage ultra-marathoners</article-title>. <source>Horm. Metab. Res.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>919</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>926</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0032-1312647</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22638835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22638835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000fc;ck</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andonie</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008b</year>). <article-title>Effects of a deca iron triathlon on body composition: a case study</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Sports Med.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>351</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2007-965354</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17879892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17879892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Running 338 kilometres within five days has no effect on body mass and body fat but reduces skeletal muscle mass &#x02013; the Isarrun 2006</article-title>. <source>J. Sports Sci. Med</source>. <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>407</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 24149470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24149470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>N. P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;les</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>A. A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sevilla</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012b</year>). <article-title>Effects of a multistage ultraendurance triathlon on aldosterone, vasopressin, extracellular water and urine electrolytes</article-title>. <source>Scott. Med. J.</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1258/smj.2011.011287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22408212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salas Fraire</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andonie</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008a</year>). <article-title>Effect of a multistage ultra-endurance triathlon on body composition: World Challenge Deca Iron Triathlon 2006</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Sports Med.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>125</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsm.2007.038034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17601765?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17601765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zingg</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosemann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000fc;st</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Feet swelling in a multistage ultraendurance triathlete: a case study</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Gen. Med</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>332</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJGM.S94542</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26508884?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26508884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krabak</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waite</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rundell</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Exercise-associated hyponatremia, hypernatremia, and hydration status in multistage ultramarathons</article-title>. <source>Wilderness Environ. Med.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>298</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wem.2017.05.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28781178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28781178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kratz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewandrowski</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flood</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Cott</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee-Lewandrowski</surname></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Effect of marathon running on hematologic and biochemical laboratory parameters, including cardiac markers</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Clin. Pathol.</source>
<volume>118</volume>, <fpage>856</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>863</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1309/14TY-2TDJ-1X0Y-1V6V</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12472278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12472278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maughan</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirreffs</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leiper</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Errors in the estimation of hydration status from changes in body mass</article-title>. <source>J. Sports Sci</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>797</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>804</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640410600875143</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17454547?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17454547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casa</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheuvront</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>National athletic trainers' asscociation position statement: fluid replacement for the physically active</article-title>. <source>J. Athletic Train</source>. <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>877</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>895</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4085/1062-6050-52.9.02</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28985128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28985128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Applied sports nutrition support, dietary intake and body composition changes of a female athlete completing 26 Marathons in 26 Days. A Case Study</article-title>. <source>J. Sports Sci. Med</source>. <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 28344459?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28344459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Ultramarathon is an outstanding model for the study of adaptive responses to extreme load and stress</article-title>. <source>BMC Med.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-10-77</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22812424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22812424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noakes</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>Waterlogged. The Serious Problem of Overhydration in Endurance Sports</source>. <publisher-loc>Leeds</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Human Kinetics</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noakes</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>Biochemical parameters in athletes before and after having run 160 kilometres</article-title>. <source>S. Afr. Med. J.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1562</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1566</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 982211?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">982211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noakes</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharwood</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Speedy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hew</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Three independent biological mechanisms cause exercise-associated hyponatremia: evidence from 2,135 weighed competitive athletic performances</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source>. <volume>102</volume>, <fpage>18550</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18555</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0509096102</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16344476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16344476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastene</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>German</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allevard</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gharib</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacour</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Water balance during and after marathon running</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00262808</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8861668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8861668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rama</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Minuzzi</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>R. J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Changes of hematological markers during a multistage ultra-marathon competition in the heat</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Sports Med.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0035-1555929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26509375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rama</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ib&#x000e1;&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prats</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pag&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Hematological, electrolyte, and biochemical alterations after a 100-km run</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>420</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/h94-033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7849657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7849657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raschka</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plath</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Body fat compartment and its relationship to food intake and clinical chemical parameters during extreme endurance performance</article-title>. <source>Schweiz. Z. Sportmed.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1561538?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1561538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000fc;st</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knechtle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosemann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Higher prevalence of exercise-associated hyponatremia in triple iron ultra-triathletes than reported for ironman triathletes</article-title>. <source>Chin. J. Physiol</source>. <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>155</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4077/CJP.2012.BAA010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22784278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22784278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannan</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Prediction of fat and fat-free mass in male athletes using dual X-ray absorptiometry as the reference method</article-title>. <source>J. Sports Sci.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>274</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/026404100365009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10824643?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10824643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stockmann</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engeldinger</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>An innovative approach to functionality testing of analysers in the clinical laboratory</article-title>. <source>J. Autom. Methods Manag. Chem</source>. <volume>2008</volume>:<fpage>183747</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2008/183747</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18320013?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18320013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stuempfle</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weschler</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hew-Butler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Race diet of finishers and non-finishers in a 100-mile (161 km) mountain footrace</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Coll. Nutr</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07315724.2011.10719999</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22331688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22331688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noakes</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Changes in total body water content during running races of 21.1 km and 56 km in athletes drinking <italic>ad libitum</italic></article-title>. <source>Clin. J. Sport Med.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JSM.0b013e31820eb8d7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21427566?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21427566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Beaumont</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of hemoconcentration from hematocrit measurements</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Physiol</source>. <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>712</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>713</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1972.32.5.712</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 5038863?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5038863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dressendorfer</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Claybaugh</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Renal function, aldosterone, and vasopressin excretion following repeated long-distance running</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Physiol</source>. <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>712</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1981.50.4.709</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7263354?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7263354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haykowsky</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Humen</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Biochemical changes as a result of prolonged strenuous exercise</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Sports Med</source>. <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>303</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsm.36.4.301</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12145122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12145122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornetti</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jallo</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pivarnik</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>A skinfold model to predict fat-free mass in female athletes</article-title>. <source>J. Athl. Train.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15496996?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15496996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsden</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zettle</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halperin</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>New clinical approach to evaluate disorders of potassium excretion</article-title>. <source>Miner. Electrolyte Metab.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>234</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 3762510?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3762510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zanchi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Viallon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Goff</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giardini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croisille</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Extreme mountain ultra-marathon leads to acute but transient increase in cerebral water diffusivity and plasma biomarkers levels changes</article-title>. <source>Front. Physiol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>664</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2016.00664</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28105018?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28105018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zouhal</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Groussard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abderrahman</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delamarche</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Athletic performance and weight changes during the &#x0201c;Marathon of Sands&#x0201d; in athletes well-trained in endurance</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Sports Med.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>516</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>521</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1202350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19301211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>