<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6335714</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5425</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-019-5425-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Low-temperature-induced changes in the transcriptome reveal a major role of <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes in regulating flowering of <italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4749-8232</contrib-id><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Fengxi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Genfa</given-names></name><address><phone>86-20-87593419</phone><email>genfazhu@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Yonglu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Gang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Lingyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Chuqiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Jianpeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0561 6611</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.135769.f</institution-id><institution>Guangdong Key Laboratory of Ornamental Plant Germplasm Innovation and Utilization, </institution><institution>Environmental Horticulture Research Institute, Guangdong Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou, 510640 People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1799 1066</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.458477.d</institution-id><institution>CAS Key Laboratory of Tropical Plant Resources and Sustainable Use, Xishuangbanna Tropical Botanical Garden, </institution></institution-wrap>Kunming, Yunnan 650223 People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>53</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1"><italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic> is one of the most horticulturally important and popular ornamental plants in the orchid family (Orchidaceae). It blooms in winter during January&#x02013;March and a period of low temperature is necessary for its normal flowering, otherwise there is flower bud abortion, which seriously affects the economic benefits. However, the molecular mechanism underlying winter-blooming behavior in <italic>C. goeringii</italic> is unclear.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">In this research, we firstly study the flowering physiology of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> by cytobiology observations and physiological experiments. Using comparative transcriptome analysis, we identified 582 differentially expressed unigenes responding to cold treatment that were involved in metabolic process, flowering time, hormone signaling, stress response, and cell cycle, implying their potential roles in regulating winter-blooming of <italic>C. goeringii</italic>. Twelve MADS-box genes among them were investigated by full-length cDNA sequence analysis and expression validation, which indicated that three genes within the SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE (SVP) sub-group had the most significant repressed expression after cold treatment. Further analysis revealed that the SVP genes showed population variation in expression that correlated with cold-regulated flowering and responded to low temperature earlier than the flowering pathway integrators <italic>CgAP1</italic>, <italic>CgSOC1</italic>, and <italic>CgLFY</italic>, suggesting a potential role of <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes in the early stage of low-temperature-induced blooming of <italic>C. goeringii.</italic> Moreover, a yeast two-hybrid experiment confirmed that CgSVP proteins interacted with CgAP1 and CgSOC1, suggesting that they may synergistically control the process of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> flowering in winter.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">This study represents the first exploration of flowering physiology of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> and provides gene expression information that could facilitate our understanding of molecular regulation of orchid plant winter-flowering, which could provide new insights and practical guidance for improving their flowering regulation and molecular breeding.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12864-019-5425-7) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic></kwd><kwd>Low-temperature</kwd><kwd>Flowering</kwd><kwd>Transcriptome</kwd><kwd>SVP</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31672184</award-id><award-id>31872151</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Genfa</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003453</institution-id><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2015A030310325</award-id><award-id>2017A030312004</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Orchid Industry Technology Innovation Alliance</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016A090924006, 2017LM1095</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Genfa</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par36">The family Orchidaceae includes some of the most horticulturally important and popular ornamental plants in the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Particularly, the genus <italic>Cymbidium</italic>, which includes <italic>C. goeringii</italic>, <italic>C. sinense</italic>, <italic>C. faberi</italic> Rolfe, <italic>C. tortisepalum</italic>, and <italic>C. kanran</italic> Makino, holds a strong position in the traditional flower market in China, Japan, Korea, and Southeast Asia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Most of these orchids bloom in winter during January&#x02013;March and need 5&#x02013;10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C low-temperature conditions to promote flower opening. <italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic>, which is typically characterized by low-temperature-induced blooming, is considered a Spring Festival flower in most Asian countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. As a low-growing perennial herb, <italic>C. goeringii</italic> needs long photoperiods to induce floral spiking initiation from June, and then the initiated floral buds grow very slowly and become semi-dormant in the following months. By winter, a period of low temperatures is needed to end this slow-growth stage and promote inflorescence elongation and flower opening, otherwise this will result in flower bud abortion and seriously affect economic benefits. The process of flower initiation to flowering needs about 6 months, and a low-temperature period is critical for blooming. This greatly restricts the planting area of <italic>C. goeringii</italic>. Unfortunately, a way to genetically manipulate the flowering time of these orchids independently of temperature control is still unavailable. Understanding how flowering time and floral organ development are regulated by ambient temperature will provide practical guidance for molecular breeding and is of great importance to the orchid industry.</p><p id="Par37">Molecular mechanisms underlying flowering regulation have been extensively studied in model annual plants such as long-day plant <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], short-day plant rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], and winter cereals wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and barley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. However, in perennials, which have typical growth cycles including the juvenile to adult and vegetative to reproductive transitions, and flower initiation with flowering completion in the next year, understanding of the molecular mechanisms controlling flowering has just started to emerge. Recent studies in perennials, such as apple, peach and poplar, have revealed striking similarities between genes and pathways that regulate flowering time in annuals and growth and dormancy cycles in perennials. As reviewed by Ding and Nilsson (2016) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], homologs of circadian-clock and photoperiod pathway key components phytochromes (PHY) and CONSTANS (CO) impact on growth cessation; and homologs of flowering integrator gene <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>), bZIP transcription factor <italic>FD</italic>, and floral meristem identity gene <italic>APETALA1</italic> (<italic>AP1</italic>) have all been shown to control the onset of reproduction.</p><p id="Par38">Some other genes, such as those encoding APETALA2/Ethylene responsive transcription factor EARLY BUD-BREAK 1 (EBB1) and the C-repeat binding factor (CBF/DREB), were also identified to determine the time of bud break in trees [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Among the transcription factors, an important class of genes clearly associated with regulation of flowering in annuals and dormancy in perennials are MADS-box genes with similarity to <italic>Arabidopsis SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE</italic> (<italic>SVP</italic>)<italic>.</italic> For example, in annuals, <italic>Arabidopsis SVP</italic> is involved in both temperature- and photoperiod-dependent flowering pathways, and it forms a complex with <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS C</italic> (<italic>FLC</italic>) and <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS M</italic> (<italic>FLM</italic>), resulting in repression of <italic>FT</italic> and flowering [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Barley SVP-group member <italic>BM1</italic> is induced by cold treatment and causes a slight delay in heading time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In contrast, the wheat SVP-group gene <italic>TaVRT2</italic> is suppressed by vernalization, suggesting a differential expression profile in adaptation to the environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In perennials, the peach <italic>SVP</italic> gene family is expanded to six <italic>DAM</italic> genes, and their expression tracks seasonal light and temperature cycles, integrating environmental cues that regulate the transition into and out of endodormancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. <italic>Prunus mume SVP</italic> gene <italic>DAM6</italic> caused early growth cessation and early terminal bud set [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. <italic>Actinidia chinensis SVP2</italic> delayed budbreak in transgenic <italic>A. deliciosa</italic> and <italic>SVP3</italic> significantly repressed flower development, delayed the time of flower opening, and diminished flower fertility in <italic>A. eriantha</italic> as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. These results demonstrate similar molecular activity and growth inhibitory function among <italic>SVP-like</italic> genes. However, differential roles have been found for individual <italic>SVP</italic> gene family members, including bud dormancy, flowering initiation, and floral development &#x02013; probably related to the matching of plant growth period in adapting to local environments and seasonal changes.</p><p id="Par39">In order to understand the molecular mechanisms underlying the winter-flowering behavior of <italic>C. goeringii</italic>, based upon data from field observations and physiological experiments, we found at least 40-day of 10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C night-temperature was required to overcome the slow-growing stage, which could promote flowering rate from less than 20 to 85% and make flowers bloom 30&#x02009;days in advance. By comparative analysis of the floral bud transcriptome after 40&#x02009;days of low-temperature treatment, we identified 582 unigenes probably related to <italic>C. goeringii</italic> flowering regulation. The genes were involved in metabolic pathways, flowering time, hormone signaling, stress response, and cell cycle. Among them, 12 MADS-box genes were further investigated by full-length cDNA sequence analysis and expression validation. Particularly, three genes of different sub-clades within the <italic>CgSVP</italic> clade were characterized. Expression of <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes showed population and cultivar variation that correlated well with cold-regulated flowering. Results from yeast two-hybrid screening further indicated that the CgSVP proteins interacted with CgAP1 and CgSOC1, implying their potential roles in the control of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> flowering process. These results represent the first exploration of flowering physiology of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> and reveal the crucial role of <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes regulating its winter-flowering behavior, which shed light on the molecular regulation of winter-flowering of the orchid plant, and provide new insights and practical guidance for improving their flowering regulation and molecular breeding.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title><p id="Par40">Wild-type plants of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> &#x02018;Songmei&#x02019; (the most widely known commercial cultivar in China) used in this study were artificially cultivated and collected from the cultivation base of the Environmental Horticulture Research Institute, Guangdong Academy of Agricultural Sciences, China. Cold treatment of day/night with temperatures of 25/10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and photoperiod of 16/8&#x02009;h was carried out from September to November, 2015. The plants were classified into four groups with a prolonged cold treatment of a further 20, 30, 40, and 50 -day and then returned to normal conditions of 25/20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Library construction and Illumina sequencing</title><p id="Par41">The primary aim of this study was to identify the genes responsible for low-temperature-induced flowering. The cDNA libraries were prepared from RNAs isolated from floral buds before and after 40-day cold treatment. The mRNAs were purified from total RNA using the Oligotex mRNA Midi Kit (QIAGEN, Germany) and quantified using a Nano-Drop 2000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, USA) to generate the cDNA library according to the Illumina manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions as in our previous work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Briefly, mRNAs were isolated from Total RNA and fragmented to approximately 200&#x02009;bp. Subsequently, the collected mRNAs were subjected to first strand and second strand cDNA synthesis following by adaptor ligation and enrichment with a low-cycle according to instructions of TruSeq&#x000ae; RNA HT Sample Prep Kit (Illumina, USA). The purified library products were evaluated using the Agilent 2200 TapeStation and Qubit&#x000ae;2.0(Life Technologies,USA) and then diluted to 10 pM for cluster generation in situ on the HiSeq2500 pair-end flow cell followed by sequencing (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100&#x02009;bp). An average of more than 60 million reads was generated for each sample.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>DEG analysis</title><p id="Par42">The gene expression level was calculated by the RPKM value: RPKM&#x02009;=&#x02009;[total exon reads / mapped reads (millions)]&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;exon length (kb). The significance of differences in gene expression between the wild-type and mutant were determined using edgeR. The false discovery rate (FDR) was applied to identify the threshold of the <italic>P</italic>-value in multiple tests; with FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and |log2 ratio|&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1 (two-fold change) as the threshold for a significant difference in gene expression.</p><p id="Par43">The differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were annotated using gene ontology (GO) and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) enrichment analyses according to a method similar to that described by Wang et al. (2014) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], which firstly mapped all DEGs to GO terms (or KEGG pathways) in the databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org/">http://www.geneontology.org/</ext-link> or <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.ad.jp/">http://www.genome.ad.jp/</ext-link>) and calculated gene numbers for every term (or pathway) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. This was followed by a hypergeometric test to find the significantly enriched terms in DEGs compared with the genome background. We used the corrected <italic>P</italic>-value &#x02264;0.05 or Q-value &#x02264;0.05 as a threshold for the significantly enriched GO terms or KEGG pathways, respectively, in DEGs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Real-time quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) analysis</title><p id="Par44">For the qRT-PCR of target genes, total RNA extracted from different tissue types was reverse-transcribed using a oligo(dT) primed cDNA synthesis protocol (Fermentas). The resulting cDNA was subjected to relative quantitative PCR using Bio-Rad CFX-96 RealTime PCR System (Bio-Rad, USA) in a final volume of 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;l containing 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of cDNA and 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of SYBR premix Ex-taq&#x02122; (Takara, Japan). <italic>Ubiquitin</italic> and <italic>Actin</italic> were used as internal controls for normalization to make a comparison of gene expression level between the accessions. For each reported result at least three independent biological samples were subjected to a minimum of three technical replicates. The primers designed with Primer 5.0 software are listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1. Genbank accession numbers of the MADS-box genes examined are MF474250, MF474239, MF474243, MF462094, MF462081, MF462082, MF462083, MF474256, MF474244, MF474248, and MF462093.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Yeast two-hybrid assay</title><p id="Par45">For the yeast two-hybrid assay, full-length CDs of <italic>CgSVP1</italic> and <italic>CgSVP2</italic> were cloned into pGBKT7, and full-length <italic>CgSVP1</italic>, <italic>CgSVP2</italic>, <italic>CgAP1</italic>, and <italic>CgSOC1</italic> were cloned into pGADT7, respectively. Growth was determined as described in the Yeast Two-Hybrid System User Manual (Clontech). Experiments were repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Transient gene expression assays</title><p id="Par46">Infiltrations were performed according to a method modified from that previously described by Wroblewski et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> was resuspended with infiltration solution (pH =5.6) which contains 10&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> 2-(N-morpholino) ethanesulphonic acid (MES), 10&#x02009;m<sc>m</sc> magnesium chloride (Mgcl2), and 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> Acetosyringone (AS). Bacterial densities were adjusted to OD600&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.4&#x02013;0.5 prior to infiltration. 500&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> suspension contained in the syringe was then ejected into the floral bud where it was rapidly absorbed and repeated the experiment 7&#x02009;days later. GFP activity was visualized using a FluoroImager (Leica Microsystems, DFC7000T).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Scanning electron microscopy</title><p id="Par47">Lateral buds were collected weekly from 20 June to 1 September, and periodically thereafter until the next spring. Buds were partially dissected by removing outer bud scales, and the dissected apices were fixed in a solution of 3% glutaraldehyde and 2% formaldehyde for 24&#x02009;h. Then samples were dehydrated in acetone, critical-point dried in liquid CO<sub>2</sub>, and mounted on stubs and sputter coated with 25&#x02009;nm gold. Finally the samples were examined by scanning electron microscope JSM-6360LV (JEOL).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Flowering physiology of <italic>C. goeringii</italic></title><p id="Par48">Meristems with a potential to differentiate flowers are initiated in the lateral buds of developing shoots of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> from July. The initiated floral buds grow very slowly and become semi-dormant in the following months. We recorded the morphogenesis, growth rate, and surface structure of floral organs in detail using scanning electron microscopy. Flower development is divided into five stages (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Stage 1 begins with the initiation of a floral buttress on the flank of the shoot and forms a flower primordium (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a and f). Stage 2 commences very soon after the flower primordium divides into sepal primordia and petal stamen (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). Gynostemium primordia appear next (stage 3, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c and d) and petal primordia grow rapidly (stage 4, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>e); then the gynostemium primordia enlarge very slowly for a long period of 5&#x02009;months which we named as semi-endodormancy (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>g and h) and the final stage (stage 5) ends when the flower opens (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>i).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Floral development of <italic>Cymbidium goeringii.</italic>
<bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>e</bold> Scanning electron micrograph (SEM) of early floral developmental stages of wild-type <italic>C. goeringii.</italic> Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x02009;mm. Im, inflorescence meristem; Fm, floral meristem; Se, sepal primordium; Pe, petal primordium; Li, lip primordium; Co, column primordium. (<bold>f</bold>-<bold>h</bold>) developing floral bud, Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;cm. <bold>f</bold> potential floral bud initiated in the lateral buds of developing shoots. <bold>g</bold> semi-endodormant floral bud. <bold>h</bold> developing bud after cold-treatment in winter. <bold>i</bold> blooming flower</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par49">Under natural growth conditions it took 6&#x02013;7&#x02009;months to progress through the five stages from initiation to flower opening. Cold conditions were needed to avoid bud abortion (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, b and c) and promote flower development (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d, e, f and g) in the period of semi-endodormancy. As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, when exposed to 6&#x02013;8&#x02009;weeks of prolonged 10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C night-temperature treatment, flower buds on plants showed accelerated shoot growth and more than 85% flowering after their return to growth-promoting conditions, compared with 18.4% of those without cold treatment. These results indicated that prolonged cold treatment of semi-endodormant floral buds resulted in a dual response that ended the slow-growing stage, and at least 40&#x02009;days was needed to fulfill the cold requirement.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Cold pre-treatment and floral development stage of <italic>Cymbidium goeringii.</italic>
<bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>c</bold> 2 representative floral buds of the plants treated with a prolonged cold condition of 0, 20, and 40&#x02009;days, respectively, and then returned to normal condition. <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> Developing floral organs the plants treated with a prolonged cold condition of 0, 20, and 40&#x02009;days, respectively, and then returned to normal condition. <bold>g</bold> blooming flower. Se, sepal; Pe, petal; Li, lip; Co, column, Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;cm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Flowering physiology of <italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treat-ment (day)</th><th>Flowering rate(%)</th><th>Early blooming (day)</th><th>pedicel length (cm)</th><th>Pedicel diameter (mm)</th><th>Sepal width (mm)</th><th>Sepal length (mm)</th><th>Petal width (mm)</th><th>Petal length (mm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>0</td><td>18.4</td><td>71&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.9</td><td>11.40</td><td>3.17</td><td>1.23</td><td>2.78</td><td>1.31</td><td>3.68</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>30.8</td><td>64&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.3</td><td>10.96</td><td>3.03</td><td>1.12</td><td>2.82</td><td>1.26</td><td>3.74</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>54.7</td><td>50&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.2</td><td>10.13</td><td>3.34</td><td>1.10</td><td>2.60</td><td>1.23</td><td>3.59</td></tr><tr><td>40</td><td>84.5</td><td>40&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.4</td><td>10.40</td><td>3.09</td><td>1.13</td><td>2.73</td><td>1.25</td><td>3.64</td></tr><tr><td>50</td><td>85.8</td><td>42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9</td><td>9.53</td><td>3.16</td><td>1.08</td><td>2.58</td><td>1.28</td><td>3.72</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Early blooming day represents the number of days after the cold treatment to fully open flowers</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Transcriptome sequencing and DEGs</title><p id="Par50">To generate the inventory of gene expression during cold-induced flowering, we collected floral buds before and after cold treatment for comparative analyses by constructing poly-A RNA-seq libraries on an Illumina platform. This generated total reads of 59,201,226 and 63,343,254 in floral buds before and after cold treatment, respectively, with corresponding clean reads of 55,771,784 (94.21%) and 59,251,576 (93.54%) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Considering that a reference genome sequence of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> is lacking, we firstly de novo assembled the total 1115.02 million clean reads and obtained a dataset of 67,854 unigenes with a mean length of 903.2&#x02009;bp, which is less than our previous de novo dataset of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> flowers that contains 98,446 unigenes with a mean length of 989&#x02009;bp [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. To maximize the exploration of transcripts expressed in the floral bud before and after cold treatment, we therefore mapped all sequencing reads to <italic>C. goeringii</italic> floral transcriptome comprising 98,446 unigenes reported in our previous work. Total mapped reads were 44,370,452 (79.56%) and 48,590,106 (82.01%), respectively. This suggests that the majority of transcriptionally active genes were captured in our initial transcriptome assembly (NCBI Genbank accession number SRP091422).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of sequencing data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Ck</th><th>Cold</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Total reads</td><td>59,201,226</td><td>63,343,254</td></tr><tr><td>Clean reads</td><td>55,771,784 (94.21%)</td><td>59,251,576 (93.54%)</td></tr><tr><td>clean_data_base</td><td>5,539,214,099 (93.57%)</td><td>5,884,364,132 (92.90%)</td></tr><tr><td>Total mapped</td><td>44,370,452 (79.56%)</td><td>48,590,106 (82.01%)</td></tr><tr><td>Multiple mapped</td><td>11,474,064 (20.57%)</td><td>13,179,113 (22.24%)</td></tr><tr><td>Uniquely mapped</td><td>32,896,388 (58.98%)</td><td>35,410,993 (59.76%)</td></tr><tr><td>Read1 mapped</td><td>22,194,071 (39.79%)</td><td>24,307,230 (41.02%)</td></tr><tr><td>Read2 mapped</td><td>22,176,381 (39.76%)</td><td>24,282,876 (40.98%)</td></tr><tr><td>Reads map to &#x02018;+&#x02019;</td><td>22,124,348 (39.67%)</td><td>24,215,890 (40.87%)</td></tr><tr><td>Reads map to &#x02018;-&#x02019;</td><td>22,246,104 (39.89%)</td><td>24,374,216 (41.14%)</td></tr><tr><td>Reads mapped in proper pairs</td><td>20,253,005 (36.31%)</td><td>22,432,511 (37.86%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par51">For the estimation of overall transcriptional activity in floral buds before and after cold treatment, we determined reads per kilobase per million of mapped reads (RPKM) for each gene and calculated the number of DEGs (RPKM &#x02265;1) based on RPKM value. Overall, 582 genes showed altered expression after cold treatment, with 381 up-regulated and 201 down-regulated (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2), suggesting they had a potential role in cold response and flower development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Annotation statistics and functional enrichment</title><p id="Par52">To reveal the major functional categories represented in these genes, we performed GO enrichment analysis and assigned 55 GO terms (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>): 22 to biological process, 18 to cellular component and 15 to molecular function. Most changes in expression occurred in cytoplasmic membrane-bounded vesicle terms, followed by nucleus, membrane, and plasma membrane in cellular component, which correlated well with the maintenance of floral organ identity and reproductive growth. For the molecular function GO terms, ATP binding and oxidoreductase activity were most representative. Consistently, the biological-process GO terms oxidation&#x02013;reduction process and metabolic were obviously enriched, and the terms of stress response including response to cadmium ion, cold, heat, karrikin, water deprivation, salt stress, nematode, wounding, and high light intensity were generally detected. This result indicated that most genes involved in cold-induced flowering of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> were associated with various aspects of flower development and stress response.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>GO classification of unigenes differentially expressed after cold treatment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par53">In addition, we conducted an enrichment analysis using KEGG pathways, which assigned 192 DEGs to 112 pathways. Of these, &#x02018;metabolic pathways&#x02019; were the majority, followed by &#x02018;biosynthesis of secondary metabolites&#x02019;. Details of the pathway annotations for significant hits in unigene sets are provided in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S3. Pathways such as Glycolysis/gluconeogenesis, Arginine and proline metabolism, Biosynthesis of amino acids, and Microbial metabolism in diverse environments which respond to flowering physiology and environmental adaptation were also represented, consistent with the obviously enriched biological-process GO terms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Differential expression of flowering-related genes</title><p id="Par54">Homology searches of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> floral transcriptome in our previous studies successfully identified a large number of unigenes potentially involved in flowering regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. These included photoperiodic flowering-related genes <italic>CRY</italic>s, <italic>LHY</italic>, <italic>TOC1</italic>, <italic>FKF1</italic>, <italic>SOC1</italic>, <italic>FT</italic>, <italic>CO-</italic>like; temperature sensitive flowering pathway genes <italic>VIN3</italic>, <italic>VRN2</italic>, and <italic>SVP</italic>; and genes encoding hormone-related GI, Aux/IAA, and other transcription factors such as NAC, bZIP, and bHLH. Of the genes identified previously, at least one member of 21 families exhibited differential expression (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Table S4) and the major changes are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Differentially expressed genes related to floral development. Fold change&#x02009;=&#x02009;log2(expression value of each gene after cold treatment/before cold treatment), expression value&#x02009;=&#x02009;RPKM [total exon reads / mapped reads (millions)]&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;exon length (kb)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Locus</th><th>Ck</th><th>Cold</th><th>log2(fold_change)</th><th><italic>p</italic>_value</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6">MADS-box gene</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL8764Contig1</td><td>9.8869</td><td>0.4959</td><td>&#x02212;4.3174</td><td>9.43E-05</td><td>SOC1 [<italic>Dendrobium hybrid cultivar</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL8650Contig1</td><td>20.9806</td><td>1.0767</td><td>&#x02212;4.2844</td><td>6.47E-05</td><td>SOC1 [<italic>Dendrobium hybrid cultivar</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp43097</td><td>0.4641</td><td>6.4672</td><td>2.4787</td><td>2.03E-02</td><td>SOC1 [<italic>Dendrobium hybrid cultivar</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp50389</td><td>4.099</td><td>71.4805</td><td>4.1242</td><td>8.95E-05</td><td>SOC1-like protein [<italic>Prunus x yedoensis</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp44547</td><td>14.9139</td><td>2.9644</td><td>&#x02212;2.3308</td><td>6.67E-61</td><td>SVP1 [<italic>Actinidia deliciosa</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp28009</td><td>114.453</td><td>5.2832</td><td>&#x02212;4.4372</td><td>0.00E+&#x02009;00</td><td>MADS-box protein SVP [<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp36141</td><td>42.2288</td><td>8.5568</td><td>&#x02212;2.3031</td><td>4.71E-190</td><td>PREDICTED: MADS-box protein SVP [<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp38228</td><td>13.3352</td><td>0.8606</td><td>&#x02212;3.9538</td><td>5.00E-04</td><td>FRUITFULL-like MADS box protein 1 [<italic>Dendrobium thyrsiflorum</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp717274</td><td>15.2507</td><td>232.579</td><td>3.9308</td><td>1.61E-04</td><td>AP1-like MADS-box protein [<italic>Cymbidium ensifolium</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL551Contig1</td><td>0.0892</td><td>5.9554</td><td>6.0604</td><td>1.87E-06</td><td>AGL66 protein [<italic>Eschscholzia californica</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp36586</td><td>10.2183</td><td>136.628</td><td>3.741</td><td>3.16E-04</td><td>AP3 [<italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp49009</td><td>0.2395</td><td>6.6177</td><td>4.7883</td><td>2.00E-04</td><td>AP3 [<italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">Other flowering and floral related gene</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp38616</td><td>3.0342</td><td>0.5423</td><td>&#x02212;1.9762</td><td>9.43E-05</td><td>Flowering locus T protein [<italic>Ananas comosus</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp59699</td><td>0.8817</td><td>0.2078</td><td>&#x02212;2.0139</td><td>5.00E-04</td><td>Flowering locus D [<italic>Zea mays</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp42797</td><td>1.0459</td><td>41.3741</td><td>5.306</td><td>6.47E-05</td><td>AP2&#x02013;7 [<italic>Erycina pusilla</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp218062</td><td>26.5682</td><td>0.7566</td><td>&#x02212;5.134</td><td>2.03E-02</td><td>LEAFY [<italic>Cymbidium hybrid cultivar</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp738577</td><td>40.6535</td><td>1.3573</td><td>&#x02212;4.9045</td><td>8.95E-05</td><td>LEAFY, partial [<italic>Cattleya hybrid cultivar</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp48048</td><td>9.3535</td><td>380.927</td><td>5.3479</td><td>6.67E-61</td><td>PREDICTED: late embryogenesis abundant protein D-29-like [<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp19364</td><td>3.8409</td><td>89.0779</td><td>4.5356</td><td>0.00E+&#x02009;00</td><td>PREDICTED: late embryogenesis abundant protein D-34-like [<italic>Cicer arietinum</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL4811Contig1</td><td>0.0451</td><td>5.3112</td><td>6.8811</td><td>4.71E-190</td><td>Putative aquaporin TIP5&#x02013;1 [<italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL3697Contig1</td><td>1.4658</td><td>44.228</td><td>4.9152</td><td>5.00E-04</td><td>PREDICTED: 18&#x02009;kDa seed maturation protein-like [<italic>Cucumis sativus</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">Plant hormone signaling pathway</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL8703Contig1</td><td>4.2816</td><td>0.1327</td><td>&#x02212;5.0116</td><td>9.43E-05</td><td>PREDICTED: DELLA protein RGL2 [<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL9507Contig1</td><td>84.2097</td><td>4.8002</td><td>&#x02212;4.1328</td><td>5.00E-04</td><td>PREDICTED: auxin-induced protein 15A-like [<italic>Glycine max</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp45207</td><td>0.1394</td><td>14.8622</td><td>6.736</td><td>6.47E-05</td><td>SAUR11 - auxin-responsive SAUR family member [<italic>Zea mays</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp58943_c0_seq9:0&#x02013;1130</td><td>0.2642</td><td>690.516</td><td>11.3521</td><td>2.03E-02</td><td>ABA related CCAAT-box binding factor HAP5 homolog [<italic>Daucus carota</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp22898</td><td>0.4163</td><td>25.9618</td><td>5.9625</td><td>8.95E-05</td><td>PREDICTED: ABA related transcription factor GTE1-like [<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">Temperature-responsive factors</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp328221</td><td>16.1755</td><td>6.2463</td><td>0.0003</td><td>9.43E-05</td><td>CBF-like transcription factor [<italic>Trachycarpus fortunei</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp36229</td><td>7.1138</td><td>&#x02212;6.1581</td><td>0</td><td>5.00E-04</td><td>Chaperone [<italic>Agave tequilana</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp38271</td><td>8.8938</td><td>&#x02212;4.5248</td><td>0</td><td>6.47E-05</td><td>Chaperone [<italic>Agave tequilana</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp54221</td><td>11.8107</td><td>&#x02212;3.6707</td><td>0.0004</td><td>2.03E-02</td><td>Chaperone [<italic>Agave tequilana</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL5833Contig1</td><td>3.8015</td><td>&#x02212;4.1095</td><td>0.0001</td><td>8.95E-05</td><td>Chloroplast small heat shock protein [<italic>Agave americana</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp38941</td><td>3.8102</td><td>&#x02212;6.1497</td><td>0</td><td>6.67E-61</td><td>Class-1 LMW heat shock protein [<italic>Ananas comosus</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp63219</td><td>89.7919</td><td>&#x02212;4.358</td><td>0.0001</td><td>4.71E-190</td><td>Class-1 LMW heat shock protein [<italic>Ananas comosus</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL8847Contig1</td><td>18.538</td><td>&#x02212;3.6826</td><td>0.0004</td><td>5.00E-04</td><td>Mitochondrial small heat shock protein [<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp39275</td><td>8.2354</td><td>&#x02212;3.6881</td><td>0.0004</td><td>1.61E-04</td><td>PREDICTED: 17.4&#x02009;kDa class III heat shock protein-like [<italic>Glycine max</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL276Contig2</td><td>8.1857</td><td>&#x02212;4.9339</td><td>0</td><td>1.87E-06</td><td>PREDICTED: 17.9&#x02009;kDa class I heat shock protein-like [<italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">Other transcription factors</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp51260</td><td>0.2133</td><td>208.395</td><td>9.9324</td><td>9.43E-05</td><td>PREDICTED: WRKY transcription factor 6-like [<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp34195</td><td>38.4439</td><td>2.4205</td><td>&#x02212;3.9894</td><td>5.00E-04</td><td>PREDICTED: WRKY transcription factor 22 [<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp25957</td><td>50.8577</td><td>3.9329</td><td>&#x02212;3.6928</td><td>6.47E-05</td><td>Putative MYB DNA-binding domain superfamily protein [<italic>Zea mays</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp42603</td><td>3.1925</td><td>364.995</td><td>6.837</td><td>2.03E-02</td><td>Putative R2R3-MYB transcription factor [<italic>Citrus sinensis</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL10849Contig1</td><td>0.0499</td><td>9.6423</td><td>7.5943</td><td>8.95E-05</td><td>TPA: putative MYB DNA-binding domain superfamily protein [<italic>Zea mays</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep123.comp101748</td><td>11.1484</td><td>0.3893</td><td>&#x02212;4.8396</td><td>6.67E-61</td><td>TPA: putative HLH DNA-binding domain superfamily protein [<italic>Zea mays</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CL2976Contig1</td><td>17.7943</td><td>0.9644</td><td>&#x02212;4.2057</td><td>0.00E+&#x02009;00</td><td>Putative bHLH transcription factor [<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ep456.comp28555</td><td>7.4971</td><td>&#x02212;6.2209</td><td>0</td><td>4.71E-190</td><td>CYP86C1 [<italic>Arabidopsis lyrata subsp. lyrata</italic>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par55">Among the various families, MADS-box family transcription factors, well known for their roles in flower initiation and floral development, were most represented. A total of 12 MADS-box genes showed differential expression &#x02013; including <italic>CgAP1</italic>, <italic>CgSOC1</italic>, <italic>CgAP3</italic>, and <italic>CgSVP</italic>s &#x02013; suggesting their potential roles in cold-induced flowering of <italic>C. goeringii</italic>. In addition, there were notable differential expressions among the auxin receptor genes, cytokinin-responsive genes, and <italic>DELLA</italic> family genes, which revealed a critical role of the complex plant hormone network in regulating flower organ primordia formation, organ specification, and final organ development. Most importantly, we found a great number of transcription factors differentially expressed after cold treatment, encoding WRKY, bHLH, MYB, CYP, temperature-responsive HSP and CBF, as well as LATE EMBRYOGENESIS ABUNDANT proteins. These data suggest that accompanying the MADS-box genes, regulators of auxin, gibberellic acid, abscisic acid, and cold signaling were differentially expressed if buds were subjected to cold, highlighting potential involvement of these regulators in <italic>C. goeringii</italic> flowering competence.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Validation of gene expression in response to cold</title><p id="Par56">The digital gene expression analysis showed that MADS-box genes represented the majority of gene families that were differentially expressed. To validate the DEG results and determine the potential roles of the MADS-box genes referred to above, we obtained their full length sequences and confirmed their expression responses to cold using qRT-PCR. EST-encoding ubiquitin and actin genes were used as internal controls, to which gene expression was normalized. The same mRNA flower samples used for transcriptome sequencing served as templates. Among the 12 genes tested, 11 showed a significant expression difference after cold treatment, with six down-regulated and five up-regulated. Among them, three paralogs of <italic>SVP</italic> genes ep123.comp44547, ep456.comp28009, and ep456.comp36141 had the most significant repressed expression, with decreases in the range of 50&#x02013;70%. In contrast, transcripts of <italic>SOC1</italic>-like ep456.comp50389, <italic>AP3</italic>-like ep123.comp36586, ep456.comp49009, and AGL66 clade CL551Contig1 increased by 2&#x02013;8 fold, identical to those obtained by DEG expression profiling (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The quantitative RT-PCR analysis of gene expression before and after cold treatment</p><p>The y-axis indicates fold change in expression among the samples. Expression levels were normalized using the threshold cycle values obtained for the <italic>Ubiquitin</italic> and <italic>Actin</italic> genes. Error bars indicate the standard deviation of the mean (SD) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Three replicates were analyzed, with similar results. One way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 between the two samples</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><italic>CgSVP</italic> expression correlates with cold-regulated flowering of <italic>C. goeringii</italic></title><p id="Par57">The <italic>SVP</italic> genes showed the most significant decrease after cold treatment, implying their potential important roles in responding to cold during the process of flower development. Phylogenetic analysis showed that the <italic>SVP</italic> homologs of orchid plants form a separate clade and divided into three sub-clades. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, ep456.comp28009, ep123.comp44547, and ep456.comp36141 showed high similarity with <italic>Apostasia odorata SVP</italic>, <italic>Erycina pusilla MADS19</italic>, and <italic>Erycina pusilla MADS18</italic>, respectively. We correspondingly named them <italic>CgSVP1</italic>, <italic>CgSVP2</italic>, and <italic>CgSVP3</italic> belonging to three different sub-clades (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Accumulation profiles in the process of floral development indicated that <italic>CgSVP1</italic>, <italic>CgSVP2</italic>, and <italic>CgSVP3</italic> accumulated in stage 1, at levels 52, 98, and 8.5-fold higher than those in stage 5, respectively. With maturing of the flower, their expressions gradually decreased, suggesting a negative relationship with flower development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). Moreover, we found these expression patterns of <italic>SVP</italic> genes altered in different cultivated varieties of <italic>Cymbidium</italic> spp. with a range of flowering habits. For example, in <italic>C. sinense</italic>, which is a close relative of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> and also flowers in winter, <italic>CsSVP</italic> genes dramatically accumulated in stage 1, and decreased during bud development stages 1&#x02013;5 from 100- to 10-fold (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S1). In contrast, <italic>C. ensifolium</italic>, which flowers in summer and needs no cold treatment, the <italic>CeSVP</italic> genes showed no more than 8-fold change during floral development (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Figure S2).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of the SVP-like proteins from different plant species. Amino acid sequences were aligned by the ClustalW 2.0, and phylogenetic relationships were reconstructed using a maximum-likelihood (ML) method in PHYML software with JTT amino acid substitution model. Bootstrap values for 1000 replicates were used to assess the robustness of the trees. Previously published plant SVP protein sequences were retrieved from GenBank database. Aa: <italic>Anthurium amnicola</italic>, Ao: <italic>Apostasia odorata</italic>, Bj: <italic>Brassica juncea</italic>, Br: <italic>Brassica rapa</italic>, Cc: <italic>Carya cathayensis</italic>, Ct: <italic>Citrus trifoliate</italic>, Eg, <italic>Elaeis guineensis</italic>, Ep: <italic>Erycina pusilla</italic>, Gm:<italic>Glycine max</italic>, Lp: <italic>Lolium perenne</italic>, Mh: <italic>Monotropa hypopitys</italic>, Os, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>.(AtSVP: BAD43004, BM10: ABM21529, LpMADS10: AAZ17549, ZMM19: NP_001105148, ZMM26: NP_001105154, ZMM21: CAD23411, OsM55: BAD35842, RMD1: BAA81880, INCO: CAG27846, BrSVP: XP_009112514, EgSVP: XP_010942683, AaSVP: JAT54145, GmSVP: NP_001240951, AoSVP: AIZ95422, CtSVP: ACJ09170, EpMADS18: AJB29196, EpMADS19: AJB29197, MhAGL24: AQM52285, CcAGL24: AHI85951, AtAGL24: OAO97218, BjAGL24: AFM77904)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Expression patterns of <italic>SVP</italic> genes in different cultivated varieties of Cymbidium genus (a-c).. The y-axis indicates fold change in expression among the&#x000a0;floral buds at different developmental stages. Expression levels were normalized using the threshold cycle values obtained for the <italic>Ubiquitin</italic> and <italic>Actin</italic> genes. Error bars indicate the standard deviation of the mean (SD) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Three replicates were analyzed, with similar results</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par58">Moreover, a time-course responses of Cg<italic>SVP</italic> and flowering integrators <italic>CgAP1</italic>, <italic>CgFT</italic>, <italic>CgSOC1</italic>, <italic>CgLFY</italic> to low temperature were determined, to further validate the <italic>CgSVP</italic> transcript associated with cold response and <italic>C. goeringii</italic> flowering behavior. <italic>CgSVP2</italic> which showed the largest decrease in expression in cold condition was chosen. The Result as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> indicated that the expression of <italic>CgSVP2</italic> began to decrease after the 12-h treatment at low temperature. However, expression levels of <italic>CgSOC1</italic>, <italic>CgLFY</italic>, and <italic>CgAP1</italic> increased after 24&#x02013;36&#x02009;h of low-temperature treatment. These results suggested that the <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes showed population and cultivar variation in expression that correlated with cold-regulated flowering and probably function in the early stage of low temperature-induced flowering of <italic>C. goeringii.</italic><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Time course cold response of <italic>CgSVP2</italic> and floral pathway integrators. The y-axis indicates fold change in expression among the samples. Expression levels were normalized using the threshold cycle values obtained for the <italic>Ubiquitin</italic> and <italic>Actin</italic> genes. Error bars indicate the standard deviation of the mean (SD) (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Three replicates were analyzed, with similar results</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig><fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Transient over-expression of <italic>CgSVP2</italic> inhibits flower bud development. <bold>a</bold> Flower bud of wild-type (WT), <italic>35S:eGFP</italic> and <italic>35S:CgSVP2.</italic> Photos were taken in 3&#x02009;weeks after injection of <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>. <bold>b</bold> Increased expression level of <italic>CgSVP2</italic> in the flower bud infiltrated with <italic>35S:CgSVP2</italic>, <bold>c</bold> Appearance of floral organs in the flower bud infiltrated with <italic>35S:CgSVP2</italic> and <italic>35S:eGFP</italic>. D-G: GFP signal detected after injection of <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> for 3&#x02009;days (<bold>d</bold>), 5&#x02009;days (<bold>e</bold>), 3&#x02009;weeks (<bold>f</bold>), and 5&#x02009;weeks (<bold>g</bold>) as a control to confirm continuous gene expression</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Transient over-expression of <italic>CgSVP</italic> in <italic>C. goeringii</italic> floral bud</title><p id="Par59">In order to verify the function of <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes in vivo, we carried out a transient expression experiment in the floral bud of <italic>C. goeringii</italic>. <italic>CgSVP2</italic> which showed the strongest changes in gene expression during floral development and in response to cold was chosen for function analysis. <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> carrying <italic>35S:CgSVP2</italic> or <italic>35S:eGFP</italic> was injected into the flower buds (60&#x02009;days after floral initiation) of <italic>C. goeringii</italic>. After 3&#x02009;weeks of growth in the condition of 25/10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and photoperiod of 16/8&#x02009;h, we observed a retarded growth of flower buds injected with <italic>CgSVP2</italic>, which showed 16&#x02013;21% decrease in length and 10&#x02013;14% decrease in width. Meanwhile, floral organ size is also remarkably repressed, especially for the differentiation of the lip and the column compared with the control group injected <italic>35S:eGFP</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). Together with functional studies of <italic>SVP-like</italic> genes in other species, these data are consistent with <italic>SVP</italic> genes being repressors of flower bud development that have been coopted for cold-induced <italic>C. goeringii</italic> flowering.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Protein&#x02013;protein interactions</title><p id="Par60">It is well known that most MADS-box proteins function in the form of homodimers and heterodimers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Considering the orchid-specific whole-genome duplication event which provided extensive genes for neo-functionalization, sub-functionalization, or dosage strengthening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], we used yeast two-hybrid assays to identify the interacting partner of CgSVP proteins. The full-length coding region of <italic>CgSVP1, CgSVP2</italic>, and <italic>CgSVP3</italic> were used as the bait to screen the cDNA library of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> floral buds, and 87 positive clones were obtained. Sequencing analyses suggested that 11 of them encoded CgSOC1, CgAP1, and CgSVP2, respectively. To further confirm the protein interactions, the full-length coding regions of <italic>CgSOC1</italic> and <italic>CgAP1</italic> were cloned, after which the interaction between the encoded proteins and CgSVP proteins was confirmed in yeast cells. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, CgSVP2 could homodimerize as well as heterodimerize with CgAP1 and CgSOC1, and interactions also exist between CgSVP1-CgAP1 and CgSVP1-CgSOC1. However, we can neither detect protein-protein interactions between CgSVP3 and CgAP1/CgSOC1 nor protein homodimerization activities of CgSVP1 and CgSVP3 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Figure&#x000a0;S3). Distinct protein interaction patterns suggest that <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes may perform conserved, but distinct functions similarly to <italic>SVP-like</italic> genes from other species which showed conservation and divergence of biological roles in floral meristem identity.<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Protein&#x02013;protein interaction among CgAP1, CgSOC1 and CgSVP proteins. Protein interaction behavior is indicated by growth on selection medium lacking leucine, tryptophan, histidine, and adenine</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec20"><title>Cold-regulated floral development of <italic>C. goeringii</italic></title><p id="Par61">The correct timing for flowering is critical in plant adaptation and survival in perennials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. After an active growth period in summer, specific photoperiod and/or temperature conditions are determinant environmental cues for bud set, growth cessation, and following release. Vegetative growth of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>goeringii</italic> dominates during summer&#x02013;autumn, when the floral transition begins in the newly developed axillary buds under long photoperiods and warm conditions. Then, the initiated floral buds grow very slowly and a 5&#x02013;10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C cold condition is required in winter to promote floral development and finally blooming during January&#x02013;March.</p><p id="Par62">In this study, comparative transcriptome analyses showed most obvious enrichment for metabolism and related gene functions within biological process. KEGG pathways related to metabolism such as glycolysis/gluconeogenesis, arginine, proline, and microbial metabolisms were also representative, consistent with previous reports showing extensive reprogramming of transcriptional and metabolic pathways involved in seasonal dormancy of perennial plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p id="Par63">Moreover, 21 gene families related to flowering and floral development exhibited differential expression, which included flowering integrator factors FT, FD, and LFY proteins and the well-known MADS-box <italic>AP1</italic>, <italic>SOC1</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>SVP</italic> homologs, as well as many other regulatory transcription factors involved in plant hormone signal transduction pathways. Most importantly, regarding the DEG data, we found significant changes in the regulators that contributed to reproductive organ development, such as pollen related aquaporin <italic>TIP5&#x02013;1</italic> (CL4811Contig1), seed maturation protein-like (CL3697Contig1), which indicated a cold response of reproductive organs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">Results also highlighted that genes responding to cadmium ion, cold, heat, karrikin, water deprivation, salt stress, nematode, wounding, and high light intensity were involved in the flowering process. Among them, we noted a higher level of cold-response <italic>CBF</italic> in the cold condition; interestingly, a great number of heat shock proteins and chaperones showed dominant expression level in normal growth conditions, and marked decreases after cold treatment. Small heat shock proteins form the first line of defense against protein aggregation in order to maintain protein homeostasis and minimize injury when exposed to a harsh environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. As mentioned above, <italic>C. goeringii</italic> only bloomed following exposure to cold. Otherwise, the buds withered in our field experiment, consistent with the DEG data showing a heat shock stress response under natural conditions. This result indicated that heat shock stress was the primary reason for failure to bloom.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Cold-responsive gene expression of <italic>CgSVP</italic>s in <italic>C. goeringii</italic></title><p id="Par65">The role of <italic>SVP</italic> genes in the temperature-dependent control of flowering in annual species and bud dormancy in perennial species have been widely studied, and appear to be functionally diversified in regulating flowering time. In addition, the expression of <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes in different cultivated varieties of <italic>Cymbidium</italic> spp. with different flowering habits fulfilled our predictions for a gene directly or indirectly involved in flowering differences between the populations. To further validate if the <italic>CgSVP</italic> transcript associated with cold response and <italic>C. goeringii</italic> flowering behavior, we used qRT-PCR to determine the time-course response of Cg<italic>SVP</italic>2 and flowering regulatory genes <italic>CgAP1</italic>, <italic>CgFT</italic>, <italic>CgSOC1</italic>, and <italic>CgLFY</italic> to low temperature, according to the transcriptome sequencing. We found that the response of <italic>CgSVP</italic>s to low temperature was earlier than that of <italic>CgSOC1</italic>, <italic>CgLFY</italic>, and <italic>CgAP1</italic>, which is very similar to the response of <italic>FLC</italic> before <italic>AP1</italic> to vernalization. Assuming they are indeed repressors, we propose that <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes play an important role upstream of <italic>CgSOC1</italic>, <italic>CgLFY</italic>, and <italic>CgAP1</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Homodimerization and Heterodimerization of SVP function in flowering regulation</title><p id="Par66">Considerable effort has been made to identify and characterize SVP genes in many monocots and dicots, and has demonstrated similar molecular activity and growth inhibitory function among <italic>SVP</italic> genes, but differential functional pathways have been found for individual <italic>SVP</italic> gene family members. For example, the dicot <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SVP protein forms a complex with related temperature-responsive proteins FLC and FLM. In monocot wheat, TaSVP protein regulates the flowering activator TaVRN1 by directly binding to the CArG box located in the promoter of <italic>TaVRN1</italic> gene, and can also homodimerize and form heterodimers with several transcription factors involved in flowering control and vernalization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The observed expression pattern of <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes that correlated with cold-regulated flowering led us to hypothesize that decreased expression of <italic>CgSVP</italic> genes during cold days negates the repressive effects on floral growth of <italic>C. goeringii</italic>. However, their exact roles in the flowering pathway remain unclear. Our yeast two-hybrid assay suggested that CgSVP2 interacts with CgSOC1 and CgAP1, similar to reports in petunia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], <italic>Antirrhinum</italic>, and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], implying that protein&#x02013;protein interactions and formation of complexes are the basis of MADS-box transcription factor function. Therefore, the interaction between members of these clades may represent an evolutionarily conserved property that is important for their function, and AP1 probably serves as a hub between the interacting proteins of the flower induction pathway (such as SVP, SOC1, and AGL24) and the floral organ identity proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. However, this might not represent a general property for homodimerization of SVP proteins, since we failed to detected homodimerization of CgSVP1 and CgSVP3, and dicot AtSVP also does not homodimerize [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. This suggests that there will be differences among the interactions of transcriptional activator/repressor MADS-box proteins that regulate flowering time in plants. Overall, the physical associations of SVP with other partners further our knowledge of the regulation of flowering in low-temperature-sensitive orchids, which could offer clues for further studies to determine their functions in flowering regulation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par67">As a horticulturally important ornamental plant in the orchid family, <italic>C. goeringii</italic> is typically characterized by its winter-blooming behavior. To better understand the molecular regulation of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> winter-blooming, we study the process of floral bud development by cytobiology observations and physiological experiments, and compared the transcriptome of floral bud before and after cold-treatment. Consequently, 582 candidate genes involved in metabolic process, flowering time, hormone signaling, stress response, and cell cycle, were found to be related to the process of low-temperature-induced flowering of <italic>C. goeringii</italic>. Based on full-length cDNA sequence analysis and expression validation, we found that three genes within the SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE (SVP) sub-group of MADS-box gene family are most closely related with low-temperature-induced flowering and interact with CgAP1 and CgSOC1, suggesting that they may synergistically control the process of <italic>C. goeringii</italic> flowering in winter. This work represents the first exploration of flowering physiology of <italic>C. goeringii,</italic> and provides gene expression information that could facilitate our understanding of molecular regulation of orchid plant winter-flowering.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec24"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> The primers used for Realtime RT-PCR. (XLSX 11 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S2.</bold> List of gene ID and transcript fold changes of the all DEGs (differentially expressed genes). (XLSX 47 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S3.</bold> Details of the pathway annotations for the DEGs by KEGG. (XLSX 18 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S4.</bold> Function annotations of the DEGs after cold treatment. (XLSX 39 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_MOESM5_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> Floral development stages of <italic>Cymbidium sinense. (TIF 3245 kb)</italic></p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_MOESM6_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S2.</bold> Floral development stages of <italic>Cymbidium ensifolium. (TIF 3232 kb)</italic></p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5425_MOESM7_ESM.jpg"><label>Additional file 7:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S3.</bold> Homodimerization and Heterodimerization of <italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic> MADS-box proteins. (JPG 142 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AGL</term><def><p id="Par4">AGAMOUS-Like</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AP1</term><def><p id="Par5">APETALA1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AP2/ERF</term><def><p id="Par6">APETALA2/Ethylene Responsive Factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AP3</term><def><p id="Par7">APETALA3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ARF</term><def><p id="Par8">Auxin response factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Aux/IAA</term><def><p id="Par9">Auxin/indole-3-acetic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>bHLH</term><def><p id="Par10">basic helix-loop-helix</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>bZIP</term><def><p id="Par11">Basic leucine zipper</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CBF</term><def><p id="Par12">C-repeat binding factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CO</term><def><p id="Par13">CONSTANS</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CYP</term><def><p id="Par14">Cytochromes P450</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DAM</term><def><p id="Par15">Dormancy-associated MADS-BOX</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DEGs</term><def><p id="Par16">Differentially expressed genes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FLC</term><def><p id="Par17">Flowering Locus C</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FT</term><def><p id="Par18">Flowering Locus T</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GI</term><def><p id="Par19">GA insensitive</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p id="Par20">Gene ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HSP</term><def><p id="Par21">Heat shock protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p id="Par22">Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LFY</term><def><p id="Par23">Leafy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LHY</term><def><p id="Par24">Late elongated hypocotyl</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MYB</term><def><p id="Par25">Myeloblastosis transcription factors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NAC</term><def><p id="Par26">NAM, ATAF, and CUC transcription factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPM</term><def><p id="Par27">Reads per million</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAM</term><def><p id="Par28">Shoot apical meristem</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAUR</term><def><p id="Par29">Small auxin up RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SOC</term><def><p id="Par30">Suppressor of CONSTANS</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SVP</term><def><p id="Par31">Short vegetative phase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TIP</term><def><p id="Par32">Tonoplast intrinsic protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TOC</term><def><p id="Par33">Timing of CAB expression</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VIN</term><def><p id="Par34">Vernalization insensitive</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VRN</term><def><p id="Par35">Vernalization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to Guangzhou Ribobio Corporation for technical assistance in data processing and bioinformatics analysis, and the Yuandong Chinese Orchid Corporation for plant cultivation.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par68">This research was funded by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31872151, 31672184), the Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong province (2017A030312004,&#x000a0;2017B020201004),the Orchid Industry Technology Innovation Alliance (2018LM1095, 2017A070702008).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par69">Uploaded as Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>, sequencing clean data were uploaded to the Sequence Read Archive (SRA) database of NCBI (Genbank accession number SRP091422, SRP6678066).</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>FX Y and GF Z designed the experiments, analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript with input from all authors. YL W, G L helped design the study and analyzed the data; FX Y, GF Z and LY P executed the experiments and assembled the figures. LY P, CQ L and J G conducted the qRT-PCR. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanneste</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Proost</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genome sequence of the orchid <italic>Phalaenopsis equestris</italic> (vol 47, pg 65, 2015)</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>304</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0315-304a</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wong DCJ, Pichersky E, Peakall R. The biosynthesis of unusual floral volatiles and blends involved in orchid pollination by deception: current Progress and future prospects. Front Plant Sci. 2017;8:1955.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Du P, Cribb P. The genus Cymbidium. London and Portland, Oregon: Christopher Helm and Timber Press.&#x000a0;1988.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity, population structure, pollen morphology and cross-compatibility among Chinese <italic>Cymbidiums</italic></article-title><source>Plant Breed</source><year>2014</year><volume>133</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbr.12125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang FX, Zhu GF, Wang Z, Liu HL, Xu QQ, Huang D, et al. Integrated mRNA and microRNA transcriptome variations in the multi-tepal mutant provide insights into the floral patterning of the orchid <italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic>. BMC Genomics. 2017;18(1):367.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity of 129 spring orchid (cymbidium goeringii) cultivars and its relationship to horticultural types as assessed by EST-SSR markers</article-title><source>Sci Hortic-Amsterdam</source><year>2014</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2014.05.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xiang L, Chen Y, Chen L, Fu X, Zhao K, Zhang J, Sun C. B and E MADS-box genes determine the perianth formation in <italic>Cymbidium goeringii</italic> Rchb.f. Physiol Plant. 2017. 10.1111/ppl.12647.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Banta</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Seufferheld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variation in Arabidopsis flowering time associated with cis-regulatory variation in CONSTANS</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3651</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms4651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24736505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putterill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Varkonyi-Gasic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FT and florigen long-distance flowering control in plants</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2016.06.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27348248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic control of flowering time in rice: integration of Mendelian genetics and genomics</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>129</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2241</fpage><lpage>2252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-016-2773-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27695876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krasileva</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasquez-Gross</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Paraiso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Clissold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Uncovering hidden variation in polyploid wheat</article-title><source>P Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>E913</fpage><lpage>E921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1619268114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruelens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>D'hauw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dochy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Torfs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A flowering locus C homolog is a Vernalization-regulated repressor in <italic>Brachypodium</italic> and is cold regulated in wheat</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>173</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1301</fpage><lpage>1315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.16.01161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28034954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Ariza</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerise</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The importance of being on time: regulatory networks controlling photoperiodic flowering in cereals</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>665</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28491078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular regulation of phenology in trees-because the seasons they are a-changin</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2015.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26748352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yordanov</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Busov</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EARLY BUD-BREAK 1 (EBB1) is a regulator of release from seasonal dormancy in poplar trees</article-title><source>P Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><issue>27</issue><fpage>10001</fpage><lpage>10006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1405621111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisniewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Norelli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Artlip</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of a peach CBF gene in apple: a model for understanding the integration of growth, dormancy, and cold hardiness in woody plants</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>85</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25774159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Niinuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomozoe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circadian clock proteins LHY and CCA1 regulate SVP protein accumulation to control flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2960</fpage><lpage>2971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.108.061531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19011118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorca-Fornell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kater</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis floral meristem identity genes AP1, AGL24 and SVP directly repress class B and C floral homeotic genes</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03985.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19656343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification of SOC1 and SVP targets during the floral transition in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2012</year><volume>70</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2012.04919.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22268548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trevaskis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemming</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short vegetative phase-like MADS-box genes inhibit floral meristem identity in barley</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>143</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.090860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17114273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Agharbaoui</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Diallo</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouellet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TaVRT2 represses transcription of the wheat vernalization gene TaVRN1</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2007</year><volume>51</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>670</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03172.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17587304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Danyluk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tardif</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouellet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalibert&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Limin</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TaVRT-2, a member of the StMADS-11 clade of flowering repressors, is regulated by vernalization and photoperiod in wheat</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>138</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2354</fpage><lpage>2363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.061762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16024692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Reighard</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielenberg</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dormancy-associated MADS genes from the EVG locus of peach [<italic>Prunus persica</italic> (L.) Batsch] have distinct seasonal and photoperiodic expression patterns</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3521</fpage><lpage>3530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19553369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vendramin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez Tarodo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verde</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielenberg</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide analysis of MADS-box genes in peach [<italic>Prunus persica</italic> (L.) Batsch]</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>41</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-015-0436-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25848674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous down-regulation of DORMANCY-ASSOCIATED MADS-box6 and SOC1 during dormancy release in Japanese apricot (<italic>Prunus mume</italic>) flower buds</article-title><source>J Hrtic Sci Biotech</source><year>2016</year><volume>91</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14620316.2016.1173524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McGie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Voogd</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellens</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of the kiwifruit SVP3 gene affects reproductive development and suppresses anthocyanin biosynthesis in petals, but has no effect on vegetative growth, dormancy, or flowering time</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2014</year><volume>65</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>4985</fpage><lpage>4995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eru264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24948678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>BAW</given-names></name><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Macknight</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Varkonyi-Gasic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kiwifruit SVP2 gene prevents premature budbreak during dormancy</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2017</year><volume>68</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1082</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erx014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28158721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang FX, Zhu GF. Digital gene expression analysis based on de novo transcriptome assembly reveals new genes associated with floral organ differentiation of the orchid plant <italic>Cymbidium ensifolium</italic>. PLoS One. 2015;10(11):e0142434.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction and de novo characterization of a transcriptome of <italic>Chrysanthemum lavandulifolium</italic>: analysis of gene expression patterns in floral bud emergence</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tiss Org</source><year>2014</year><volume>116</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11240-013-0404-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Gomez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Terol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Talon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>3674</fpage><lpage>3676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.27</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wroblewski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomczak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Michelmore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transient assays of gene expression in lettuce, tomato and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-7652.2005.00123.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complexes of MADS-box proteins are sufficient to convert leaves into floral organs</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>409</volume><issue>6819</issue><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35054083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11206550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Folter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Immink</surname><given-names>RGH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parenicova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Henz</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive interaction map of the Arabidopsis MADS box transcription factors</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1424</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.031831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohaus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Apostasia</italic> genome and the evolution of orchids</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>549</volume><issue>7672</issue><fpage>379&#x02212;+</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature23897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28902843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in gene regulation underlying annual and perennial flowering in Arabideae species</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>3324</fpage><lpage>3326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.14171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28632342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhalerao</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant dormancy in the perennial context</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2007.03.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayub</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Alleva</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Guaimas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Erijman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TIP5;1 is an aquaporin specifically targeted to pollen mitochondria and is probably involved in nitrogen remobilization in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2010</year><volume>64</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1038</fpage><lpage>1047</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04395.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21143683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haslbeck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A first line of stress defense: small heat shock proteins and their function in protein homeostasis</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>427</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1537</fpage><lpage>1548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2015.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25681016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulatory network of plant heat stress response</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2016.08.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27666516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendahmane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The heat-shock protein/chaperone network and multiple stress resistance</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27860233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Immink</surname><given-names>RGH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrario</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Busscher-Lange</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kooiker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Busscher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Angenent</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the petunia MADS-box transcription factor family</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genomics</source><year>2003</year><volume>268</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>606</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Parenicova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Falasca</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelucchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Masiero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciannamea</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of OsMADS18, a member of the AP1/SQUA subfamily of MADS box genes</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>135</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2207</fpage><lpage>2219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.045039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15299121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masiero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Will</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>INCOMPOSITA: a MADS-box gene controlling prophyll development and floral meristem identity in antirrhinum</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2004</year><volume>131</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>5981</fpage><lpage>5990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15539492</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>