<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6256256</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.02710</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Putative Nitrogen-Fixing Bacteria Associated With the Rhizosphere and Root Endosphere of Wheat Plants Grown in an Andisol From Southern Chile</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rilling</surname><given-names>Joaquin I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/580597/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Acu&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>Jacquelinne J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/538823/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sadowsky</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/162182/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>Milko A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/536969/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Applied Microbial Ecology Laboratory, Departamento de Ciencias Qu&#x000ed;micas y Recursos Naturales, Universidad de La Frontera</institution>, <addr-line>Temuco</addr-line>, <country>Chile</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Center of Plant, Soil Interaction and Natural Resources Biotechnology, Scientific and Technological Bioresource Nucleus (BIOREN), Universidad de La Frontera</institution>, <addr-line>Temuco</addr-line>, <country>Chile</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Programa de Doctorado en Ciencias de Recursos Naturales, Universidad de La Frontera</institution>, <addr-line>Temuco</addr-line>, <country>Chile</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Soil, Water, and Climate, Department of Plant and Microbial Biology, BioTechnology Institute, University of Minnesota</institution>, <addr-line>Saint Paul, MN</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Benjamin Gourion, Plant Interactions Laboratory Microorganisms (LIPM), France</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Andrzej Tkacz, University of Oxford, United Kingdom; Feth-el-zahar Haichar, Microbial Ecology, France</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Milko A. Jorquera <email>milko.jorquera@ufrontera.cl</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Microbe Interactions, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>2710</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Rilling, Acu&#x000f1;a, Sadowsky and Jorquera.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Rilling, Acu&#x000f1;a, Sadowsky and Jorquera</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Acidic ash derived volcanic soils (Andisols) support 50% of cereal production in Chile. Nitrogen (N) is essential for cereal crops and commonly added as urea with consequent environmental concerns due to leaching. Despite the relevance of N to plant growth, few studies have focused on understanding the application, management and ecological role of N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial populations as tool for improve the N nutrition of cereal crops in Chile. It is known that N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria commonly inhabits diverse plant compartments (e.g., rhizosphere and root endosphere) where they can supply N for plant growth. Here, we used culture-independent and dependent approaches to characterize and compare the putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria associated with the rhizosphere and root endosphere of wheat plants grown in an Andisol from southern Chile. Our results showed significantly greater bacterial loads in the rhizosphere than the root endosphere. Quantitative PCR results indicated that the copy number of the 16S rRNA gene ranged from 10<sup>12</sup>~10<sup>13</sup> and 10<sup>7</sup>~10<sup>8</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample in rhizosphere and root endosphere, respectively. The <italic>nif</italic>H gene copy number ranged from 10<sup>5</sup>~10<sup>6</sup> and 10<sup>5</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample in rhizosphere and root endosphere, respectively. The total culturable bacteria number ranged from 10<sup>9</sup>~10<sup>10</sup> and 10<sup>7</sup>~10<sup>8</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample in rhizosphere and 10<sup>4</sup>~10<sup>5</sup> and 10<sup>4</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample in root endosphere using LB and NM-1 media, respectively. Indirect counts of putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria were 10<sup>3</sup> and 10<sup>2</sup>~10<sup>3</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample in rhizosphere and root endosphere using NFb medium, respectively. Sequencing of 16S rRNA genes from randomly selected putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria revealed the presence of members of Proteobacteria (<italic>Bosea</italic> and <italic>Roseomonas</italic>), Actinobacteria (<italic>Georgenia, Mycobacterium, Microbacterium, Leifsonia</italic>, and <italic>Arthrobacter</italic>), Bacteroidetes (<italic>Chitinophaga</italic>) and Firmicutes (<italic>Bacillus</italic> and <italic>Psychrobacillus</italic>) taxa. Differences in 16S rRNA and putative <italic>nif</italic>H-containing bacterial communities between rhizosphere and root endosphere were shown by denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE). This study shows a compartmentalization between rhizosphere and root endosphere for both the abundance and diversity of total (16S rRNA) and putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial communities on wheat plants grown in Chilean Andisols. This information can be relevant for the design and application of agronomic strategies to enhance sustainable N-utilization in cereal crops in Chile.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Andisol</kwd><kwd>root endosphere</kwd><kwd>N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria</kwd><kwd>rhizosphere</kwd><kwd>wheat</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Consejo Nacional de Innovaci&#x000f3;n, Ciencia y Tecnolog&#x000ed;a<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100009068</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Fondo Nacional de Desarrollo Cient&#x000ed;fico y Tecnol&#x000f3;gico<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100002850</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="70"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="9080"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Agricultural production in southern Chile is established in acidic ash derived volcanic soils (Andisols), which support around 50% of cereal production in Chile (Laval and Garcia, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In these soils, nitrogen (N) fertilization (as urea and other chemicals) is a common practice to improve agricultural production. The application of N is essential for crop yields and its availability is crucial during plant vegetative development and seed development (Ohyama et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), but also contributes to Andisol acidification and contamination of water bodies by N leaching (Nu&#x000f1;ez et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>Currently, it is widely accepted that the plant rhizomicrobiome contributes in a direct or indirect way to the growth and fitness of plants, providing phytohormones, solubilizing nutrients, fixing nitrogen (N<sub>2</sub>), establishing biocontrol of phytopathogens, and chelating metallic ions (De-la-Pe&#x000f1;a and Loyola-Vargas, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Biological N<sub>2</sub> fixation by bacteria is the most ecologically and agronomically relevant benefit obtained by plants from their interaction with bacteria, Atmospheric N<sub>2</sub> is reduced to ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) by the bacterial nitrogenase enzyme complex making it accessible for plant uptake. Thus, the recruitment of N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria under symbiotic or non-symbiotic relationships (e.g., nodulation of legume plants by <italic>Rhizobium</italic> spp. or interaction with free-living associative N<sub>2</sub> fixers) helps the host plant to obtain N directly from atmosphere and fulfill its nutritional requirements (de Bruijn, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Studies have also show that some genera of free-living bacteria (e.g., <italic>Azospirillum</italic> and <italic>Azotobacter</italic>, and others) can colonize diverse plant niches such as the rhizosphere (soil influenced by plant roots) and endosphere (inner tissues of plants), contributing to the N needs of non-leguminous plants (Bhattacharyya and Jha, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>The inoculation or bioaugmentation of plants with N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria is an attractive alternative to traditional N-fertilization practices and results in decreased fertilization costs and an environmentally friendly alternative to use of agrochemicals. In pastures grown in Chilean Andisols, studies have demonstrated that N<sub>2</sub> fertilization induces changes in total rhizobacterial populations, including potential plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria and populations harboring the <italic>nif</italic>H gene (Mart&#x000ed;nez et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Jorquera et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>). Symbiotic N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria (e.g., <italic>Bradyrhizobium</italic>) have been isolated from nodules of yellow lupin (<italic>Lupinus luteus</italic>) grown in Chilean Andisols (Campos et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Partial sequencing of 16S rRNA genes, the application of denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE), and 454-Roche pyrosequencing revealed a great diversity of bacterial group present in pasture and cereal rhizospheres of plants grown in Chilean Andisols, including also some N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria such as the bradyrhizobia (Jorquera et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2014b</xref>; Lagos et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>However, despite the relevance of N nutrition in cereal production in Andisols in southern Chile, few studies have been done to explore the association of N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria with cereals grown in Chilean acid volcanic soils. Several studies have demonstrated that the abundance, diversity, and activity of bacterial populations associated with plants may play a central role in its productivity (Turner et al., <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Berg et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Therefore, information on N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial populations in cereal crops can be relevant for bioprospecting of native bacterial strains as inoculants as well as the develop of management strategies to improve the N nutrition of plants and decreasing our dependency to chemical N fertilization.</p><p>In this study, we used culture-independent and dependent approaches to characterize and compare putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial populations associated with the rhizosphere and root endosphere of wheat plants grown in an Andisol from southern Chile.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Sampling</title><p>Wheat plants and their adhered rhizosphere soil were placed into sterile flasks (in triplicates) and immediately transported on ice to the Applied Microbial Ecology Laboratory (EMAlab) of Universidad de La Frontera, Temuco, Chile. The samples were taken from four wheat cultivars (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> cv. Fe&#x000f1;a, Patras, Joker, and Rocky, labeled as F, P, J and R, respectively) grown in an Andisol located in the La Araucan&#x000ed;a region (38&#x000b0;32&#x02032;47.5&#x02033;S, 72&#x000b0;27&#x02032;43.6&#x02033;W) of Chile under yearly rotation with rapeseed (<italic>Brassica napus</italic>) and oat (<italic>Avena sativa</italic>) since 2012. Prior to sampling, the soil was fertilized with 140 kg of urea ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and treated with Bacara (Bayer Crop Science, Inc.), and a commercial mixture of the pre-emergence herbicides flufenacet, flurtamone, and diflufenican, to a final concentration of 1 L ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Rhizosphere, roots and shoots were separated separately prior to further activities.</p><p>The chemical properties of rhizosphere samples was determined from composited samples as follows: the soil pH was measured in 1:2.5 soil:deionized water suspensions, extractable P (P<sub>Olsen</sub>) was extracted using Na-bicarbonate (0.5 M) and analyzed using the molybdate-blue method (Murphy and Riley, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">1962</xref>), exchangeable cations (K, Ca, Mg, and Na) were extracted with CH<sub>3</sub>COONH<sub>4</sub> (1 M) at pH 7.0 and analyzed by flame atomic adsorption spectrophotometry (FAAS) (Warncke and Brown, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>), and exchangeable aluminum was extracted with KCl (1 M) and analyzed by FAAS (Bertsch and Bloom, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Counts of putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria</title><p>Total and N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria populations in rhizosphere and root endosphere samples were estimated by quantitative PCR (qPCR) using the 16S rRNA and <italic>nif</italic>H as target genes. Total DNA was extracted from rhizosphere samples (0.25 g) by using DNeasy PowerSoil Kits (Qiagen, Inc.), according to manufacturer instructions. For endosphere samples (0.15 g), root samples were initially vigorously washed with sterile distilled water (SDW) and rhizoplane surfaces were disinfected by three continuous washes in 80% ethanol for 5 min, followed by a 20 min immersion in 4% sodium hypochlorite and three rinses with SDW as described by Dur&#x000e1;n et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The roots were macerated on sterile ceramic mortars and homogenized in 1.5 mL of sterile 0.85% saline solution. To verify sterility of rhizoplane samples, SDW from the third rinse was collected and processed as a sample for sterility control purposes. Root endosphere total DNA was extracted from 0.25 mL of surface sterile root homogenate using Quick-DNA&#x02122; Plant/Seed Miniprep Kit (Zymo Research Corp.), according to manufacturer instructions. The DNA concentrations were adjusted by dilution to 20 ng ul<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and quality (260:280 ratio) was confirmed at ~1.8.</p><p>The quantitation of <italic>nif</italic>H genes was done by using the primer set nifH-g1-forB (5&#x02032;-GGT TGT GAC CCG AAA GCT GA-3&#x02032;) and nifH-g1-rev (5&#x02032;-GCG TAC ATG GCC ATC ATC TC-3&#x02032;) (B&#x000fc;rgmann et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The following PCR conditions were used: 95&#x000b0;C for 11 s followed by cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 15s, 60&#x000b0;C for 30 s, and a final extension step at 75&#x000b0;C for 8 s and at 72&#x000b0;C for 10 s (B&#x000fc;rgmann et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The quantitation of 16S rRNA genes was done by using the mitochondria- and chloroplast excluding primer set 799f (5&#x02032;-AAC MGG ATT AGA TAC CCK G-3&#x02032;) and 1115r (5&#x02032;-AGG GTT GCG CTC GTT G-3&#x02032;) (Shade et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) with the following program: cycles of 94&#x000b0;C for 1 min, annealing at 53&#x000b0;C for 1 min and extension at 72&#x000b0;C during 1 min; with a final extension step at 72&#x000b0;C during 10 min. (Beckers et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Both qPCR assays were done using PowerUp&#x02122; SYBR&#x000ae; Green Master Mix (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc.). The quantitation of gene copies was estimated by using standard curves prepared with synthetic ~1,500 bp dsDNA ultramers (Integrated DNA Technologies, Inc.) of the <italic>nif</italic>H gene from <italic>Azospirillum brasilense</italic> Sp7 (NCBI accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="X51500">X51500</ext-link>) and the 16S rRNA gene from <italic>Azospirillum picis</italic> (NCBI accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AM922283">AM922283</ext-link>), respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Counts of culturable and putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria</title><p>Rhizosphere soil (2 g) was suspended in 50 mL of SDW. Previously macerated root samples (1 mL) from section Counts of Putative N<sub>2</sub>-Fixing Bacteria above were resuspended in 25 mL of SDW. Both sample types were homogenized by sonication for 30 s at 120 kHz. Suspensions were serially diluted in 0.85% saline used in plate counting methods described as follow. Counts of total culturable bacteria were done on Luria Bertani agar medium (LB) (10 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> Triptone; 5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; Yeast Extract; 5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> NaCl; Sambrook and Russell, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>), and on NM-1 oligotrophic medium (0.5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> D-glucose, 0.5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> polypeptone, 0.5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> Na- glutamate, 0.5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> yeast extract, 0.44 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.1 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (NH<sub>4</sub>)2SO<sub>4</sub>, 0.1 gl<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> MgSO<sub>4</sub> &#x000b7; 7H<sub>2</sub>O, 15 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> agar, and 1 ml vitamin solution containing 1 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> nicotinamide, 1 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> thiamine hydrochloride, 0.05 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> biotin, 0.5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> 4-aminobenzoic acid, 0.01 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> vitamin B12, 0.5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> D- pantothenic acid hemicalcium salt, 0.5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> pyridoxamine dihydrochloride, 0.5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> folic acid; (Nakamura et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>)). Both culture media were amended with 10 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cycloheximide prevent fungal growth. Autoclaved agar was added before plating at final concentration of 1.5% for both media, as recommended by Tanaka et al. (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), to prevent hydrogen peroxide formation, resulting in bacterial growth inhibition with the concomitant underestimation of total culturable bacteria counts (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>). Aliquots (50 &#x003bc;l) of appropriated dilutions of the rhizosphere and root endosphere suspensions were separately plated onto petri dishes containing LB and NM-1 media, and incubated for 4 days at 28&#x000b0;C. Colonies grown on agar plates were automatically counted by using CLIQS Colony Counter software (TotalLab Inc., UK).</p><p>In parallel, indirect counts of putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria were carried-out by MPN analyses as recommend by Baldani et al. (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), using semisolid (0.5% agar) NFb medium tubes [5 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> malic acid, 0.5 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> K<sub>2</sub>HPO4, 0.1 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> NaCl, 0.02 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> CaCl<sub>2</sub>&#x000d7;2H<sub>2</sub>O, 2 mL of micronutrient solution (0.4 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> CuSO<sub>4</sub>&#x000d7;5H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.12 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ZnSO<sub>4</sub>, 1.4 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 1 g Na<sub>2</sub>MoO<sub>4</sub>&#x000d7;2H<sub>2</sub>O, 1.5 g and MnSO<sub>4</sub>&#x000d7;H<sub>2</sub>O), 2 mL 0.5% bromothymol blue in 0.2N KOH, 4 mL of 1.64% Fe[III] EDTA, and 1 mL of vitamin solution containing 100 mg L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> biotin and 200 mg L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> pyridoxamine dihydrochloride; (Hartmann and Baldani, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>)]. Tubes containing 5 mL of NFb medium were inoculated with 100 &#x003bc;L of sample and incubated for 4 days at 37&#x000b0;C. The presence of white layer (or pellicle), an indicator of N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial growth, was checked, and aseptically removed by using sterile cork borers. After MPN analyses, the isolation of putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria was performed by resuspension of the pellicle on 1 mL 0.85% NaCl, and 100 &#x003bc;L reinoculated into fresh tubes of NFb medium. Tubes were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 4 days. After second incubation, the pellicle was newly aseptically removed, resuspended on 1 mL 0.85% NaCl, serially diluted and plated onto LB and Congo red malic-acid (CRMA; 0.5 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>; 0.2 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> MgSO<sub>4</sub> &#x000d7; 7H<sub>2</sub>O; 0.1 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> NaCl, 0.5 g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> yeast extract, 0.015 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> FeCl<sub>3</sub>&#x000d7;H<sub>2</sub>O; 5 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DL-malic acid, 4.8 g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> KOH, and 15 mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of 1:400 Congo red; Rodriguez-Caceres, <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">1982</xref>) agar media. Colonies (75) were randomly selected from CRMA agar plates according to their morphology, purified by streaking on NFb agar plates, and stored in 1 mL sterile LB-Glycerol (7:3) at&#x02212;80&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Characterization of putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria</title><p>Total DNA from selected rhizosphere and root endosphere isolates was extracted by using the Proteinase K-CTAB (cetyl-trimethylammonium bromide) method as described by Wilson (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). To prevent analysis of clones, all isolates were firstly genotyping by using rep-PCR DNA fingerprinting and ERIC primers as described by Versalovic et al. (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>). The 16S rRNA genes were amplified from 20 and 18 genetically-different rhizosphere and root endosphere isolates, respectively, by using PCR and the universal bacterial primer set 27f (5&#x02032;-AGA GTT TGA TCC TGG CTC AG-3&#x02032;) and 1492r (5&#x02032;-TAC GGY TAC CTT GTT ACG ACT T-3&#x02032;) (Lane, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>) and by using the PCR conditions suggested by Jorquera et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In parallel, <italic>nif</italic>H genes was also amplified by using the primer set PolF (5&#x02032;-TGC GAY CCS AAR GCB GAC TC-3&#x02032;) and PolR (5&#x02032;-ATS GCC ATC ATY TCR CCG GA-3&#x02032;) and PCR condition suggested by Jorquera et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>).</p><p>Synthetic 16S rRNA and <italic>nif</italic>H genes from <italic>Azospirillum picis</italic> and <italic>Azospirillum brasilense</italic> Sp7 were used as positive controls, respectively.</p><p>In addition, a variety of universal <italic>nif</italic>H primer combinations were also tested, including PolFI and PolR; PolF and AQER; nifH-g1-forA and nifH-g1-rev; nifH-g1-forB and nifH-g1-rev; MehtaF and MehtaR (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>). Despite the large number of primers used, however, sequence analyses indicated that the amplicons were unspecific and not related to <italic>nif</italic>H.</p><p>The PCR products were sequenced by Macrogen Inc. (Seoul, South Korea), trimmed, cleaned up, and compared with those deposited in GenBank database using BLASTn tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>). To the presence of <italic>nif</italic>H, nucleotide sequences were translated into amino acids and compared with those present in GenBank by using BLASTx. Sequences (1 from rhizosphere and 7 from the root endosphere) showing positive alignment with the <italic>nif</italic>H enzyme were used to build a neighbor-joining tree using representative sequences of <italic>nif</italic>H reported in literature, including <italic>Azoarcus, Azospirillum, Azotobacter, Bosea, Bradyrhizobium, Bacillus, Burkholderia, Chitinophaga, Herbaspirillum, Mesorhizobium Microbacterium, Pontibacter, Rhizobium</italic>, and <italic>Roseomonas</italic>. The alignment of amino acids sequences was done by CLUSTAL W (Larkin et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) and neighbor-joining trees were built using Geneious version R11 (Bootstrap = 1000) (Kearse et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>Sequences obtained in this study were deposited in GenBank under accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835569">MG835569</ext-link> to <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835606">MG835606</ext-link> for 16S rRNA gene, and <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175481">MH175481</ext-link> - <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175487">MH175487</ext-link> as well as <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175490">MH175490</ext-link> for <italic>nif</italic>H gene sequences.</p></sec><sec><title>DGGE fingerprinting of total and N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial communities</title><p>Fingerprinting of total and N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial communities in rhizosphere and root endosphere samples was done by using DGGE of 16S rRNA and <italic>nif</italic>H as target genes, respectively. For total bacterial communities, 16S rRNA genes were first amplified by using primer set 933f (5&#x02032;-GCA CAA GCG GTG GAG CAT GTG G-3&#x02032;) and 1492r. Then, ~600 bp bands were confirmed on electrophoresis, and used as template for a nested PCR with primer set 933f-gc and 1387r (5&#x02032;-GCC CGG GAA CGT ATT CAC CG-3&#x02032;). The GC-clamp (5&#x02032;-CGC CCG CCG CGC GCG GCG GGC GGG GCG GGG GCA CGG GGG-3&#x02032;) was attached to the 5&#x02032;-end of primer 933f, and PCR reactions were carried as described by Jorquera et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In parallel, the amplification of <italic>nif</italic>H was done by nested PCR using in the first PCR round the PolF (5&#x02032;-TGC GAY CCS AAR GCB GAC TC-3&#x02032;) and PolR (5&#x02032;-ATS GCC ATC ATY TCR CCG GA-3&#x02032;) primer set. After specific ~400 bp bands were confirmed on electrophoresis, a second PCR reaction was carried with the PolFI (5&#x02032;-TGC GAI CCS AAI GCI GAC TC-3&#x02032;) and AQER-GC30 (5&#x02032;-GAC GAT GTA GAT YTC CTG GGG-3&#x02032;) primer set. The GC-clamp (5&#x02032;-CGC CCG CCG CGC CCC GCG CCC GGC CCG CCC GAC GAT GTA GAT YTC CTG-3&#x02032;) was attached to the 5&#x02032;-end of primer AQER and the PCR conditions were carried out according to described by Jorquera et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>).</p><p>The DGGE analysis was performed using a DCode system (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc.). PCR products (20 &#x003bc;L) were loaded onto 6% (w/v) polyacrylamide gel with a 50&#x02013;75% denaturing gradient (7 M urea and 40% formamide) and electrophoresis was run for 16 h at 80 V. The gel was stained with SYBR Gold (Molecular Probes, Invitrogen Co.) for 30 min and photographed on a UV transilluminator. Image analysis and clustering of DGGE banding profiles were done under CLIQS 1D Pro software (TotalLab Ltd). Based on the matrix obtained from CLIQS 1D Pro analysis, the distances between the bacterial communities from rhizosphere and root endosphere 16S rRNA and <italic>nif</italic>H genes were calculated by similarity profile analysis (SIMPROF test) with Bray-Curtis similarity index with a 5% significance level and &#x0003c;0.15 stress values with Primer-E v6 (Primer-E Ltd.; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.primer-e.com/">http://www.primer-e.com/</ext-link>) (Clarke, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>; Clarke et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). A graphical representation of this results was generated through non-metric multidimensional scaling (nMDS) plots, developed with the same software. The similarities of rhizosphere and root endosphere 16S rRNA and <italic>nif</italic>H communities were compared at 40 and 60%.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The culture-dependent (dilutions, plating, and isolation) as well as -independent (DNA extractions, PCR, DGGE, and qPCR) procedures were performed in triplicates and analyzed by one-way ANOVA. Comparisons were carried out for each pair with Tukey HSD test using IBM SPSS Statistics 24 (IBM Corporation). Values are given as means &#x000b1; standard deviation on means. Differences were considered to be significant when the <italic>P</italic>-value was &#x02264; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Rhizosphere soil properties</title><p>No large differences in soil chemical properties were observed between the rhizosphere soils of different wheat cultivars, showing typical characteristics of Chilean Andisols used in agriculture. The properties of rhizosphere soils (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were as follows: pH ranged from 6.29 to 6.39, organic matter ranged from 15 to 16%, and the ranges for the macronutrients N, P, and K were 52.7~63.1, 29~37, and 138~159 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively. The cation exchange capacity ranged from 16.08 to 18.01 cmol<sub>(+)</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, with an Al saturation between 0.06 and 0.25%.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Chemical properties of rhizosphere soils used in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Property</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Wheat cultivars</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fe&#x000f1;a (F)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Patras (P)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Joker (J)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Rocky (R)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P (mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K (mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH (H<sub>2</sub>O)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.29</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organic matter (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K (cmol<sub>(+)</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na (cmol<sub>(+)</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca (cmol<sub>(+)</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.07</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mg (cmol<sub>(+)</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Al (cmol<sub>(+)</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEC (cmol<sub>(+)</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003a3; Bases (cmol<sub>(+)</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Al saturation (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>a</label><p><italic>Calculated as Al/cation exchange capacity [&#x003a3; (K, Ca, Mg, Na, and Al)] &#x000d7; 100</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Counts of total- and N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria</title><p>The qPCR analyses indicated that there were larges differences in total bacteria loads between rhizosphere and root endosphere samples (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Significantly greater (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05) counts of total bacteria were observed in the rhizosphere (1.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup>~9.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>13</sup> copies of 16S rRNA genes g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample) compared with the root endosphere (2.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup>~3.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> copies of 16S rRNA genes g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample) samples. Similarly, significantly greater (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05) counts of total N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria were also observed in the rhizosphere (3.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>~8.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> copies of <italic>nif</italic>H gene g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample) compared with root endosphere (1.7~6.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> copies of <italic>nif</italic>H gene g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample) samples. However, the differences between rhizosphere and root endosphere samples were lower when counts of the <italic>nif</italic>H gene are compared with 16S rRNA genes.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Counts (gene copy number per g of sample) of total and N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria in rhizosphere and root endosphere samples of wheat plants by quantitative PCR (qPCR) using specific primer set for 16S rRNA and <italic>nif</italic>H genes. Samples labeled as F, P, J, and R correspond to Fe&#x000f1;a, Patras, Joker, and Rocky wheat cultivars, respectively. Error bars represent standard deviation and different lower letters denote statistical difference (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05, Tukey HSD test) (<italic>n</italic> = 3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02710-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Counts of culturable and putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria</title><p>The use of culture media also showed larges differences in total culturable bacterial counts between rhizosphere and root endosphere samples (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Significantly greater (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05) counts of total cultural bacteria were observed in the rhizosphere (1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>9</sup>~1.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>10</sup> and 9.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup>~1.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample with LB and NM1 media, respectively) compared with root endosphere samples (1.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup>~3.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> and 1.2~5.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sample) on the same media. Smaller distances (less than one order) (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05) were observed between on putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing culturable bacteria in CRMA medium for rhizosphere samples (2~8.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) compared with those from the root endosphere (8.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>2</sup>~1.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Counts (CFU per g of sample) of total culturable <bold>(A)</bold> in rhizosphere and root endosphere samples of wheat plants using general (LB and NM&#x02212;1) and putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria <bold>(B)</bold> with selective (Congo red malic&#x02013;acid; CRMA) media. Samples labeled as F, P, J, and R correspond to Fe&#x000f1;a, Patras, Joker, and Rocky wheat cultivars, respectively. Error bars represent standard deviation and different lower letters denote statistical difference (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05, Tukey HSD test) (<italic>n</italic> = 3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02710-g0002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Characterization of putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria</title><p>Thirty-eight of 77 strains examined with ERIC-PCR analysis (49.3%) were recognized as non-redundant putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial isolates, whose taxonomic assignments are shown in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Based on partial sequencing of 16S rRNA genes, most of isolates from the rhizosphere samples had an affiliation with the genus <italic>Bacillus</italic> (15 of 20 isolates), followed by members of genera <italic>Microbacterium</italic> (3 isolates), <italic>Chitinophaga</italic> (1) and <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> (1) genera. In contrast, only 4 of 18 isolates from the root endosphere samples were characterized as member of the genus <italic>Bacillus</italic> based on sequencing of 16S rRNA genes. Other isolates were characterized as being members of the genera <italic>Roseomonas</italic> (3), <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> (3), <italic>Georgenia</italic> (2 isolates), <italic>Bosea</italic> (2), <italic>Microbacterium</italic> (1), <italic>Psychrobacillus</italic> (1), <italic>Chitinophaga</italic> (1) and <italic>Leifsonia</italic> (1).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Taxonomic identity of putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria isolates obtained by sequencing of 16S rRNA genes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Isolate</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Taxonomy group<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Closest relatives or cloned sequences (accession no.)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Identity</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Accession no</bold>.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" style="background-color:#bdbec1" rowspan="1"><bold>RHIZOSPHERE</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62CR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Micrococcales; Microbacteriaceae; Microbacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microbacterium proteolyticum</italic> from <italic>Halimione portulacoides</italic> roots (NR_132869)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835569">MG835569</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72CR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain p102_H06 from ma&#x000ed;ze rhizosphere (JQ832067)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835570">MG835570</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102BR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen-fixing <italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain ADU08 from date palm soil (KX694270)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835571">MG835571</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112BR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain ARD47 from acid soil (KX023249)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835572">MG835572</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154AR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus</italic> sp. strain SZ177 from straw decomposition (KU986708)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835573">MG835573</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173CR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain PSC1 from sugarcane rhizosphere (KU196781)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835574">MG835574</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184AR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Micrococcales; Microbacteriaceae; Microbacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diazotrophic <italic>Microbacterium</italic> sp. S2SP302 from sugarcane rhizosphere (KT183549)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835575">MG835575</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184AR-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain yangyueK8 from <italic>Juglans regia</italic> rhizosphere (KU977121)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835576">MG835576</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214AR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain yangyueN10 from <italic>Juglans regia</italic> rhizosphere (KU977110)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835577">MG835577</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214AR-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain yangyueN10 from <italic>Juglans regia</italic> rhizosphere (KU977110)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835578">MG835578</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222BR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus</italic> sp. MR35 from rice rhizosphere (LT629146)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835579">MG835579</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">623EA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacteroidetes; Chitinophagia; Chitinophagales; Chitinophagaceae; Chitinophaga</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Chitinophaga arvensicola</italic> strain MRP-16 from Dioscorea batatas rhizoplane (AB908086)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835588">MG835588</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243AR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Micrococcales; Micrococcaceae; Arthrobacter</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. strain JQ-1 from phtalate contaminated soil (KX055564)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835580">MG835580</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">322CR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain ARD47 from acid soil (KX023249)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835583">MG835583</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">342CR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus huizhouensis</italic> strain WJB150 from rice rhizosphere 1(KU877672)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835584">MG835584</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354AR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Micrococcales; Microbacteriaceae; Microbacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microbacterium</italic> sp. SIB_Cu_R3 from <italic>Betula pendula</italic> L. rhizosphere (KX036571)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835585">MG835585</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354AR-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain Hd from arsenic contaminated soil (KY098770)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835586">MG835586</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen-fixing <italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain ADU08 from date palm soil (KX694270)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835587">MG835587</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">503CR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus aryabhattai</italic> strain He from arsenic contanimated soil (KY098771)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835581">MG835581</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">503CR-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> strain Y14 from peanut rhizosphere (CP017953)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835582">MG835582</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" style="background-color:#bdbec1" rowspan="1"><bold>ROOT ENDOSPHERE</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Corynebacteriales; Mycobacteriaceae; Mycobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mycobacterium</italic> sp. Site1-11a from manure-fertilized grassland (JF304596)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835593">MG835593</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">382EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Micrococcales; Microbacteriaceae; Microbacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microbacterium</italic> sp. SIB_Cu_R3 from <italic>Betula pendula</italic> L. rhizosphere (KX036571)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835590">MG835590</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">424EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Micrococcales; Bogoriellaceae; Georgenia</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Georgenia soli</italic> strain MC-14-2 from <italic>Populus euphratica</italic> endosphere (KF848489)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835591">MG835591</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Psychrobacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Psychrobacillus psychrodurans</italic> strain EC1 from corn roots (KP334982)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835592">MG835592</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">491EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Corynebacteriales; Mycobacteriaceae; Mycobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mycobacterium</italic> sp. strain OTB74 from Sandy soil (KN022865)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835594">MG835594</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">513EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteobacteria; Alphaproteobacteria; Rhodospirillales; Acetobacteraceae; Roseomonas</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Roseomonas</italic> sp. A2 from tomato rhizosphere (KP789481)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835595">MG835595</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">523EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteobacteria; Alphaproteobacteria; Rhodospirillales; Acetobacteraceae; Roseomonas</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Roseomonas</italic> sp. Esch5-313 from poplar endosphere (AM489616)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835596">MG835596</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">543EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteobacteria; Alphaproteobacteria; Rhodospirillales; Acetobacteraceae; Roseomonas</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Roseomonas</italic> sp. strain THG-N2.22 from soil (KX456186)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835598">MG835598</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">564EB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> strain Y14 from peanut rhizosphere (CP017953)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835599">MG835599</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">584EA-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus aryabhattai</italic> strain He from arsenic contanimated soil (KY098771)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835600">MG835600</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">592BR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus aryabhattai</italic> strain He from arsenic contanimated soil (KY098771)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835601">MG835601</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">643EA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacteroidetes; Chitinophagia; Chitinophagales; Chitinophagaceae; Chitinophaga</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Chitinophaga</italic> sp. W-9 from tomato rhizosphere (KX082640)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835602">MG835602</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693EB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteobacteria; Alphaproteobacteria; Rhizobiales; Bradyrhizobiaceae; Bosea</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bosea</italic> sp. strain SR 5-12 from <italic>Artemisa pr&#x000ed;nceps</italic> endorhiza (KM253172)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835603">MG835603</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">703EB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteobacteria; Alphaproteobacteria; Rhizobiales; Bradyrhizobiaceae; Bosea</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bosea</italic> sp. strain J1 from soil (KP125320)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835604">MG835604</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">274EB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Micrococcales; Microbacteriaceae; Leifsonia</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Leifsonia</italic> sp. URHA0017 from grassland rhizosphere (LN876290)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835589">MG835589</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Corynebacteriales; Mycobacteriaceae; Mycobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mycobacterium</italic> sp. Site1-11a from manure-fertilized grassland (JF304596)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835593">MG835593</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">714EA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes; Bacilli; Bacillales; Bacillaceae; Bacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic> strain Hd (KY098770)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835605">MG835605</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">734EA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria; Micrococcales; Bogoriellaceae; Georgenia</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Georgenia soli</italic> strain CC-NMPT-T3 from iron ore-contaminated soil (NR_116959)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MG835606">MG835606</ext-link></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN2"><label>a</label><p><italic>The phylogenetic assignment is based on sequence analysis by BLASTn of GenBank database from NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>). It is given the phylum as well as the lowest predictable phylogenetic rank</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>b</label><p><italic>Based on partial sequencing of 16S rRNA gene and comparison with those present in GenBank by using BLASTn algorithm</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>BLASTx analyses (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) predicted eight amino acid sequences (1 from the rhizosphere and 7 from the root endosphere) that coded the nitrogenase-characteristic P-loop NTPase conserved superfamily domain. The neighbor-joining tree analysis also revealed that our partial predicted nitrogenase-like enzymes showed higher dissimilarities compared with those representatives of nitrogenase enzymes taken from GenBank (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), except for sequences from <italic>Chitinophaga</italic> sp. 643EA and <italic>Roseomonas</italic> sp. 523EC.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Characterization of predicted nitrogenase enzymes obtained in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Isolate</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Closest relative (accession no.)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Identity</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Accession no</bold>.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" style="background-color:#bdbec1" rowspan="1"><bold>RHIZOSPHERE</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">503CR-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dinitrogenase reductase from uncultured bacterium of saline-alkaline soil (AEO13485)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175490">MH175490</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" style="background-color:#bdbec1" rowspan="1"><bold>ROOT ENDOSPHERE</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">513EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase iron protein from uncultured bacterium of Sorghum rhizosphere (ABW87180)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175481">MH175481</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">523EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase reductase from endosymbiont <italic>Burkholderia</italic> sp. (AF194084)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175482">MH175482</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">543EC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dinitrogenase reductase from uncultured bacterium of saline-alkaline soil (AEO13447)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175483">MH175483</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">564EB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dinitrogenase reductase from <italic>Azospirillum zeae</italic> of wheat rhizosphere (CBL85086)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175484">MH175484</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">592BR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dinitrogenase reductase from uncultured bacterium of <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> biomass (AAK91227)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175485">MH175485</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">643EA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase reductase from <italic>Azospirillum doebereinerae</italic> of <italic>Miscanthus</italic> plant roots (ACO35353)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175486">MH175486</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693EB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase reductase from <italic>Azospirillum thiophilum</italic> of sulfide spring (ACO35352)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MH175487">MH175487</ext-link></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN4"><label>a</label><p><italic>Assignment based on the closest sequence according to BLASTx analysis</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Neighbor-joining tree showing the phylogenetic affiliation between predicted amino acid sequences from <italic>nif</italic>H gene obtained from rhizosphere and root endosphere isolates in this study (red) and representative <italic>nif</italic>H-coded enzyme amino acid sequences from known representative plant-soil bacteria deposited in NCBI GenBank database (black). Scale represents substitution sites (Bootstrap = 1,000). In parenthesis is shown the accession number of representative sequences in GenBank or the taxonomic affiliation based on 16S rRNA gene sequencing of isolates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02710-g0003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Fingerprinting of total and N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial communities</title><p>Fingerprint analysis of bacterial communities by DGGE revealed significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05) between the total bacterial communities found in rhizosphere and root endosphere samples from the wheat cultivars examined (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). Two clusters were clearly observed at the 40% similarity level. However, a specific bacterial community for each of the wheat cultivars was not observed, even at higher similarity percentages (60%). Similarly, significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05) between rhizosphere and root endosphere samples of wheat cultivars with respect to <italic>nif</italic>H-harboring bacterial populations. However, a specific <italic>nif</italic>H-harboring bacterial community for each cultivar was not observed at higher similarity (60%), except for the root endosphere samples from wheat cv &#x0201c;Fe&#x000f1;a&#x0201d; (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Non-metric multidimensional scaling (nMDS) analysis of DGGE fingerprinting of 16S rRNA <bold>(A)</bold> and nifH <bold>(B)</bold> analysis generated by Primer v6 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.primer-e.com">http://www.primer-e.com</ext-link>) with the Bray-Curtis similarity index, 5% significance level, and &#x0003c; 0.1 stress values. Red and blue shapes represent rhizosphere and root endosphere, respectively. Samples labelled as F, P, J and R correspond to Fe&#x000f1;a, Patras, Joker and Rocky wheat cultivars, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02710-g0004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Nitrogen is an essential nutrient for plant growth and N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria play an important role in plant nutrition. Studies focused to N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria in Chilean agroecosystems are scarce, particularly with respect to cereal cropping systems. By using culture-dependent methods, N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria have previously been isolated from alfalfa and lupin plants grown in Andisols from southern Chile (Langer et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Campos et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Culture-independent methods based on partial sequencing of 16S rRNA genes have also revealed the occurrence of <italic>Sinorhizobium</italic> strains on wheat (Jorquera et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2014b</xref>) and <italic>Azospirillum</italic> in ryegrass (Lagos et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) rhizospheres. In addition, and to our knowledge, no studies on endophytic N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria in Chilean agroecosystems have not been done so far.</p><p>In this study, qPCR revealed the occurrence of <italic>nif</italic>H-harboring bacterial population in all samples of wheat cultivars analyzed, with a significantly higher abundance of total and N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria in the rhizosphere, compared with root endosphere samples. Our results showed a large number of copies, 10<sup>12</sup>~10<sup>13</sup>, of 16S rRNA genes g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> are present in rhizosphere soils, which is two orders of magnitude greater than those reported by Sanguin et al. (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) in rhizosphere soils from wheat. Lower abundances (~10<sup>8</sup> gene copies g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were also reported in wheat rhizospheres by Reardon et al. (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The difference between our results and other wheat studies in literature could be attributed to the variability of 16s rRNA copy number of present in environmental bacteria, which could contain as much as 15 copies per cell (Kembel et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; V&#x0011b;trovsk&#x000fd; and Baldrian, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Similarly, 16S rRNA copies in cotton plants has been reported around the values that we report here (10<sup>12</sup> copies g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> rhizosphere; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>In relation to the abundance of <italic>nif</italic>H genes, the values obtained in this study were close to those reported by Reardon et al. (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). We found ~10<sup>6</sup> copies of <italic>nif</italic>H genes g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of rhizosphere soils in wheat plants. In contrast, Bouffaud et al. (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) reported greater <italic>nif</italic>H gene abundances (~10<sup>9</sup> gene copies g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) in rhizosphere soils of wheat plants.</p><p>Reported counts of 16S rRNA genes, by qPCR, in inner tissues or root endosphere of plants are scarce because of the potential for biased results due to the presence of ribosomes in chloroplasts and mitochondria (Shade et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The use of the chloroplast- and mitochondria-excluding primer set 799f and 1115r (Shade et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) has been reported to produce reliable qPCR results on root endosphere samples (Beckers et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Our results showed ~ 10<sup>7</sup>-10<sup>8</sup> copies of 16S rRNA genes g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root, which are similar to those obtained by Ruppel et al. (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) in the rice endosphere. Higher loads of endophytic bacteria (10<sup>10</sup>~10<sup>13</sup> copies of 16S rRNA genes g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root) were reported in a rice-maize rotation (Breidenbach et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In relation to <italic>nif</italic>H genes, studies have reported abundances of ~10<sup>8</sup> copies of <italic>nif</italic>H genes g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root in wheat and rapeseed plants (Bouffaud et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Puri et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Both studies reported three orders higher <italic>nif</italic>H gene numbers, compared to those obtained in this study (~10<sup>5</sup> genes copies g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root).</p><p>Similar to qPCR results, bacterial numbers obtained by the plate-counting studies done here suggested the occurrence of culturable N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria in all samples of wheat cultivars analyzed, with a significant higher abundance in rhizosphere compared with root endosphere samples. Our results showed counts of total culturable bacteria of 10<sup>9</sup>~10<sup>10</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 10<sup>7</sup>~10<sup>8</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> on LB and NM-1 media, respectively. In this context, Jorquera et al. (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2014b</xref>) reported counts of 10<sup>7</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> rhizosphere on cereals (wheat and oats) and pastures (ryegrass) by using NM-1 medium, similar to the results described by Jia et al. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) in wheat rhizosphere on meat-peptone agar (10<sup>8</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> rhizosphere). In addition, the counts of culturable bacteria in root endosphere samples we examined (10<sup>4</sup>-10<sup>5</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root) were similar to those observed on wheat roots by Ruppel (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>) and Robinson et al. (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) with counts of ~10<sup>4</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root in wheat.</p><p>Our counts of putative N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria in the rhizosphere (10<sup>3</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) of wheat were lower than those reported in the wheat (10<sup>4</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), chickpea and sugarcane (10<sup>4</sup>-10<sup>5</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) rhizospheres examined by Pathania et al. (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and Ahmad et al. (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). This may, in part, due to different culture conditions used in each study. However, our counts of endospheric N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria (10<sup>3</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root) are similar to those obtained by Ruppel (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>) (10<sup>4</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root) in wheat and Patel and Archana (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) in several <italic>Poaceae</italic> plant tissues (10<sup>3</sup>-10<sup>5</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root). Most studies on N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial communities in the wheat root endosphere have examined colonization niches and physiological effect of different diazotrophic endophytes (Liu et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2017a</xref>,<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>), instead of determining how abundant are the N<sub>2</sub>-fixing root endosphere communities. That said, however, it is well known that culture medium type greatly affects the reported numbers of bacteria obtained via plate-counting. Media bias is always an issue in examining microbiota in environmental niches. In this context it has been described that the use of diluted of culture media improves CFU number determination and enhance isolation of N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacteria (Janssen et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Hashimoto et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Despite this limitation, however, our analyses do allow relative comparisons of total and N<sub>2</sub>-fixing microbes in the plant compartments we examined.</p><p>Sequencing of 16S rRNA genes of rhizosphere isolates revealed the occurrence of members of genera <italic>Bacillus, Microbacterium, Chitinophaga</italic>, and <italic>Arthrobacter</italic>. Most of isolates were characterized as belonging to the genus <italic>Bacillus</italic>, which is a common inhabitant in the rhizosphere soil of plants grown in Andisols from southern Chile (Acu&#x000f1;a and Jorquera, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Mart&#x000ed;nez et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). In this context, diazotrophic <italic>Bacillus</italic> sp. strains have been shown to be associated with N<sub>2</sub>-fixation in wheats (Pathania et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), as well as sugarcane (Madhaiyan et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). It is noteworthy that most of isolates characterized as <italic>Bacillus</italic> (10 of 15) were phylogenetically close to <italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic>, a well-known N<sub>2</sub>-fixing and phosphate-solubilizing bacterium commonly studied as plant growth-promoting bacteria (Ding et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Elkoca et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). The remaining five rhizosphere isolates we examined were characterized as <italic>Microbacterium, Chitinophaga</italic>, and <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. strains, these microorganisms were previously proposed to be associated with N<sub>2</sub>-fixation in the rhizospheres of other plant species (Mirza and Rodrigues, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Beneduzi et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Moyes et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>Our results also showed the occurrence of members of the genera <italic>Bacillus, Georgenia, Mycobacterium, Bosea, Microbacterium, Psychrobacillus, Roseomonas, Chitinophaga</italic>, and <italic>Leifsonia</italic> genera in the root endosphere of wheat. Bacteria belonging to the phylum Actinobacteria, such as members of the genera <italic>Georgenia, Mycobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Leifsonia</italic>, have been described as common inhabitants of the root endosphere of plants, as well as have many diazotrophs (M&#x000e5;rtensson et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Han et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Liaqat and Eltem, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). It is noteworthy, that the isolation of Proteobacteria belonging to the genera <italic>Bosea</italic> and <italic>Roseomonas</italic> have not been previously reported either soils or <italic>in planta</italic> in Chile. Isolates characterized as <italic>Bosea</italic> have been isolated from lupin root nodules by De Meyer and Willems (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In this context, <italic>Bosea</italic> spp. appear to be related to bacteria within the genus <italic>Rhizobium</italic>, well known for forming N<sub>2</sub>-fixation symbioses with legumes worldwide, as well as with plants grown in acidic soils in Chile (Langer et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).</p><p>In addition, despite that our analysis with BLASTx suggested the presence of the nitrogenase enzyme in genomes of our isolates; the neighbor-joining tree analysis did not show a high similarity when our predicted nitrogenase-like enzymes were compared with representative nitrogenases taken from GenBank. This result also might explain the low specificity of universal primer sets found in the literature and used in this study (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>), which could not adequately cover the nitrogenases harbored by native bacteria living in Chilean Andisols. Accordingly, and as discussed by Gaby and Buckley (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), while several universal primers have been designed and empirically tested for nitrogenase, some of them can generate false positive reactions; and therefore, primers must be used with caution and validated with genomic DNA from phylogenetically diverse N<sub>2</sub>-fixing strains from different environments.</p><p>Likewise, members of the genus <italic>Roseomonas</italic> have been recognized as a PGPB found in a wide variety of environments, including the in rhizospheres of rice (Ramaprasad et al., <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and Chinese cabbage (Kim and Ka, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), and in contaminated soils (Chen et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In this study, we noted that there were large differences in microbiota present in rhizosphere and root endosphere samples. Similarly, Robinson et al. (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) found differences in endophytic bacteria between roots and leaves, which were attributed to tissue type, phenological stage of plants, and soil nutrient availability. Bouffaud et al. (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) also proposed that plants recruit its own N<sub>2</sub>-fixing endophytic microbiome. These differences in the composition and structure of bacterial communities between rhizosphere and root endosphere were also confirmed by DGGE. Our results suggest a compartmentalization between rhizosphere and root endosphere for both studied communities (16s rRNA and <italic>nif</italic>H). Such separation has been described as being common in plants (Mahaffee and Kloepper, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>) and we propose that these differences might also be influenced by a combination of different factors, including soil composition (pH, organic matter, and nutrients), soil management (fertilization, rotation, and tillage) and plant (genotype, phonological stages, and defense mechanisms) and the presence of other microbial communities (fungi, nematode, and protozoa).</p><p>In Chilean Andisols, as wells as other agroecosystems, our knowledge on N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial populations associated with plants is very limited. In this sense, based on the relevance of plant microbiome upon fitness and production of crops, an exhaustive study on the abundance, diversity and activity of N<sub>2</sub>-fixing bacterial populations could be essential to the develop of novel fertilizers and management agronomic strategies to improve the efficiency of N fertilization in the field with the consequent low cost for the farmers and environmental benefits.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JR performed experiments and developed the manuscript. JA, MS, and MJ contributed to statistical and elaboration of the article.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This study was funded in part by grants from the Chilean government: FONDECYT Regular No. 1160302 and FONDECYT Initiation into Research No. 11160112, and by the University of Minnesota Agricultural Experiment Station (to MS). Joaqu&#x000ed;n Rilling acknowledges the support of CONICYT Doctoral Scholarship program, Grant No. 21150794.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2018.02710/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2018.02710/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acu&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Indole acetic acid and phytase activity produced by rhizosphere bacilli as affected by pH and metals</article-title>. <source>J. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4067/S0718-95162011000300001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aqil</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousche</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Plant growth promoting potential of free-living diazotrophs and other rhizobacteria isolated from Northern Indian soil</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol. J.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>1112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1123</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/biot.200600132</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17004301?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17004301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldani</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Videira</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boddey</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldani</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The art of isolating nitrogen-fixing bacteria from non-leguminous plants using N-free semi-solid media: a practical guide for microbiologists</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>
<volume>384</volume>, <fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>431</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-014-2186-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beckers</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Op De Beeck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thijs</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Truyens</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weyens</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boerjan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Performance of 16s rDNA primer pairs in the study of rhizosphere and endosphere bacterial microbiomes in metabarcoding studies</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>650</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00650</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27242686?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27242686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beneduzi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lisboa</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Favreto</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Diversity and plant growth promoting evaluation abilities of bacteria isolated from sugarcane cultivated in the South of Brazil</article-title>. <source>Appl. Soil Ecol.</source>
<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2012.08.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grube</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schloter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smalla</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Unraveling the plant microbiome: looking back and future perspectives</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2014.00148</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24926286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24926286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertsch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Aluminum</article-title>, in <source>Methods of Soil Analysis, Part 3: Chemical Methods</source> (<publisher-loc>Madison, WI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Soil Science Society of America, American Society of Agronomy Madison</publisher-name>), <fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>550</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria (PGPR): emergence in agriculture</article-title>. <source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1350</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-011-0979-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22805914?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22805914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouffaud</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renoud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moenne-Loccoz</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Is plant evolutionary history impacting recruitment of diazotrophs and <italic>nif</italic>H expression in the rhizosphere?</article-title>
<source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep21690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28442746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breidenbach</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenzinger</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaser</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The effect of crop rotation between wetland rice and upland maize on the microbial communities associated with roots</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>
<volume>419</volume>, <fpage>435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>445</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-017-3351-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;rgmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Widmer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigler</surname><given-names>W. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeyer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>mRNA extraction and reverse transcription-PCR protocol for detection of <italic>nifH</italic> gene expression by <italic>Azotobacter vinelandii</italic> in soil</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>1928</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1935</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.4.1928-1935.2003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12676666?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aravena</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amiard</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Microencapsulation by spray drying of nitrogen-fixing bacteria associated with lupin nodules</article-title>. <source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2378</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-014-1662-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24806812?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24806812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title><italic>Roseomonas rhizosphaerae</italic> sp. nov., a triazophos-degrading bacterium isolated from soil</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>1127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1133</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.057000-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24408520?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24408520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Non-parametric multivariate analyses of changes in community structure</article-title>. <source>Austr. J. Ecol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>143</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1442-9993.1993.tb00438.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerfield</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorley</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Testing of null hypotheses in exploratory community analyses: similarity profiles and biota-environment linkage</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Mar. Biol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>366</volume>, <fpage>56</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jembe.2008.07.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Bruijn</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <source>Biological Nitrogen Fixation</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
<publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9781119053095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Meyer</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Multilocus sequence analysis of Bosea species and description of <italic>Bosea lupini</italic> sp. nov., <italic>Bosea lathyri</italic> sp. nov. and <italic>Bosea robiniae</italic> sp. nov., isolated from legumes</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>2505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2510</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.035477-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22155761?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22155761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De-la-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loyola-Vargas</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Biotic interactions in the rhizosphere: a diverse cooperative enterprise for plant productivity</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>166</volume>, <fpage>701</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>719</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.241810</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25118253?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25118253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Isolation and identification of nitrogen-fixing bacilli from plant rhizospheres in Beijing region</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <fpage>1271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1281</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2005.02738.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16238759?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16238759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dur&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acu&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azc&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paredes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rengel</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Endophytic bacteria from selenium-supplemented wheat plants could be useful for plant-growth promotion, biofortification and <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> biocontrol in wheat production</article-title>. <source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>983</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>990</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00374-014-0920-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elkoca</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kantar</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Influence of nitrogen fixing and phosphorus solubilizing bacteria on the nodulation, plant growth, and yield of chickpea</article-title>. <source>J. Plant Nutr.</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>171</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01904160701742097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaby</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A comprehensive evaluation of PCR primers to amplify the <italic>nif</italic>H gene of nitrogenase</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e42149</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22848735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Culturable bacterial community analysis in the root domains of two varieties of tree peony (<italic>Paeonia ostii</italic>)</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source>
<volume>322</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2011.02319.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21623895?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21623895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldani</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The genus <italic>Azospirillum</italic></article-title>, in <source>The Prokaryotes</source>, <volume>Vol. 5</volume>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/0-387-30745-1_6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masaoka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Advantages of a diluted nutrient broth medium for isolating N<sub>2</sub>-producing denitrifying bacteria of &#x003b1;-Proteobacteria in surface and subsurface upland soils</article-title>. <source>Soil Sci. Plant Nutr.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>659</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1747-0765.2009.00404.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinton</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sait</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Improved culturability of soil bacteria and isolation in pure culture of novel members of the divisions <italic>Acidobacteria, Actinobacteria, Proteobacteria</italic>, and <italic>Verrucomicrobia</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>2391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2396</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.5.2391-2396.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11976113?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Elevated temperature altered photosynthetic products in wheat seedlings and organic compounds and biological activity in rhizosphere soil under cadmium stress</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>14426</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep14426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26395070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inostroza</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagos</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barra</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marileo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rilling</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014a</year>). <article-title>Bacterial community structure and detection of putative plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria associated with plants grown in Chilean agro-ecosystems and undisturbed ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1153</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00374-014-0935-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marileo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acu&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saggar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014b</year>). <article-title>Effect of nitrogen and phosphorus fertilization on the composition of rhizobacterial communities of two Chilean Andisol pastures</article-title>. <source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-013-1427-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23842756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23842756</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaharoona</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadeem</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>De</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria associated with ancient clones of creosote bush (<italic>Larrea tridentata</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Microb. Ecol.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>1008</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1017</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-012-0071-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22639075?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22639075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kearse</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moir</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stones-Havas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturrock</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Geneious Basic: an integrated and extendable desktop software platform for the organization and analysis of sequence data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1649</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts199</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22543367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22543367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kembel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Incorporating 16S gene copy number information improves estimates of microbial diversity and abundance</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e1002743</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002743</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23133348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23133348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title><italic>Roseomonas soli</italic> sp. nov., isolated from an agricultural soil cultivated with Chinese cabbage (<italic>Brassica campestris</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>1024</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1029</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.053827-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24363292?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24363292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagos</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarrete</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cid</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Bacterial community structures in rhizosphere microsites of ryegrass (<italic>Lolium perenne</italic> var. <italic>Nui</italic>) as revealed by pyrosequencing</article-title>. <source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1266</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00374-014-0939-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>16S/23S sequencing</article-title>, in <source>Nucleic Acid Techniques in Bacterial Systematics</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Stackebrandt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>), <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandasena</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howieson</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borie</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Genetic diversity of <italic>Sinorhizobium meliloti</italic> associated with alfalfa in Chilean volcanic soils and their symbiotic effectiveness under acidic conditions</article-title>. <source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>308</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-007-9471-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackshields</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>McWilliam</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2947</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2948</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm404</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17846036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17846036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laval</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Cereales: producci&#x000f3;n, precios y comercio exterior de trigo, ma&#x000ed;z y arroz</article-title>. Oficina de Estudios y Pol&#x000ed;ticas Agrarias (ODEPA), Ministerio de Agricultura, Gobierno de Chile, <fpage>4</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liaqat</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltem</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Identification and characterization of endophytic bacteria isolated from <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures of peach and pear rootstocks</article-title>. <source>3 Biotech</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13205-016-0442-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28330195?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28330195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017a</year>). <article-title>The infection and impact of <italic>Azorhizobium caulinodans</italic> ORS571 on wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0187947</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0187947</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29190702?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29190702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017b</year>). <article-title>Isolation and molecular identification of endophytic diazotrophs from seeds and stems of three cereal crops</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0187383</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0187383</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29084254?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29084254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000e5;rtensson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;ez</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wartiainen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Shehawy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Diazotrophic diversity, <italic>nif</italic>H gene expression and nitrogenase activity in a rice paddy field in Fujian, China</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>
<volume>325</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>218</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-009-9970-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madhaiyan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poonguzhali</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hari</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title><italic>Bacillus rhizosphaerae</italic> sp. nov., an novel diazotrophic bacterium isolated from sugarcane rhizosphere soil</article-title>. <source>Antonie van Leeuwenhoek</source>
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>444</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-011-9600-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21671194?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21671194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahaffee</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloepper</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Bacterial communities of the rhizosphere and endorhiza associated with field-grown cucumber plants inoculated with a plant growth-promoting rhizobacterium or its genetically modified derivative</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/m97-048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9115091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luz Mora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Influence of nitrogen fertilisation on pasture culturable rhizobacteria occurrence and the role of environmental factors on their potential PGPR activities</article-title>. <source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>875</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>885</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00374-011-0593-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Development of a direct isolation procedure for free-living diazotrophs under controlled hypoxic conditions</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>78</volume>, <fpage>5542</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5549</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00714-12</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22660701?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22660701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moyes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kueppers</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pett-Ridge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carper</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandehey</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Neil</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Evidence for foliar endophytic nitrogen fixation in a widely distributed subalpine conifer</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>
<volume>210</volume>, <fpage>657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>668</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13850</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27000956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27000956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>). <article-title>A modified single solution method for the determination of phosphate in natural waters</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chim. Acta</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-2670(00)88444-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiraishi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawaharasaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamagata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title><italic>Microlunatus phosphovorus</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov., a new gram-positive polyphosphate-accumulating bacterium isolated from activated sludge</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-45-1-17</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7857797?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7857797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nu&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demanet</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Misselbrook</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfaro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Nitrogen Losses under Different Cattle Grazing Frequencies and Intensities in a Volcanic Soil of Southern Chile</article-title>. <source>Chilean J. Agri. Res.</source>
<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>250</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4067/S0718-58392010000200007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Momose</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtake</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sueyoshi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Nitrogen fixation in sugarcane</article-title>, in <source>Advances in Biology and Ecology of Nitrogen Fixation</source>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ohyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>InTech</publisher-name>), <fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5772/56993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Archana</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Diverse culturable diazotrophic endophytic bacteria from <italic>Poaceae</italic> plants show cross-colonization and plant growth promotion in wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>
<volume>417</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-017-3244-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pathania</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saroa</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vikal</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Molecular characterization of diazotrophic bacteria isolated from rhizosphere of wheat cropping system from central plain region of Punjab</article-title>. <source>Afr. J. Microbiol. Res.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>862</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>871</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/AJMR2013.5948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Padda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanway</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Evidence of nitrogen fixation and growth promotion in canola (<italic>Brassica napus</italic> L.) by an endophytic diazotroph <italic>Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> P2b-2R</article-title>. <source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>125</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00374-015-1051-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramaprasad</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasikala</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramana</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title><italic>Roseomonas oryzae</italic> sp. nov., isolated from paddy rhizosphere soil</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>3535</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3540</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijsem.0.000449</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26297330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26297330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reardon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gollany</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuest</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Diazotroph community structure and abundance in wheat-fallow and wheat-pea crop rotations</article-title>. <source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>412</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2013.10.038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraaije</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauchline</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Endophytic bacterial community composition in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) is determined by plant tissue type, developmental stage and soil nutrient availability</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>
<volume>405</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>396</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-015-2495-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Caceres</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Improved medium for isolation of <italic>Azospirillum</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>990</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>991</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16346123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruppel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of dinitrogen-fixing bacteria from the rhizosphere of Triticum aestivum and Ammophila arenaria</article-title>, in <source>Developments in Soil Science</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Van&#x0010d;ura</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunc</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Prague</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>), <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruppel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000fc;hlmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merbach</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Quantification and localization of bacteria in plant tissues using quantitative real-time PCR and online emission fingerprinting</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>
<volume>286</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-006-9023-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Analysis of gene expression in cultured mammalian cells</article-title>, in <source>Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual</source>, <volume>Vol. 3</volume>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Press</publisher-name>), <fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanguin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarniguet</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gazengel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo&#x000eb;nne-Loccoz</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundmann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Rhizosphere bacterial communities associated with disease suppressiveness stages of take-all decline in wheat monoculture</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>184</volume>, <fpage>694</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>707</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03010.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19732350?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19732350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shade</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Handelsman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Unexpected diversity during community succession in the apple</article-title>. <source>MBio</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00602-12</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23443006?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23443006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daimon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamaki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>A hidden pitfall in the preparation of agar media undermines microorganism cultivability</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>7659</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7666</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02741-14</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25281372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25281372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The plant microbiome</article-title>. <source>Adv. Bot. Res.</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2013-14-6-209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Versalovic</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koeuth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupski</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Distribution of repetitive DNA sequences in eubacteria and application to fingerprinting of bacterial genomes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>6823</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6831</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/19.24.6823</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1762913?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1762913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x0011b;trovsk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldrian</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The variability of the 16S rRNA gene in bacterial genomes and its consequences for bacterial community analyses</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e57923</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0057923</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23460914?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23460914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warncke</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Potassium and other basic cations</article-title>, in <source>Recommended Chemical Soil Test Procedures for the North Central Region, NCR Publication No. 221, Missouri Agricultural Experiment Station SB 1001</source>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Columbia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NCR Publications</publisher-name>), <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Preparation of Genomic DNA from Bacteria</article-title>, in <source>Current Protocols in Molecular Biology</source>, <volume>Vol. 56</volume>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Inc.</publisher-name>), <fpage>2.4.1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2.4.5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/0471142727.mb0204s56</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Dynamics of microbial population size in rhizosphere soil of Monsanto's Cry1Ac cotton</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil Environ.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17221/770/2015-PSE</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>