<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Pharm Investig</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Pharm Investig</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJPI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Pharmaceutical Investigation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2230-973X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2230-9713</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4286833</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJPI-5-35</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2230-973X.147231</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of the efficacy of 2% <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> gel in the treatment of experimental periodontitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hosadurga</surname><given-names>Rajesh Ramesh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>Sudarshan Narayan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Edavanputhalath</surname><given-names>Rejeesh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jose</surname><given-names>Jobin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rompicharla</surname><given-names>Narayana Charyulu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shakil</surname><given-names>Moidin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raju</surname><given-names>Shashidhara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><italic>Department of Periodontics, Yenepoya Dental College, Mangalore, India</italic></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label><italic>Department of Pharmacology, Yenepoya University, Mangalore, India</italic></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>2</label><italic>Department of Pharmaceutics, NGSM Institute of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Mangalore, India</italic></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>3</label><italic>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology, Yenepoya Dental College, Mangalore, India</italic></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>4</label><italic>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology, Coorg Institute of Dental Sciences, Karnataka, India</italic></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Rajesh Ramesh Hosadurga, Department of Periodontics, Yenepoya Dental College, Yenepoya University, Mangalore, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="drsharaj@gmail.com">drsharaj@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Mar</season><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; International Journal of Pharmaceutical Investigation</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Introduction:</title><p>One of the options for the treatment of periodontitis is local drug delivery systems (LDD). Tulsi (<italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic>), a traditional herb, has many uses in medicine. It could be a suitable agent as LDD for the treatment of periodontitis.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Aim:</title><p>The aim was to formulate, evaluate the anti-inflammatory activity; assess duration of the action and the efficacy of 2% tulsi (<italic>O. sanctum</italic>) gel in the treatment of experimental periodontitis in Wistar Albino rat model.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Settings and Design:</title><p>Thirty six Wistar albino rats were randomly assigned to 3 groups. Periodontitis was induced using ligature model. Group 1-control; Group 2-Plain gel and Group 3-2% tulsi (<italic>O. sanctum</italic>) gel.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>2% tulsi (<italic>O. sanctum</italic>) gel were prepared. The anti-inflammatory activity and duration of action were assessed. Silk ligature 5-0 was used to induce periodontitis. Gingival index (GI) and probing pocket depth were measured. Treatment was done. The rats were sacrificed. Morphometric analysis was done using Stereomicroscope and ImageJ software.</p></sec><sec id="st5"><title>Statistical Analysis Used:</title><p>ANOVA followed by Bonferroni's test, Wilcoxon's test for intergroup comparison, Mann-Whitney test for <italic>P</italic> value computation was used. The observations are mean &#x000b1; standard deviation and standard error of the mean. <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 as compared to control was considered as statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="st6"><title>Results:</title><p>2% tulsi (<italic>O. sanctum</italic>) gel showed 33.66% inhibition of edema and peak activity was noted at 24 h. There was statistically significant change in the GI and probing pocket depth. Morphometric analysis did not show any significant difference between groups. No toxic effects were seen on oral administration of 2000 mg/kg of Tulsi extract.</p></sec><sec id="st7"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>2% tulsi (<italic>O. sanctum</italic>) gel was effective in the treatment of experimental periodontitis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Anti-inflammatory activity</kwd><kwd>experimental periodontitis</kwd><kwd>local drug delivery</kwd><kwd>morphometric analysis</kwd><kwd>tulsi gel</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The Babylonians, Sumerians, and Assyrians had suffered from periodontal disease and used clay tablets for gingival massage along with various herbal medicines. The <italic>Susrutha Samhitha</italic> and the <italic>Charaka Samhitha</italic>, the medical works of ancient India, contain numerous descriptions of severe periodontal disease with loose teeth and purulent discharge from the gingiva or gums. Chronic periodontitis is a destructive disease that affects the supporting structures of the teeth namely, periodontal ligament, cementum, and alveolar bone.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] It may develop in any age group, but is most common in adults. The prevalence and severity of the disease increase with age. The number of teeth affected may vary, and the rate of progression also varies. Bacteria accumulate around the teeth in the form of biofilm and initiate the disease.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] The main clinical features of chronic periodontal disease include supra and subgingival plaque accumulation (associated with calculus formation), gingival inflammation, bleeding on probing, periodontal pocket formation, attachment loss, and alveolar bone loss. If treatment is not given, the disease progresses and results in tooth loss.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</p><p>Mechanical instrumentation is the first treatment of choice; however, remnants of plaque and calculus left behind can cause the treatment to fail. Complete removal of plaque and calculus is difficult in deep pockets. The remnants of plaque and calculus can cause failure in periodontal treatment.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] The drugs can act as valuable adjuncts to treat plaque-associated periodontal diseases. Many studies have addressed the need for the local application of antimicrobial agents to the subgingival area for the treatment of periodontitis. Many studies have extensively studied the efficacy of the tetracycline group of drugs as local drug delivery (LDD) systems and found to be effective in the treatment of periodontitis.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] Most of these LDD systems are difficult to procure and expensive. India being a developing country, the cost of the treatment is a matter of concern for our patients. Hence, the use of indigenous herbal drugs has been an area of significant interest in the treatment of periodontal diseases. Several research studies have established their efficacy in the treatment of periodontal diseases.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</p><p>Medicinal plants can be natural composite sources that act as new anti-infectious agents. The emergence of bacterial resistance has necessitated the search for new and effective antimicrobial compounds. Globally, plant extracts are employed for their anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, antifungal, and antiviral activities.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Eugenol-based gels are available for the treatment of periodontits.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Free eugenol can cause bone resorption. Literature report is available where osteoradionecrosis has occurred when there is an excess free eugenol.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Low concentrations of eugenol exert anti-inflammatory and local anesthetic effects on the dental pulp, on the other hand, high eugenol concentrations are cytotoxic. Direct application of eugenol to pulp tissue may result in extensive tissue damage.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] Whole tulsi extract, on the other hand, have been widely used in traditional medicine and human clinical trial without significant side effects.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] Hence, we used supercritical fluid extract of tulsi leaves for 2% <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> gel preparation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>Institutional Animal Ethical Committee, approval was obtained. <italic>O. sanctum</italic> gel was formulated. Dosage of the gel was selected based on the results of Acute Oral Toxicity Study of <italic>O. sanctum</italic> done in Wistar Albino Rats as per the OECD Guidelines No. 420. The rats were housed in polypropylene cages under standard conditions with access to food and water <italic>ad libitum</italic>.</p><p>The aim of the present study was to formulate, evaluate the anti-inflammatory activity, to assess the duration of action and the efficacy of 2% <italic>O. sanctum</italic> gel in the treatment of experimentally induced periodontitis in Wistar Albino rat model.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-3"><title>PREPARATION OF 2% <italic>OCIMUM SANCTUM</italic> GEL BY SIMPLE DISPERSION METHOD</title><p>Two percentage <italic>O. sanctum</italic> gel were prepared in the following manner. Carbopol-940 was soaked in purified water containing 0.2% w/v sodium benzoate overnight. Using tissue homogenizer hydroxypropyl methyl cellulose (HPMC) solution was mixed with propylene glycol. 2 ml of tulsi extract (Supercritical fluid extract, procured from Sami labs, Bengaluru) was transferred into HPMC solution and homogenized. This drug solution was later transferred to Carbopol solution and homogenized. Triethanolamine was added to neutralize the pH [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>]. Control gel was prepared in the same manner. The gel was stored at ambient temperature. This gel was stable over a period of 6 months. Slight pH changes were noted and corrected.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] The formulation was done in NSGM institute of Pharmaceutical sciences, NITTE university, Mangalore [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Formula used to prepare 2% Tulsi (<italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic>) gel</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g001"/></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>2% tulsi gel</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec1-4"><title>EVALUATION OF PHYSICOCHEMICAL PARAMETERS OF 2% <italic>OCIMUM SANCTUM</italic> GEL</title><p>The formulations were subjected to various tests like physical evaluation, homogeneity, spreadabilty, grittiness, extrudability, and pH measurement.</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Physical evaluation</title><p>Physical observations such as color and appearance were checked.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Spreadability</title><p>Spreadability was determined by an apparatus that consists of a wooden block with a pulley at one end. The basis for this method was the slip and drag characteristics of gels. 2 g of the gel was placed on the ground slide. The gel was sandwiched between the ground slide and a glass slide of similar dimensions with an attached hook. 1 kg weight was placed on the top of the two slides for 5 min to remove air bubbles and to provide a uniform gel film between the slides. Excess gel was removed from the edges. The upper plate was then subjected to pull of 80 g by the help of string attached to the hook and the time (in seconds) taken by the upper slide to cover a distance of 7.5 cm was noted. A shorter interval indicates better spreadability.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] Spreadability was calculated using the following formula:</p><p>S = M &#x000d7; L/T</p><p>Where, S = Spreadability,</p><p>M = Weight in the pan (tied to the upper slide),</p><p>L = Length moved by the glass slide and</p><p>T = Time (in seconds) taken to separate the slide completely each other.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Homogeneity</title><p>The formulation was tested for homogeneity by visual observation after it set in a container. We checked for any aggregates. Grades were allotted as +++ Good, ++ fair, + Poor.[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Extrudability</title><p>The formulation was filled in a clean, lacquered aluminum collapsible one ounce tube with a nasal tip of 5 mm opening. The extrudability was then determined by measuring the amount of gel extruded through the tip when a constant load of 1 kg was placed. The extruded gel was collected and weighed. The percentage of gel extruded was calculated, and grades were allotted.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Determination of viscosity</title><p>Viscosity of the formulation was measured at 25&#x000b0;C using Brookfield digital viscosimeter. The measurements were made over the whole range of speed settings from 10 rpm to 100 rpm with 30 s interval between two successive speeds and then in a descending order.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Determination of pH</title><p>2.5 g of the gel was accurately weighed and dispersed in 25 ml of water. It was stored for 2 h. The pH was measured using a pH meter.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Evaluation of anti-inflammatory activity of 2% <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> gel</title><p>18 healthy Wistar albino rats of either sex were randomly allocated to test (2% <italic>O. sanctum</italic> gel), standard (1% Voveron<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Emulgel<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> gel, Novartis, India) and control group (plain gel) with six animals (<italic>n</italic> = 6) in each group. The anti-inflammatory activity was assessed by Carrageenan induced Paw edema method. The average weight of the rats was 237.50 &#x000b1; 22.305 g in the test group, 227.33 &#x000b1; 62.199 g in the standard group and 228.33 &#x000b1; 9.832 g in the control group. Inflammation was induced in the paws by sub plantar injection of 0.1% Carrageenan. After 1 h, 50 mg of the 2% gel was divided into two equal parts of 25 mg. The first part of 25 mg gel was applied on the plantar surfaces of their left hind paw surface by gentle rubbing with the index finger approximately 50 times until no gel was seen or felt on the skin. After 5 min, 25 mg gel was applied in a similar manner.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] The control gel base and the standard gel were applied by the same mode of application. This was followed by paw thickness measurement using Vernier Caliper method. This reading was the 0<sup>th</sup> h reading. Then rats were housed in cages without bedding to minimize the chances of the bias of drug being washed out by the bedding material. After 3 h readings were repeated. The rats were then transferred back to cages with bedding.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Percentage inflammation was calculated using the formula</title><p>Percentage inflammation = (V&#x02212;Vi&#x000f7;Vi) &#x000d7; 100. Where V<sub>i</sub> = 0 h reading and V = 3 h reading. The average paw thickness in the drug-treated group was compared with the control group.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Percent inhibition of the edema was calculated using the formula</title><p>Percent inhibition of the edema = (Vt&#x000f7;Vc) &#x000d7; 100 Where Vt is percentage swelling of the drug treated group, and Vc is percentage swelling of the control group.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Duration of anti-inflammatory activity of 2% <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> gel</title><p>36 healthy Wistar albino rats of either sex were divided into six groups (<italic>n</italic> = 6) based on the time duration at which 2% <italic>O. sanctum</italic> gel was applied prior to injection of 0.1% carrageenan. In Group 1-6, 50 mg of 2% <italic>O. sanctum</italic> gel was applied at 0, 2, 4, 6, 12, 24, and 48 h prior to administration of Carrageenan.</p><p>50 mg of the 2% gel was divided into two equal parts of 25 mg. The first part of 25 mg gel was applied on the plantar surfaces of their left hind paw surface by gentle rubbing with the index finger approximately 50 times until no gel was seen or felt on the skin. After 5 min, 25 mg gel was applied in a similar manner at 2, 4, 6, 12, 24, and 48 h prior to injection of 0.1 ml of 1% Carrageenan solution.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] Three hours after the injection the 3<sup>rd</sup> h reading was noted. The percentage inflammation and the percent inhibition of edema at each dosing interval were calculated using the above-mentioned formulae. In the control group, (<italic>n</italic> = 6) the plain gel and standard (Voveron<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> gel) group (<italic>n</italic> = 6) gel was applied 3 h prior to the Carrageenan injection.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Experimental periodontitis</title><p>36 Wistar albino rats (5-10 weeks old) weighing between 150 and 250 g were used in the study. 5 rats weighing 150-250 g were taken in a polypropylene cage each day of the experiment for 9 days. In order to carry out dental procedures in the mouth of rats, a profound and safe general anesthesia is a must.[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] Use of inhalational anesthesia and the equipment hamper the visual field and maneuverability during oral surgical procedures. Using single drug intraperitoneally to achieve all three components of anesthesia will make the procedure easy. Ketamine (Anket, Lupin Ltd., India), a cyclohexamine, was used in the current study as it is easy to use and has a greater margin of safety for most laboratory animals.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] High doses of ketamine induce catalepsy and is not accompanied by central nervous system depression. Respiratory functions are depressed, but cardiovascular function is maintained. The swallowing reflex is maintained, and this might help to prevent aspiration pneumonia if the animal regurgitates. The chance of animal morbidity and mortality is low. Hence, we used Ketamine anesthesia.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</p><p>The rats were anesthetized with ketamine anesthesia using intraperitoneal route. Pre-periodontal examination was done, and the upper second molars were ligated using a sterile braided silk suture (5-0) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>]. Soft tissue indicators were measured.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Ligature placement</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-12"><title>Treatment of experimental periodontitis</title><p>4 weeks after ligature placement the rats were divided into three groups. The rats in the group 1-control group did not receive any treatment, group 2 received plain gel, group 3 received 2% Tulsi gel. The gels were applied with a tuberculin syringe with a blunt tip. The application was done every alternate day for 6 days. The soft tissue indicators were measured prior to euthanizing the rats.[<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-13"><title>Soft tissue indicators of periodontitis</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Gingival index</title><p>Gingival index (GI) was recorded on maxillary 2<sup>nd</sup> molar on four surfaces - Mesial, Buccal, Distal, and Palatal surface. GI was recorded 1 week after ligature placement and 1 week after treatment.[<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Pocket probing depth</title><p>Pocket probing depth (PPD) was taken from the gingival margin to the bottom of the pocket using a modified graduated silver cone with round-ended tip of approximately 0.4 mm in diameter. Six values were recorded and averaged (mesiobuccal, midbuccal, distobuccal, mesiopalatal, mid palatal, and distopalatal). PPD was examined 1 week after ligature placement and 1 week after treatment.[<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-14"><title>Sacrificial indicator</title><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Morphometric analysis of alveolar bone loss</title><p>After the rats were euthanized with ketamine overdose the specimens were dissected carefully to maintain their integrity then, immersed in sodium hypochlorite for 4 h and manual scavenging of the remaining tissue was done. The specimens were stained with methylene blue dye (1 g/100 mL, Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, MO, USA) for 1 min to demarcate the cemento enamel junction [CEJ] and examined under a stereomicroscope. In order to ensure reproducibility of the alignment of the image, the buccal cusp tip of the first and second molars were placed such that they superimposed on the corresponding lingual/palatal cusp tip. Photographs were obtained with a 6.1-megapixel digital camera (Nikon D100, Ayutthaya, Thailand). Measurements were made on the maxillary second molar in a blinded fashion, three times using ImageJ, image-analysis software (Java based image processing software, NIH, USA), and the mean values were used in statistical analysis.[<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] The distance method applied by Crawford, Taubman and Smith on digitalized images was used to perform linear measurements from the CEJ to the alveolar bone crest, on half of each root following the axis. Six measurements were obtained for the maxillary second molar [Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>]. The data were subjected to statistical analysis.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Morphometric analysis: Buccal view</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g004"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Morphometric analysis: Palatal view</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g005"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-5"><title>RESULTS</title><p>All statistical analysis was done using InStat-GraphPad software (GraphPad software Inc. CA, USA). <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 was considered highly significant and <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered significant.</p><sec id="sec2-15"><title>Evaluation of physicochemical parameters of the 2% <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> gel</title><p>The developed gel was grayish in color, translucent in appearance and showed good homogeneity with absence of lumps. The gel showed optimum spreadability of 15 g cm/s. Hence, the spreadability was good. The gel showed homogeneity of +++ grade and good extrudability. The pH was within the acceptable range of 6.9-7.2 even at the end of 30 days [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Physicochemical characters of 2% tulsi gel</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g006"/></table-wrap><p>We could not do determine drug content uniformity and drug release studies, as it was a whole leaf extract, and we had technical difficulties.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-16"><title>Evaluation of anti-inflammatory action of 2% tulsi (<italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic>) gel</title><p>The results of the ANOVA show that there was no statistically significant difference in the mean weight of the rats which, in the control, standard, and the test group was 238.33 &#x000b1; 9.83 g, 227.33 &#x000b1; 62.19 g, and 237.50 &#x000b1; 22.30 g, respectively. (<italic>P</italic> = 0.861).</p><p>The test group showed moderate anti-inflammatory activity compared to the standard. Percent inhibition of edema in the test group was 33.66%, and the standard group was 76.97% [Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Weight of the animals selected for the study</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g007"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Percentage of inflammation in control, standard, and test group</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g008"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Percentage of inhibition of edema</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g009"/></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-17"><title>Duration of the anti-inflammatory activity of 2% Ocimum sanctum gel</title><p>Tulsi gel showed peak anti-inflammatory activity during 24 h, and the activity was seen even at the end of 48 h. Percent inhibition of edema at 24 h was 67.58% [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref>]. Hence, the gel was applied every 24 h to treat periodontitis.</p><table-wrap id="T6" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Duration of anti inflammatory action of 2% Tulsi gel</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g010"/></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-18"><title>Soft tissue indicators of periodontitis</title><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Gingival index</title><p>There was a statistically significant reduction in the mean GI scores in the test group at the end of the treatment when compared to the control and the plain gel group. The mean percentage change was &#x02212;40.35, &#x02212;39.62, and 43.23% (<italic>P</italic> = 0.001) [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">Table 7</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T7" position="float"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Comparison of GI before and after treatment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g011"/></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Pocket probing depth</title><p>There was no statistically significant difference between the groups in PPD at the baseline. But at the end of the treatment, tulsi gel showed statistically significant different reduction in probing pocket depth, Mean difference was 1. There was no statistically significant difference between the control group and plain gel. Mean difference was 0.054 [Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T8">8</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T9">9</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T8" position="float"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Probing pocket depth</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g012"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T9" position="float"><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Comparison between control and treatment group at the end of treatment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g013"/></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-6"><title>Sacrificial indicators</title><p>Morphometric analysis</p><p>On the comparison using Bonferroni's multiple comparisons test, there was no statistically significant bone loss between the various groups at the mesiobuccal, midbuccal, distobuccal, mesiopalatal, midpalatal, and distopalatal site [Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T16">16</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T10" position="float"><label>Table 10</label><caption><p>Mean bone level at sites treated with control, plain gel and 2% tulsi gel</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g014"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T11" position="float"><label>Table 11</label><caption><p>Comparison of the effect of control, plain gel, and 2% tulsi gel on bone loss (mesiobuccal site)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g015"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T12" position="float"><label>Table 12</label><caption><p>Comparison of the effect of control, plain gel and 2% tulsi gel on bone loss (midbuccal site)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g016"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T13" position="float"><label>Table 13</label><caption><p>Comparison of the effect of control, plain gel and 2% tulsi gel on bone loss (distobuccal site)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g017"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T14" position="float"><label>Table 14</label><caption><p>Comparison of the effect of control, plain gel and 2% tulsi gel on bone loss (mesiopalatal site)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g018"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T15" position="float"><label>Table 15</label><caption><p>Comparison of the effect of control, plain gel and 2% tulsi gel on bone loss (mid palatal site)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g019"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T16" position="float"><label>Table 16</label><caption><p>Comparison of the effect of control, plain gel and 2% tulsi gel on bone loss (distopalatal site)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJPI-5-35-g020"/></table-wrap><p>Acute oral toxicity</p><p>All the animals survived for the period of 14 days. They appeared healthy throughout the study. All the animals appeared to gain weight during the observation period of 14 days. There were no signs of gross toxicity, adverse pharmacological events or changes in behavior. Gross necropsy findings did not show any abnormalities.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-6"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Local drug delivery to the periodontal pocket as a method to treat periodontal disease has been extensively studied. Several herbal drugs in the form of LDD have been an area of interest in the treatment of periodontal diseases.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</p><p>The common methods used to induce periodontitis in the rats are by tying ligature braided silk (2-0-5-0) around the cervix of the maxillary or mandibular molars or by injecting lipopolysaccharides into the papilla or combination of both.[<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] The time period used for induction of periodontitis in the maxillary molars was 4 weeks.[<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] It was similar to the study period used in our study.</p><p>Anti-inflammatory agents have been used in the treatment of periodontitis.[<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] The methanol extract and the aqueous extract of <italic>O. sanctum</italic> have shown to inhibit acute as well as chronic inflammation in rats.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] Eugenol (l-hydroxy-2-methoxy-4-allylbenzene), the active constituent present in <italic>O. sanctum</italic>, has been found to be largely responsible for the anti-inflammatory property of tulsi. It demonstrated 97% cyclooxygenase-1 inhibitory activity when assayed at 1000 &#x003bc;M concentration.</p><p>The results of anti-inflammatory activity of <italic>O. sanctum</italic> support the dual inhibition of arachidonic acid metabolism as indicated by its activity in inflammation models that are insensitive to selective cyclooxygenase inhibitors. Linolenic acid present in <italic>O. sanctum</italic> fixed oil has the capacity to block both the cyclo-oxygenase and lipoxygenase pathways of arachidonate metabolism and could be responsible for the anti-inflammatory activity of the oil.[<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] Civsilineol, Civsimavitin, Isothymonin, Apigenin, and Rosavinic acid displayed 37, 50, 37, 65, and 58% cyclooxygenase-1 inhibitory activity, respectively, when assayed at 1000 &#x003bc;M concentrations. The activities of these compounds were comparable to Ibuprofen, Naproxen and aspirin at 10, 100 and 1000 &#x003bc;M concentrations.[<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] Literature review is not clear about the active ingredient responsible for anti-inflammatory, analgesic and antimicrobial actions of tulsi. Hence, we used a supercritical fluid extract of <italic>O. sanctum</italic> instead of single active ingredient to prepare a 2% gel by simple gel dispersion method. The gel showed a standard physicochemical profile. Drug content uniformity and drug release studies were not done, as it was a whole extract, and we faced technical difficulties. Percent inhibition of edema was 33.66%. Maximum inhibition was seen at 24 h. The anti-inflammatory activity lasted for 48 h. Hence, the gel was applied on alternate days to treat experimental periodontitis.</p><p>The GI scores in the control group and plain gel group increased indicating that the inflammation progressed. In the 2% tulsi gel group, a highly significant mean percentage decrease was noted. This showed that the test gel had good anti-inflammatory effect.</p><p>Morphometric analysis did not show any significant difference between the groups. The effect of LDD system on bone regeneration is controversial. In our study, we did not notice any significant difference in the residual periodontal bone level among various groups.</p><sec id="sec2-19"><title>Limitations of the study</title><p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Pressure sensitive probe and stent needs to be used.</p></list-item><list-item><p>No scaling and root planing was done.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Microbial profiling, Biochemical, and immuno-histochemical parameters have to be evaluated.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Drug content uniformity and drug release studies were not done.</p></list-item><list-item><p>It is worthwhile to do chronic toxicity study. But, the animals were monitored closely during the entire study period for any signs of toxicity. No signs of chronic toxicity were noted.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-7"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>2% tulsi (<italic>O. sanctum</italic>) gel have shown good anti-inflammatory effect for 24-48 h. The 2% tulsi gel showed good anti-inflammatory effect resulting in a reduction of gingival inflammation and pocket depth. The alveolar bone loss was not statistically significant. LDD systems help in the disease limitation and its role in bone regeneration is not established. Hence, 2% tulsi (<italic>O. sanctum</italic>) gel can be used as useful adjunct to enhance the results of conventional periodontal therapy.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alger</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Solt</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuddhakanok</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The histologic evaluation of new attachment in periodontally diseased human roots treated with tetracycline-hydrochloride and fibronectin</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>1990</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2388142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barney</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioceramic implants in surgical periodontal defects. A comparison study</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>1986</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3025405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Carranza</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic periodontitis</article-title><source>Carranza's Clinical Periodontology &#x02014; A South Asia Edition</source><year>2012</year><edition>11th ed</edition><publisher-loc>Saunders, Pennsylvania</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabbani</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ash</surname><given-names>MM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Caffesse</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effectiveness of subgingival scaling and root planing in calculus removal</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>1981</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7014822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Needleman</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlled drug release in periodontics: A review of new therapies</article-title><source>Br Dent J</source><year>1991</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2059528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiorellini</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Paquette</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential role of controlled-release delivery systems for chemotherapeutic agents in periodontics</article-title><source>Curr Opin Dent</source><year>1992</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1520942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kornman</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlled-release local delivery antimicrobials in periodontics: Prospects for the future</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>1993</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8410618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirasawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Makimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Otake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvement of periodontal status by green tea catechin using a local delivery system: A clinical pilot study</article-title><source>J Periodontal Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12472837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aibinu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Odugbemi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants as antimicrobials</article-title><source>Outline and Pictures of Medicinal Plants from Nigeria</source><year>2006</year><edition>1st ed</edition><publisher-loc>Lagos</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Lagos press</publisher-name><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahadlek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Charoenteeraboon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Phaechamud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zinc oxide gels for periodontitis treatment</article-title><source>J Met</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jovanovic</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Buric</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Krunic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihajlovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maxillary osteonecrosis caused by toxic effect of zinc-oxide-eugenol paste</article-title><source>Stomatologiia (Mosk)</source><year>2007</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17828069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markowitz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moynihan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biologic properties of eugenol and zinc oxide-eugenol. A clinically oriented review</article-title><source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol</source><year>1992</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>729</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1437045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelo</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>da Costa</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical effect of a mouth rinse containing <italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic> on plaque and gingivitis control</article-title><source>J Contemp Dent Pract</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22269195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shawetha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Upendra</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and evaluation of topical Curcumin from different combination of polymers formulation and evaluation of herbal gel</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>4452</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formulation and evaluation of herbal gel containing <italic>Sesbania Grandiflora (L.)</italic> Poir. Leaf extract</article-title><source>Acta Chim. Pharm. Indica</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijaybhaskar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>kumar</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histopathological effect of mucoadhesive herbal gel on Tobacco carcinogenicity</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Biol Arch</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourishyam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanjay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formulation development and standardisation of herbal gel containing methanolic extract of <italic>Butea Frondosa</italic></article-title><source>Int Res J Pharm</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaud</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory activity of Tenoxicam gel on carrageenan induced paw oedema in rats</article-title><source>Indian J Pharm sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petcu</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kocher</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Buga</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kl&#x000f6;ting</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mild systemic inflammation has a neuroprotective effect after stroke in rats</article-title><source>Curr Neurovasc Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18991656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative studies on some antagonists of N-methyl D-aspartate in slices of rat cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>1985</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2858237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajesh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rejeesh</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ketamine as a single general anesthetic agent for oral surgical procedures in wistaralbino rats-an experimental study</article-title><source>Int J Bioassays</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1094</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of systemic ornidazole, systemic and local compound ornidazole and pefloxacin mesylate on experimental periodontitis in rats</article-title><source>Med Sci Monit</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>BR95</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22367122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f6;e</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The gingival index, the plaque index and the retention index systems</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>1967</year><volume>38 Suppl</volume><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5237684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elverdin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Solari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiarenza</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vacas</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced methacholine-induced submandibular salivary secretion in rats with experimental periodontitis</article-title><source>Arch Oral Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21145037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Struillou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutigny</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Soueidan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Layrolle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental animal models in periodontology: A review</article-title><source>Open Dent J</source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20556202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado Fde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado Mde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of two morphometric methods of bone loss percentages caused by periodontitis in rats in different locations</article-title><source>J Appl Oral Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21085806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drisko</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-surgical pocket therapy: Pharmacotherapeutics</article-title><source>Ann Periodontol</source><year>1996</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9118269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehan</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of anti-inflammatory potential of fixed oil of <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> (Holybasil) and its possible mechanism of action</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>1996</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8941864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godhwani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Godhwani</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic>: An experimental study evaluating its anti-inflammatory, analgesic and antipyretic activity in animals</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>1987</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3501819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelm</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasburg</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWitt</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and cyclooxygenase inhibitory phenolic compounds from <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> Linn</article-title><source>Phytomedicine</source><year>2000</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10782484</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>