<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5349111</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00281</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Biofortification of Wheat Cultivars to Combat Zinc Deficiency</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chattha</surname><given-names>Muhammad U.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>Muhammad U.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/373688/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Imran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chattha</surname><given-names>Muhammad B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/384613/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>Athar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/369951/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chattha</surname><given-names>Muhammad U.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Subhani</surname><given-names>Muhammad N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/396111/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kharal</surname><given-names>Mina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Sadia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Agronomy, University of Agriculture Faisalabad, Faisalabad</institution><country>Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Institute of Agricultural Sciences, University of the Punjab</institution><country>Lahore, Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Agronomy, Bahauddin Zakariya University</institution><country>Multan, Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>College of Agriculture, Bahadur Campus Layyah, Bahauddin Zakariya University</institution><country>Multan, Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Management Sciences, National Textile University</institution><country>Faisalabad, Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Department of Agriculture, Government of Punjab</institution><country>Lahore, Pakistan</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: <italic>Raul Antonio Sperotto, Centro Universit&#x000e1;rio Univates, Brazil</italic></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: <italic>James Stangoulis, Flinders University, Australia; Hakoomat Ali, Bahauddin Zakariya University, Pakistan</italic></p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: <italic>Muhammad B. Chattha, <email xlink:type="simple">bilal1409@yahoo.com</email></italic></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Nutrition, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>281</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2017 Chattha, Hassan, Khan, Chattha, Mahmood, Chattha, Nawaz, Subhani, Kharal and Khan.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chattha, Hassan, Khan, Chattha, Mahmood, Chattha, Nawaz, Subhani, Kharal and Khan</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Zinc (Zn) deficiency caused by inadequate dietary intake is a global nutritional problem, particularly in developing countries. Therefore, zinc biofortification of wheat and other cereal crops is being urgently addressed and highly prioritized as a research topic. A field study was planned to evaluate the influence of zinc application on grain yield, grain zinc content, and grain phytic acid concentrations of wheat cultivars, and the relationships between these parameters. Three wheat cultivars, C<sub>1</sub> = Faisalabad-2008, C<sub>2</sub> = Punjab-2011, and C<sub>3</sub> = Millet-2011 were tested with five different methods of zinc application: T<sub>1</sub> = control, T<sub>2</sub> = seed priming, T<sub>3</sub> = soil application, T<sub>4</sub> = foliar application, and T<sub>5</sub> = soil + foliar application. It was found that grain yield and grain zinc were positively correlated, whereas, grain phytic acid and grain zinc were significantly negatively correlated. Results also revealed that T<sub>5</sub>, T<sub>3</sub>, and T<sub>4</sub> considerably increased grain yield; however, T<sub>2</sub> only slightly enhanced grain yield. Grain zinc concentration increased from 33.1 and 33.7 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in T<sub>1</sub> to 62.3 and 63.1 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in T<sub>5</sub> in 2013&#x02013;2014 and 2014&#x02013;2015, respectively. In particular, T<sub>5</sub> markedly decreased grain phytic acid content; however, maximum concentration was recorded in T<sub>1</sub>. Moreover, all the tested cultivars exhibited considerable variation in grain yield, grain zinc, and grain phytic acid content. In conclusion, T<sub>5</sub> was found to be most suitable for both optimum grain yield and grain biofortification of wheat.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>zinc deficiency</kwd><kwd>zinc application methods</kwd><kwd>grain zinc contents</kwd><kwd>grain phytic acid</kwd><kwd>biofortification</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="54"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Zinc (Zn) is an essential micronutrient in biological metabolism, and is receiving growing attention around the globe because of increasing reports of zinc deficiency in food crops as well as in humans (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Alloway, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Hotz and Brown, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>). Zinc is required for normal growth and development of humans and plants (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Hafeez et al., 2013</xref>). Moreover, it affects multiple aspects of the immune system (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Shankar and Prasad, 1998</xref>) and is required for normal development and proper function of cell mediating immunity, neutrophils, and natural killer cells (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Prasad, 2008</xref>). Similarly, in plants, zinc plays a crucial role in enzymatically driven metabolism (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Tisdale et al., 1984</xref>). It also makes a notable contribution toward gene expression, stress tolerance (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2000</xref>), and pollen tube formation (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Pandey et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>Zinc deficiency is among the top five micronutrient deficiencies and severely affects one-third of the world&#x02019;s population, especially rural communities (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Hotz and Brown, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Stein, 2010</xref>). Inadequate intake of food low in zinc content is a major contributor to the prevalence of zinc deficiency in humans. As one of the commonest cereal crops, wheat contributes to the provision of daily calories, proteins, and bioavailable micronutrients. In many developing nations, wheat provides over 50% of the daily calorific intake (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>).</p><p>An excessive intake of monotonous wheat products is a major reason for zinc malnutrition in humans because wheat is inherently low in zinc content and high in phytate, which further limits zinc bioavailability (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Welch and Graham, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak et al., 2010b</xref>). Different reports are available indicating that more than 50% of wheat around the globe is cultivated on zinc-deficient soils (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Alloway, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>), which further lowers grain zinc content. The adoption of high-yielding cultivars seems to have aggravated this problem (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Zhao and McGrath, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Stein, 2010</xref>). Furthermore, wheat processing after harvesting markedly decreases grain zinc and micronutrients such as iron, which enhances the chance of zinc deficiency in humans (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Kutman et al., 2011</xref>). Hence, there is an urgent challenge and dire need to increase grain zinc content and bioavailability in developing countries (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Welch and Graham, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Zhao and McGrath, 2009</xref>).</p><p>In response to the aforementioned problem, different approaches have been suggested and applied in developing nations (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Bouis, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Pfeiffer and McClafferty, 2007</xref>), where the biofortification of cereals with important micronutrients is receiving a great deal of attention (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Zhao and McGrath, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Bouis and Welch, 2010</xref>). Key tools in biofortification include breeding and agronomic techniques such as fertilizer application. Breeding techniques are prime, and there are long-term strategies to deal with micronutrient malnutrition through evolving new genotypes with higher grain nutrient content (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Welch and Graham, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bouis et al., 2011</xref>). However, breeding techniques take time and are costly, so agronomic techniques may provide a quicker solution to the micronutrient malnutrition problem. Agronomic techniques involve fertilizer application by seed priming or soil and foliar application. Moreover, the fertilization approach is a quick and complementary strategy, which maintains and builds a pool of zinc for translocation and uptake (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>). Zinc has moderate phloem mobility (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Haslett et al., 2001</xref>), so its application as a foliar feed alone or as a combination of soil plus foliar application markedly increases grain zinc content (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>). Furthermore, grain zinc concentration is severely affected by the availability of a physiological pool of zinc in vegetative tissues as a result of foliar application (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak et al., 2010a</xref>); the latter can substantially increase zinc concentration in wheat endosperm (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak et al., 2010a</xref>; <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2010a</xref>). On the other hand, soil application of zinc is less effective in increasing grain zinc concentration because of poor zinc mobility and its rapid absorption in alkaline calcareous soils (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Alloway, 2008</xref>). Furthermore, zinc application substantially reduces grain phytic acid concentration, which is widely used as an indicator of zinc bioavailability in diets (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Erdal et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak et al., 2010b</xref>). Therefore, agronomic biofortification through fertilization is the most valuable approach for combatting zinc malnutrition.</p><p>Zinc is an active nutrient and has antagonisms [phosphorus (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Mousavi, 2011</xref>), copper (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Imtiaz et al., 2003</xref>), and cadmium (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Moustakas et al., 2011</xref>) and synergisms [iron (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Mousavi, 2011</xref>) and boron (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Rengel et al., 1998</xref>)]. Higher phosphorus levels in soil reduce zinc concentrations in plant aerial parts and also reduce total zinc content; similarly, phosphorus exerts P-Zn antagonism in plants (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 1986</xref>). Phytic acid binds nutritionally important minerals such as zinc and impairs their biological utilization. Thus, a high concentration of phytic acid in cereal-based foods is a major cause of zinc deficiency in humans (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Gibson et al., 1997</xref>). To combat this, the application of zinc substantially reduces grain phytic acid content and increases zinc bioavailability, as shown in soybean after enhanced zinc supply (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Raboy and Dickinson, 1984</xref>). In most cases, there is an inverse relationship between grain yield and grain zinc concentration (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Garvin et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">McDonald et al., 2008</xref>) with higher grain zinc concentrations being most commonly associated with lower yielding genotypes (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Oury et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Fan et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">McDonald et al., 2008</xref>). Moreover, some studies reveal that grain yield increases simultaneously, along with a remarkable increase in grain zinc concentration, as shown in Pakistan (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Zou et al., 2012</xref>), China (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Karim et al., 2012</xref>), and Turkey (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Yilmaz et al., 1997</xref>). Thus, this study aimed to address the following questions: (1) what is the influence of zinc application method on grain yield, grain zinc concentration, and grain phytic acid concentration of wheat, (2) what is the relationship between grain zinc concentration and grain yield, and (3) what is the relationship between grain zinc and grain phytic acid content?</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Experimental Site and Planting Material</title><p>The experiment was conducted at the Agronomic Research Farm, University of Agriculture, Faisalabad, Pakistan, during the winter seasons (November to April) of 2013&#x02013;2014 and 2014&#x02013;2015. The temperature of this region ranges between &#x02212;1&#x000b0;C in January and 48&#x000b0;C in June, with a mean annual rainfall of around 200&#x02013;250 mm. The prevailing conditions during both years are presented in <bold>Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1A">1A</xref>,<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1B">B</xref></bold>. Seeds from three wheat cultivars, Faisalabad-2008, Punjab-2011, and Millet-2011 were obtained from the Wheat Research Institute, Ayub Agricultural Research Institute, Faisalabad, Pakistan.</p><table-wrap id="T1A" position="float"><label>Table 1A</label><caption><p>Prevailing climatic conditions for the experimental site during crop growing seasons for the years 2013&#x02013;2014.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Months</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rainfall (mm)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monthly mean maximum temperature (&#x000b0;C)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monthly mean minimum temperature (&#x000b0;C)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monthly average temperature (&#x000b0;C)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative humidity (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">November-13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">December-13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">January-14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feburary-14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">March-14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">April-14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T1B" position="float"><label>Table 1B</label><caption><p>Prevailing climatic conditions for the experimental site during crop growing seasons for the years 2014&#x02013;2015.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Months</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rainfall (mm)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monthly mean maximum temperature (&#x000b0;C)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monthly mean minimum temperature (&#x000b0;C)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monthly average temperature (&#x000b0;C)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative humidity (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">November-14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">December-14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">January-15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feburary-15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">March-15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">April-15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Treatments and Crop Husbandry</title><p>The experiment included three different wheat cultivars, C<sub>1</sub> = Faisalabad-2008, C<sub>2</sub> = Punjab-2011, and C<sub>3</sub> = Millet-2011, and five zinc application protocols: T<sub>1</sub> = control, T<sub>2</sub> = seed priming, T<sub>3</sub> = soil application, T<sub>4</sub> = foliar application, and T<sub>5</sub> = soil + foliar application. The source of zinc was &#x0201c;Naya Zinc,&#x0201d; which is 98% pure containing 21% zinc as ZnSO<sub>4</sub>&#x022c5;7H<sub>2</sub>O. For T<sub>1</sub>, no zinc was applied, while in T<sub>2</sub>, seeds were soaked in 0.3% ZnSO<sub>4</sub> solution; for T<sub>3</sub>, ZnSO<sub>4</sub>&#x022c5;7H<sub>2</sub>O was applied at the rate of 50 kg ZnSO<sub>4</sub> per ha; for T<sub>4</sub>, ZnSO<sub>4</sub>&#x022c5;7H<sub>2</sub>O was applied at the rate of 0.5% at two growth stages (booting and milking); and in T<sub>5</sub>, zinc was applied in both the soil and as a foliar feed. Furthermore, for T<sub>2</sub>, seeds were initially soaked in 0.3% ZnSO<sub>4</sub> solution and subsequently given three surface washings with distilled water, then dried close to the original moisture level with forced air, after which they were sealed in polythene bags and stored in a refrigerator at 7 &#x000b1; 1&#x000b0;C until use. In T<sub>3</sub>, ZnSO<sub>4</sub>&#x022c5;7H<sub>2</sub>O was applied to the soil surface and after that incorporated into soil prior to sowing. For T<sub>4</sub>, each application of an aqueous solution of ZnSO<sub>4</sub>&#x022c5;7H<sub>2</sub>O was sprayed in the late afternoon until most leaves were wet.</p><p>The seeds were sown on November, 19 in 2013&#x02013;2014 and November, 23 in 2014&#x02013;2015. In both growing seasons, wheat cultivars were planted in rows 22.5 cm apart using a hand drill and a seed rate of 125 kg ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Nitrogen, phosphorus, and potassium were applied at a rate of 100:50:50 (N:P:K) kg ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Nitrogen, phosphorus, and potash were applied in the form of urea (46% N), single super phosphate (14% P), and sulfate of potash (50% K), respectively. Nitrogen was applied in three splits, one-third as a basal dose and the remaining two-thirds in two equal splits at the tillering and booting stages. All the potash and phosphorus were applied as basal doses. During crop growth, field water conditions were managed by flood irrigation.</p></sec><sec><title>Soil Analysis</title><p>To determine the physicochemical properties of experimental soil, composite soil samples were taken from the top (0&#x02013;30 cm) soil layer of the experimental site prior to sowing. Collected samples were analyzed using the protocols described by <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Homer and Pratt (1961)</xref>. The soil was loamy containing sand (41.23%), silt (39.35%), and clay (19.42%) particles, having a bulk density of 1.36 g cm<sup>-3</sup>, pH 7.8, EC 1.03 dSm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, organic matter 0.81%, available nitrogen 0.031%, available phosphorus 22 ppm, available potassium 121 ppm, and available zinc 29 ppm.</p></sec><sec><title>Sampling and Measurements</title><p>At maturity, the crop was harvested and tied into bundles for determination of yield. The individual plots were threshed using a mini thresher. Grain weight for each treatment was recorded by digital balance in kilograms and later expressed in tons per hectare (t ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The harvested grain was stored for determination of grain zinc and phytic acid concentration.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample Preparation and Analysis</title><p>Samples of wheat grain were dried in a drying oven at 60&#x000b0;C for 48 h (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2006</xref>). Dried samples were ground in a mill (IKA Werke, MF 10 Basic, Staufen, Germany) fitted with a stainless steel chamber and blades. Subsequently, finely ground 1.0 g samples of wheat flour were placed in a conical flask and kept overnight after adding a di-acid (HNO<sub>3</sub>:HClO<sub>4</sub> ratio of 2:1) digestion mixture (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jones and Case, 1990</xref>). After 24 h, samples were digested on a hot plate at 150&#x000b0;C until all the material was digested. After digestion, the material was cooled and diluted to 50 ml by adding de-ionized water. Digesta was then filtered with Whatman filter paper No. 42 and stored in air tight plastic bottles. Zinc concentration in the digested samples was determined by atomic absorption spectrophotometer (PerkinElmer, 100 AAnalyst, Waltham, MA, USA). Phytic acid in the extract was measured by an indirect method that uses absorption of the pink color developed by un-reacted Fe (III) with 2,2&#x02032;-bi-pyridine (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Haug and Lantzsch, 1983</xref>) at 519 nm with a spectrophotometer (Shimadzu, UV-1201, Kyoto, Japan). All samples for zinc and phytic acid determinations were prepared and analyzed in duplicate.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental Design and Statistical Analysis</title><p>The experiment was laid out in a randomized complete block design in a factorial arrangement with three replications. Data were statistically analyzed using Statistix 8.1 (Analytical, Tallahassee, FL, USA), while the least significant difference (LSD) test at 5% probability was used to compare treatment means. Graphs for experimental and climatic data were prepared using Microsoft Excel 2007.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Zinc application methods significantly (<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05) affected economic yield, grain zinc, and grain phytic acid concentrations (see <bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>). Maximum improvement in grain yield, 24.27 and 24.06%, was recorded with T<sub>5</sub> in 2013&#x02013;2014 and 2014&#x02013;2015, respectively, and the minimum improvement in grain yield was recorded under T<sub>1</sub>. The overall trend of zinc application methods regarding grain yield was: T<sub>5</sub> &#x0003e; T<sub>3</sub> &#x0003e; T<sub>4</sub> &#x0003e; T<sub>2</sub> &#x0003e; T<sub>1</sub>. Similarly, zinc application via different methods markedly (<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05) influenced grain zinc and phytic acid concentrations. As for grain zinc concentration, a maximum increase of 50.08 and 46.59% was observed in T<sub>5</sub>, followed by 47.81 and 46.59% increase in T<sub>4</sub> during both years. T<sub>5</sub> appeared to be an excellent strategy to increase grain zinc concentration, whereas minimum increase was observed with T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>1</sub> (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>). Grain phytic acid concentration was also significantly (<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05) reduced by zinc application (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>). During 2013&#x02013;2014 and 2014&#x02013;2015, a reduction of 29.05 and 28.69% in grain phytic acid was recorded under T<sub>5</sub> followed by T<sub>4</sub> and T<sub>3</sub> (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>); minimum reduction in grain phytic acid content was recorded with T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>1</sub>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The effect of zinc application methods on grain yield, grain zinc, and grain phytic acid concentrations of wheat cultivars.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc application method</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Grain yield (t ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Grain zinc concentration (mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Grain phytic acid concentration (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#x02013;2014</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014&#x02013;2015</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#x02013;2014</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014&#x02013;2015</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#x02013;2014</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014&#x02013;2015</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No zinc</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59 e</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66 e</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1 e</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7 e</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.68a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.53a</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seed priming</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90 d</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.99 d</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.4 d</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5 d</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.37a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.18a</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.69 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.4 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.6 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.68b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.56b</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foliar</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.6 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.7 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.74c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.66c</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil + foliar</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.10 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.18 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.3 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.28d</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.19c</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD (<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.024</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.050</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.06</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.27</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.43</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.51</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cultivars</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faisalabad-2008</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.88 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.90a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.88a</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punjab-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.89 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.4 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.73b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.53b</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Millat-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.34 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.21c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.11c</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD (<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.031</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.039</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.59</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.78</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.33</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.39</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>LSD values were shown as bold in order to differentiate from data values.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Similarly, all wheat cultivars differed significantly for grain yield, grain zinc, and phytic acid concentrations (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>). Wheat cultivar Punjab-2011 had a higher grain yield and grain zinc concentration followed by Millet-2011 and Faisalabad-2008 for both study years. Minimum grain yield and grain zinc concentrations were recorded in Faisalabad-2008 (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>). However, for grain phytic acid, considerable variation was observed among the wheat cultivars. Punjab-2011 had the lowest grain phytic acid content, followed by Millet-2011. However, Faisalabad-2008 performed poorly and had a higher grain phytic acid content when compared to Punjab-2011 and Millet-2011 (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>).</p><p>Interactions between zinc application methods and wheat cultivars were found to be significant for grain zinc concentration but not for grain yield or grain phytic acid concentration (see <bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref></bold>). For the interactive effect of grain zinc concentration and wheat cultivars, Punjab-2011 registered the highest values for grain zinc concentration at T<sub>5</sub> in the first (71.8 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and second (70.6 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) year, respectively. However, Faisalabad-2008 registered the lowest value of grain zinc concentration under T<sub>1</sub> (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref></bold>). There was a significant positive correlation between grain yield and grain zinc during both years of study (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A,B</xref></bold>); an increase in grain zinc concentration substantially enhanced grain yield. Similarly, and interestingly, a strong negative correlation was found between grain zinc and grain phytic acid concentration (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C,D</xref></bold>); it was found that zinc enriched seeds had a lower phytic acid content than seeds with lower zinc content.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Interactive effect of zinc application methods and wheat cultivar on grain yield, grain zinc, and phytic acid concentrations.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc application method</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cultivars</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Grain yield (t ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Grain zinc concentration (mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Grain phytic acid concentration (mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#x02013;2014</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014&#x02013;2015</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#x02013;2014</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014&#x02013;2015</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#x02013;2014</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014&#x02013;2015</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No zinc</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faisalabad-2008</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0i</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.3i</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punjab-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9 fg</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0gh</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Millat-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5hi</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9 hi</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seed priming</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faisalabad-2008</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3gh</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3h</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punjab-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8d</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2 d</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Millat-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.2f</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9fg</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faisalabad-2008</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8 ef</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7 ef</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punjab-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.2 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.2c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Millat-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.3 de</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.0 de</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foliar</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faisalabad-2008</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punjab-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.4 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.1 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Millat-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.6 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.3 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil + foliar</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faisalabad-2008</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.9 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punjab-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.8 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.6 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Millat-2011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.2 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.7 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD (<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NS</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NS</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.57</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.93</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NS</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NS</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>LSD values were shown as bold in order to differentiate from data values.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p><bold>Relationships between grain zinc concentration and grain yield (A,B)</bold>, and grain zinc and phytic acid concentration <bold>(C,D)</bold> during the years 2013&#x02013;2014 and 2014&#x02013;2015. mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, milligram per kilogram; t ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, tons per hectare.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-08-00281-g001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Zinc is essential for all biological systems in humans, animals, and plants. Low zinc availability and zinc fixation resulted in greater reduction of grain yield and grain zinc content; further, it also enhanced grain phytic acid content (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>).</p><p>Zinc application improves yield and yield components through various mechanisms, for example, it improves chlorophyll content and triggers photosynthetic activity and auxin synthesis which lead to better growth and development of the crop, thus effectively amplifying yield and yield components (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Rakesh and Jitendra, 2014</xref>). Seed priming is a cheap source of zinc application, which can increase the yield of various crops (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Harris et al., 2008</xref>); however, in the present study, T<sub>2</sub> was unable to fulfill the zinc requirement of the wheat crop for optimum yield (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>). The slight improvement in grain yield with T<sub>2</sub> could be explained by the fact that zinc synchronizes stand establishment and also helps in increasing the range of temperature during germination, which ultimately enhances wheat grain yield (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Farooq et al., 2008</xref>). For the other application methods, T<sub>5</sub> markedly enhanced grain yield as compared to T<sub>3</sub> and T<sub>4</sub> (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>). These results agree with previous literature (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Torun et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Zorita et al., 2001</xref>) where it is reported that foliar feeding of zinc ensures the increased availability of zinc at anthesis and grain filling stages, while <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al. (2009)</xref> also states that soil application substantially improves the translocation of nutrients from soil, which leads to better stand establishment and grain yield. Variation in grain yield, grain zinc, and phytic acid concentration among wheat cultivars might be due to their genetic makeup and their response toward zinc uptake.</p><p>Wheat, inherently, has a lower grain zinc concentration, especially when grown on zinc-deficient soils. Wheat cultivars are mostly zinc deficient and unable to fulfill human zinc requirements. For a measurable impact on human health, agronomic biofortification should enhance grain zinc content from 35 to 45 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Pfeiffer and McClafferty, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>). In our study T<sub>5</sub>, T<sub>4</sub>, and T<sub>3</sub> significantly increased grain zinc content as compared to T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>1</sub>. The improvement in grain zinc concentration in T<sub>5</sub> could be due to the improved availability of nutrients and maintenance of a greater zinc pool within plant tissues during the later growth stages. However, T<sub>4</sub> was superior to T<sub>3</sub> for improving grain zinc concentration even though just a small amount of zinc was applied in T<sub>4</sub> compared to T<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Erdal et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak et al., 2010a</xref>). On the other hand, T<sub>3</sub> was less effective as compared with T<sub>5</sub> and T<sub>4</sub> because of poor mobility and rapid adsorption of zinc in soil (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Alloway, 2008</xref>). This explains why better results were obtained regarding grain zinc concentration from T<sub>5</sub> (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>). Soil application was less effective for several reasons. Mostly, wheat roots and applied zinc have different soil distribution profiles, which reduces the uptake of zinc by plant roots (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Holloway et al., 2010</xref>). In addition, top soil is mostly dry during the reproductive stages, meanwhile root activity is generally reduced due to lower allocation of photo-assimilates. Thus, zinc uptake from soil or zinc fertilizers is usually reduced during the reproductive stages, a factor that substantially decreases zinc accumulation in grains. Zinc accumulation in wheat grain largely depends on re-translocation of zinc from vegetative tissue during the reproductive stages (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak et al., 2010a</xref>). Foliar feeding of zinc maintains a high concentration of zinc in vegetative tissues during re-translocation periods and contributes significantly to zinc biofortification of wheat grain under field conditions.</p><p>Phytate is a major phosphorus storing compound in cereal grains and acts as a metal chelator in the human intestine; it therefore hinders the absorption of dietary zinc and other metals into the blood (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bohn et al., 2008</xref>). According to <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Rengel and Graham (1995b)</xref>, soil zinc deficiency enhances plant phosphorus uptake and reduces zinc availability. Zinc application decreased grain phytic acid concentrations (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>), and this may be attributed to the inhibitory effect of zinc on root uptake and the accumulation of phosphorus in plant shoots (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Erdal et al., 2002</xref>). In the present study, T<sub>5</sub> substantially reduced grain phytic acid concentration followed by T<sub>4</sub> (<bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold>). These results agree with previous findings of <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Mabesa et al. (2013)</xref>. On the other hand, foliar application of zinc is useful for increasing grain zinc concentration and decreasing phytic acid concentration, which ultimately increase zinc bioavailability in both whole wheat grain and in wheat flour (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cakmak et al., 2010a</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Kutman et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>In most previous cases, authors report an inverse relationship between grain yield and grain zinc concentration (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Garvin et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">McDonald et al., 2008</xref>). However, our results indicated that grain yield and grain zinc were positively correlated, resulting in a substantial yield increase (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A,B</xref></bold>). These results are not consistent with previous studies of <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Oury et al. (2006)</xref> and <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">McDonald et al. (2008)</xref> who reported an inverse relation between grain yield and grain zinc concentration. However, our findings support the results of <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Zou et al. (2012)</xref> in Pakistan, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Karim et al. (2012)</xref> in China, and <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Yilmaz et al. (1997)</xref> in Turkey, who reported a simultaneous increase in grain yield and grain zinc concentrations with applied zinc. Considering the ever-growing global demand for food and widespread occurrence of zinc malnutrition, increasing grain Zn concentration in high-yielding wheat cultivars is important (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Graham et al., 2007</xref>). In the current study, a negative correlation was also found between grain zinc and grain phytic acid content (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C,D</xref></bold>). The decreasing effect of applied zinc on phytic acid content could be explained by the fact that zinc inhibits root uptake and shoot accumulation of phosphorus. It is well-reported that zinc deficiency increases the potential of plants for phosphorus uptake; however, zinc supply to zinc-deficient plants decreases phosphorus uptake and accumulation (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Rengel and Graham, 1995a</xref>). Therefore, the substantial reduction in grain phytic acid content seen in <bold>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref></bold> can be attributed to zinc application reducing the uptake and accumulation of phosphorus.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Zinc application via different methods substantially improved grain yield; however, seed priming had a marginal influence on grain yield. A combined application of soil + foliar zinc gave a higher grain yield on zinc-deficient soil. Similarly, maximum grain zinc concentration and lowest values for grain phytic acid were recorded in the same treatment. Therefore, the soil + foliar application of zinc was a more successful agronomic practice for achieving optimum yields, as well as grain biofortification. This study has also reported that grain yield and grain zinc were positively correlated, while grain zinc and grain phytic acid content were significantly negatively correlated.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MC (1st author) and IK designed the experiment and wrote the manuscript. MH performed the experiment. MBC and AM analyzed the data. MC (6th author), MN, and MS contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. MK and SK revised statistical analysis and manuscript. All the authors read and approved the manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The reviewer HA declared a shared affiliation, though no other collaboration, with one of the authors MUC to the handling Editor, who ensured that the process nevertheless met the standards of a fair and objective review.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> University of the Punjab may pay funding for publishing this manuscript. They need acceptance letter for the application of funding.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We wish to thank Mr. Wajid Ishque, Senior Scientist at the Nuclear Institute for Agriculture and Biology, Faisalabad, Pakistan, for his generous input and institutional support during this research and preparation of the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alloway</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source><italic>Zinc in Soils and Crop Nutrition.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IZA Publications.</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alloway</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source><italic>Zinc in Soils and Crop Nutrition</italic></source>, <edition>2nd Edn.</edition>
<publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IZA and IFA</publisher-name>, <fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bohn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Phytate: impact on environment and human nutrition. A challenge for molecular breeding.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Zhejiang Univ. Sci. B</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1631/jzus.B0710640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18357620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouis</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Micronutrient fortification of plants through plant breeding: can it improve nutrition in man at low cost?</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Nutr. Soc.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>411</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/PNS2003262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14506888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouis</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>McClafferty</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meenakshi</surname><given-names>J. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Biofortification: a new tool to reduce micronutrient malnutrition.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Nutr. Bull.</italic></source>
<volume>32(1 Suppl.)</volume>, <fpage>S31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15648265110321S105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21717916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouis</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Biofortification&#x02013;a sustainable agricultural strategy for reducing micronutrient malnutrition in the global south.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>S20</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2009.09.0531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Role of zinc in protecting plant cells from reactive oxygen species.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>146</volume>
<fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>205</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1469-8137.2000.00630.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Enrichment of cereal grains with zinc: agronomic or genetic biofortification?</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>302</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-007-9466-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalayci</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torun</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010a</year>). <article-title>Biofortification and localization of zinc in wheat grain.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>9092</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9102</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf101197h</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23654236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>McClafferty</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010b</year>). <article-title>Biofortification of durum wheat with zinc and iron.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cereal Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/CCHEM-87-1-0010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erdal</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taban</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Phytic acid and phosphorus concentrations in seeds of wheat cultivars grown with and without zinc fertilization.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Plant Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>127</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/PLN-100108784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairweathertait</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulton</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Evidence of decreasing mineral density in wheat grain over the last 160 years.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Trace Elem. Med. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>324</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtemb.2008.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19013359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Basra</surname><given-names>S. M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Seed priming enhances the performance of late sown wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) by improving chilling tolerance.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agron. Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>194</volume>
<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-037X.2007.00287.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garvin</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Finley</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Historical shifts in the seed mineral micronutrient concentration of US hard red winter wheat germplasm.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sci. Food Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>86</volume>
<fpage>2213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2220</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.2601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>U. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>A. L. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Dietary strategies to improve the iron and zinc nutriture of young women following a vegetarian diet.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Foods Hum. Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1007966104442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9498689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz-Monasterio</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouis</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonierbale</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Nutritious subsistence food systems.</article-title>
<source><italic>Adv. Agron.</italic></source>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2113(04)92001-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hafeez</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanif</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Role of zinc in plant nutrition: a review.</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. J. Exp. Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>374</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>391</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9734/AJEA/2013/2746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miraj</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arif</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yunas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>&#x02018;On-farm&#x02019; seed priming with zinc in chickpea and wheat in Pakistan.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>306</volume>
<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-007-9465-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haslett</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rengel</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Zinc mobility in wheat: uptake and distribution of zinc applied to leaves or roots.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>386</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbo.2000.1349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haug</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lantzsch</surname><given-names>H.-J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Sensitive method for the rapid determination of phytate in cereals and cereal products.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sci. Food Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>1423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1426</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.2740341217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McBeath</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brace</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The use of a zinc efficient wheat cultivar as an adaptation to calcareous subsoil: a glasshouse study.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>336</volume>
<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-010-0435-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Homer</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>). <source><italic>Methods of Analysis for Soils, Plants and Waters.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Davis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California, Davis.</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Assessment of the risk of zinc deficiency in populations and options for its control.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Nutr. Bull.</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>S91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S204</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imtiaz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alloway</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Memon</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Zinc nutrition of wheat: II: interaction of zinc with other trace elements.</article-title>
<source><italic>Asian J. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>156</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>160</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/ajps.2003.156.160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>V. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Sampling, handling, and analysing plant tissue samples,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Testing and Plant Analysis</italic></source>, <role>ed.</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Westerman</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Madison, WI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Soil Science Society of America</publisher-name>), <fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Alleviation of drought stress in winter wheat by late foliar application of zinc, boron, and manganese.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Plant Nutr. Soil Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>175</volume>
<fpage>142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>151</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jpln.201100141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurmani</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurmani</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Residual, direct and cumulative effect of zinc application on wheat and rice yield under rice wheat system.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kutman</surname><given-names>U. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Improved nitrogen status enhances zinc and iron concentrations both in the whole grain and the endosperm fraction of wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Cereal Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>125</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcs.2010.10.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Genotypic and spike positional difference in grain phytase activity, phytate, inorganic phosphorus, iron, and zinc contents in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Cereal Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>212</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcs.2006.06.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mabesa</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Impa</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson-Beebout</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Contrasting grain-Zn response of biofortification rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) breeding lines to foliar Zn application.</article-title>
<source><italic>Field Crops Res.</italic></source>
<volume>149</volume>
<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Genc</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A simple method to evaluate genetic variation in Zn grain concentration by correcting for differences in grain yield.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>306</volume>
<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2013.05.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mousavi</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Zinc in crop production and interaction with phosphorus.</article-title>
<source><italic>Aust. J. Basic Appl. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>1503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1509</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moustakas</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akoumianaki</surname><given-names>A. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barouchas</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The effects of cadmium and zinc interactions on the concentration of cadmium and zinc in pot marigold (<italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>Aust. J. Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>282</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-008-9555-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oury</surname><given-names>F. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leenhardt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Remesy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanliaud</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duperrier</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balfourier</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Genetic variability and stability of grain magnesium, zinc and iron concentrations in bread wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Agron.</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eja.2006.04.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Zinc is critically required for pollen function and fertilisation in lentil.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Trace Elem. Med. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtemb.2005.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16785048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>McClafferty</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>HarvestPlus: breeding crops for better nutrition.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>S88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2007.09.0020IPBS</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Clinical, anti inflammatory and antioxidant role of zinc.</article-title>
<source><italic>Exp. Gerintol.</italic></source>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>377</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2007.10.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raboy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Effect of phosphorus and zinc nutrition on soybean seed phytic acid and zinc.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>1094</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1098</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.75.4.1094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16663741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rakesh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jitendra</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Effect of NPKS and Zn application on growth, yield, economics and quality of baby corn.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Agron. Soil Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>1193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1206</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03650340.2013.873122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rengel</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995a</year>). <article-title>Wheat genotypes differ in zinc efficiency when grown in the chelate-buffered nutrient solution. II. Nutrient uptake.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>176</volume>
<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>324</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00011796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rengel</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995b</year>). <article-title>Importance of seed Zn content for wheat growth on Zn-deficient soil.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>173</volume>
<fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>274</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00011464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rengel</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romheld</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marschner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Uptake of zinc and iron by wheat genocatypes differing in tolerance to zinc deficiency.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>142</volume>
<fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0176-1617(98)80260-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Zinc and immune infection: the biology of altered resistance to infection.</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karamonas</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>J. W. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Phosphorus-induced zinc deficiency in wheat on residual phosphorus plots.</article-title>
<source><italic>Agron. J.</italic></source>
<volume>78</volume>
<fpage>668</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>675</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj1986.00021962007800040023x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Global impacts of human mineral malnutrition.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>335</volume>
<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>154</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-009-0228-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tisdale</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaten</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source><italic>Zinc in Soil Fertility and Fertilizers</italic></source>, <edition>4th Edn.</edition>
<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan Publishing Company</publisher-name>, <fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>391</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torun</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;ltekin</surname><given-names>I. G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalayci</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Effects of zinc fertilization on grain yield and shoot concentrations of zinc, boron, and phosphorus of 25 wheat cultivars grown on a zinc-deficient and boron-toxic soil.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Plant Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>1817</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1829</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/PLN-100107314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Breeding for micronutrients in staple food crops from a human nutrition perspective.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erh064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekiz</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gultekin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karanlik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagci</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Effect of different zinc application methods on grain yield and zinc concentration in wheat grown on zinc-deficient calcareous soils in Central Anatolia.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Plant Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>471</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01904169709365267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezaul</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010a</year>). <article-title>Iron and zinc concentrations in grain and flour of winter wheat as affected by foliar application.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>12268</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12274</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf103039k</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21073194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010b</year>). <article-title>Mineral element concentrations in grains of Chinese wheat cultivars.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>174</volume>
<fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>313</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-009-0082-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Biofortification and phytoremediation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>380</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2009.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19473871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zorita</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canigia</surname><given-names>M. V. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosso</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Applications of foliar fertilizers containing glycinebetaine improve wheat yields.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agron. Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>186</volume>
<fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>215</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1439-037X.2001.00469.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savasli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arisoy</surname><given-names>R. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz-Monasterio</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Biofortification of wheat with zinc through zinc fertilization in seven countries.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>361</volume>
<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>130</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-012-1369-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>