<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5802724</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">19016</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-19016-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chitosan nanoparticles having higher degree of acetylation induce resistance against pearl millet downy mildew through nitric oxide generation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Siddaiah</surname><given-names>Chandra Nayaka</given-names></name><address><email>moonnayak@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prasanth</surname><given-names>Keelara Veerappa Harish</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Satyanarayana</surname><given-names>Niranjan Raj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mudili</surname><given-names>Venkataramana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1565-5918</contrib-id><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Vijai Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalagatur</surname><given-names>Naveen Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Satyavati</surname><given-names>Tara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Xiao-Feng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Jie-Yin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mocan</surname><given-names>Andrei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9911-4125</contrib-id><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Bhim Pratap</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>Rakesh Kumar</given-names></name><address><email>r.k.srivastava@cgiar.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10">10</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0805 7368</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413039.c</institution-id><institution>Department of Studies in Biotechnology, </institution><institution>University of Mysore, </institution></institution-wrap>Manasagangotri, Mysore, 570006 Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418099.d</institution-id><institution>Department of Biochemistry, Central Food Technological Research Institute, </institution><institution>Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Mysore, 570 020 Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.445109.d</institution-id><institution>Department of Studies in Microbiology, </institution><institution>Karnataka State Open University, </institution></institution-wrap>Mukthagangotri, Mysore, 570006 Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8735 2850</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411677.2</institution-id><institution>Microbiology Division, DRDO-BU-Centre for Life sciences, </institution><institution>Bharathiar University Campus, </institution></institution-wrap>Coimbatore, 641046 Tamil Nadu India </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000110107715</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6988.f</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemistry and Biotechnology, School of Science, </institution><institution>Tallinn University of Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Tallinn, Estonia </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0643 7375</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418105.9</institution-id><institution>All India Coordinated Research Project on Pearl Millet, </institution><institution>Indian Council of Agricultural Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Mandor, Jodhpur, 342 304 Rajasthan India </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0526 1937</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410727.7</institution-id><institution>Institute of Food Science and Technology, </institution><institution>Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 100193 China </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0571 5814</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411040.0</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmaceutical Botany, Faculty of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>University of Medicine and Pharmacy &#x0201c;Iuliu Ha&#x0021b;ieganu&#x0201d;, </institution></institution-wrap>Ghe. Marinescu 23, 400337 Cluj-Napoca, Romania </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label>9</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9217 3865</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411813.e</institution-id><institution>Molecular Microbiology and Systematics Laboratory, Department of Biotechnology, </institution><institution>Mizoram University, </institution></institution-wrap>Mizoram, India </aff><aff id="Aff10"><label>10</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9323 1772</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419337.b</institution-id><institution>International Crops Research Institute for the Semi-Arid Tropics (ICRISAT), </institution></institution-wrap>Patancheru, 502324 Telangana India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>6</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>2485</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Downy mildew of pearl millet caused by the biotrophic oomycete <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> is the most devastating disease which impairs pearl millet production causing huge yield and monetary losses. Chitosan nanoparticles (CNP) were synthesized from low molecular weight chitosan having higher degree of acetylation was evaluated for their efficacy against downy mildew disease of pearl millet caused by <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic>. Laboratory studies showed that CNP seed treatment significantly enhanced pearl millet seed germination percentage and seedling vigor compared to the control. Seed treatment with CNP induced systemic and durable resistance and showed significant downy mildew protection under greenhouse conditions in comparison to the untreated control. Seed treatment with CNP showed changes in gene expression profiles wherein expression of genes of phenylalanine ammonia lyase, peroxidase, polyphenoloxidase, catalase and superoxide dismutase were highly upregulated. CNP treatment resulted in earlier and higher expression of the pathogenesis related proteins PR1 and PR5. Downy mildew protective effect offered by CNP was found to be modulated by nitric oxide and treatment with CNP along with NO inhibitors cPTIO completely abolished the gene expression of defense enzymes and PR proteins. Further, comparative analysis of CNP with Chitosan revealed that the very small dosage of CNP performed at par with recommended dose of Chitosan for downy mildew management.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Pearl millet is a drought tolerant, coarse cereal grown on infertile soils under water-limited conditions serving as a staple food for millions of poor people of semi-arid tropical regions of Africa and Asia. India has 10 million ha under pearl millet cultivation and the grain is the major source of human diet and the stover forms the basis of livestock ration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Nutritional aspects of pearl millet are unique when compared to other cereal crops. Feeding trials have shown that millet is nutritionally superior to maize and rice. Among the diseases of pearl millet, downy mildew caused by the biotrophic oomycete Sclerospora graminicola is the most devastating disease responsible for wide-spread yield and economic losses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> is highly variable and has the ability to quickly adapt to the newly released hybrids and consequently breaks down the host resistance thereby leading to regular withdrawal of the downy mildew-resistant hybrids. Chemical treatment is not feasible for a poor crop like pearl millet and the currently used chemicals are known to cause harmful effects on both human and environmental health. Consequently, exploring more safe and eco-friendly options like stimulating the innate immunity or inducing resistance have become potential alternatives for management of pearl millet downy mildew.</p><p id="Par3">The derivative of chitin, Chitosan, is a &#x003b2;-1,4-linked glucosamine which has been shown to have resistance stimulating ability against several plant pathogens. Specifically, chitosan pre-treatment primes the host plant defense responses by inducing earlier and higher phytoalexin synthesis, lignification, callose deposition, activities of reactive oxygen species, enhanced defense enzymes and PR proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Plant protective efficiency of chitosan against a wide range of phytopathogens has been well established in several crops<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Conversion of chitosan to nanochitosan presents many characteristics like biocompatibility, biodegradability and reduced toxicity which are best suited for effective delivery of the elicitor. In comparison to chitosan, nanochitosan has altered physiochemical properties like size, surface area, cationic nature which consequently alters the biological activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Ability of nanochitosan in eliciting resistance against various plant diseases has been demonstrated in many host-pathogen interactions. Cu-chitosan nanoparticles effectively controlled tomato early blight and <italic>Fusarium</italic> wilt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Chitosan nanoparticles effectively suppressed of rice and finger millet blast fungus <italic>Pyricularia grisea</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The aim of the present study was to comparatively evaluate chitosan and chitosan nanoparticles (CNP) synthesized specially from water soluble patent granted low molecular weight chitosan having higher degree of acetylation, for their defense stimulating efficiency against pearl millet downy mildew disease and to understand some of the biochemical and molecular events underlying the induced resistance process.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Preparation of chitosan nanoparticles</title><p id="Par6">To obtain viscosity free and readily water soluble low molecular weight, LMWC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> with higher degree of acetylation (Even though, native chitosan used to prepare LMWC was having ~20% acetylation, LMWC thus prepared showed ~70% acetylation, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) was adopted to prepare nanoparticles for this study. Further, the nanoparticles were well characterized and reported elsewhere previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Low molecular weight (LMWC) used for nanoparticles preparation (<bold>a</bold>) HPLC-SEC profile showing single peak having MW ~20&#x02009;kDa and (<bold>b</bold>) 13C-NMR spectrum for LMWC having ~70% acetylation. 13C-NMR (&#x003b4;, ppm) C1: 101.03, 97.08; C2: 55.68; C3: 69.72 (69&#x02013;71); C4: 78.94, 78.30, 76.05; C5: 74.2; C6: 59.84; C=O: 174.44; CH<sub>3</sub>: 21.93.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e523"/></fig></p><p id="Par7">Effect of CNP on seed germination and seedling vigor of pearl millet under laboratory conditions.</p><p id="Par8">The effect of CNP on pearl millet seed germination and seedling vigor was assessed by preparing different concentrations of CNP and compared with untreated control and chitosan. Seed treatment with 250&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> concentration of CNP offered the best results in terms of seed growth parameters. 250&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> concentration of CNP resulted in 97% pearl millet seed germination and 1937 seedling vigor which were significantly higher than the chitosan treatment and the untreated control. Chitosan treatment recorded 89% seed germination and 1917 seedling vigor. The untreated control showed 82% germination and 1866 seedling vigor (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Efficiency of CNP to elicit resistance against downy mildew under greenhouse</title><p id="Par9">Since 250&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg (&#x02212;1) concentration of CNP was found to be the optimum connotation for seed treatment it was further tested for downy mildew disease reaction under greenhouse conditions, along with chitosan, apron and untreated control as checks. CNP recorded 18.1% downy mildew disease incidence which was lowest among the tested treatments. Chitosan treatment showed 19.6% downy mildew incidence. Apron and untreated control showed 8.3 and 97.5% downy mildew disease incidence respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of seed treatment with CNP on downy mildew disease incidence of pearl millet under greenhouse conditons. Pearl millet seeds of 7042&#x02009;S (highly downy mildew susceptible variety) were treated with different concentration of CNP and were sown in earthen pots and the emerging seedlings were inoculated with <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> zoospores at 4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup>/ml concentration. After 30 days of sowing downy mildew incidence was recorded. Greenhouse experiments were carried out in four replicates and repeated twice. Bars indicate the standard error; means with different superscripts are significantly different as indicated by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e559"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Demonstration of the nature of resistance induction by CNP</title><p id="Par10">CNP treatment was further tested to the nature of protection offered under greenhouse conditions. The nature of resistance elicitation was demonstrated following the spatial and temporal separation method. The results showed that the resistance elicited by CNP treatment to pearl millet seeds is systemic. Initially, when the time gap between seed treatment and pathogen inoculation was 1&#x02009;day, CNP treatment resulted in 63% downy mildew protection. The protection percentage was raised to 73% on the second day which consistently maintained throughout the experimental period thus indicating that a minimum 2 days were required for the total resistance build up. The trend was similar in the second set of experiments where the inducer treatment was given as root dip inoculation. Initially, at 1-day gap, the protection offered was 64%. This shot up to 75% on the second-day gap. This protection percentage was sustained throughout the experimental period (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Demonstrations of systemic nature of resistance induction by CNP by spatiotemporal separation of the inducer and pathogen inoculation. Emerging pearl millet seedlings raised from 7042&#x02009;S seeds treated with CNP were challenge-inoculated with the zoospore suspension of <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> by adding 4&#x02013;5 drops (0.5&#x02009;ml) to the leaf whorl of each plant at intervals of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 days between the seedling emergence and pathogen inoculation in different sets of plants. After 30 days of sowing downy mildew incidence was recorded. The experiments were carried out in four replicates and repeated twice. Bars indicate the standard error; means with different superscripts are significantly different as indicated by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e579"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Biochemical studies</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Enzyme assays</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Phenylalanine ammonia-lyase assay</title><p id="Par11">Constitutive PAL activity was observed in all categories of seedlings with or without pathogen inoculation. At all tested time points, PAL activity was significantly higher in pathogen-inoculated seedlings compared to the uninoculated seedlings. In all the tested seedlings PAL activity peaked at 6 hpi as against the control seedlings in which PAL activity peaked at 9 hpi. At 6 hpi, among the treated seedlings maximum PAL activity was recorded by CNP treated seedlings which showed 1.08, 2.12 and 2.73 folds higher than Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO and untreated control seedlings respectively. Further, PAL activity in inoculated CNP treated seedlings was 2.24 folds more than the uninoculated seedlings (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Pattern of accumulation of Phenylalanine ammonia lyase in two-day old pearl millet seedlings with (inoculated) or without (uninoculated) <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> inoculation. Chitosan-Seedlings treated with Chitosan, CNP-Seedlings treated with the chitosan nanoparticles, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO &#x02013; seedlings treated with CNP followed by cPTIO treatment, Control: Seedlings of downy mildew susceptible cultivar. Phenylalanine ammonia lyase was determined as activity was determined as the amount of t-cinnamic acid formed from L-Phenylalanine per mg of protein per min measured spectrophotometrically at a wavelength of 290&#x02009;nm. Data of enzyme activity are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three different experiments. The values were the means of three replicates of three different experiments. Bars indicate the standard error as indicated by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e605"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Peroxidase assay</title><p id="Par12">Constitutive POX activity was observed in all categories of seedlings with or without pathogen inoculation. At all tested time points, POX activity was significantly higher in pathogen-inoculated seedlings compared to the uninoculated seedlings. In all the tested seedlings POX activity gradually increased from 3&#x02009;h peaked at 9 with or without pathogen inoculation. At 9 hpi, among the treated seedlings maximum POX activity was recorded by CNP treated seedlings which showed 1.03, 2.51 and 3.29 folds higher than Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO and untreated control seedlings respectively. Further, POX activity in inoculated CNP treated seedlings was 2.12 folds more than the uninoculated seedlings (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Pattern of accumulation of Peroxidase in two-day old pearl millet seedlings with (inoculated) or without (uninoculated) <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> inoculation. Chitosan-Seedlings treated with Chitosan, CNP-Seedlings treated with the chitosan nanoparticles, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO &#x02013; seedlings treated with CNP followed by cPTIO treatment, Control: Seedlings of downy mildew susceptible cultivar. Peroxidase activity determined as the increase in absorbance recorded 470&#x02009;nm. POX activity is expressed in terms of the change in A470 min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> protein. Data of enzyme activity are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three different experiments. The values were the means of three replicates of three different experiments. Bars indicate the standard error as indicated by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e631"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Polyphenol oxidase assay</title><p id="Par13">Constitutive PPO activity was observed in all categories of seedlings with or without pathogen inoculation. At all tested time points, PPO activity was significantly higher in pathogen-inoculated seedlings compared to the uninoculated seedlings. In all the tested seedlings PPO activity gradually increased from 3&#x02009;h peaked at 24 with or without pathogen inoculation. At 24 hpi, among the treated seedlings maximum PPO activity was recorded by CNP treated seedlings which showed 1.10, 2.48 and 3.33 folds higher than Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO and untreated control seedlings respectively. Further, PPO activity in inoculated CNP treated seedlings was 2.33 folds more than the uninoculated seedlings (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Pattern of accumulation of Polyphenol oxidase in two-day old pearl millet seedlings with (inoculated) or without (uninoculated) <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> inoculation. Chitosan-Seedlings treated with Chitosan, CNP-Seedlings treated with the chitosan nanoparticles, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO &#x02013; seedlings treated with CNP followed by cPTIO treatment, Control: Seedlings of downy mildew susceptible cultivar. Polyphenol oxidase determined as increase in absorbance at 420&#x02009;nm was recorded for 1&#x02009;min. The results are expressed as the change in A per min per mg protein Data of enzyme activity are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three different experiments. The values were the means of three replicates of three different experiments. Bars indicate the standard error as indicated by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e651"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Superoxide dismutase assay</title><p id="Par14">Constitutive SOD activity was observed in all categories of seedlings with or without pathogen inoculation. At all tested time points, SOD activity was significantly higher in pathogen-inoculated seedlings compared to the uninoculated seedlings. In all the tested seedlings SOD activity peaked at 6 hpi as against the control seedlings in which SOD activity peaked at 9 hpi. At 6 hpi, among the treated seedlings maximum SOD activity was recorded by CNP treated seedlings which showed 1.10, 1.96 and 3.09 folds higher than Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO and untreated control seedlings respectively. Further, SOD activity in inoculated CNP treated seedlings was 2.32 folds more than the uninoculated seedlings (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Pattern of accumulation of Superoxide dismutase in two-day old pearl millet seedlings with (inoculated) or without (uninoculated) <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> inoculation. Chitosan-Seedlings treated with Chitosan, CNP-Seedlings treated with the chitosan nanoparticles, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO &#x02013; seedlings treated with CNP followed by cPTIO treatment, Control: Seedlings of downy mildew susceptible cultivar. Superoxide dismutase was determined as change in absorbance at 560&#x02009;nm was recorded for 1&#x02009;min. Data of enzyme activity are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three different experiments. The values were the means of three replicates of three different experiments. Bars indicate the standard error as indicated by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e671"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Catalase assay</title><p id="Par15">Constitutive CAT activity was observed in all categories of seedlings with or without pathogen inoculation. At all tested time points, CAT activity was significantly higher in pathogen-inoculated seedlings compared to the uninoculated seedlings. In all the tested seedlings CAT activity peaked at 6 hpi as against the control seedlings in which CAT activity peaked at 9 hpi. At 6 hpi, among the treated seedlings maximum CAT activity was recorded by CNP treated seedlings which showed 1.03, 1.76 and 2.59 folds higher than Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO and untreated control seedlings respectively. Further, CAT activity in inoculated CNP treated seedlings was 2.04 folds more than the uninoculated seedlings (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).<fig id="Fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Pattern of accumulation of Catalase in two-day old pearl millet seedlings with (inoculated) or without (uninoculated) <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> inoculation. Chitosan-Seedlings treated with Chitosan, CNP-Seedlings treated with the chitosan nanoparticles, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO &#x02013; seedlings treated with CNP followed by cPTIO treatment, Control: Seedlings of downy mildew susceptible cultivar. Catalase was determined as change in absorbance at 240&#x02009;nm was recorded for 1&#x02009;min. Data of enzyme activity are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three different experiments. The values were the means of three replicates of three different experiments. Bars indicate the standard error as indicated by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e691"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Gene expression studies</title><p id="Par16">Quantitative real-time PCR analysis (qPCR) for defense enzymes, and pathogenesis-related proteins.</p><p id="Par17">Real-time PCR analysis was carried out to investigate the effect of different treatments on mRNA expression of defense-related genes in comparison untreated control with or without pathogen inoculation. The CNP treated pearl millet seedlings, with or without pathogen inoculation, showed rapid and significantly enhanced expression of PAL, POX, PPO, SOD, CAT, PR1, and PR5 genes in comparison with the untreated control seedlings. Constitutive levels of gene expression were observed for all the tested genes in all categories of seedlings, which gradually increased after pathogen inoculation.</p><p id="Par18">After inoculation with the downy mildew pathogen PAL expression gradually increased and peaked at 6 hpi in treated seedlings, whereas in control seedlings PAL activity peaked at 9 hpi. At 6 hpi, among the treatments, maximum PAL expression was recorded in CNP treated seedlings which was 1.01, 1.78, and 3.45 folds higher than the Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO treated and the untreated control respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9a</xref>).<fig id="Fig9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>qRT-PCR determined relative expression of genes of various defense enzymes in two-day-old pearl millet seedlings with (I) or without (U) <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> inoculation harvested 0, 3, 6, 9, 12, 24, 48, and 72&#x02009;h. Chitosan-Seedlings treated with Chitosan, CNP-Seedlings treated with the chitosan nanoparticles, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO &#x02013; seedlings treated with CNP followed by cPTIO treatment, Control: Seedlings of downy mildew susceptible cultivar. (<bold>a</bold>) Phenylalanine ammonia lyase (<bold>b</bold>) Peroxidase (<bold>c</bold>) Polyphenol oxidase (<bold>d</bold>) Superoxide dismutase and (<bold>e</bold>) Catalase. Expression levels were measured by qPCR and normalized to the constitutive PP2A gene. Values are means of a single experiment carried out in triplicate. The bars indicate&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE and the data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey&#x02019;s test and p-value *&#x0003c; or =0.05 was significant compared with control and **&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 significant with treated control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig9_HTML" id="d29e731"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">POX gene expression gradually increased from 3&#x02009;h onwards and maximum POX transcript level was recorded at 9 hai which decreased thereafter. At 9 hpi POX expression in CNP treated seedlings was 1.07, 2.03, and 2.79 folds higher than that of Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO treated and untreated control seedlings respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9b</xref>).</p><p id="Par20">PPO gene expression gradually increased following pathogen inoculation and the expression peaked at 24 hpi. In CNP treated seedlings maximum PPO expression was recorded at 24 hpi which was 1.12, 1.65, and 4.76 folds higher than that of Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO treated and untreated control seedlings respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9c</xref>).</p><p id="Par21">SOD expression gradually increased following pathogen inoculation and maximum expression was recorded at 6 hpi in treated seedlings, whereas in control seedlings maximum expression was observed at 9 hpi. SOD expression in CNP treated seedlings at 6 hpi was 1.10, 1.81, and 3.47 folds higher than that of Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO treated and untreated control seedlings respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9d</xref>).</p><p id="Par22">CAT gene expression gradually increased after pathogen inoculation and the transcript accumulation peaked at 6 hpi in treated seedlings, whereas in control seedlings maximum expression was observed at 9 hpi. CAT gene expression at 6 hpi in CNP treated seedlings was 1.11, 2.58, and 3.65 folds higher that of Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO treated and untreated control seedlings respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9e</xref>).</p><p id="Par23">PR-1 gene expression gradually increased after pathogen inoculation and the expression level peaked at 48 hpi. CNP treated seedlings at 48 hpi recorded 1.04, 1.99, and 2.96 folds higher PR-1 expression than that of Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO treated and untreated control seedlings respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10a</xref>).<fig id="Fig10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>qRT-PCR determined relative expression of genes of (<bold>a</bold>) PR-1 and (<bold>b</bold>) PR-5 in two-day-old pearl millet seedlings with (I) or without (U) <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> inoculation harvested 0, 3, 6, 9, 12, 24, 48, and 72&#x02009;h. Chitosan-Seedlings treated with Chitosan, CNP-Seedlings treated with the chitosan nanoparticles, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO &#x02013; seedlings treated with CNP followed by cPTIO treatment, Control: Seedlings of downy mildew susceptible cultivar. Expression levels were measured by qPCR and normalized to the constitutive PP2A gene. Values are means of a single experiment carried out in triplicate. The bars indicate&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE and the data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey&#x02019;s test and p-value *&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;or&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05 was significant compared with control and **&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 significant with treated control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Fig10_HTML" id="d29e774"/></fig></p><p id="Par24">PR-5 gene expression gradually increased following pathogen inoculation and maximum expression was recorded at 24 hpi. CNP treated seedlings at 24 hpi recorded 1.08, 2.31, and 2.68 folds higher PR-5 expression than that of Chitosan treated, CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO treated and untreated control seedlings respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10b</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par25">A wide array of biotic and abiotic substances is known to act as elicitors of plant defense responses imparting increased resistance against a range of plant pathogens, and this phenomenon of elicitor stimulated plant defenses is broadly termed as induced resistance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Inducing resistance is fast gaining worldwide importance and acceptance as an eco-friendly and safe approach of plant disease management. Adoption of this plant disease control mechanism aims at reducing the risks of chemical application which are otherwise harmful to human and environmental health. With this background the present study aimed at evaluation of nanochitosan particles for their resistance eliciting efficiency against pearl millet downy mildew disease and decipher some of the important biochemical and molecular events involved in the process.</p><p id="Par26">The results of the present study clearly showed that nanochitosan particles are potent elicitors of systemic resistance against pearl millet downy mildew disease. The level of disease resistance induced correlated with the enhanced enzyme activities and gene expression of defense enzymes like phenylalanine ammonia lyase, peroxidase and polyphenoloxidase. Enzymes play an important role in lowering the ROS levels and helping avoid oxidative stress. Superoxide dismutase and catalase activities and gene expression were also significantly enhanced over the control. Important markers of induced resistance like PR-1 and PR-5 were substantially overexpressed in nanochitosan particles treated pearl millet plants. The involvement of NO in nanochitosan mediated induced resistance was also demonstrated in this study.</p><p id="Par27">Of the different concentration of chitosan nanoparticles evaluated in this study, it was found that 250&#x02009;mg/kg seed concentration treatment for 6&#x02009;hours produced the maximum seed germination and seedling vigor which was significantly higher in comparison to the chitosan treatment and untreated control. Therefore, this concentration and time of treatment was used for all further studies. Chitosan is known to quickly penetrate the seed coats and teguments and positively influences the cellular metabolism at the seed development stages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> resulting in enhancing the seed growth parameters like the seed germination, seedling vigor, shoot and root length and also increased biomass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Similar results have been reported in maize, rice, wheat and millet crops wherein chitosan treatment stimulated the seed germination and seedling vigor significantly over the control<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Chitosan treatment increased seed germination, plant growth and yield in soybean<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Chitosan nanoparticles to rice seeds resulted in enhanced seed growth parameters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par28">Chitosan nanoparticles when treated to pearl millet seeds and evaluated against downy mildew disease under greenhouse conditons provided significant downy mildew control over the untreated control. The level of protection offered by nanochitosan was on par with the Chitosan treatment though the amount of nanochitosan used was very little though there are several reports of chitosan induced resistance against plant diseases, use of nanochitosan particles in plant disease management are very few. Systemic resistance was elicited in grapevine against <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> and <italic>Plasmopara viticola</italic> by Chitosan and 60 and 70% infection was reduced respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Resistance against <italic>Verticillium</italic> wilt of potato caused by <italic>Verticillium dahliae</italic> was elicited by chitosan resulting in effective control of the disease under greenhouse conditons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Tea leaves treated with chitosan nanoparticles significantly enhanced disease resistance through induction of systemic resistance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Early blight and Fusarium wilt of tomato were significantly reduced due to Cu-chitosan nanoparticles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Blast disease of rice and finger millet were effectively suppressed by Chitosan nanoparticles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par29">It is well demonstrated that the concentration of chitosan and the treatment time are very important for the achieving increased plant defense stimulation, and particularly treatment of chitosan prior to pathogen infection has been proven to be highly effective than applying chitosan after pathogen infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Further, duration of treatment varies depending upon the type of elicitor and the host-pathogen system. Varied time requirements by chitosan treatments for development of optimum defense stimulation ability was recorded in earlier studies in different plant-pathogen systems wherein tobacco-TMV interactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> required one-day time interval and rape seed <italic>Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</italic> interactions required three-day interval<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. In this study, chitosan nanoparticles at 250&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> concentration were prior-treated to pearl millet seeds for 6&#x02009;h followed by pathogen inoculation, and it was shown this treatment required a time of 2 days between treatment and pathogen inoculation for complete development of resistance which was sustained thereafter. It is important to note here that, in our previous studies we have demonstrated that chitosan seed treatment to pearl millet seeds induced systemic and durable resistance against downy mildew disease and there was a time gap of three days between chitosan treatment and downy mildew pathogen inoculation for maximum buildup of resistance. The reduced time requirement by nanochitosan to develop optimum resistance against <italic>S. graminicola</italic> might be attributed to the nano-nature of the chitosan particles which might have moved through the tissues rather rapidly and stimulated the necessary defense mechanisms.</p><p id="Par30">Subsequent to elicitor recognition, defense signaling and transducing pathways get activated which leads to elevated production of a cascade of defense reactions like production of active oxygen species, synthesis of phytoalexins, cell wall strengthening, synthesis of defense enzymes, and the accumulation of pathogenesis-related (PR) proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Mechanism of Chitosan induced resistance is well studied in various host-pathogen systems and it is established that chitosan treatment is known to contain the invading pathogens by forming chemical and mechanical barriers and also by enhancing the synthesis of phytoalexins, defense enzymes and PR-proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par31">In the present study it was shown that the activities of various defense enzymes like phenylalanine ammonia lyase, peroxidase, polyphenol oxidase, superoxide dismutase and catalase were significantly enhanced in chitosan nanoparticles treated pearl millet in comparison to the control seedlings. It was also observed that the level of enzyme activities in chitosan nanoparticles treated seedlings was on par with the chitosan treatment. Further, the activities of defense enzymes were increased significantly to a higher level after the inoculation of the downy mildew pathogen. Our results are in line with previous reports which have showed increased defense enzyme activities during chitosan induced resistance in different crops. Chitosan treatment effectively controlled pitch canker caused by <italic>Fusarium circinatum</italic> in <italic>Pinus patula</italic> by stimulating innate immunity and this was associated with increased transcript accumulation of genes of defense enzyme PAL<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Activities of PAL, POX and PPO were significantly enhanced over the controls in sunflower and wheat plants treated with chitosan resulting in activation of systemic resistance against downy mildew of sunflower and root and foot rot of wheat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par32">Activation of the pathogenesis related proteins PR-1, PR-2, and PR-5 and their pattern of expression are long been considered as importnat markers of systemic acquired resistance signaled via the SA pathway. The results of the present study clearly showed that, both PR-1 and PR-5 were activated early and in significantly higher amounts in the nanochitosan treated seedlings compared to the untreated seedlings; and the increase was more pronounced after the inoculation of the downy mildew pathogen. Further, the increase in expression of PR proteins were on par with the chitosan treatment. Similar observations of PR protein expression have been reported earlier in many crop systems. Increased PR proteins were activated during chitosan induced resistance against <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> and <italic>Plasmopara viticola</italic> in grapevines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Chitosan oligosaccharides induced resistance to tobacco mosaic virus (TMV) in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> by activating the SA singalling pathway and the resistance was associated with the increased expression of PR-1 gene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par33">Involvement of NO in plant disease resistance elicitation has been well established in several host-pathogen systems using various elicitors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Chitosan induced resistance against different plant pathogens has also suggested a possible role for NO in mediating the resistance elicitation. Chitosan oligosaccharide induced resistance against TMV in Arabidopsis was shown to mediated by increased NO generation acting as early signaling molecule upstream of SA-dependent defense signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The results of the present study demonstrated that induction of resistance by chitosan nanoparticles was through NO signaling and nanochitosan treated pearl millet treated seedlings showed significantly higher generation of NO compared to the untreated control and the seedlings treated with nanochitosan along with the NO scavenger cPTIO showed significantly lesser NO. This variation in NO generation in nanochitosan treated and CNP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO treated seedlings positively correlated with the level of activities of various defense enzymes and expression of PR proteins and also the degree of downy mildew resistance achieved under field conditions. Further, in our earlier studies, chitosan induced resistance against pearl millet downy mildew was also shown to be mediated by NO<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Chitosan induced NO generation in <italic>Brassica napus</italic> leaves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par34">In conclusion, this study clearly showed that pearl millet seed treatment with nanochitosan particles will significantly promote seed germination and seedling vigor and also effectively induced systemic and durable resistance against downy mildew disease under greenhouse conditions. The induced resistance correlated with the enhanced activities and gene expression of phenylalanine ammonia lyase, peroxidase, polyphenol oxidase, superoxide dismutase and catalase. PR-1 and PR-5 gene expression were significantly higher in the nanochitosan treated seedlings compared to the untreated seedlings. The resistance elicited by nanochitosan treated was found to be mediated by NO and scavenging of NO resulted in complete reduction of disease protection. Though the amount of nanochitosan used for seed treatments was very less, its effect on the resistance elicitation and the associated biochemical and molecular mechanism was on par with the chitosan treatment which is comparatively required in higher amounts. The findings of the present study can be extended to other crop-systems wherein nanochitosan can be used as a simple, inexpensive and effective strategy for plant disease management.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Host</title><p id="Par35">Seeds of pearl millet cultivars 7042&#x02009;S and AIMP 92901-P3, highly susceptible and highly resistant to <italic>S. graminicola</italic>, respectively, were obtained from the International Crop Research Institute for Semi-Arid Tropics (ICRISAT), Hyderabad, India, and the All India Co-ordinated Research Project on Pearl Millet (AICRP-PM), Mandor, Jodhpur, India.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Source of pathogen and inoculum preparation</title><p id="Par36"><italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic> was isolated from severely infected pearl millet cv. 7042&#x02009;S grown under field conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Leaves showing profuse sporulation of <italic>S. graminicola</italic> on the abaxial side were collected in the evening hours and thoroughly washed under running tap water to remove sporangia. The leaves were then blotted dry, cut into small pieces, and maintained in a moist chamber to promote sporulation. The following morning fresh sporangia were washed into distilled water. For use as inoculum, the resulting zoospore concentration was adjusted to 40,000 zoospores/ml using a hemocytometer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Preparation of chitosan nanoparticles (CNP)</title><p id="Par37">Preparation of low molecular weight chitosan (LMWC) was done according to the procedure described by Tharanathan and Harish Prashanth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Chitosan solution (~80% deacetylated chitosan,; viscosity 1% solution having viscosity average molecular weight ~110&#x02009;kDa), was taken in a three-necked flat-bottomed flask, are purged with nitrogen at 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with constant stirring at 200&#x02009;rpm. Subsequently, potassium persulfate (KPS, 0.8&#x02009;mM) was added to the solution and the reaction was completed in 2&#x02009;h. The reaction mixture was precipitated with isopropyl alcohol (3 volumes) to get LMWC with MW of ~20&#x02009;kDa, ~70 acetylated (characterized by HPLC and <sup>13</sup>CNMR respectively, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), re-dissolved in deionized water, dialyzed (dialysis membrane -150, Sigma Chemical Co., MO, USA) overnight and lyophilized (Virtis, Gardiner, NY, USA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The LMWC nanoparticles were prepared by the method of Calvo <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> with slight modification. Briefly LMWC (20&#x02009;mg) was taken in 4&#x02009;mL distilled water and 1&#x02009;mL of sodium tripolyphosphate (TPP, 0.1%) solution was added slowly dropwise and stirred at 500&#x02009;rpm at room temperature (27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C). Initially, the contents appear opalescent. To this, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of distilled water was added and stirred for 1&#x02009;min to obtain clear solution of LMWC nanoparticles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Seed treatment with chitosan nanoparticles (CNP)</title><p id="Par38">CNP was treated to pearl millet as seed treatment. For seed treatment, 7042&#x02009;S seeds were surface-sterilized with 0.02% mercuric chloride for 5&#x02009;min, and rinsed thoroughly in SDW. LMWC solutions were prepared by dissolving LMWC in distilled water and sodium tripolyphosphate solution so as to obtain final concentrations of 50, 100, 250, and 500&#x02009;mg LMWC per 100&#x02009;ml, and this solution was treated at the rate of 100&#x02009;ml&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> seed. Seeds were coated with 1% gum arabic as an adhesive and suspended in different concentration of nanochitosan solution and kept at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in a rotary shaker for 6&#x02009;h to ensure uniform coating. Seeds of pearl millet cultivars AIMP 92901-P3 treated with distilled water and 7042&#x02009;S treated with chitosan (@ 3&#x02009;g&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> seed) for 3&#x02009;h served as resistant and induced resistant checks respectively. 7042&#x02009;S seeds treated with distilled water for the same duration served as control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Effect of CNP on seed germination and seedling vigor of pearl millet under laboratory conditions</title><p id="Par39">CNP treated seeds and controls were seeded onto distilled water soaked brown germination paper. Fifty seeds of pearl millet were placed equidistantly on the paper. Another presoaked paper towel was placed on the first one so that the seeds were held in position. The towels were then rolled and wrapped with polythene to prevent drying. After incubation for 7 days, the towels were unrolled and the numbers of seeds germinated were counted. Seedling vigor was analyzed at the end of 7 days of incubation by the method of Abdul-Baki and Anderson<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The length of the root and shoot of individual seedlings was measured to determine the vigor index. The vigor index was calculated using the formula: Vigor index&#x02009;=&#x02009;(mean root length&#x02009;+&#x02009;mean shoot length)&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;(% germination). The experiment was carried out with four replicates of 100 seeds each and was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Efficiency of CNP to elicit resistance against downy mildew under greenhouse</title><p id="Par40">In the greenhouse, CNP was applied as seed treatment. 7042&#x02009;S seeds treated with SDW and chitosan served as the control and induced resistance check respectively. 7042&#x02009;S seeds treated with the systemic fungicide, metalaxyl (Apron 35&#x02009;SD at 6&#x02009;g&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> seeds) served as fungicide treated control.</p><p id="Par41">The treated seeds were sown in earthen pots filled with autoclaved soil, sand and manure at the ratio of 2:1:1. Each treatment consisted of 4 replications, ten pots per replication, and ten seedlings per pot. Treatments were arranged in a randomized complete block design. Three-day-old seedlings were challenge-inoculated by the whorl inoculation method with a zoospore suspension of <italic>S. graminicola</italic> at a concentration of 40,000 zoospores/ml prepared as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. In the whorl inoculation method, droplets of <italic>S. graminicola</italic> zoospores were dropped onto the leaf whorl formed by the emerging seedlings and allowed to flow down to the base. These pathogen-inoculated plants were maintained under greenhouse conditions (90&#x02013;95% RH, 20&#x02013;25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C temperature), and observed for disease development. The plants were rated for disease when they showed any one of the typical downy mildew symptoms such as sporulation on the abaxial leaf surface, chlorosis, stunted growth, or malformation of the earheads. Downy mildew disease incidence was recorded at 30 DAS (days after sowing) and final counts were made at 60 DAS. The experiment consisted of 4 replicates of 100 seedlings each and was repeated twice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Demonstration of the nature of resistance induction by CNP</title><p id="Par42">This included two sets of experiments. In the first set, 7042&#x02009;S seeds treated with <italic>CNP</italic> as described above were sown in earthen pots filled with autoclaved soil, sand and manure in the ratio 2:1:1. The emerging seedlings were challenge-inoculated with the zoospore suspension of <italic>S. graminicola</italic> by adding 4&#x02013;5 drops (0.5&#x02009;ml) to the leaf whorl of each plant at intervals of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 days between the seedling emergence and pathogen inoculation in different sets of plants. In the second set 7042&#x02009;S seeds were plated on moist blotters and were incubated at 25&#x02009;+&#x02009;2&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in an incubator. Thirty-six hours later the roots of the seedlings were treated with nanochitosan by soaking the roots in the fungal spore suspension of 10<sup>8</sup> cfu ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> concentration for three hours and later the seedlings were transplanted into earthen pots filled with soil, sand and manure in the ratio 2:1:1. The seedlings were then challenge-inoculated with zoospore suspension of <italic>S. graminicola</italic> (40,000 zoospores/ml) following the whorl inoculation procedure with a time gap of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 days in different sets of plants. 7042&#x02009;S seeds treated with distilled water was maintained as control for both the above sets of experiments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. The experiment consisted of 4 replicates of 100 seedlings each and was repeated twice. All the above sets of plants were maintained under greenhouse conditions, observed for the downy mildew disease reaction, and downy mildew disease data recorded as described earlier and the disease protection (%) was calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{Downy}}\,{\rm{mildew}}\,{\rm{disease}}\,{\rm{protection}}=\frac{{\rm{C}}-{\rm{T}}}{{\rm{C}}}\times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Downy</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mildew</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">disease</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">protection</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_19016_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where, C, is percent downy mildew disease incidence in control; T - percent downy mildew disease incidence in treated plants (Safeeulla)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Biochemical and gene expression studies</title><sec id="Sec25"><title>Plating of treated seeds</title><p id="Par43">7042&#x02009;S seed treatments with CNP and chitosan were same as described above for germination studies. In addition, AIMP 92901-P3 seeds treated with distilled water served as resistant check. After treatment, the seeds were plated on pre-soaked blotters in perspex plates and incubated for two days.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Challenge inoculation and harvesting of seedlings</title><p id="Par44">Two-day-old seedlings were root-dip inoculated with a zoospore suspension of 40,000 zoospores/ml, and incubated in dark at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. One set of the treated seedlings were inoculated with sterile distilled water which served as uninoculated control. A total of 1&#x02009;g seedlings for each experiment in three replicates were harvested at 0, 3, 6, 9, 12, 24, 48 and 72&#x02009;h after inoculation (hai) and immediately wrapped in aluminum foil and stored at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until further use for enzyme assays and RT-PCR analysis.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Biochemical studies</title><sec id="Sec28"><title>Enzyme assays</title><sec id="Sec29"><title>Enzyme extraction</title><p id="Par45">Harvested pearl millet seedlings (1&#x02009;g fresh weight) were ground to a fine paste in 1&#x02009;ml of buffer. The extract was centrifuged at 12,000&#x02009;g for 20&#x02009;min at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and the supernatant was transferred to a new tube and used as the enzyme extract.</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Protein estimation &#x02013; Lowry&#x02019;s method</title><p id="Par46">To calculate the specific activity of the enzymes, protein content in the crude extract was estimated by Lowry&#x02019;s method using BSA (Sigma) as a standard<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Phenylalanine ammonia-lyase assay</title><p id="Par47">PAL enzyme was extracted with 25&#x02009;mM Tris HCl buffer (pH 8.8). PAL activity was assayed according to the procedure of Beaudoin-Eagan and Thorpe<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. One hundred microlitres of extracts were mixed with 900&#x02009;ml of 50&#x02009;mM L-Phenylalanine and 100&#x02009;mM Tris HCl buffer solution (pH 8.01). The mixture was placed in a water bath at 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 120&#x02009;min. The reaction was stopped by adding 60&#x02009;ml of 5&#x02009;N HCl. Enzyme activity was determined as the amount of t-cinnamic acid formed from L-Phenylalanine per mg of protein per min measured spectrophotometrically at a wavelength of 290&#x02009;nm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Peroxidase assay</title><p id="Par48">POX enzyme was extracted in 10&#x02009;mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 6.9). POX activity was assayed according to the procedure of Hammerschmidt <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. The reaction mixture (3&#x02009;ml) consisted of 0.25% v/v guaiacol in 10&#x02009;mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 6.0) containing 100&#x02009;mM hydrogen peroxidase. The crude enzyme (10&#x02009;mL) was added to initiate the reaction, which was measured spectrophotometrically at 470&#x02009;nm. One unit of POX enzyme activity is defined as the increase in absorbance recorded 470&#x02009;nm. POX activity is expressed in terms of the change in A<sub>470</sub> min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> protein.</p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Polyphenol oxidase assay</title><p id="Par49">PPO enzyme was extracted in Tris&#x02013;HCL buffer (pH 7.0) containing 0.1&#x02009;M KCl, 1% (v/v) TritonX-100,1&#x02009;mM EDTA and 5% (w/v) Polyvinylpolypyrrolidone (PVPP). The reaction mixture (3&#x02009;ml) consisted of 10&#x02009;mM catechol in 100&#x02009;mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 6.5) was assayed as described by Arora and Bajaj<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. The standard reaction mixture consisted of 3&#x02009;ml of 10&#x02009;mM sublimated catechol in 100&#x02009;mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 6.5) and 10&#x02009;ml of enzyme extract. Increase in absorbance at 420&#x02009;nm was recorded for 1&#x02009;min. The results are expressed as the change in A per min per mg protein.</p></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Superoxide dismutase assay</title><p id="Par50">SOD enzyme was extracted in 50&#x02009;mm potassium phosphate buffer (pH 7&#x000b7;0). The activity of SOD was assayed by measuring its ability to inhibit the photochemical reduction of nitroblue tetrazolium (NBT) using the method of Beauchamp and Fridovich<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. The 3&#x02009;mL reaction mixture contained 50&#x02009;mm phosphate buffer, pH 7&#x000b7;8, 13&#x02009;mm methionine, 75&#x02009;&#x000b5;m NBT, 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;m riboflavin, 0&#x000b7;1&#x02009;mm EDTA, and 150&#x02009;&#x000b5;L enzyme extract. Riboflavin was added at the end and the tubes were shaken and placed 30&#x02009;cm below a light source consisting of two 15&#x02009;W fluorescent lamps. The reaction was started by switching on the light and was allowed to run for 15&#x02009;min. The reaction was stopped by switching off the light and the tubes were covered with a black cloth. The absorbance of the reaction mixture was read at 560&#x02009;nm. A nonirradiated reaction mixture did not develop colour and served as control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec35"><title>Catalase assay</title><p id="Par51">Catalase was extracted in sodium phosphate buffer (68&#x02009;mM, pH 6.8) and assayed following the method of Bailly <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. The reaction mixture contained 3&#x02009;ml of phosphate buffer along with 40&#x02009;ml crude enzyme extract. The reaction was initiated by adding 40&#x02009;ml of 10&#x02009;mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and which was measured spectrophotometrically at 240&#x02009;nm (Hitachi U 2000, Japan). Catalase activity was expressed in terms of the change in absorbance at 240&#x02009;nm in the linear phase of the slope (D240 min<sup>1</sup> mg<sup>1</sup> protein).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec36"><title>Gene expression studies</title><sec id="Sec37"><title>Quantitative real-time PCR analysis (qPCR) for defense enzymes, and pathogenesis-related proteins</title><sec id="Sec38"><title>RNA extraction</title><p id="Par52">A total of 100&#x02009;mg of frozen seedlings was ground to fine powder in a 2&#x02009;ml SealRite microcentrifuge tube using stainless steel beads and an automated shaker SO-10&#x02009;M (Fluid Management, Wheeling, IL, USA). Total RNA was extracted from seedlings harvested at different times noted above by using the RNeasy plant mini Kit (Qiagen) as per the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Eluted RNA was stored at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and then treated with DNase I (RNase free) (Fermentas). The concentration and purity of RNA was determined by means of spectrophotometer and its integrity by agarose gel electrophoresis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec39"><title>RT-PCR analysis</title><p id="Par53">The relative quantitation of PAL (NM001174615.1), POX (EU492461), PPO (AY881993.1), SOD (AY823553.1), CAT (JN627402.1), PR1 (HQ699781.1), and PR5 (EU725133.1) <italic>mRNAs</italic> in pearl millet seedlings was done by using gene-specific primers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>, designed with Primer Express version 3.0 software (Applied Biosystems) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). PP2A (protein phosphatase 2A) served as endogenous reference gene. Primer specificities were confirmed by agarose gel electrophoresis of the RT-PCR products. Each qPCR reaction (20&#x02009;&#x003bc;L) consisted of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;SYBR Green PCR master mix (SYBR Green mix, Applied Biosystems), 3 pmol of each primer and 20 ng each of cDNA and used StepOnePlus&#x02122; Real-Time PCR Systems (Applied Biosystems). qPCR steps were: denaturation at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min, 40 cycles of 15&#x02009;s at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 60&#x02009;s at 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. At the end of each reaction, a melting curve was created using a single cycle consisting of 15&#x02009;s at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and 60&#x02009;s at 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. This was followed by a slow temperature increase to 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at the rate of 0.3&#x02009;&#x000b0;C s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The quantification of target mRNAs used a comparative Ct method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primer sequences used for qRT-PCR amplification.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sl. No.</th><th>Target gene amplified</th><th>Forward primer sequence (5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032;)</th><th>Reverse primer sequence (5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032;)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Phenyl alanine ammonia lyase</td><td>ATGGAGTGCGAGAACGGCC</td><td>CTGCGCGATGCTGAGGCT</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Peroxidase</td><td>CCCCAGAAGCACATTTGTGA</td><td>CATGGCTGCGGGCGGAG</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Polyphenol oxidase</td><td>AGTCGAGGTTTGGCCACCAT</td><td>CCACCTGATGCGCTCGATG</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Superoxide dismutase</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Catalase</td><td>GGCAAGTCCCACTACGTCAA</td><td>AGCTGCTCGTTCTCGTTGAA</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>PR1</td><td>TGGACGTGCCGCTGCCG</td><td>GAACTGCGCCGCCACACG</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>PR-5</td><td>GCGTCCTCGGTCCTCCTG</td><td>CACACGCGGCCGGAGCTG</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Reference housekeeping gene</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Protein phosphatase 2&#x02009;A</td><td>TGAGAGCAGACAAATCACTCAA</td><td>AAGAGCTGTGAGAGGCAAATAA</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effect of pearl millet seed treatment with different concentrations of CNP on seed germination and seedling vigour under laboratory conditions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treatment</th><th>Concentration</th><th>Germination (%)</th><th>Seedling vigor</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4">CNP</td><td>50&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>(&#x02212;1)</sup></td><td>94&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1<sup>b</sup></td><td>1918&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.4<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td>100&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>(&#x02212;1)</sup></td><td>95&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3<sup>ab</sup></td><td>1922&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td>250&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>(&#x02212;1)</sup></td><td>97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8<sup>a</sup></td><td>1937&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.1<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>500&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>(&#x02212;1)</sup></td><td>93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3<sup>b</sup></td><td>1905&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.6<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Chitosan</td><td>3&#x02009;g&#x02009;kg<sup>(&#x02212;1)</sup></td><td>89&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9<sup>c</sup></td><td>1917&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.1<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Control</td><td>Untreated</td><td>82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8<sup>c</sup></td><td>1866&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.9<sup>cd</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Percentages of seed germination and vigour index are mean from three repeated experiments. Vigour index was calculated on percentage germination and mean root and shoot lengths of the seedlings. The values are mean from three experiments. Means designated with the same letter in column are not significantly different according to Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test at P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec40"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par54">Germination experiments were carried out with four replicates and were repeated thrice, greenhouse experiments were carried out in four replicates and were repeated twice, biochemical and molecular were carried out in three replicates and were repeated thrice. Data were analyzed separately for each experiment and were subjected to arcsine transformation and analysis of variance (JMP Software; SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC). Significance effects of treatments were determined by the magnitude of the F value (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05). Treatment means were separated by Tukey&#x02019;s honest significant difference test.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Vijai Kumar Gupta and Xiao-Feng Dai contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors are grateful to ICAR (Indian Council of Agricultural Research), New Delhi, India for providing the financial support under AICRP scheme.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Chandra Nayaka Siddaiah (C.N.S.), Chellapilla Tara satyavati (C.T.S.), Rakesh Kumar Srivastava (R.K.S.), Vijai Kumar Gupta (V.K.G.), Xiao-Feng Dai (X.F.D.), Jie-Yin Chen (J.Y.C.), Andrei Mocan (A.M.), Bhim Pratap Singh (B.P.S.), designed the experiments; C.N.S., Keelara Veerappa Harish Prasanth (V.H.P.), Niranjan Raj Satyanarayana (N.R.S.), Venkataramana Mudili (V.M.), Naveen Kumar Kalagatur (N.K.K.) performed the experiment; C.N.S.; C.T.S., N.R.S., V.H.P., V.K.G. prepared the manuscript, C.N.S., N.R.S., C.T.S., R.K.S., V.K.G., X.F.D., J.Y.C., A.M., B.P.S., reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par55">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yadav, H. Project coordinators review: All India coordinated project on pearl millet&#x02013;49th Annual Group Meeting. (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Prakash, H. S., Chandra Nayaka S. &#x00026; Kini K. R. Pearl millet downy mildew. Goyal, A. &#x00026; Manoharachary, C. (eds), <italic>Future Challenges in Crop Protection against fungal pathogens. Fungal Biology</italic> 109&#x02013;129. https://doi.org/10.1007/978&#x02013;1&#x02013;4939&#x02013;1188&#x02013;2&#x02013;4. Springer Science, USA (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amborab&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>B-E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonmort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleurat-Lessard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Roblin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early events induced by chitosan on plant cells</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>2317</fpage><lpage>2324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ern096</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18515832?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18515832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitosan antimicrobial and eliciting properties for pest control in agriculture: a review</article-title><source>Agron Sustain Dev.</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13593-014-0252-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Orzali, L., Corsi, B., Forni, C. &#x00026; Riccioni, L. Chitosan in Agriculture: A new challenge for managing plant disease, in biological activities and application of marine polysaccharides. Eds Publishers &#x02013; Intech. pp&#x02013;17&#x02013;36. 10.5772/66840 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitosan nanoparticles: a positive modulator of innate immune responses in plants</article-title><source>Sci Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>15195</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep15195</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26471771?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26471771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saharan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and <italic>in vitro</italic> antifungal efficacy of Cu&#x02013;chitosan nanoparticles against pathogenic fungi of tomato</article-title><source>Int J Biol Macromol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2015.01.027</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25617841?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25617841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manikandan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sathiyabama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation of chitosan nanoparticles and its effect on detached rice leaves infected with <italic>Pyricularia grisea</italic></article-title><source>Int J Biol Macromol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2015.11.083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26656594?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26656594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sathiyabama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Manikandan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitosan nanoparticle induced defense responses in finger millet plants against blast disease caused by <italic>Pyricularia grisea</italic> (Cke.) Sacc</article-title><source>Carbohydr Polym.</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><issue>154</issue><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2016.06.089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tharanathan, R. &#x00026; Harish Prashanth, K. A process for preparation of low molecular weight chitosan. <italic>Indian Patent</italic> 231588 (2001).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arunkumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Prashanth</surname><given-names>KVH</given-names></name><name><surname>Baskaran</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Promising interaction between nanoencapsulated lutein with low molecular weight chitosan: Characterization &#x00026; bioavailability of lutein <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2013</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2013.02.108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23768365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23768365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Loon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systemic resistance induced by rhizosphere bacteria</article-title><source>Annu Rev Phytopathol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.36.1.453</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15012509?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratsep</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Havis</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling crop diseases using induced resistance: challenges for the future</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2013</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1263</fpage><lpage>1280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23386685?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23386685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benhamou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicole</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of systemic resistance to <italic>Fusarium</italic> crown and root rot in tomato plants by seed treatment with chitosan</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>1994</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1432</fpage><lpage>1444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/Phyto-84-1432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liz&#x000e1;rraga&#x02013;Paul&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>E&#x02013;G</given-names></name><name><surname>Miranda&#x02013;Castro</surname><given-names>S&#x02013;P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno&#x02013;Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lara&#x02013;Sagah&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>A&#x02013;V</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres&#x02013;Pacheco</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maize seed coatings and seedling sprayings with chitosan and hydrogen peroxide: their influence on some phenological and biochemical behaviors</article-title><source>J Zhejiang Univ Sci B.</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1631/jzus.B1200270</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23365007?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23365007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhaskara Reddy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arul</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Angers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Couture</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitosan treatment of wheat seeds induces resistance to <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> and improves seed quality</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem.</source><year>1999</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1208</fpage><lpage>1216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf981225k</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10552439?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10552439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of chitosan coating on seed germination and salt&#x02013;tolerance of seedling in hybrid rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Acta Agron. Sinica.</source><year>2001</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>808</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y-j</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X-j</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seed priming with chitosan improves maize germination and seedling growth in relation to physiological changes under low temperature stress</article-title><source>J Zhejiang Univ Sci B.</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1631/jzus.B0820373</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19489108?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19489108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Elicitation of resistance and associated defense responses in <italic>Trichoderma hamatum</italic> induced protection against pearl millet downy mildew pathogen</article-title><source>Sci Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>43991</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep43991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28322224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zeng, D., Luo, X. &#x00026; Tu, R. Application of bioactive coatings based on chitosan for soybean seed protection. <italic>Int J Carbohydr Chem</italic>. ID 104565, 10.1155/2012/104565 (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jannoey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Channei</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesized nanochitosan induced rice chitinase isozyme expression; application in brown planthopper (BPH)control. NU</article-title><source>Int J Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitosan oligomers and copper sulfate induce grapevine defense reactions and resistance to gray mold and downy mildew</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2006</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>1188</fpage><lpage>1194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-96-1188</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18943955?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Amini, J. Induced resistance in potato plants against <italic>Verticilliu</italic>m wilt invoked by chitosan and Acibenzolar&#x02013;S&#x02013;methyl. <italic>Australian J Crop Sci</italic>. <bold>9</bold>, 570, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cropj.com/amini_9_6_2015_570_576.pdf">http://www.cropj.com/amini_9_6_2015_570_576.pdf</ext-link> (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manikandan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tailoring the surface&#x02013;oxygen defects of a tin dioxide support towards an enhanced electrocatalytic performance of platinum nanoparticles</article-title><source>Phys Chem Chem Phys.</source><year>2015</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>5932</fpage><lpage>5937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5CP04714E</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oligochitosan: a plant diseases vaccine&#x02013;a review</article-title><source>Carbohyd Polym.</source><year>2010</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2010.03.066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of antiviral resistance and stimulary effect by oligochitosan in tobacco</article-title><source>Pestic Biochem Phys.</source><year>2007</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pestbp.2006.06.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yin, H., Bai, X. &#x00026; Du, Y. The primary study of oligochitosan inducing resistance to <italic>Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</italic> on <italic>Brassica napus</italic>. <italic>J Biotechnol</italic>. <bold>136</bold>, S600&#x02013;S601, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cas-ir.dicp.ac.cn/handle/321008/113266">http://cas-ir.dicp.ac.cn/handle/321008/113266</ext-link> (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thakur, M. &#x00026; Sohal, B. S. Role of elicitors in inducing resistance in plants against pathogen infection: a review. ISRN Biochemistry 762412. (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iriti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Faoro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitosan as a MAMP, searching for a PRR</article-title><source>Plant Signal Behav.</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.4.1.7408</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19704712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19704712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Falc&#x000f3;n&#x02013;Rodr&#x000ed;guez, A. B., W&#x000e9;gria, G., Cabrera, J.-C. Exploiting plant innate immunity to protect crops against biotic stress: chitosaccharides as natural and suitable candidates for this purpose. In: Ali, R. Bandani (Eds) New perspectives in plant protection. InTech. Rikeka, <italic>Coratia</italic> 7:139&#x02013;166 (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitza</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Payn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Myburg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Naidoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitosan application improves resistance to <italic>Fusarium circinatum</italic> in <italic>Pinus patula</italic></article-title><source>S Afr J Bot.</source><year>2013</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2012.12.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nandeeshkumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitosan induced resistance to downy mildew in sunflower caused by <italic>Plasmopara halstedii</italic></article-title><source>Physiol Mol Plant Pathol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmpp.2008.09.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orzali</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Forni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Riccioni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of chitosan seed treatment as elicitor of resistance to <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> in wheat</article-title><source>Seed Sci Technol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15258/sst.2014.42.2.03</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitosan oligosaccharide induces resistance to Tobacco mosaic virus in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> via the salicylic acid&#x02013;mediated signalling pathway</article-title><source>Sci Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>26144</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep26144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27189192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27189192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindermayr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Durner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide and gene regulation in plants</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erj053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16396997?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16396997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide function and signalling in plant disease resistance</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erm244</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18039741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18039741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manjunatha</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide is involved in chitosan&#x02010;induced systemic resistance in pearl millet against downy mildew disease</article-title><source>Pest Manag Sci.</source><year>2009</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ps.1710</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19222022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19222022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitosan oligosaccharides&#x02013;triggered innate immunity contributes to oilseed rape resistance against <italic>Sclerotinia Sclerotiorum</italic></article-title><source>Int J Plant Sciences</source><year>2013</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/669721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Safeeulla</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biology and control of the downy mildews of pearl millet, sorghum and finger millet.</source><year>1976</year><publisher-loc>Mysore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wesley Press</publisher-name><fpage>304</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prashanth</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tharanathan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depolymerized products of chitosan as potent inhibitors of tumor&#x02013;induced angiogenesis</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2005</year><volume>1722</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2004.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15716061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Remunan&#x02010;Lopez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vila&#x02010;Jato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel hydrophilic chitosan&#x02010;polyethylene oxide nanoparticles as protein carriers</article-title><source>J Appl Poly Sci.</source><year>1997</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4628(19970103)63:1&#x0003c;125::AID-APP13&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdul&#x02013;Baki</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vigor determination in soybean seed by multiple criteria</article-title><source>Crop Sci.</source><year>1973</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1973.0011183X001300060013x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Singh, S. D., Gopinath, R. &#x00026; Pawar, M. N. Effects of environmental factors on asexual sporulation of <italic>Sclerospora graminicola</italic>. <italic>Indian Phytopathol</italic>. <bold>40</bold>, 186&#x02013;193. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://oar.icrisat.org/id/eprint/1434">http://oar.icrisat.org/id/eprint/1434</ext-link> (1987).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niranjan-Raj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Induction of growth promotion and resistance against downy mildew on pearl millet (<italic>Pennisetum glaucum</italic>) by rhizobacteria</article-title><source>Plant Dis.</source><year>2003</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS.2003.87.4.380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowry</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosebrough</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein measurement with the Folin phenol reagent</article-title><source>J Biol Chem.</source><year>1951</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>275</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaudoin&#x02013;Eagan</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyrosine and phenylalanine ammonia lyase activities during shoot initiation in tobacco callus cultures</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1985</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.78.3.438</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16664262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16664262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammerschmidt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuckles</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ku&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of enhanced peroxidase activity with induced systemic resistance of cucumber to <italic>Colletotrichum lagenariu</italic>m</article-title><source>Physiol. Plant Pathol.</source><year>1982</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0048-4059(82)90025-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bajaj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peroxidase and polyphenol oxidase associated with induced resistance of mung bean to <italic>Rhizoctonia solani</italic> Kuhn</article-title><source>J Phytopathol.</source><year>1985</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0434.1985.tb00627.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridovich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superoxide dismutase: improved assays and an assay applicable to acrylamide gels</article-title><source>Anal Biochem.</source><year>1971</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(71)90370-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 4943714?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4943714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Catalase activity and expression in developing sunflower seeds as related to drying</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2004</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erh050</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14739269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eddo, A. Characterization of the pathway leading to the synthesis of salicylic acid in plants resisting pathogen infection. Ph.D. Thesis submitted to the East Tennessee State University, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dc.etsu.edu/etd/1958">http://dc.etsu.edu/etd/1958</ext-link> (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real&#x02013;time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;C</sup> T method</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11846609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>