<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Insect Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1536-2442</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6195417</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jisesa/iey102</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">iey102</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Development of <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) Reared on Spring Cereals Versus Soybean</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>Ant&#x000f4;nio R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>antonio.panizzi@embrapa.br</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lucini</surname><given-names>Tiago</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Possebom</surname><given-names>Taynara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Entomologia, Embrapa Trigo, Passo Fundo, RS, Brasil</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Faculdade de Agronomia, Universidade de Passo Fundo, Passo Fundo, RS, Brasil</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding author, e-mail: <email>antonio.panizzi@embrapa.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-10-20"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>17</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Entomological Society of America.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="iey102.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The performance and preferences of the stink bug, <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> (F.), for spring cereals (wheat, rye, triticale, oat, and barley) were compared in the laboratory to their preferred host crop, soybean pods. Nymphs took significantly less time to reach adulthood on soybean pods compared to those fed seed heads of the five spring cereals tested. Wheat and rye yielded the longest developmental times, while nymphs fed triticale, oat, or barley developed faster, but still not as fast as those reared on soybean pods. On all foods &#x02265;78% of nymphs reached adulthood. Adult body weight was significantly greater on soybean pods than on any of the spring cereals, and adults increased in body weight on all food sources tested. Fecundity was significantly greater for females fed soybean pods than those reared on the cereals. Egg viability was &#x02265;66.9% except for bugs fed triticale (31.4%). In general, adult <italic>D. furcatus</italic> preferred soybean pods to seed heads of spring cereals, with wheat being preferred over the other spring cereals.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>stink bug</kwd><kwd>biology</kwd><kwd>feeding</kwd><kwd>preference</kwd><kwd>plant</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Council of Research and Technology of Brazil</named-content></funding-source><award-id>471517/2012-7</award-id><award-id>405157/2017-7</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Stink bugs (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) are crop pests worldwide (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">McPherson and McPherson 2000</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi et al. 2000</xref>). Recently, various pentatomids have colonized new agroecosystems and proliferated as invasive pests (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi 2015</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">McPherson 2018</xref>). Under no-till farming in the Neotropics, some stink bugs are able to reproduce year-round due to the availability of crop residues in fields (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi 1997</xref>), sometimes resulting in drastic increases in pentatomid populations.</p><p>The &#x02018;green-belly&#x02019; stink bug, <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> (F.), occurs in several South American countries, primarily in the so-called south-cone countries, including Argentina, Brazil, and Uruguay (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Grazia et al. 2015</xref>). In southern Brazil during the 1970s this species was only an occasional pest of soybean, <italic>Glycine max</italic> (L.) Merrill (Fabaceae) (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Galileo et al. 1977</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi et al. 1977</xref>). More recently, however, <italic>D. furcatus</italic> is occurring in greater abundance on cultivated and non-cultivated plants (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Chiaradia et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Smaniotto and Panizzi 2015</xref>).</p><p>Cultivated host plants of <italic>D. furcatus</italic> include wheat, <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L. (Poaceae), during winter and spring in the Neotropics (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Chocorosqui and Panizzi 2004</xref>); sunflower, <italic>Helianthus annuus</italic> L. (Asteraceae) (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Frota and Santos 2007</xref>); and maize, <italic>Zea mays</italic> (L.) (Poaceae) (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Roza-Gomes et al. 2011</xref>) during the summer. In addition, <italic>D. furcatus</italic> colonizes other spring cereals in southern Brazil such as oat, <italic>Avena sativa</italic> L. (Poaceae), during the vegetative (early plant development) and the reproductive periods (booting and seed-filling stage of the plant heads) (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al. 2013</xref>). On soybean, the main damage occurs during the pod-filling stage (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi et al. 1977</xref>); conversely, on wheat and maize, severe damage occurs primarily on seedlings (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi et al. 2016</xref>). However, on wheat, green-belly stink bugs damage the booting and/or milk-grain stages resulting in discolored seed heads, and undeveloped and malformed grain (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi et al. 2016</xref>); eventually, this damage may be of concern to wheat growers.</p><p>In the Near East, <italic>Aelia</italic> spp. stink bugs and <italic>Eurygaster</italic> spp. shield bugs (Scutelleridae) are perpetual pests of cereals wheat and barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L. (Poaceae)) (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Javahery 1996</xref>). Several pentatomids are wheat pest in the United States, mainly <italic>Oebalus pugnax</italic> (F.) and <italic>Euschistus</italic> spp. (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Buntin and Greene 2004</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al. 2016</xref>).</p><p>
<italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> damages spring cereals in south-cone countries, yet information is lacking regarding its impact, and on its plant preferences. This dearth of information led us to conduct the present research. The objectives of this research were: 1) to evaluate the effect of reproductive structures of different spring cereals on nymphal development, survivorship, and body weight; 2) to evaluate the effect of these food sources on adult reproduction, survivorship, and body weight; and 3) to evaluate preferences of the bugs for the reproductive structures of the cereals tested versus soybean pods.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2"><title>Laboratory Stink Bug Colony</title><p>Adults of <italic>D. furcatus</italic> were collected at the Embrapa wheat field station, located in Passo Fundo, Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil (28&#x000b0;15&#x02032;S, 52&#x000b0;24&#x02032;W). Adults, collected from the soil surface under crop residues in early spring 2017), were transported to the laboratory for rearing. Cages (25 &#x000d7; 20 &#x000d7; 20 cm) with filter paper in the bottoms were provided as needed with fresh green bean pods, <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L., raw shelled peanuts, <italic>Arachis hypogaea</italic> L. (Fabaceae), and mature seeds of soybean. Cages were kept in a walk-in chamber maintained at 25 &#x000b1; 1&#x000b0;C and 65 &#x000b1; 5% RH, with a photoperiod of 14:10 (L:D) h hourly cycle. Cotton balls were provided as an oviposition substrate, and egg masses were collected daily. Collected egg masses were placed inside plastic boxes (11 &#x000d7; 11 &#x000d7; 3.5 cm) with filter paper in the bottom. Nymphs were reared to adulthood as described above. Egg masses obtained from the laboratory-reared adults were used for the nymphal study. As additional nymphs reached the adult stage, they were used for the adult study.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Greenhouse Host Plants</title><p>Seeds of the different spring cereals and, for comparison, of soybean (pod-filling stage) since soybean is the main crop host exploited by <italic>D. furcatus</italic>), were seeded in pots (2L) maintained in a greenhouse. The following cultivars were used: wheat, &#x02018;BRS Reponte&#x02019;; oat, &#x02018;BRS Neblina&#x02019;; barley, &#x02018;BRS Quaranta&#x02019;; rye, <italic>Secale cereale</italic> L. &#x02018;BRS Serrano&#x02019;; triticale, <italic>Triticosecale semisecale</italic> (Mackey) K. Hammer &#x00026; Filat &#x02018;BRS Resoluto&#x02019;; and soybean, &#x02018;BRS 5601 RR&#x02019;. For the nymph and adult studies (described below), the spring cereals were used at the R11.1 stage (milk-grain stage) (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Large 1954</xref>); soybean plants were used at the R5 stage (pod-filling stage) (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Fehr et al. 1971</xref>). Plants were grown using a standard oxysoil prepared for greenhouse studies at Embrapa. For the spring cereal plants, potted plants were placed under a shaded area, and a blower was used to provide cooler air (ca. 22&#x000b0;C); soybean plants were cultivated in a sunnier and warmer compartment of the greenhouse (ca. 28&#x000b0;C).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Nymphal Development Study</title><sec id="s5"><title>Developmental Time and Survivorship</title><p>This study was conducted from December 2017 to January 2018. On the first day of the second instar (first instars aggregate and do not feed&#x02014;but see <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Esquivel and Medrano 2014</xref>), nymphs were placed in plastic boxes (11 &#x000d7; 11 &#x000d7; 3.5 cm) lined with filter paper. The following food sources were tested: seed heads at milk-grain stage for wheat, oat, barley, rye, and triticale; and pods at the grain filling stage for soybean. For each food source, 10 nymphs were placed inside a respective box and replicated five times, totaling 50 nymphs/food source. One seed head or one piece of soybean stem with three pods were placed in each box, and stems were wrapped with wet cotton to prevent desiccations. The food and filter paper in boxes were changed every 2 d. The test boxes were placed at random in an environmental chamber maintained at 25 &#x000b1; 1&#x000b0;C and 65 &#x000b1; 5% RH with a photoperiod of 14:10 (L:D) h hourly cycle. Daily observations were made on molting and mortality. Total nymphal developmental time and total percentage mortality (from second instar to adult) were calculated.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Fresh Body Weight at Adult Emergence</title><p>As nymphs reached the adult stage, each adult was placed in a small plastic cup and had its body weight recorded using an electronic balance (Mettler Toledo MS 3002S/A01, Barueri, SP, Brazil). Mean body weights were calculated for females and males obtained from each food source.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Adult Development Study</title><sec id="s8"><title>Adult Survivorship and Reproduction</title><p>This study was conducted from December 2017 to January 2018. Adults were obtained from nymphs reared in the laboratory using the foods described for maintaining the stink bug colonies. On the day of emergence, 60 pairs were separated and, each bug was weighed; this was done to allow calculation of subsequent body weight change (see below). The female/male pairs were formed at random, and each pair was placed in a plastic rearing box (11 &#x000d7; 11 &#x000d7; 3.5 cm) lined with filter paper. Adult performance was evaluated on the following foods (<italic>n</italic> = 10 pairs for each food): seed heads at milk-grain stage for wheat, oat, barley, rye and triticale, and pods at the filling stage for soybean. Each test box was provided with a single seed head of each cereal or a piece of soybean stem with three pods and maintained as described previously for nymphs. Daily observations were made to determine survivorship up to 40 d, and reproduction (% females that laid eggs, pre-oviposition time, egg masses and total eggs laid, and egg fertility). If a female or a male died before day 40, they were not replaced.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Fresh Body Weight</title><p>Adults (females and males) had their weight measured weekly for 4 wk. The percent fresh adult body weight changes of females and males over time were calculated weekly and compared during each week and cumulatively over the total time (4 wk). For analysis, fresh body weight change was calculated pooling the data for females and males.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Preferences for Plant Reproductive Structures</title><p>To test the preferences of <italic>D. furcatus</italic> for different reproductive structures of the spring cereals and soybean, dual comparisons (i.e., two different plant species) were conducted using cages (30 &#x000d7; 30 &#x000d7; 30 cm) with bottoms lined with filter paper. Four vials (10.0 &#x000d7; 4.5 &#x000d7; 2.0 cm diameter) (i.e., two for each food source were compared) containing water and short stems with seed heads (at the milk-grain stage) of the respective spring cereals or short branch of soybean with pods (at the pod-filling stage) were placed alternatively in the corners of each cage. Vials were topped with aluminum foil to avoid water evaporation. The following comparisons were tested: soybean pods versus seed heads of each one of the spring cereals studied (wheat, rye, barley, oat, and triticale); and seed heads of wheat versus those of the remaining cereals (rye, barley, oat, and triticale).</p><p>One adult <italic>D. furcatus</italic> (either female or male) was released in the center of each cage. After 24 h, twice daily observations were taken (9:00 a.m. and 4:00 p.m.) for 5 d, and the location of the bugs on one of the seed heads of cereals or pods of soybean were recorded. Each dual comparison was replicated four times (four cages). The number of observations per comparison totaled 40 (4 cages &#x000d7; 2 observations &#x000d7; 5 d). The percentage values of the preferences for the reproductive structures tested were calculated.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>The analyzed variables for nymphs (developmental time and fresh body weight at adult emergence) and adults (reproductive performance and body weight change) were previously submitted to the Bartlett test using the &#x02018;Bartlett.test&#x02019; function in the R software (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">R Development Core Team 2016</xref>) to determine the homogeneity of variances. Data were then transformed as necessary, to fulfill the normality distribution requirement prior to the analysis of variance (ANOVA), using an appropriate transformation for each case: &#x0221a;(x) for counting data, and arcsine &#x0221a;(x/100) to percentage data.</p><p>Data for female body weight at adult emergence were transformed, whereas males data were not, because they were normally distributed. Comparisons were done within each sex among all foods, therefore, any possible effect of female&#x02019;s transformed data on male&#x02019;s untransformed data was avoided, since no comparisons between sexes were performed.</p><p>In the sequence, dataset from each analyzed variable were fit in a one-way analysis of variance model using the &#x02018;aov&#x02019; function in R, in which the dependent variable was the analyzed variable and the independent variable was the food sources tested. When applicable, means separations were done using the Tukey&#x02019;s test, at <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, using the &#x02018;TukeyC&#x02019; package (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Faria et al. 2018</xref>). Data on the bugs preference for reproductive structures of plants were separated using the Pearson&#x02019;s chi-square test (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>) using the &#x02018;chisq.test&#x02019; function in the R software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Results</title><sec id="s13"><title>Nymphal Development</title><sec id="s14"><title>Developmental Time and Survivorship</title><p>Total nymphal developmental time (second instar to adult) was variable (21&#x02013;29 d) depending on the food source (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Nymphs took significantly less time to reach adulthood on soybean pods compared to those on the seed heads of the five spring cereals (<italic>F</italic> = 59.45; df = 5, 261; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Among them, seed heads of wheat and rye required the longest times for development, while nymphs fed triticale, oat, or barley developed faster, but still not as fast as those reared on soybean pods.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Developmental time of <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> nymphs feeding on seed heads of spring cereals and pods of soybean in laboratory conditions. Means (&#x000b1;SE) followed by the same letter are not significantly different using Tukey&#x02019;s test, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iey10201"/></fig><p>Despite the significant differences of developmental time between treatments, <italic>D. furcatus</italic> nymphs were able to reach adulthood on all foods tested. Survivorship of nymphs was variable, from the minimum of 78% on seed heads of oat to the maximum of 98% on soybean pods. On triticale and barley, nymphal survivorship was 94%, decreasing to 86 and 84% on seed heads of rye and wheat, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Fresh Body Weight at Adult Emergence</title><p>Body weight on the first day of adulthood was also variable according to the different foods tested. As for nymphs, females and males achieved significantly greater weight when fed on soybean pods than when fed seed heads of any of the spring cereals (females: <italic>F</italic> = 41.86; df = 5, 112; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; males: <italic>F</italic> = 50.52; df = 5, 143; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Among them, significantly less fresh body weight-gain occurred for females on seed heads of oat, barley, wheat, and rye; weight did not differ among these cereal sources, and these weights were lower than for the triticale treatment. For males, a similar situation was observed, with wheat and rye yielding the lower weight-gain compared to that for triticale and oat treatments, with the barley treatment being intermediate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Fresh body weight of females and males <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> at the first day of the adult life feeding on seed heads of spring cereals and pods of soybean in laboratory conditions. Means (&#x000b1;SE) followed by the same letter in each gender are not significantly different using Tukey&#x02019;s test, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05. Original data presented for females [for analysis, data were transformed to &#x0221a;(x)].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iey10202"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Adult Development</title><sec id="s17"><title>Adult Survivorship and Reproduction</title><p>At 40 d of adult life survivorship for both <italic>D. furcatus</italic> females and males remained &#x02265;85% on most food sources tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). On seed heads of rye survivorship for both sexes was the lowest (60%). On soybean pods percent survivorship was intermediate (70%). In general, survivorship values for females and males were similar, although survivorship for males tended to be lower, except on rye, for which the opposite was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Survivorship (%) of adult females and males <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 10) up to 40 d feeding on seed heads of spring cereals and pods of soybean in laboratory conditions. Seed heads of oat (A), barley (B), wheat (C), triticale (D), and rye (F); and pods of soybean (E).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iey10203"/></fig><p>The reproductive performance of <italic>D. furcatus</italic> was variable according to the food source utilized. Oviposition varied from 30% (on rye and triticale) to 80% (on oat) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Pre-oviposition time was significantly shorter (about half) on soybean pods, compared to that observed for seed heads of most spring cereals tested (<italic>F</italic> = 5.53; df = 5, 23; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). Fecundity, in terms of total egg masses deposited, was significantly greater (two to seven times) on soybean pods than on the seed heads of the spring cereals (<italic>F</italic> = 15.82; df = 5, 23; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001); the lowest number of egg masses laid were observed for the barley and on triticale treatments (&#x02264;3.4 masses). A similar situation was observed for the total number of eggs laid; females on soybean pods laid significantly more eggs (two to seven times more) compared to those fed on seed heads of cereals (<italic>F</italic> = 11.99; df = 5, 23; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Egg fertility was, in general, high (&#x02265;66.9%), except for those females fed on seed heads of triticale (ca. 30%) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Reproductive performance of adult female <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> feeding on seed heads of spring cereals and pods of soybean in laboratory conditions</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% females laying eggs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-oviposition time (d)<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egg masses <italic>(n</italic>)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of eggs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egg hatch (%)<sup><italic>b</italic></sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (10)<sup><italic>c</italic></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6 &#x000b1; 0.4b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8 &#x000b1; 1.8a (84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218.0 &#x000b1; 26.4a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.0 &#x000b1; 7.2a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.1 &#x000b1; 1.7a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 &#x000b1; 0.9b (63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.5 &#x000b1; 14.2b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.8 &#x000b1; 2.2a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4 &#x000b1; 1.8a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 &#x000b1; 1.2b (23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.8 &#x000b1; 16.6b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.9 &#x000b1; 2.9a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rye</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0 &#x000b1; 6.0ab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 &#x000b1; 2.3b (15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.0 &#x000b1; 32.7b</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.9 &#x000b1; 14.7ab</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barley</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6 &#x000b1; 2.1a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 &#x000b1; 0.9b (17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2 &#x000b1; 13.9b</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5 &#x000b1; 13.2ab</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triticale</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0 &#x000b1; 2.0a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 &#x000b1; 0.7b (7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0 &#x000b1; 9.0b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.4 &#x000b1; 23.6b</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0001"><p>Means (&#x000b1;SE) followed by the same letter in columns (except for % females laying eggs) are not significantly different using Tukey&#x02019;s test, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0002"><p>
<sup><italic>a</italic></sup>Original data presented [for analysis, data were transformed in &#x0221a;(x)].</p></fn><fn id="fn-0003"><p>
<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>Original data presented [for analysis, data were transformed in arcsine &#x0221a;(x/100)].</p></fn><fn id="fn-0004"><p>
<sup><italic>c</italic></sup>Value within brackets indicates the initial number of females per food source.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Fresh Body Weight</title><p>The change in fresh body weight during adult life was variable on the different food sources utilized. During the first week, in general, adults (females and males) significantly increased more weight on soybean pods compared to most of the cereal treatments (<italic>F</italic> = 12.52; df = 5, 113; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001); however, on seed heads of oat, adults significantly lost body weight. During the following 3 wk, body weight-gain was minimal on all foods, except on seed heads of oat, for which the body weight lost during the first week was recovered (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). At 4 wk, adults increased in body weight on all food sources tested, and did not significantly differ among treatments (<italic>F</italic> = 1.70; df = 5, 106; <italic>P</italic> = 0.14). However, weight-gain tended to be greater for bugs fed soybean pods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Fresh body weight change (%) of adult (female + male) <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> during the first 4 wk of adult life feeding on seed heads of spring cereals and pods of soybean in laboratory conditions</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First week<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second week<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third week<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fourth week<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.9 &#x000b1; 4.1aA (20)<sup><italic>b</italic></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 &#x000b1; 1.6aB (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 &#x000b1; 1.1aB (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 &#x000b1; 1.2aB (18)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rye</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 &#x000b1; 4.7bA (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.5 &#x000b1; 3.3aA (19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 &#x000b1; 2.7aA (17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 &#x000b1; 3.1aA (16)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barley</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 &#x000b1; 3.2abA (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 &#x000b1; 3.2aAB (19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 &#x000b1; 2.5aA (19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.9 &#x000b1; 2.5aB (19)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triticale</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 &#x000b1; 4.0bA (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 &#x000b1; 3.3aA (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 &#x000b1; 2.6aA (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 &#x000b1; 2.8aA (20)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 &#x000b1; 2.8bA (19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 &#x000b1; 3.3aA (19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 &#x000b1; 3.3aA (19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 &#x000b1; 2.9aA (19)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10.1 &#x000b1; 2.4cB (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9 &#x000b1; 3.4aA (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 &#x000b1; 3.7aA (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 &#x000b1; 2.8aA (20)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0005"><p>Means (&#x000b1;SE) followed by the same lowercase and uppercase letters in columns and rows, respectively, are not significantly different using Tukey&#x02019;s test, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0006"><p>
<sup><italic>a</italic></sup>Original data presented [for analysis, data were transformed to arcsine &#x0221a;(x/100)].</p></fn><fn id="fn-0007"><p>
<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>Value within brackets indicates the number of adults (female + male).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Fresh body weight change (%) of adult (female + male) <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> after 4 wk of adult life feeding on seed heads of spring cereals and pods of soybean in laboratory conditions. Means (&#x000b1;SE) followed by the same letter are not significantly different using Tukey&#x02019;s test, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iey10204"/></fig></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Preferences for Reproductive Structures</title><p>On the reproductive structures of plants, with dual preference tests conducted, <italic>D. furcatus</italic> adults preferred soybean pods compared to most seed heads of spring cereals 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IN01"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>&#x003c7;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>calc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>84</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>6</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
against triticale; 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IN02"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>&#x003c7;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>calc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>23.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
against wheat; 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IN03"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>&#x003c7;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>calc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>54.8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
against rye; 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IN04"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>&#x003c7;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>calc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>19.4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
against barley, all <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), except for oat seed heads 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IN05"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>&#x003c7;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>calc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.00</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>P</italic> = 0.161) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Preference ratios (%) of <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> on different combinations between pods of soybean and seed heads of spring cereals (A) and between seed heads of wheat and seed heads of other spring cereals (B). ns, nonsignificant different and ***significant different (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) using Pearson&#x02019;s chi-square test (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iey10205"/></fig><p>When the preference tests were run comparing the seed heads of wheat against the seed heads of the remaining spring cereals, the former was preferred compared to seed heads of triticale 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IN06"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>&#x003c7;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>calc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>13.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), or rye 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IN07"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>&#x003c7;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>calc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>54.8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). However, no significant differences were obtained when seed heads of wheat were compared to those of barley 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IN08"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>&#x003c7;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>calc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.00</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>P</italic> = 0.317) or oat 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IN09"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>&#x003c7;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>calc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.36</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>P</italic> = 0.548) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5B</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Discussion</title><p>We demonstrated that, in addition to soybean, the green-belly stink bug, <italic>D. furcatus</italic>, can develop and reproduce when fed seed heads of the common spring cereals grown in South America. Nevertheless, nymphs fed on soybean pods matured more quickly and were heavier than those reared on the spring cereals tested, which was to be expected since soybean is the principal crop food-plant for <italic>D. furcatus</italic> (see references in <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Smaniotto and Panizzi 2015</xref>). Because we used legumes (fresh green bean pods, raw shelled peanuts, and mature seeds of soybean) to rear the bugs one could argue that this might have preconditioned the bugs to perform better on soybean. However, in insects the argument of preimaginal (nymphal) food host-choice conditioning, known as Hopkins&#x02019; host-selection principle, is controversial (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Barron 2001</xref>). On the spring cereals, the delay in nymphal development and lower body weight at adult emergence points to differences in chemical (nutritional quality and or presence of allelochemicals) and/or physical attributes (e.g., variable size and anatomy of seed heads; see <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. 2010</xref>) of cereal versus legume host plants. However, nymphal survivorship on the cereals tested (&#x02265;78%) was surprisingly high compared to that for other pentatomid pests of legumes (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi 1997</xref>).</p><p>To date, there has been little research conducted on the feeding habits of <italic>D. furcatus</italic>; most existing data for <italic>Dichelops</italic> is for the similar congeneric species, <italic>D. melacanthus</italic> (Dallas). In general, nymph developmental time of the latter species on seeds/fruits of different plants fell within the range observed in the present study (21 to 29 d) (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Chocorosqui and Panizzi 2002</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Silva et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Bortolotto et al. 2016</xref>). Exceptions are on immature soybean pods plus mature seeds (shorter time &#x02013; ca. 18 d &#x02013; <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Chocorosqui and Panizzi 2003</xref>), on seed heads of wheat (longer time &#x02013; ca. 33 d &#x02013; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Chocorosqui and Panizzi 2008</xref>), and on seeds of tropical spiderwort, <italic>Commelina benghalensis</italic> L. (even longer &#x02013; ca. 37 d &#x02013; <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Silva et al. 2013</xref>).</p><p>Nymphal survivorship for <italic>D. furcatus</italic>, which varied from 78 to 98%, were generally higher that reported for <italic>D. melacanthus</italic> fed on various food sources, as follows: 23&#x02013;40% on seed heads of wheat (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Chocorosqui and Panizzi 2008</xref>); 56 and 70% on immature soybean pods plus mature seeds (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Chocorosqui and Panizzi 2002</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>, respectively); 55% on immature soybean pods (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi et al. 2007</xref>), and 73 and 68% on immature maize ears (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Bortolotto 2016</xref>, respectively).</p><p>These developmental and survivorship variations mentioned above for <italic>Dichelops</italic> nymphs may be due to the different food sources and/or rearing methods (e.g., nymphs reared singly or in groups). In our study, nymphs were raised in groups and, in part, this may explain the higher survivorship obtained as compared to other similar studies in which nymphs were raised singly. Phytophagous heteropterans reared in groups usually perform better than when reared singly in the laboratory (e.g., <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Ralph 1976</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Panizzi et al. 2005</xref>).</p><p>It is interesting to note that, except on soybean, nymphs of <italic>D. furcatus</italic> are seldom found in the field colonizing the spring cereals tested. Apparently, adults do not oviposit on them at the time cereal plants produce seed heads, and prefer to colonize other crops available in the area, such as canola, <italic>Brassica napus</italic> L. (Brassicaceae) (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Marsaro Jr. et al. 2017</xref>). Adults of <italic>D. furcatus</italic>, although polyphagous, may not recognize the spring cereals as suitable hosts.</p><p>The fact that the majority (&#x02265;60%) of <italic>D. furcatus</italic> survived past 40 d of adult life fed on the reproductive structures of spring cereals tested and on soybean, were able to lay eggs, and gain body weight demonstrates that these food sources are potentially important to their phenology. For example, adult survivorship of the congeneric <italic>D. melacanthus</italic> on seed heads of wheat, past 40 d, was ca. 50% for both females and males (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Chocorosqui and Panizzi 2008</xref>), lower than the values we obtained for <italic>D. furcatus</italic> on seed heads of wheat (100% for females and 70% for males).</p><p>Fecundity, which was variable among the food sources tested, was greater on soybean pods, as to be expected from the known phenology of <italic>D. furcatus</italic>. This is similar to the results obtained with <italic>D. melacanthus</italic> fed on soybean pod/ immature seeds where egg masses were laid almost five times more compared to females fed on seed heads of wheat (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Chocorosqui and Panizzi 2008</xref>). All spring cereals were considered less suitable and, although we could not find a clear explanation, these food sources may possess detrimental factors or poorer nutrition. In fact, they were less preferred (except oat) compared to soybean.</p><p>In summary, stink bugs seem to be expanding worldwide. They are colonizing crops such as soybean and maize (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Koch and Pahs 2014</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), and winter and spring wheat (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al. 2016</xref>) in areas as far north as Minnesota where they were seldom observed in the past. These associations may occur only sporadically and bugs may not reach pest status on these crops in such areas, but these associated plants may play an important role to their phenology. Therefore, our results conducted with <italic>D. furcatus</italic> in the Neotropics presents a similar situation to observations in northern temperate regions.</p><p>In conclusion, these laboratory studies coupled with field observations indicate that the spring cereals tested, i.e., wheat, oat, barley, rye, and triticale, during the reproductive period (presence of seed heads) provide a potential alternate food source for the green-belly stink bug, <italic>D. furcatus</italic>. Nymphs were able to complete development when feeding on them and adults reproduced and gained body weight in the laboratory. However, in the field, populations do not yet seem to have attained economically damaging levels. This fact led us to conclude that these spring cereals serve as alternate hosts mostly to sustain populations that will subsequently colonize summer crops, such as soybean, which is known as a preferred host plant and upon which <italic>D. furcatus</italic> could potentially reach pest status.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Jeffrey R. Aldrich, Jesus F. Esquivel, and an anonymous reviewer for critically reading the manuscript and improving its readability. We also thank M&#x000e1;rcio Nicolau for his statistical advice. This study was partially supported by a National Council of Research and Technology of Brazil grant 471517/2012-7 to A. R. P., and by a post-doctorate scholarship grant 405157/2017-7 to T. L. We also thank the Embrapa Unit at Passo Fundo, RS, for support. Approved by the Publication Committee of the Embrapa Trigo, Passo Fundo, RS, Brazil under number 21205.001548/2018-2088.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References Cited</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barron</surname><given-names>A. B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The life and death of Hopkins&#x02019; host-selection principle</article-title>. <source>J. Insect Beh</source>. <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>737</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortolotto</surname><given-names>O. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>A. Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bueno</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>G. V.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Queiroz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Biological aspects of <italic>Dichelops melacanthus</italic> at three temperatures, reared on immature 2B688Hx and 2B688 corn grains</article-title>. <source>Ci&#x000ea;nc. Rur</source>. <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buntin</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Abundance and species composition of stink bugs (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) in Georgia winter wheat</article-title>. <source>J. Entomol. Sci</source>. <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>290</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiaradia</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rebonatto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smaniotto</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davila</surname><given-names>M. R. F.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nesi</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Arthropods associated with soybean crop</article-title>. <source>Rev. Ci&#x000ea;nc. Agrovet</source>. <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chocorosqui</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Temperature influence on the nymphal biology of <italic>Dichelops melacanthus</italic> (Dallas, 1851) (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae)</article-title>. <source>Semina</source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chocorosqui</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Photoperiod influence on the biology and phenological characteristics of <italic>Dichelops melacanthus</italic> (Dallas, 1851) (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae)</article-title>. <source>Braz. J. Biol</source>. <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>655</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>664</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15029376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chocorosqui</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Impact of cultivation systems on <italic>Dichelops melacanthus</italic> (Dallas) (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) populations and damage and its chemical control on wheat</article-title>. <source>Neotrop. Entomol</source>. <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chocorosqui</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Nymph and adult biology of <italic>Dichelops melacanthus</italic> (Dallas) (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) feeding on cultivated and non-cultivated host plants</article-title>. <source>Neotrop. Entomol</source>. <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>360</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18813735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Esquivel</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Ingestion of a marked bacterial pathogen of cotton conclusively demonstrates feeding by first instar southern green stink bug (Hemiptera: Pentatomidae)</article-title>. <source>Environ. Entomol</source>. <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24342007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jelihovschi</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Allaman</surname><given-names>I. B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<comment>TukeyC: conventional Tukey test package: R package</comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://TukeyC/TukeyC">TukeyC/TukeyC</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caviness</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burmood</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1971</year>
<article-title>Stage of development descriptions for soybeans, <italic>Glycine max</italic> (L.)</article-title><source>Merrill. Crop Sci</source>. <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>929</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>931</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frota</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>R. S. S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Pentatomidae bugs associated with sunflower crops in the northwest of Rio Grande do Sul state and the action of <italic>Euschistus heros</italic> (Fabricius, 1794) (Hemiptera: Pentatomidae) on sunflower seeds</article-title>. <source>Biotemas</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galileo</surname><given-names>M. H. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gastal</surname><given-names>H. A. O.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Grazia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1977</year>
<article-title>Population survey of Pentatomidae (Hemiptera) on the soybean crop (<italic>Glycine max</italic> (L.) Merr.) in Gua&#x000ed;ba Co., Rio Grande do Sul</article-title>. <source>Rev. Bras. Biol</source>. <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grazia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwertner</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garbelotto</surname><given-names>T. de A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>J. A. M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Stink bugs (Pentatomidae)</article-title>, pp. <fpage>681</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>756</lpage>. <italic>In</italic><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="given-only"><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grazia</surname></name></person-group> (eds.), <source>True bugs (Heteroptera) of the neotropics</source>. <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javahery</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Sunn pest of wheat and barley in the I. R. of Iran: chemical and cultural methods of control</article-title>, pp. <fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <italic>In</italic><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="given-only"><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morse</surname></name></person-group> (eds.), <source>Sunn pests and their control in the near east</source>. <publisher-name>FAO Pub. No. 138</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pahs</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Species composition, abundance, and seasonal dynamics of stink bugs (Hemiptera: Pentatomidae) in Minnesota soybean fields</article-title>. <source>Environ. Entomol</source>. <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>883</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>888</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24937441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pahs</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Species composition and abundance of stink bugs (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) in Minnesota field corn</article-title>. <source>Environ. Entomol</source>. <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26313176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pahs</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Statewide and season-long surveys for Pentatomidae (Hemiptera: Heteroptera) of Minnesota wheat</article-title>. <source>Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am</source>. <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>396</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>404</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Large</surname><given-names>E. C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1954</year>
<article-title>Growth stages in cereals. Illustration of the Feekes scale</article-title>. <source>Plant Path</source>. <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>129</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong-Gang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Awn anatomy of common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) and its relatives</article-title>. <source>Caryologia</source><volume>63</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsaro</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>P. R. V. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grazia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Scarparo</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<source>Percevejos (Heteroptera) fit&#x000f3;fagos e predadores associados &#x000e0; cultura da canola no Norte do Estado do Rio Grande do Sul. Doc. Num. 167</source>. <publisher-name>Embrapa</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Passo Fundo, RS, Brazil</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>McPherson</surname></name>, <name name-style="given-only"><given-names>J. E</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.). <year>2018</year>
<source>Invasive stink bugs and related species (Pentatomoidea). Biology, higher systematics, semiochemistry, and management</source>. <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="given-only"><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McPherson</surname></name></person-group> (eds.). <year>2000</year>
<source>Stink bugs of economic importance in America North of Mexico</source>. <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Wild hosts of Pentatomids: ecological significance and role in their pest status on crops</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Entomol</source>. <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Growing problems with stink bugs (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) - species invasive to the U.S. and potential Neotropical invaders</article-title>. <source>Am. Entomol</source>. <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corr&#x000ea;a</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gazzoni</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Turnipseed</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1977</year>
<source>Insetos da soja no Brasil. Bol. Tec., n. 1</source>. <publisher-name>Embrapa</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Londrina, PR, Brazil</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Javahery</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Stink bugs (Pentatomidae)</article-title>, pp. <fpage>421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>474</lpage>. <italic>In</italic><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="given-only"><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname></name></person-group> (eds.), <source>Heteroptera of economic importance</source>. <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Biology and descriptions of nymphal and adult <italic>Jadera choprai</italic> (Hemiptera: Rhopalidae)</article-title>. <source>Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am</source>. <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>526</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duo</surname><given-names>L. J. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bortolato</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Nymph developmental time and survivorship, adult longevity, reproduction and body weight of <italic>Dichelops melacanthus</italic> (Dallas) feeding on natural and artificial diets</article-title>. <source>Rev. Bras. Biol</source>. <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>484</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>488</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agostinetto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucini</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>P. R. V. S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Effect of green-belly stink bug, <italic>Dichelops furcatus</italic> (F.) on wheat yield and development</article-title>. <source>Crop Prot</source>. <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>P. R. V. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salvadori</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marsaro</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>., and <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<source>Trigo: manejo integrado de pragas. Doc. Num. 113</source>. <publisher-name>Embrapa</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Passo Fundo, RS, Brazil</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>C. P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>Natural food requirements of the large milkweed bug, <italic>Oncopeltus fasciatus</italic> (Hemiptera: Lygaeidae), and their relation to gregariousness and host plant morphology</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>. <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28309260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Development Core Team</collab></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<source>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</source>. <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roza-Gomes</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salvadori</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>P. R. S. V.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Injuries of four species of stink bugs to corn seedlings</article-title>. <source>Cienc. Rural</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1119</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>J. J., M. U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Population dynamics of <italic>Dichelops melacanthus</italic> (Dallas) (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) on Host Plants</article-title>. <source>Neotrop. Entomol</source>. <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>145</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23949747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smaniotto</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Panizzi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Interactions of selected species of stink bugs (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) from leguminous crops with plants in the Neotropics</article-title>. <source>Florida Entomol</source>. <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>