<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6277769</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.02920</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Symbiosis Specificity of the Preceding Host Plant Can Dominate but Not Obliterate the Association Between Wheat and Its Arbuscular Mycorrhizal Fungal Partners</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>Catarina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/597688/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>M&#x000e1;rio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Br&#x000ed;gido</surname><given-names>Clarisse</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/594333/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/631499/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nobre</surname><given-names>T&#x000e2;nia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/307213/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Instituto de Ci&#x000ea;ncias Agr&#x000e1;rias e Ambientais Mediterr&#x000e2;nicas, Instituto de Investiga&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o e Forma&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Avan&#x000e7;ada, Universidade de &#x000c9;vora</institution>, <addr-line>&#x000c9;vora</addr-line>, <country>Portugal</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>School of Environmental Sciences, University of Guelph</institution>, <addr-line>Guelph, ON</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Pierre-Emmanuel Courty, Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique (INRA), France</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Marcela Claudia Pagano, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais, Brazil; Muthu Venkateshwaran, University of Wisconsin&#x02013;Platteville, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Catarina Campos, <email>mccampos@uevora.pt</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Microbe Interactions, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>2920</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Campos, Carvalho, Br&#x000ed;gido, Goss and Nobre.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Campos, Carvalho, Br&#x000ed;gido, Goss and Nobre</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The symbiosis established between arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) and roots of most land plants plays a key role in plant nutrient acquisition and alleviation of environmental stresses. Despite the ubiquity of the symbiosis, AMF and host species display significant specificity in their interactions. To clarify preferential associations between wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) and AMF, we characterized root AMF communities in the transition from two first host species, ryegrass (<italic>Lolium rigidum</italic>) and yellow-serradella (<italic>Ornithopus compressus</italic>), grown separately or together, to a second host (wheat), by sequencing the large subunit ribosomal DNA (LSU rDNA) gene. The response of AMF communities in wheat to prior soil disturbance &#x02013; and consequently of the mycelial network [intact extraradical mycelium (ERM) vs. disrupted mycelium] established with either of the first hosts &#x02013; was also investigated. Since the outcome of a specific host&#x02013;symbiont interaction depends on the molecular responses of the host plant upon microbial colonization, we studied the expression of six key symbiosis-related genes in wheat roots. AMF communities on <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and <italic>O. compressus</italic> roots were clearly distinct. Within an undisturbed ERM, wheat AMF communities were similar to that of previous host, and <italic>O. compressus</italic>-wheat-AMF interactions supported a greater growth of wheat than <italic>L. rigidum</italic>-wheat-AMF interactions. This effect declined when ERM was disrupted, but generated a greater activation of symbiotic genes in wheat, indicating that plant symbiotic program depends on some extent on the colonizing symbiont propagule type. When a mixture of <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and <italic>O. compressus</italic> was planted, the wheat colonization pattern resembled that of <italic>O. compressus</italic>, although this was not reflected in a greater growth. These results show a lasting effect of previous hosts in shaping wheat AMF communities through an efficient use of the established ERM, although not completely obliterating host&#x02013;symbiont specificity.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi symbiosis</kwd><kwd>extraradical mycelium</kwd><kwd>host&#x02013;symbiont specificity</kwd><kwd>host plant transition</kwd><kwd>soil disturbance</kwd><kwd>symbiosis-related genes</kwd><kwd><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o para a Ci&#x000ea;ncia e a Tecnologia<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001871</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="69"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>It is strongly held that the symbiosis with arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) was a major driver of colonization of land by plants and fundamentally altered environmental conditions on earth (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Humphreys et al., 2010</xref>). Amongst the plant microbiome, the interaction with AMF is one of the most important symbiotic associations. AMF communities can enhance plant diversity and productivity of natural ecosystems (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Van Der Heijden et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Klironomos et al., 2000</xref>) and affect multiple functions and processes, from nutrient uptake to drought and soil metal stress alleviation (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Brito et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2017</xref>). The symbionts are horizontally transmitted (through mycelial networks) and individual plants can simultaneously associate with multiple species of AMF that may differ in provision and delivery of benefits.</p><p>Despite their ubiquity and ability to colonize most plants, AMF can exhibit considerable selectivity in their association with different host species, and <italic>vice-versa</italic> (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Helgason and Fitter, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">&#x000d6;pik et al., 2009</xref>). Coexisting plant species can harbor distinct AMF communities (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">&#x000d6;pik et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Hazard et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Davison et al., 2015</xref>); this is not surprising since in common with their hosts, arbuscular mycorrhiza differ in life-history traits and some host&#x02013;symbiont combinations can be more beneficial than others (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bever, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Walder et al., 2012</xref>). Therefore, the functional attributes of both partners seem to relate to the strength or weakness of the host&#x02013;symbiont interaction. In addition to the specific host plant genotype, there is also a strong relation between composition and richness of AMF communities in a particular plant species and the structure of the neighboring plant communities (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Hausmann and Hawkes, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Kohout et al., 2015</xref>). The closeness of different plant species harboring distinct AMF communities can increase both species richness and induce shifts in the AMF root community composition of a particular host (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Meadow and Zabinski, 2012</xref>).</p><p>The delivery of AMF-induced benefits to crop plants is of particular interest for agricultural crop production and sustainability. However, it is clear that a well-established AMF extraradical mycelial (ERM) network is crucial for an adequate degree of benefit delivery (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Kabir, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Brito et al., 2012</xref>). <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Brito et al. (2014)</xref> reported that a greater growth of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) in a soil with excessive levels of manganese occurred when yellow-serradella (<italic>Ornithopus compressus</italic> L.) rather than ryegrass (<italic>Lolium rigidum</italic> Gaudin) was grown prior to wheat, provided that the soil was undisturbed and therefore an intact ERM was present when wheat was planted. More recently, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Br&#x000ed;gido et al. (2017)</xref> reported that wheat grown in undisturbed soil after <italic>O. compressus</italic> acquired an AMF community closely related to that of the previous host plant, and different to the one found when soil was disturbed or not cropped prior to planting wheat. These findings indicated that the host relation with the inoculum source (intact ERM or disrupted mycelium) is dynamic and important for plant performance. Furthermore, the outcome of a specific host&#x02013;symbiont interaction depends on the dynamic molecular responses that the host plant set up upon microbial colonization. For example, closely related AMF have been shown to alter transcriptional profiles of <italic>Medicago trunculata</italic> (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Hohnjec et al., 2005</xref>). The greater growth of wheat after undisturbed <italic>O. compressus</italic> than after <italic>L. rigidum</italic> seems, therefore, to indicate molecular specificities of the symbiosis.</p><p>In this context, the present study explores the composition of indigenous AMF assemblages in plant roots in a transition from a Poaceae (<italic>L. rigidum</italic>) or a Fabaceae (<italic>O. compressus</italic>) to a different Poaceae (wheat). Since mixed planting occurs universally in natural and cultivated ecosystems, the effect of co-planting two host species was also included in this study. We hypothesize that: (i) there are preferential associations between AMF and host species; however, these mutual preferences are modified when two plant species grow together (neighbor effect); (ii) there is an influence of the AMF symbiosis established with the first host species on the succeeding symbiosis formed with the second host (wheat); and (iii) the disturbance state of the soil and consequently of the established mycelial network with the first host plants has an influence on the AMF communities of the succeeding plant and on the regulation of key symbiosis-related genes [<italic>CASTOR</italic>, <italic>POLLUX</italic>, <italic>CCaMK</italic>, <italic>Cyclops</italic>, <italic>SCL26</italic> (<italic>NSP2</italic>), and <italic>PhT1</italic>
<italic>Myc</italic>]. Our experimental design allowed us to investigate symbiont-host preferences at contrasting levels of soil disturbance and relative AMF composition of the mycelial network.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Biological Samples</title><p>Biological material was obtained through a two-phase greenhouse experiment designed to evaluate the AMF symbiotic community associated with two first host plant species, and after the transition to a second host species (wheat). We used an unsterilized sandy loam Eutric Cambisol soil obtained from a natural pasture, as described by <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Brito et al. (2014)</xref>.</p><p>In phase 1 of the experiment, two different mycotrophic plant species (Poaceae <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and Fabaceae <italic>O. compressus</italic>) (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Goss et al., 2017</xref>) were grown in 8 L pots over 8 weeks, either individually or as a mixture of both species (the <italic>O. compressus</italic> system, the <italic>L. rigidum</italic> system and the mixture system). Six replicate pots were used per system, with three plants per pot in the case of the individual species and six in the case of the mixture (three plants of each species). Plants were grown under the natural light/dark regime. At the end of phase 1, we excised the plant shoots. In half of the replicates of each system (three pots) we passed the soil through a 4 mm sieve, thus creating an AMF source comprising spores and fragmented extraradical mycelium (ERM) (disturbed treatment). In the other half (three pots), soil was kept undisturbed and consequently the mycelial network remained intact (undisturbed treatment). Samples of soil from the disturbed treatments were taken from each pot (total of nine samples), dried and cleared of root fragments. Root samples of <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic> were also taken from each pot where soil was disturbed: three samples from <italic>L. rigidum</italic> (hereafter designated as Lol), three from <italic>O. compressus</italic> (hereafter designated as Orn), three from <italic>L. rigidum</italic> from the mixture (hereafter designated as LolMix) and three samples from <italic>O. compressus</italic> from the mixture (hereafter designated as OrnMix). Roots were washed, dried at 50&#x000b0;C during 24 h, crushed using liquid nitrogen and kept at -80&#x000b0;C for later DNA extraction.</p><p>In phase 2 of the experiment, wheat (Family: Poaceae, <italic>T. aestivum</italic> L., var. Ardila) seedlings were planted in the same pots as before (three plants per pot). Living plants of <italic>L. rigidum</italic> or <italic>O. compressus</italic> were never present during this second phase of the experiment, only roots or root fragments remained (for undisturbed and disturbed treatments, respectively). Therefore the wheat treatments were as following: wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic> undisturbed (hereafter designated as WOU), wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic> disturbed (hereafter designated as WOD), wheat after <italic>L. rigidum</italic> undisturbed (hereafter designated as WLU), wheat after <italic>L. rigidum</italic> disturbed (hereafter designated as WLD), wheat after the mixture undisturbed (hereafter designated as WMixU), wheat after the mixture disturbed (hereafter designated as WMixD). Wheat was allowed to grow for 5 weeks and then root samples were taken. Roots were cleaned, washed in distilled water, dried at 50&#x000b0;C during 24 h, crushed in liquid nitrogen and stored at -80&#x000b0;C for further DNA extractions. For RNA extraction, root samples were washed in distilled water, snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at -80&#x000b0;C. For each individual plant, fresh weight of the shoot was measured. Significant differences in wheat shoot fresh weight between the different treatments (with disturbance and preceding host as factors) were determined by two-way ANOVA using the R package &#x02018;stats.&#x02019;</p></sec><sec><title>DNA Extraction and Sequencing</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from each root sample with the DNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. DNA from soil samples was extracted with ZR Soil Microbe DNA MicroPrep<sup>TM</sup> (Zymo Research, Irvine, CA, United States) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The quality and concentration of the DNA extracted were assessed using a NanoDrop 2000-C spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, DE, United States).</p><p>DNA samples of soil and roots were prepared for Illumina MiSeq sequencing technology with 2 bp &#x000d7; 250 bp chemistry in a two-step nested polymerase chain reaction (PCR) procedure. The specific eukaryotic primers LR1 and NDL22 (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Van Tuinen et al., 1998</xref>) were used to amplify a fragment of the large ribosomal subunit (LSU) DNA (rDNA) genes in the first PCR, whereas the primers FRL3 and FRL4 (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Gollotte et al., 2004</xref>) were used to amplify the LSU-D2 rDNA genes of AMF in the second PCR. To identify each sample, the primers FRL3 and FRL4 were tagged with a 10-mer multiplex identifier sequence at the 5&#x02032; end of the primers. At least three technical replicates per sample were used in each step. Further preparatory procedures, such as equimolar pooling of PCR reactions, addition of adaptors and PCR product purification were performed by GenoScreen<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref></sup>, prior to Illumina sequencing.</p><p>Illumina MiSeq sequencing yielded 3,542,923 raw sequences. Raw sequence data were processed using the CLC Genomics Workbench version 8.5.1. (Qiagen Aarhus A/S, Denmark). Data were sorted by index and forward and reverse reads merged for each of the samples. Sequences were trimmed to a minimum length of 300 bp and reads with low coverage removed from subsequent analyses. The remaining sequence reads were checked for chimeric sequences using the CLC Genomics Workbench (26,322 chimeric sequences were discarded), <italic>de novo</italic> clustered at 97% similarity threshold and assigned to operational taxonomic units (OTUs). OTU abundance tables were created using the clustered sequences. Affiliation to AMF was checked by BLAST against the public databases DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank and MaarjAM (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">&#x000d6;pik et al., 2010</xref>). Raw sequencing data were submitted to the Sequence Read Archive under the accession SRP128462.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequencing Statistical Analysis</title><p>To evaluate sampling effort, a rarefaction analysis of data subsets was done using the function <italic>rarecurve</italic> from the R package &#x02018;vegan&#x02019; (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Oksanen et al., 2016</xref>). However, to compare AMF communities between samples regardless of sampling depth artifacts, the number of sequences per sample was normalized down to that of the sample with the lowest number of reads through a random selection of sequences in each sample, using the function <italic>rrarefy</italic> from the R package &#x02018;vegan&#x02019; (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Oksanen et al., 2016</xref>). The effect of data normalization on the variation in AMF communities&#x02019; composition was evaluated by repeating the analyses with the non-standardized data.</p><p>Permutational multivariate analysis of variance (PERMANOVA) (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Anderson and Walsh, 2013</xref>) with the Bray&#x02013;Curtis dissimilarity as a measure of distance between AMF communities, was performed using the <italic>adonis</italic> routine of the &#x02018;vegan&#x02019; package (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Oksanen et al., 2016</xref>). PERMANOVA was used to address the partition variance in AMF community composition in soil after different host species (<italic>O. compressus</italic>, <italic>L. rigidum</italic> or mixture of both), and to assess AMF variance between first hosts and its putative neighbor effect (<italic>O. compressus</italic>, <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, <italic>O. compressus</italic> neighbored by <italic>Lolium</italic>, and <italic>L. rigidum</italic> neighbored by <italic>Ornithopus</italic>).</p><p>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi &#x003b2;-diversity among <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic> was analyzed by testing homogeneity of OTU dispersion among the four different groups: Orn, Lol, OrnMix and LolMix. &#x003b2;-Diversity, here defined as the dissimilarity in species composition between hosts, was partitioned following <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Baselga (2010)</xref> in &#x0201c;turnover or replacement&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;nestedness or species loss.&#x0201d; We used OTU&#x02019;s abundances based on Bray&#x02013;Curtis dissimilarity index (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bray and Curtis, 1957</xref>) because quantitative data has been shown to provide more useful information on the mechanisms shaping diversity patterns within and amongst communities (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Ulrich and Gotelli, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Baselga, 2013</xref>). Overall and partitioned &#x003b2;-diversity were calculated using the functions <italic>bray.part</italic>, <italic>betadisper</italic>, and <italic>permutest.betadisper</italic> from the &#x02018;vegan&#x02019; and &#x02018;betapart&#x02019; packages (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Oksanen et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Baselga et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>To test the independent and interacting effects of disturbance and previous host species on AMF &#x003b2;-diversity in wheat, we performed PERMANOVA using the function <italic>adonis</italic> from the R package &#x0201c;vegan.&#x0201d; For that, we partitioned &#x003b2;-diversity into its two components and the output of this partitioning approach consists of three distance matrices representing: (1) &#x003b2;-diversity&#x02014; i.e., Bray&#x02013;Curtis; (2) the nestedness component; and (3) the turnover component. The obtained <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> values quantify the explanatory power of the factors (disturbance, first host and their interaction). Non-metric multidimensional scaling (NMDS) was also used to represent AMF community variation amongst species/treatments in two-dimensional space using the function <italic>metaMDS</italic> from the R package &#x02018;vegan.&#x02019;</p><p>The number of unique and shared OTUs between different treatments/plant species was found using the function <italic>vennDiagram</italic> from the R package &#x02018;VennDiagram&#x02019; (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Boutros, 2011</xref>).</p><p>To detect the specific OTUs differentially abundant between first hosts and wheat plants, we used the <italic>metastats</italic> command based on the Metastats program (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">White et al., 2009</xref>) using 1000 permutations, implemented in the Mothur platform (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Schloss et al., 2009</xref>). Indicator AMF taxa for first host species were determined using the <italic>indVal</italic> function of the &#x02018;labdsv&#x02019; package of R (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Roberts, 2012</xref>).</p><p>Significant differences in the frequencies of shared OTUs grouped by genera between hosts/neighbor effect/disturbance were determined by two-way ANOVA or <italic>t</italic>-test using the R package &#x02018;stats.&#x02019;</p></sec><sec><title>Wheat Symbiosis-Related Genes Analysis by Quantitative Real Time RT-PCR (qPCR)</title><p>Six key plant genes involved in the symbiotic process between AMF were chosen to investigate if wheat showed a differentiated response to previous AMF host and to ERM disturbance: <italic>TaCASTOR</italic>, <italic>TaPOLLUX</italic>, <italic>TaCCaMK</italic>, <italic>TaCyclops</italic>, <italic>TaSCL26</italic> (<italic>NSP2</italic>), and <italic>TaPhyT1</italic>
<italic>Myc</italic>. <italic>CASTOR</italic> and <italic>POLLUX</italic> are twin cation channel-enconding genes acting upstream of calcium spiking (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Kistner et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2009</xref>). The Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions then bind to a calcium and calmodulin-dependent kinase (CCaMK) leading to the activation of Cyclops, regulating arbuscule formation (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Yano et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al., 2013</xref>). Downstream of this signaling pathway are the genes regulating the transcriptional outputs, including the GRAS transcription factors. The scarecrow-like protein 26/nodulation signaling pathway (SCL26/NSP2) belongs to the GRAS family and has been found to facilitate mycorrhizal colonization (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Maillet et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Gobbato et al., 2012</xref>). Given that disturbed or undisturbed ERM affects how early and fast the colonization occurs (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Goss and De Varennes, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Brito et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Alho et al., 2015</xref>), we also looked at the expression of the specific AMF induced phosphate transporter <italic>PhT1</italic> Myc gene. Gene sequences were retrieved from Ensembl Plants database. Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (<italic>GAPDH</italic>) and <italic>Ta54227</italic> were used as endogenous reference genes to normalize target gene expression (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Paolacci et al., 2009</xref>). For each gene, specific primers were designed to span at least one intron/exon border to avoid amplification of potential contaminating genomic DNA, and then its quality analyzed with Netprimer<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn02">2</xref></sup>.</p><p>Total RNA extraction was performed on individual roots (three plants per pot, three pots per treatment) using the Maxwell<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> 16 LEV simplyRNA purification kit (Promega, Madison, WI, United States), according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. RNA was quantified using a NanoDrop-2000C spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific) and its integrity was checked by gel electrophoresis. First strand cDNA was synthesized with 500 ng of purified total RNA using the GoScript<sup>TM</sup> Reverse Transcription System (Promega) using random decamer primers, following manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p><p>Quantification of gene expression was performed by RT-qPCR using 5 &#x003bc;l of 10x diluted cDNA with the Maxima SYBR Green/ROX qPCR Master Mix (2x) (Thermo Scientific) on a 7500 Real Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, United States). RT-qPCR was conducted as described elsewhere (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Campos et al., 2016</xref>). Primer sequences, amplicon sizes and qPCR amplification efficiencies are shown in Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>. Evaluation of expression stability for the reference genes was done using the statistical application <italic>geNorm</italic> (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Vandesompele et al., 2002</xref>). Expression of target genes was evaluated by relative quantification using the geometric normalization factors obtained from <italic>geNorm</italic>. Differences in gene expression were analyzed by <italic>t</italic>-test and Nested ANOVA, using pot as random factor and disturbance and previous host as fixed factors, using the R packages &#x02018;nlme&#x02019; and &#x02018;multcomp.&#x02019;</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Illumina MiSeq Data Analysis</title><p>From the 9 soil and 30 root samples analyzed, a total of 238,163 high quality and filtered sequences of the LSU rDNA were obtained. After clustering at 97% sequence identity threshold, all the sequences corresponded to 92 representative distinct OTUs. BLAST searches assigned all sequences to phylum Glomeromycotina (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Spatafora et al., 2016</xref>) (see Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref> for details regarding % coverage and identity), in spite of the previously noted lack of exclusivity of the used nested primer set (which seem to also amplify some basidiomycetes (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Mummey and Rillig, 2008</xref>)). These representative sequences were deposited in GenBank (Accession Nos. MG774934 to MG775025). Based on the rarefaction analysis, the number of sequences obtained provided adequate coverage of the AMF diversity in soil and root samples, as curves reached an asymptote (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>).</p><p>AMF showed a wide diversity, particularly in root samples (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). The sequences from all samples were distributed taxonomically amongst six different families within Glomeromycotina, varying greatly in their frequencies: Glomeraceae (65.6%), Claroideoglomeraceae (29.0%), Acaulosporaceae (5.2%), Gigasporaceae (0.2%), Archaeosporaceae (0.03%) and Paraglomeraceae (0.01%). Within the Glomeraceae (55 OTUs), 17 representative sequences (30.9%) were assigned to the genus <italic>Rhizophagus</italic>, 4 to <italic>Funneliformis</italic> (7.3%) and 1 to <italic>Dominikia</italic> (1.8%). The remaining 33 OTUs (60% of the total) had no match in the databases at genus level, thus being reported as uncultured Glomeraceae (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>General AMF Community Composition in Soil and Roots of Ryegrass and Yellow-Serradella</title><p>In the soil and first host species, AMF richness varied from 4 to 45 OTUs, with the smallest values observed in the soil and largest in <italic>O. compressus</italic> (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>), having average values of 7 OTUs for soil, 29 for <italic>L. rigidum</italic> as standalone species and 27 in the mixture with <italic>O. compressus</italic>, 40 OTUs for <italic>O. compressus</italic> as standalone species and 38 in the mixture with <italic>L. rigidum</italic>.</p><p>The most abundant taxa in soil samples matched with uncultured Glomeraceae (&#x0223c;78%), followed by <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> (&#x0223c;20%) and <italic>Rhizophagus</italic> genus (&#x0223c;2%). <italic>Acaulospora</italic>, <italic>Archaeospora</italic>, <italic>Scutellospora</italic>, and <italic>Paraglomus</italic> comprised less than 1% (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S2a</xref>). In roots of <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic> the most abundant sequences also belonged to uncultured Glomeraceae (50 and 59%, respectively), but <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> was much more abundant in ryegrass (&#x0223c;27%) than in yellow-serradella (&#x0223c;11%). <italic>Acaulospora</italic> was the opposite, being 23% in <italic>Ornithopus</italic> and less than 3% in <italic>Lolium</italic>. <italic>Funneliformis</italic>, <italic>Scutellospora</italic>, <italic>Archaeospora</italic>, and <italic>Paraglomus</italic> sequences comprised less than 2% in both hosts.</p><p>Seventy two OTUs were found in <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, of which 25 were shared by the four experimental groups: Orn, Lol, OrnMix, and LolMix (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B,C</xref>). The majority of the shared OTUs fell within the uncultured Glomeraceae match (48% of the 72 OTUs), followed by the <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> genus with around 22% and then by <italic>Acaulospora</italic> (16%). <italic>Rhizophagus</italic> sequences were 14% and <italic>Scutellospora</italic> less than 1%. <italic>O. compressus</italic> had a slightly larger number of unique OTUs (6) than <italic>L. rigidum</italic> (5), and both species showed a slightly greater diversity of AMF genera when in the neighboring of each other (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3a</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Shared and unique OTUs between <italic>Ornithopus compressus</italic> and <italic>Lolium rigidum</italic>. <bold>(A)</bold> Representation of OTU composition in all <italic>O. compressus</italic> and all <italic>L. rigidum</italic> plants in a multidimensional space (NMDS plot), showing that they cluster depending on host. Ellipses represent ordination confidence intervals (95%) (stress = 0.13). <bold>(B)</bold> Venn diagram representing the number of unique and shared OTUs between the different hosts. <bold>(C)</bold> Frequencies of shared arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) taxa grouped by genera in the different hosts. Significant differences between hosts for the same AMF genus (<italic>N</italic> = 3) are indicated. In all cases: Orn, <italic>O. compressus</italic> alone; OrnMix, <italic>O. compressus</italic> neighbored by <italic>L. rigidum</italic>; Lol, <italic>L. rigidum</italic> alone; LolMix, <italic>L. rigidum</italic> neighbored by <italic>O. compressus</italic>. OTUs with no match in the databases at genus level were considered as uncultured Glomeraceae.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02920-g001"/></fig><p>The PERMANOVA on the sequencing data from soil DNA did not show any significant differences between soil samples surrounding <italic>O. compressus</italic> or <italic>L. rigidum</italic> (<italic>F</italic> = 0.45, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.13, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). However, AMF community structure between soil and these two hosts was significantly different (PERMANOVA, <italic>F</italic> = 5.82, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.23, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). This was further corroborated by NMDS ordination (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S2b</xref>), which was also consistent with the differences in AMF richness described above.</p><p>PERMANOVA analysis revealed that AMF communities were significantly different between <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic> (<italic>F</italic> = 3.47, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.25, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>); however, there was no significant plant neighboring effect on AMF communities (PERMANOVA <italic>F</italic> = 0.75, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.05, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05), indicating that co-planting did not influence AMF communities in these two species.</p><p><italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> abundance was greater in <italic>L. rigidum</italic> than in <italic>O. compressus</italic> (Two-way ANOVA, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). Also, <italic>Acaulospora</italic> frequency was greatly influenced by host (Two-way ANOVA, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), being much higher in <italic>O. compressus</italic>, regardless whether it was grown alone or in co-planting (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). Unique OTUs belonging to <italic>Acaulospora</italic> were found in <italic>O. compressus</italic>, and unique OTUs of <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> were found in <italic>L. rigidum</italic> (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3</xref>). These results of non-random association were further supported by the IndVal index, since four <italic>Acaulospora</italic> OTUs were clear indicators of <italic>O. compressus</italic> and one <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> OTU was an indicator for <italic>L. rigidum</italic> (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Wheat Growth Performance and AMF Dynamics in Host Transition</title><p>Shoot and root fresh weight of wheat was significantly different between disturbance regimes for all host combinations, being much greater in the undisturbed one (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S4</xref>). Within the undisturbed regime, shoot weight of WOU was significantly greater (1.31 &#x000b1; 0.33 g, mean &#x000b1; SD) than weight of WLU (0.96 &#x000b1; 0.19 g) or WMixU (0.97 &#x000b1; 0.20 g) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S4</xref>). Root weight of WOU was significantly greater (0.45 &#x000b1; 0.20 g) than weight of WMixU (0.25 &#x000b1; 0.11 g) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S4</xref>). No significant differences were found within the disturbed regime for either shoot or roots.</p><p>Eighty two OTUs were found considering all wheat samples (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> genus represented an average of 42% of the sequences, uncultured Glomeraceae around 41%, <italic>Rhizophagus</italic> 10%, <italic>Acaulospora</italic> 6%, Funneliformis around 2%, and <italic>Scutellospora</italic>, <italic>Gigaspora</italic>, <italic>Paraglomus</italic>, <italic>Archaeospora</italic>, <italic>Entrophospora</italic>, and <italic>Dominikia</italic> comprised less than 1% (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). AMF richness varied from 36 to 56 OTUs per sample. When comparing all OTUs from wheat, <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, regardless of the treatment, it was found that wheat had 24 OTUs that were not found in either of the previous hosts, but 40 OTUs were shared by the three species (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S4</xref>).</p><p>For each host combination separately, the number of OTUs shared between first hosts and wheat ranged between 24 and 29 (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A&#x02013;C</xref>). For the system with <italic>O. compressus</italic> alone as first host, the number of unique OTUs (8) was the same between Orn and WOU. Ten OTUs were exclusive to these two groups, more than any of the other pairwise comparisons (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A&#x02013;C</xref>). In the system with <italic>L. rigidum</italic> as first host (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>), Lol had more unique OTUs (11) than WLD (8) or WLU (10). Five OTUs were found only in Lol and WLU, and three OTUs were exclusive to Lol and WLD. In the system where both first hosts grew as a mixture (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>), nine OTUs were exclusive to OrnMix and WMixU. <italic>L. rigidum</italic> in the mixture (LolMix, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>) only had 1 OTU (<italic>Claroideoglomus</italic>) shared with WMixU, but shared six with WMixD (three <italic>Claroideogmus</italic> and three uncultured Glomeraceae).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Shared and unique OTUs between <italic>Ornithopus compressus</italic>, <italic>Lolium rigidum</italic> and wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>), and root AMF communities&#x02019; structure. <bold>(A&#x02013;C)</bold> Venn diagrams from the three treatments, representing the number of unique and shared OTUs between the different hosts. <bold>(D&#x02013;F)</bold> Frequencies of AMF taxa grouped by genera in the different hosts and treatments. OTUs with no match in the databases at genus level were considered as uncultured Glomeraceae. In all cases: Orn (<italic>O. compressus</italic>), Lol (<italic>L. rigidum</italic>), OrnMix (<italic>O. compressus</italic> from the mixture with <italic>L. rigidum</italic>), LolMix (<italic>L. rigidum</italic> from the mixture with <italic>O. compressus</italic>). Wheat: WOU (wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic>, undisturbed), WOD (wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic>, disturbed), WLU (wheat after <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, undisturbed), WLD (wheat after <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, disturbed), WMixU (wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic> grown in a mixture, undisturbed), WMixD (wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic> grown in a mixture, disturbed).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02920-g002"/></fig><p>Based on the frequencies of the AMF taxa on each system, WOU had a larger proportion of <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> and <italic>Acaulospora</italic> than in the disturbed treatment (WOD) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>). In the system with <italic>L. rigidum</italic> as first host, <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> was more abundant in WLU than in Lol or WLD, whereas <italic>Acaulospora</italic> was almost absent in all (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>). For the mixture system (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>), the frequencies of AMF taxa showed a pattern more similar to OrnMix and WMixU (having, for example, more <italic>Acaulospora</italic>), and LolMix and WMixD; the first pattern was comparable to <italic>O. compressus</italic> grown on its own and also to WOU, and the latter to WOD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>).</p><p>PERMANOVA analysis revealed that, regardless of the previous host, wheat OTUs differed between intact and disturbed ERM (<italic>F</italic> = 4.2, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.21, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Furthermore, wheat, when analyzed together with <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, also formed clusters according to the first host groups (<italic>O. compressus</italic>, <italic>L. ridigum</italic> and the mixture of both) (<italic>F</italic> = 2.8, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.17, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01), which was corroborated by NMDS ordination (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). This indicated that AMF communities of wheat, although highly influenced by ERM disturbance, were not independent of the AMF communities developed by the previous plants.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Effects of extraradical mycelium (ERM) disturbance and previous host on AMF communities&#x02019; composition in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>). <bold>(A)</bold> Effect of extra-radicular mycelia (ERM) network disruption on wheat AMF composition represented in multidimensional space (NMDS plot) considering the communities associated to wheat from the undisturbed and disturbed treatments. Ellipses represent ordination confidence intervals (95%), stress = 0.12. <bold>(B)</bold> NMDS plot of OTU composition in wheat + <italic>O. compressus</italic>+ <italic>L. rigidum</italic> on standardized data, showing that they form groups according to first host: <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, <italic>O. compressus</italic> or a mixture of both species. Ellipses represent ordination confidence intervals (95%), stress = 0.20. <bold>(C)</bold> Frequencies of shared AMF taxa grouped by genera in wheat. OTUs with no match in the databases at genus level were considered as uncultured Glomeraceae. Significant differences between treatments were assessed by Two-way ANOVA, with disturbance and first hosts as factors. WOU (wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic>, undisturbed soil), WOD (wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic>, disturbed soil), WLU (wheat after <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, undisturbed soil), WLD (wheat after <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, soil disturbed), WMixU (wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic> + <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, undisturbed soil), WMixD (wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic> + <italic>L. rigidum</italic>, disturbed soil).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02920-g003"/></fig><p>The analysis of the OTUs shared by the six wheat treatments revealed that OTUs belonging to uncultured Glomeraceae, <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> and <italic>Acaulospora</italic> were significantly influenced by disturbance regime (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). Previous host also had an effect on the relative abundance of <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic>, since wheat after <italic>L. ridigum</italic> had more <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic> than the other systems (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). When analyzing only the undisturbed treatment, we found that wheat after <italic>O. compressus</italic> or after the mixture had a greater frequency of <italic>Acaulospora</italic> than wheat after <italic>L. ridigum</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). These results are similar to those described above for <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic>.</p><p>The analysis of unique OTUs from the six wheat treatments showed that WOU had the greatest diversity of AMF genera (four OTUs, corresponding to four genera), while WLD had the smallest (1 OTU) (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S3b</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>AMF &#x003b2;-Diversity in the Transition From First Host Species to Wheat</title><p>Differences in AMF composition between first host species were clarified by considering AMF &#x003b2;-diversity in principal component analysis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and <italic>O. compressus</italic> formed different clusters, whether they were planted singly or in a mixture.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi &#x003b2;-diversity in the transition from <italic>Ornithopus compressus</italic> and/or <italic>Lolium rigidum</italic> to wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>). <bold>(A)</bold> AMF total &#x003b2;-diversity in the roots of first hosts in a principal coordinates space. <bold>(B&#x02013;G)</bold> Boxplots showing the turnover and nestedness components of &#x003b2;-diversity between <italic>O. compressus</italic> and wheat <bold>(B,C)</bold>, <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and wheat <bold>(D,E)</bold>, and <italic>O. compressus</italic> + <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and wheat <bold>(F,G)</bold>, being wheat planted in either undisturbed (Und) or disturbed soil (Dis). Bold line represents median and the bottom and top of the box represent lower and upper quartiles. <bold>(H)</bold> Total amount of explanatory power (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>, scaled to 100) provided by disturbance, previous host species and their interaction on wheat global AMF &#x003b2;-diversity and components, as calculated based on PERMANOVA. Nestedness was null. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05. NS, non-significant. In all cases: Orn, <italic>O. compressus</italic> alone; OrnMix, <italic>O. compressus</italic> neighbored by <italic>L. rigidum</italic>; Lol, <italic>L. rigidum</italic> alone; LolMix, <italic>L. rigidum</italic> neighbored by <italic>O. compressus</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02920-g004"/></fig><p>We compared the multivariate homogeneity of dispersion (i.e., distance from objects to cluster centroid) in OTU turnover and nestedness between <italic>O. compressus</italic> and wheat (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B,C</xref>), <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and wheat (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D,E</xref>), and <italic>O. compressus</italic> + <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and wheat (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4F,G</xref>). Only for <italic>L. rigidum</italic> as first host were there significant differences in the distances to the centroid (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D,E</xref>). Moreover, these differences were more obvious when the ERM was disturbed (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D,E</xref>). The analyses with Metastats indicated that the major distances obtained between the AMF community composition in <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and wheat in the disturbed treatment were mainly due to significant changes (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S5</xref>) in the abundances of <italic>Rhizophagus</italic> OTUs (OTUs 18, 20, 31, 41), together with an <italic>Acaulospora</italic> OTU (OTU 49), and an uncultured Glomeraceae OTU (OTU 62). In the Undisturbed treatment, the differences were due to <italic>Rhizophagus</italic> OTUs (OTUs 26 and 47) and an uncultured Glomeraceae OTU (OTU 27).</p><p>The total amount of explanatory power (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>, scaled to 100) provided by disturbance, previous host species and their interaction on wheat global AMF &#x003b2;-diversity and components, was calculated based on PERMANOVA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4H</xref>). It showed that ERM disturbance and previous host had an effect on global &#x003b2;-diversity (<italic>F</italic> = 4.60, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.19, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 and <italic>F</italic> = 2.39, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.20, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, respectively) and on its turnover component (<italic>F</italic> = 4.85, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.20, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 and <italic>F</italic> = 2.36, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.19, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, respectively). Nestedness was found to have a null effect on variation between wheat treatments.</p></sec><sec><title>Expression of Wheat Symbiosis-Related Genes</title><p>Five symbiosis-related <italic>T. aestivum</italic> genes &#x02013; <italic>TaCASTOR</italic>, <italic>TaPOLLUX</italic>, <italic>TaCCaMK</italic>, <italic>TaCyclops</italic>, <italic>TaSCL26</italic> (<italic>NSP2</italic>) &#x02013; were more strongly expressed in roots when the ERM network was disturbed, regardless of the previous host (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A&#x02013;E</xref>). Moreover, within the undisturbed regime, <italic>TaPOLLUX</italic> and <italic>TaCCaMK</italic> showed significantly greater expression after <italic>L. rigidum</italic> than after <italic>O. compressus</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B,C</xref>). Expression of the specifically induced AMF phosphate transporter <italic>TaPhT1</italic> Myc was significantly greater in wheat roots from the undisturbed treatments than in the disturbed ones (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic>CASTOR</italic>, <italic>POLLUX</italic>, <italic>CCaMK, Cyclops</italic>, <italic>SCL26</italic> (<italic>NSP2</italic>) and <italic>PhT1</italic> Myc genes in wheat roots. Expression of wheat <italic>TaCASTOR</italic>
<bold>(A)</bold>, <italic>TaPOLLUX</italic>
<bold>(B)</bold>
<italic>CCaMK</italic>
<bold>(C)</bold>, <italic>TaCyclops</italic>
<bold>(D)</bold>, <italic>TaSCL26</italic> (<italic>NSP2</italic>) <bold>(E),</bold> and <italic>TaPhT1</italic>Myc <bold>(F)</bold> as determined by RT-qPCR. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 indicate significant differences between undisturbed and disturbed treatments, and <sup>a,b</sup> between different previous AMF hosts (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Error bars indicate the standard error of the mean. Previous hosts: Orn, <italic>O. compressus</italic>; Lol, <italic>L. rigidum</italic>; Mix, <italic>O. compressus</italic>, <italic>L. rigidum</italic> grown in a mixture.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02920-g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>AMF Colonization Shows Host&#x02013;Symbiont Preference</title><p>The strength of the relationship between symbiotic organisms, such as plants and their obligate biotrophic AMF colonizers, is expected to relate to the functional attributes of both partners and to favor relationships that better cope with environmental constraints. Defining the degree of preferential or non-random associations between AMF and plant host is crucial to understand the relative importance of both partners in driving this relationship.</p><p>In this study the AMF communities in soil and roots were dominated by members of the Glomerales, consistent with that of previous studies (e.g., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Helgason et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x000d6;pik et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Lumini et al., 2010</xref>). The AMF taxa found in the soil were similar following the growth of either of the first host species, and showed limited richness, though this might reflect the discrete sampling that was performed (prone to sampling only the most abundant species). Nevertheless, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bainard et al. (2014)</xref> reported previously that the plant host identity had minimal effect on the composition of the AMF community in the soil. Also a comparison of AMF taxa between soil mycelium, soil spores and colonized root propagules revealed a higher number of OTUs in roots than in soil, and that AMF taxa can be differentially allocated in these fractions (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Varela-Cervero et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>The community structure of AMF on yellow-serradella (<italic>O. compressus</italic>) differed greatly from that on ryegrass (<italic>L. rigidum</italic>), reflecting strong host&#x02013;symbiont preferences. Yellow-serradella (Fabaceae) showed much greater overall OTU richness than did ryegrass (Poaceae). Differences in AMF type and richness between legumes and non-legumes have been described previously (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Scheublin et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bainard et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Br&#x000ed;gido et al., 2017</xref>). This can partially be attributed to host taxonomic position, but factors such as ecosystem characteristics and functional specificities of the species cannot be disregarded.</p><p>Although our results were consistent with the hypothesis of host-specificity, the associated hypothesis on the existence of a neighbor effect was not supported. The simultaneous growth of the two species, yellow-serradella and ryegrass, had a minor effect on the network of symbionts established, only influencing the number of AMF genera among the unique OTUs present in the roots (just slightly greater when both species were grown together). Indeed, the reciprocal effect of neighboring hosts on root AMF communities seems to differ amongst species. For example, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Hausmann and Hawkes (2009)</xref> reported that AMF communities on the grasses <italic>Bromus hordeaceus</italic> and <italic>Nassella pulchra</italic> were largely invariant, so that the presence of a neighbor was essentially neutral. In contrast, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al. (2016)</xref> showed that mycorrhizal colonization of a legume tree was enhanced by legume neighbors but inhibited by grass neighbors. Our study showed almost no changes in the symbiotic community between yellow-serradella and ryegrass, possibly as a result of the different preferential host&#x02013;symbiont associations. Thus, in AMF communities established on ryegrass there was a dominance of <italic>Claroideoglomus</italic>, whereas <italic>Acaulospora</italic> prevailed in those on yellow-serradella. A similar observation was reported by <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Br&#x000ed;gido et al. (2017)</xref>. This might relate to fungal colonization strategies and the development of ERM, which differ between AMF species (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Hart and Reader, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Schnepf et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Powell et al., 2009</xref>) and could have implications for the delivery of functional benefits to the host plant.</p></sec><sec><title>Shape of AMF Communities on Wheat Relates to Previous Host in an Undisturbed Environment</title><p>It is known that the order of plant establishment may differently filter AMF communities from the available species pool (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Hausmann and Hawkes, 2010</xref>). The inheritance of a cohort of microorganisms gone through the plant filtering system can therefore provide a consortium that allows the plant to rapidly adjust to environmental conditions. The transition from yellow-serradella or ryegrass shaped wheat AMF consortia &#x02013; when growing in the presence of an undisturbed mycelial &#x02013; in a way that related to the identity of the previous host but did not relate to their taxonomic proximity (at least not at family level). Nevertheless, since wheat has evolved under cultivation, it is possible that this might modulate its mycorrhizal response in a different way from non-domesticated species (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Mart&#x000ed;n-Robles et al., 2018</xref>). Domesticated plants have been bred to grow quickly and develop at a faster pace, and they probably exude different amounts and types of organic compounds in their roots, which can affect microbial communities (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">P&#x000e9;rez-Jaramillo et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>While it was clear that wheat inherited AMF taxa from the previous host, the partitioning of root AMF &#x003b2;-diversity into its two components revealed a pattern that was not obvious from the analysis of genera frequency only: turnover and nestedness were significant in shaping AMF communities in the system with ryegrass as first host. However, differences between ryegrass and wheat, particularly wheat grown after soil disturbance, have been confined largely within the same taxa (<italic>Rhizophagus</italic>). It seems therefore that wheat and ryegrass specificities led to changes (AMF replacement or loss), but within closely related AMF species. Whether this is due to the taxonomical proximity of the two plant species (Poaceae) is currently unknown.</p><p>Soil disturbance has previously been related to changes in AMF composition in wheat roots (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Br&#x000ed;gido et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Hartman et al., 2018</xref>). We also found great differences between OTU composition of wheat from disturbed and undisturbed treatments. This must relate to the main propagule source being spores and mycelia or colonized root fragments rather than a well-established ERM network. These sources are not equally effective at producing new infection units. Indeed, colonization initiated by an intact ERM starts earlier and develop faster (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Goss and De Varennes, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Brito et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Alho et al., 2015</xref>) whereas the slower colonization from spores is linked to the need for germination to be initiated by signaling from the host plant (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Garg and Chandel, 2010</xref>). Similarly to previous observations by <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Brito et al. (2014)</xref>, we found significant differences in wheat growth between the undisturbed and disturbed regimes, but also between the yellow-serradella and ryegrass systems. Thus, it seems that AMF mediation of yellow-serradella-wheat facilitation (in the form of plant host benefit) occurred in an undisturbed environment. In fact, AMF have been shown to mediate plant interactions through a direct influence on plant biomass or by an indirect influence on plant photosynthesis and macronutrient acquisition (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Co-planting of <italic>O. compressus</italic> and <italic>L. rigidum</italic> Reveals Wheat-AMF Non-random Associations</title><p>The mixture system (yellow-serradella and ryegrass planted as a mixture) generated in wheat an AMF frequency pattern, at the genera level, that more resembled that of yellow-serradella than of ryegrass. The difference specifically reflected the significantly greater frequency of <italic>Acaulospora</italic>. This suggests that, in an undisturbed environment, there was a non-random selection by wheat (and perhaps reciprocally by <italic>Acaulospora</italic>) from the available pool of AMF left after <italic>L. rigidum</italic> and <italic>O. compressus</italic>, and not simply passive root colonization by the most abundant taxa. Hence, AMF inheritance occurred (as observed by the single host species systems) but wheat-symbiont specificity emerges in the co-planting system. We see additional support for wheat-symbiont specificity as a large number of OTUs that did not occur in either <italic>O. compressus</italic> or <italic>L. rigidum</italic> were found in wheat. Among the six wheat treatments, overall &#x003b2;-diversity and the turnover component were influenced not only by the first host but also by soil disturbance. However, the contribution of nestedness or species loss to dissimilarities between wheat AMF communities was irrelevant, suggesting that AMF richness was mostly associated with plant species identity.</p><p>Complementary beneficial effects of different AMF can result in a more efficient exploitation of the soil nutrients. Facilitation was found in wheat from the yellow-serradella undisturbed treatment; by contrast, the effect declined when co-planting yellow-serradella and ryegrass, despite the AMF communities of wheat still resemble that of yellow-serradella. The reasons for this are unknown; however, functional consequences of the existence or abundance of specific OTUs (even within the same taxa) might be the explanation. In fact, genetic variability in different isolates of the same AMF species has been found to cause variations in plant growth (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al., 2006</xref>). It has also been suggested that, as different plant species have distinct strategies for nutrient absorption, soil nutrients are used more effectively in the presence of a greater plant diversity, which may lead to a reduction in amount of nutrients available for uptake by the ERM for a specific plant (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">McKane et al., 2002</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>In Wheat, Symbiosis-Related Genes Respond to ERM Disturbance</title><p>Prior to and during colonization, molecular signals are exchanged between the two symbionts, leading to a stage-specific pattern of gene expression and hormonal signaling (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Garg and Chandel, 2010</xref>). Our analysis of wheat root gene expression showed for the first time that ERM disturbance state had a considerable effect on five key symbiotic-related genes: <italic>CASTOR, POLLUX</italic>, <italic>CCaMK</italic>, <italic>Cyclops</italic>, and <italic>SCL26</italic> (<italic>NSP2</italic>) were expressed much more in roots from the disturbed than the undisturbed treatments. Soil disturbance implies the disruption of the mycelial network and thus the main propagule sources remaining were spores and colonized root fragments or mycelial fragments. These must re-enter the entire process of symbiosis establishment. On the other hand, in the undisturbed treatment a mycelial network was already established and apparently could easily colonize new roots; this easier colonization was further confirmed by the greater expression of the AMF-induced <italic>PhT1</italic> Myc gene in the systems with intact ERM. Also, the greater weight of wheat from the undisturbed treatments, regardless of the previous host indicates a more positive outcome of the cost-benefit balance for the symbiosis. The reduced activation of the genes in the undisturbed treatments certainly reflects the suitability of the existing ERM network. On the contrary, the greater expression of <italic>CASTOR, POLLUX</italic>, <italic>CCaMK</italic>, <italic>Cyclops</italic>, and <italic>SCL26</italic> in plants grown after soil disturbance might reflect an earlier stage in the symbiotic process. Consistent with our results, it has been observed that the requirements for CCaMK seem to be carefully regulated depending on the stage of root colonization (epidermal or cortical cell infection) (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Liao et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>We also found that the expression levels of <italic>POLLUX</italic> and <italic>CCaMK</italic> within roots from the undisturbed soil were significantly greater in wheat after <italic>L. rigidum</italic> than after <italic>O. compressus</italic>, which might relate to differential abundance of specific taxa. In fact, closely related AMF have been shown to alter transcriptional profiles of <italic>Medicago trunculata</italic> (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Hohnjec et al., 2005</xref>). Moreover, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Colard et al. (2011)</xref> showed that genetic exchange within the AMF <italic>R. intraradices</italic> species altered rice growth and the transcription of symbiotic genes. <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Kamel et al. (2017)</xref> found that the secretomes of <italic>R. irregularis</italic> and <italic>G. rosea</italic> when colonizing host plants differed according to host. Also genes related to stress responses have sequence polymorphisms between different <italic>R. irregularis</italic> isolates, which are likely to be related to its origin and natural environmental constraints and can have functional consequences for the host plant (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Campos et al., 2015</xref>). Since disturbance and prior host changed the relative abundances of specific AMF taxa on wheat roots [for instance <italic>Acaulospora</italic> was highly sensitive to ERM disturbance, consistent with what has been described previously (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Goss et al., 2017</xref>)], it remains to be seen if different AMF can induce changes in patterns of wheat gene expression and if or how this relates to the greater growth observed with <italic>O. compressus</italic> as previous host.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our results show that at least a part of wheat AMF consortia was shaped by the preceding plant host but without obliterating wheat-symbiont preferences; this was shown by wheat establishing preferential symbioses with specific AMF taxa on the undisturbed co-planting system. The ERM disturbance effect served therefore as proof-of-concept for wheat symbiotic preferences but also for wheat facilitation, as disrupted AMF communities were linked to a poorer growth. Root colonization starting from an intact indigenous and well-adapted AM fungal population therefore enhances the potential of AMF for promoting plant growth. Furthermore, we found that expression patterns of key symbiosis-related genes depended on ERM disturbance state and also partially on previous host, indicating that plant genetic program depends to some extent on the colonizing symbiont and on the type of propagule involved. Unraveling the molecular mechanisms beyond specific AMF-host interactions could provide a strategy to enhance performance of susceptible plants growing in adverse environments.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MC and TN conceived the study and experimental design. CC did the experiments and writing of the publication. CC and CB performed the bioinformatic data analyses. CC, TN, MC, CB, and MG did the interpretations. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was funded by National Funds through FCT &#x02013; Foundation for Science and Technology, under the Project UID/AGR/00115/2013, and co-financed by the European Union through the European Regional Development Fund, under ALENTEJO 2020 (Alentejo Regional Operational Program) through the project &#x0201c;Improving pasture production in acid soils in montado: chemical and biological approach,&#x0201d; Reference No. ALT20-03 -0145-FEDER-000039. CC and CB acknowledge the postdoctoral fellowships from the Portuguese Foundation for Science and Technology (Reference Nos. SFRH/BPD/108734/2015 and SFRH/BPD/94751/2013). TN was supported by a Marie Curie fellowship (FP7-PEOPLE-2012-CIG Project Reference 321725).</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank to Filipa Santos and Manuel Figo for technical assistance to carry out the pot experiment.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genoscreen.fr/en/">http://genoscreen.fr/en/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn02"><label>2</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.premierbiosoft.com/">http://www.premierbiosoft.com/</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2018.02920/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2018.02920/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alho</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The effect of arbuscular mycorrhiza fungal propagules on the growth of subterranean clover (<italic>Trifolium subterraneum</italic> L.) under Mn toxicity in ex situ experiments.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Use Manag.</italic></source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>344</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/sum.12183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>D. C. I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>PERMANOVA, ANOSIM, and the mantel test in the face of heterogeneous dispersions: what null hypothesis are you testing?</article-title>
<source><italic>Ecol. Monogr.</italic></source>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>557</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>574</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/12-2010.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bainard</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bainard</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Spatial and temporal structuring of arbuscular mycorrhizal communities is differentially influenced by abiotic factors and host crop in a semi-arid prairie agroecosystem.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>88</volume>
<fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>344</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6941.12300</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24527842?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24527842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baselga</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Partitioning the turnover and nestedness components of beta diversity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>134</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>143</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1466-8238.2009.00490.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baselga</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Separating the two components of abundance-based dissimilarity: balanced changes in abundance vs. abundance gradients.</article-title>
<source><italic>Methods Ecol. Evol.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>557</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210X.12029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baselga</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orme</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villeger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bortoli</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leprieur</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <source><italic>Package &#x02018; Betapart.&#x02019; R Packag. Ver. 1.4.1.</italic></source></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bever</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Negative feedback within a mutualism: host-specific growth of mycorrhizal fungi reduces plant benefit.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>269</volume>
<fpage>2595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2601</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2002.2162</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12573075?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12573075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>). <article-title>An ordination of the upland forest communities of Southern Wisconsin.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ecol. Monogr.</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1942268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Br&#x000ed;gido</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tuinen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alho</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Management of the biological diversity of AM fungi by combination of host plant succession and integrity of extraradical mycelium.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Biol. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>112</volume>
<fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>247</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2017.05.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alho</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Managing arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi for bioprotection: Mn toxicity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Biol. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2013.09.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Carvalho</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatagnier</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tuinen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Impact of tillage system on arbuscular mycorrhiza fungal communities in the soil under Mediterranean conditions.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Tillage Res.</italic></source>
<volume>121</volume>
<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.still.2012.01.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogales</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-R&#x000e1;ez</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozo</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Intra and inter-spore variability in rhizophagus irregularis AOX gene.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>e0142339</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142339</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26540237?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26540237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogales</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of plastid terminal oxidase gene from carrot and its relation to carotenoid accumulation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Gene</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plgene.2015.10.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Antiquity and function of CASTOR and POLLUX, the twin ion channel-encoding genes key to the evolution of root symbioses in plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>149</volume>
<fpage>306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.131540</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18978069?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18978069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutros</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>VennDiagram: a package for the generation of highly-customizable Venn and Euler diagrams in R.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>:<issue>35</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-35</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21269502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21269502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Genetic exchange in an arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus results in increased rice growth and altered mycorrhiza-specific gene transcription.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>77</volume>
<fpage>6510</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6515</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.05696-11</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21784911?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21784911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Opik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adholeya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ainsaar</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ba</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Global assessment of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus diversity reveals very low endemism.</article-title>
<source><italic>Science</italic></source>
<volume>349</volume>
<fpage>970</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>973</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aab1161</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26315436?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26315436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Arbuscular mycorrhizal networks?: process and functions. A review.</article-title>
<source><italic>Agron. Sustain. Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>599</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/agro/2009054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gobbato</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verni&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maillet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A GRAS-type transcription factor with a specific function in mycorrhizal signaling.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>2236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2241</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2012.09.044</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23122845?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23122845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gollotte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Tuinen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Diversity of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi colonising roots of the grass species <italic>Agrostis capillaris</italic> and <italic>Lolium perenne</italic> in a field experiment.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mycorrhiza</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>117</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00572-003-0244-7</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12768382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12768382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <source><italic>Functional Diversity of Mycorrhiza and Sustainable Agriculture &#x02013; Management to Overcome Biotic and Abiotic Stresses.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-804244-1.00006-X</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Varennes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Soil disturbance reduces the efficacy of mycorrhizal associations for early soybean growth and N2 fixation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Biol. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>1167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1173</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0038-0717(02)00053-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reader</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Taxonomic basis for variation in the colonization strategy of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>153</volume>
<fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>344</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0028-646X.2001.00312.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Heijden</surname><given-names>M. G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittwer</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walser</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaeppi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Cropping practices manipulate abundance patterns of root and soil microbiome members paving the way to smart farming.</article-title>
<source><italic>Microbiome</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>14</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40168-017-0389-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29338764?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29338764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hausmann</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Plant neighborhood control of arbuscular mycorrhizal community composition.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>183</volume>
<fpage>1188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02882.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19496954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19496954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hausmann</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Order of plant host establishment alters the composition of arbuscular mycorrhizal communities.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ecology</italic></source>
<volume>91</volume>
<fpage>2333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2343</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/09-0924.1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20836455?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20836455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosling</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Gast</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doohan</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bending</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The role of local environment and geographical distance in determining community composition of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi at the landscape scale.</article-title>
<source><italic>ISME J.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>498</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>508</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2012.127</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23096401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23096401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helgason</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitter</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Natural selection and the evolutionary ecology of the arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (Phylum Glomeromycota).</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>2465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2480</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp144</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19429838?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19429838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helgason</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merryweather</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Denison</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J. P. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitter</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Selectivity and functional diversity in arbuscular mycorrhizas of co-occurring fungi and plants from a temperate deciduous woodland.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>384</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2745.2001.00674.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hohnjec</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieweg</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000fc;hler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;ster</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puhler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Overlaps in the transcriptional profiles of <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> roots inoculated with two different glomus fungi provide insights into the genetic program activated during arbuscular mycorrhiza.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>137</volume>
<fpage>1283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1301</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.056572</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15778460?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15778460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Alleviation of drought stress by mycorrhizas is related to increased root H 2 O 2 efflux in trifoliate orange.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>42335</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep42335</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28176859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28176859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bidartondo</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leake</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beerling</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Mutualistic mycorrhiza-like symbiosis in the most ancient group of land plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>:<issue>103</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms1105</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21045821?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21045821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Tillage or no-tillage: impact on mycorrhizae.</article-title>
<source><italic>Can. J. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4141/P03-160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malbreil</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>San Clemente</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Marquer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The comparison of expressed candidate secreted proteins from two arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi unravels common and specific molecular tools to invade different host plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>124</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00124</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28223991?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28223991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kistner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winzer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitzschke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Seven <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic> genes required for transcriptional reprogramming of the root during fungal and bacterial symbiosis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>2217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2229</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.032714</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15980262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klironomos</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCune</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neville</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The influence of arbuscular mycorrhizae on the relationship between plant diversity and productivity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ecol. Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>141</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1461-0248.2000.00131.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croll</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Genetic variability in a population of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi causes variation in plant growth.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ecol. Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>110</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2005.00853.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16958874?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16958874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohout</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doubkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahram</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tedersoo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo&#x000f8;&#x000ed;&#x00161;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Niche partitioning in arbuscular mycorrhizal communities in temperate grasslands: a lesson from adjacent serpentine and nonserpentine habitats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>1831</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1843</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.13147</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25753913?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25753913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>S. U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonetta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Negative regulation of CCaMK is essential for symbiotic infection.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>572</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>584</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2012.05098.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22775286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22775286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lumini</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orgiazzi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borriello</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfante</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianciotto</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Disclosing arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal biodiversity in soil through a land-use gradient using a pyrosequencing approach.</article-title>
<source><italic>Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>2165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2179</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2009.02099.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21966911?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21966911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maillet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poinsot</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puech-Pag&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haouy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gueunier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Fungal lipochitooligosaccharide symbiotic signals in arbuscular mycorrhiza.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>469</volume>
<fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09622</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21209659?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n-Robles</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seco</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aroca</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rillig</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milla</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Impacts of domestication on the arbuscular mycorrhizal symbiosis of 27 crop species.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>218</volume>
<fpage>322</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>334</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14962</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29281758?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29281758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKane</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaver</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadelhoffer</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rastetter</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Resource-based niches provide a basis for plant species diversity and dominance in arctic tundra.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>415</volume>
<fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/415068a</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11780117?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11780117</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meadow</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabinski</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Linking symbiont community structures in a model arbuscular mycorrhizal system.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>194</volume>
<fpage>800</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>809</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04096.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22432474?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22432474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratap</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyahara</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bornemann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Calcium/calmodulin-dependent protein kinase is negatively and positively regulated by calcium, providing a mechanism for decoding calcium responses during symbiosis signaling.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>5053</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5066</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.113.116921</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24368786?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24368786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mummey</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rillig</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Spatial characterization of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal molecular diversity at the submetre scale in a temperate grassland.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>270</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.2008.00475.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18363704?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18363704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oksanen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kindt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Hara</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <source><italic>Vegan: Community Ecology Package. R Packag. 2.3-3.</italic></source> Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/vegan">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/vegan</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;pik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Metsis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniell</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zobel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Large-scale parallel 454 sequencing reveals host ecological group specificity of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi in a boreonemoral forest.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>184</volume>
<fpage>424</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>437</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02920.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19558424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19558424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;pik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liira</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zobel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Composition of root-colonizing arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal communities in different ecosystems around the globe.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>778</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>790</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2745.2006.01136.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;pik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanatoa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanatoa</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalwij</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The online database MaarjAM reveals global and ecosystemic distribution patterns in arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (Glomeromycota).</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>188</volume>
<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03334.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20561207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20561207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paolacci</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanzarella</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Porceddu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciaffi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Identification and validation of reference genes for quantitative RT-PCR normalization in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>11</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2199-10-11</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19232096?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19232096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Jaramillo</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raaijmakers</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Impact of plant domestication on rhizosphere microbiome assembly and functions.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>644</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-015-0337-7</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26085172?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26085172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrent</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klironomos</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rillig</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maherali</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic trait conservatism and the evolution of functional trade-offs in arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>276</volume>
<fpage>4237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4245</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2009.1015</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19740877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19740877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source><italic>Ordination and Multivariate Analysis for Ecology. R Packag. Version 1.5-0.</italic></source> Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org/package=labdsv">http://cran.r-project.org/package=labdsv</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheublin</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridgway</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J. P. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Heijden</surname><given-names>M. G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Nonlegumes, legumes, and root nodules harbor different arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal communities.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>6240</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6246</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.70.10.6240-6246.2004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15466571?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schloss</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westcott</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryabin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollister</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Introducing mothur: open-source, platform-independent, community-supported software for describing and comparing microbial communities.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>7537</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7541</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01541-09</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19801464?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19801464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnepf</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roose</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweiger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Growth model for arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. R. Soc. Interface</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>784</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2007.1250</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18077246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Arbuscular mycorrhiza augments arsenic tolerance in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) by strengthening antioxidant defense system and thiol metabolism.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>906</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00906</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28642762?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28642762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spatafora</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benny</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berbee</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A phylum-level phylogenetic classification of zygomycete fungi based on genome-scale data.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mycologia</italic></source>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>1028</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1046</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3852/16-042</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27738200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27738200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ulrich</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotelli</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Null model analysis of species associations using abundance data.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ecology</italic></source>
<volume>91</volume>
<fpage>3384</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3397</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/09-2157.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21141199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Der Heijden</surname><given-names>M. G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klironomos</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ursic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moutoglis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Streitwolf-Engel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Mycorrhizal fungal diversity determines plant biodiversity, ecosystem variability and productivity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>396</volume>
<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/23932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Tuinen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquot</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gollotte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gianinazzi-Pearson</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Characterization of root colonization profiles by a microcosm community of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi using 25s rDNA-targeted nested PCR.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>879</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>887</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-294x.1998.00410.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9691489?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9691489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandesompele</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Preter</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattyn</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poppe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Roy</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Paepe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Accurate normalization of real-time quantitative RT-PCR data by geometric averaging of multiple internal control genes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>:<issue>RESEARCH0034</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2002-3-7-research0034</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12184808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12184808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varela-Cervero</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barea</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;pik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azc&#x000f3;n-Aguilar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The composition of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungal communities differs among the roots, spores and extraradical mycelia associated with five Mediterranean plant species.</article-title>
<source><italic>Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>2882</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2895</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.12810</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25677957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25677957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walder</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niemann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiemken</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Mycorrhizal networks: common goods of plants shared under unequal terms of trade.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>159</volume>
<fpage>789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>797</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.195727</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22517410?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22517410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Statistical methods for detecting differentially abundant features in clinical metagenomic samples.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Comput. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>:<issue>e1000352</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000352</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19360128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19360128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>T. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The roles of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) in phytoremediation and tree-herb interactions in Pb contaminated soil.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>20469</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep20469</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26842958?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26842958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banba</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>CYCLOPS, a mediator of symbiotic intracellular accommodation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>105</volume>
<fpage>20540</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20545</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0806858105</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19074278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19074278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Positive feedback between mycorrhizal fungi and plants influences plant invasion success and resistance to invasion.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>:<issue>e12380</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012380</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20808770?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20808770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>