<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with OASIS Tables v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing-oasis-article1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mycobiology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mycobiology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TMYB</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tmyb20</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Mycobiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1229-8093</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2092-9323</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6319468</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/12298093.2018.1542970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1542970</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genomic Insights into the Rice Blast Fungus through Estimation of Gene Emergence Time in Phylogenetic Context</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">J. Choi ET&#x000a0;AL.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2206-4593</contrib-id><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Jaeyoung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Jong-Joon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0617-4007</contrib-id><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>Junhyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><label>a</label><institution>Convergence Research Center for Smart Farm Solution, Korea Institute of Science and Technology</institution>, Gangneung25451, <country>Korea</country>; </aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>b</label><institution>Department of Biotechnology, College of Life and Applied Sciences, Yeungnam University</institution>, Gyeongsan, Gyeongbuk38541, <country>Korea</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="AUFN1"><p>Supplemental data for this article can be accessed <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/12298093.2018.1542970">here</ext-link>.</p></fn><corresp id="AN0001">CONTACT Junhyun Jeon <email>jjeon@yu.ac.kr</email><institution>Department of Biotechnology, College of Life and Applied Sciences, Yeungnam University</institution>, Gyeongsan, Gyeongbuk38541, <country>Korea</country></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage seq="8">361</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group on behalf of the Korean Society of Mycology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="tmyb-46-1542970.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The rice blast fungus, <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>, is an important pathogen of rice plants. It is well known that genes encoded in the genome have different evolutionary histories that are related to their functions. Phylostratigraphy is a method that correlates the evolutionary origin of genes with evolutionary transitions. Here we applied phylostratigraphy to partition total gene content of <italic>M. oryzae</italic> into distinct classes (phylostrata), which we designated PS1 to PS7, based on estimation of their emergence time. Genes in individual phylostrata did not show significant biases in their global distribution among seven chromosomes, but at the local level, clustering of genes belonging to the same phylostratum was observed. Our phylostrata-wide analysis of genes revealed that genes in the same phylostratum tend to be similar in many physical and functional characteristics such as gene length and structure, GC contents, codon adaptation index, and level of transcription, which correlates with biological functions in evolutionary context. We also found that a significant proportion of genes in the genome are orphans, for which no orthologs can be detected in the database. Among them, we narrowed down to seven orphan genes having transcriptional and translational evidences, and showed that one of them is implicated in asexual reproduction and virulence, suggesting ongoing evolution in this fungus through lineage-specific genes. Our results provide genomic basis for linking functions of pathogenicity factors and gene emergence time.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>rice blast fungus</kwd><kwd>gene emergence time</kwd><kwd>phylostratigraphy</kwd><kwd>evolution</kwd><kwd>orphan genes</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Yeungnam University</named-content><named-content content-type="funderidentifier">10.13039/501100002649</named-content></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by 2016 Yeungnam University Research Grant.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="4538"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0001"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> is one of the best studied fungal pathogens, largely because of agricultural and food security relevance of the rice blast disease it causes, in addition to the fundamental studies that have contributed broadly to our understanding of development and pathogenesis in the fungal pathogens of plants [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. <italic>M. oryzae</italic> initiates its infection on plant by disseminating asexual spore, conidium. Conidium that lands on plant leaf surface germinates and starts to develop a specialized infection structure called appressorium at the germ tube apex upon recognition of surface hardness and hydrophobicity [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Using appressorium, the fungus mechanically penetrates into and grows inside the plant tissues [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Such invasive growth ultimately leads to formation of visible leaf lesions, which can result in significant yield losses or even death of entire plant [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The genome sequences of <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolates and related species have already provided valuable knowledge about genetic mechanisms and evolution of fungal pathogenesis [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. To date, more than hundred genes implicated in fungal development and pathogenesis were identified and characterized in the fungus [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Phylostratigraphy is a method that allows researchers to study the characteristics of genes over time in the context of grouping of genes by their phylogenetic origin [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Phylostratigraphy is devised based on the observations that comparison of genome sequences shows that a significant proportion of genes in the genome occur only in delimited evolutionary lineages. This points out that such genes have arisen during the evolution of the corresponding lineages, potentially contributing to lineage-specific adaptation. Phylostratigraphy approaches have been used to answer interesting questions such as tracking origin of cancer genes in metazoan lineages and delineating birth of new genes [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11&#x02013;13</xref>]. Recently, comparative genomics for four species of <italic>Armillaria</italic> (fungal forest pathogens) took advantage of phylostratigraphic approach to show that rhizomorphs express an evolutionarily young transcriptome [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Lineage-specific genes are often called orphan genes or taxonomically restricted genes, and considered to originate from two mechanisms: duplication-divergence model and <italic>de novo</italic> model. Duplication-divergence model posits that genes are duplicated and undergo fast divergence, providing raw materials for functional innovation [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Such duplication and rearrangement mechanisms have long been thought to be the primary driving force of gene evolution. In contrast, <italic>de novo</italic> model, which recently emerges as an additional important mechanism, predicts that genes can arise from non-coding genomic regions [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Lineage-specific genes are known to be involved in lineage-specific adaptations or evolutionary transitions [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>Here in this study, we took advantage of phylostratigraphy approach for dissection of gene repertoire in the genome of <italic>M. oryzae</italic>. Instead of rigorous statistical analysis, however, we applied the concept of mapping gene emergence time across a defined phylogeny. Such breakdown of genes by their evolutionary age showed that physical and functional characteristics of genes correlate with their ages. Analysis on evolutionary ages of known pathogenicity genes suggested that our efforts to understand fungal pathogenesis at the molecular level are biased toward the genes that are highly conserved among diverse organisms. Orphan genes, for which no orthologs can be found in the database, accounted for a significant fraction of <italic>M. oryzae</italic> genome, and yet their functions, in most cases, were obscure. We provided an example of orphan gene that are implicated in fungal pathogenicity, suggesting that at least some of the orphan genes are recent addition to the genome for evolution of fungal pathogenesis.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0003"><label>2.1.</label><title>Estimation of gene emergence time in the phylogenetic context</title><p>Seven different phylogenetic levels were defined, based on phylogeny in MycoCosm (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genome.jgi.doe.gov/programs/fungi/">https://genome.jgi.doe.gov/programs/fungi/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. We chose major evolutionary transitions leading to the <italic>M. oryzae</italic> lineages, resulting in seven phylogenetic strata (phylostrata). In order to estimate emergence time of protein-coding genes, the predicted protein sequences of <italic>M. oryzae</italic> 70&#x02013;15 were obtained from MycoCosm. The protein sequences were subjected to BLASTP search against the NCBI nr database with the cutoff threshold of 1e<sup>-5</sup> [<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. For each BLASTP hit, the taxon in which the target sequence belongs to was retrieved by using NCBI taxonomy database [<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Subsequently, each protein sequence was assigned into one of the seven phylogenetic strata (phylostrata) to investigate major evolutionary transitions leading to the <italic>M. oryzae</italic> lineages. Each protein sequence was assigned into one of the seven taxonomic levels (phylostrata) if the number of total significant hits becomes equal to that of the corresponding phylostratum.</p></sec><sec id="s0004"><label>2.2.</label><title>Analysis of gene structure and function</title><p>Genome annotation information was downloaded from Magnaporthe Comparative Genomics Project website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/scientific-community/science/projects/fungal-genome-initiative/magnaporthe-comparative-genomics-proj/">https://www.broadinstitute.org/scientific-community/ sci ence/projects/fungal-genome-initiative/magnaporthe-co mparative-genomics-proj/</ext-link>). Comparison and statistical analysis of gene structure and function were performed using packages available in R programming environment [<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. GC content and amino acid composition of proteins were analyzed using &#x0201c;seqinr&#x0201d; package. For calculation of codon adaptation index (CAI), codon table for <italic>Magnaporthe</italic> was downloaded from the codon usage database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kazusa.or.jp/codon/">http://www.kazusa.or.jp/codon/</ext-link>) and used for calculation of CAI in R. Hydropathy index was calculated using functions built in &#x0201c;Peptides&#x0201d; package. Transcript abundance of genes in mycelia tissue was obtained from a previous study [<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and used for comparing phylostrata-wise transcription levels of genes. Circular representation of genomes and genes were drawn using &#x0201c;circlize&#x0201d; package. Gene ontology analysis was carried out using topGO package. Analyses of putative secreted proteins were performed using the data obtained from Fungal Secretome Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fsd.snu.ac.kr/">http://fsd.snu.ac.kr/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><label>2.3.</label><title>Targeted deletion of orphan genes</title><p>For targeted deletion of orphan genes, gene deletion construct was designed for targeted replacement of ORF with hygromycin B phosphotransferase gene (HPH) cassette by homologous recombination. At least over 1&#x02009;kb regions flanking the 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; of the ORF were amplified and fused to the HPH sequence by fusion PCR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/12298093.2018.1542970">Table 1 in Supplementary Material</ext-link> for primer information on <italic>MoHKR1</italic> knockout). The construct was introduced to the wild-type KJ201 protoplasts by PEG-mediated transformation. Transformants were selected on solid TB3 media (0.3% yeast extract, 0.3% casamino acid, 1% glucose, 20% sucrose and 0.8% agar powder; all w/v) containing 200&#x02009;ppm hygromycin B and screened by PCR to identify successful deletion mutants with a single integration event. Genetic complementation was carried out by re-introducing ORF with the aforementioned flanking regions into the mutant protoplasts together with plasmid pII99 containing the geneticin resistance marker. Complementation strains were screened first on solid TB3 medium supplemented with 800&#x02009;ppm geneticin and then by PCR.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0006"><label>3.</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="s0007"><label>3.1.</label><title>Phylostratigraphy of M. oryzae genome</title><p>The phylostratigraphic approach was used to estimate emergence time of each of 12,832 annotated protein-coding loci in the genome of <italic>M. oryzae</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/12298093.2018.1542970">Figure 1 and Table 2 in Supplementary Material</ext-link>). Alternative splicing was not considered here in our analysis. In phylostratigraphic approach using BLASTP, e-value cutoff was set to 1e<sup>-5</sup>. BLAST was shown to be sensitive enough to detect orthologs among distantly related species, and e-value threshold of &#x0003c;1e<sup>-3</sup> is known to provide optimal compromise between sensitivity and accuracy [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Seven phylogenetic classes (phylostrata) were defined according to consensus phylogenetic relationship (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genome.jgi.doe.gov/programs/fungi/">https://genome.jgi.doe.gov/programs/fungi/</ext-link>). The first phylostratum (PS1) represents genes that underlie the basis of all cellular life, while the last phylostratum represents lineage-specific genes leading to <italic>M. oryzae</italic>. Intermediate phylostrata (PS2 to PS6) correspond to major evolutionary events such as split of Ascomycota fungi from Dikarya. We checked out our results by two methods. First, we examined placement of histone-modifying enzymes in phylostrata. Histone-modifying enzymes such as histone acetyltransferase (HAT), histone deacetylase (HDAC), histone methyltransferase (HMT), and histone demethylase (HME) should be related to evolution of eukaryotes. Our data are congruent with evolution of such eukaryotic histone-modifying system by placing these enzymes only in PS2 and PS3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/12298093.2018.1542970">Figure 1 in Supplementary Material</ext-link>) [<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Some of the histone-modifying enzymes in PS3 indicates that they are fungal-specific histone-modifying enzymes. Indeed, Rtt109 among them is a well-known fungal-specific histone acetyltransferase that has attracted attention as a potential anti-fungal drug target. We also examined placement of a well-characterized pathogenicity factor, <italic>DES1</italic>, which is known to be Pezizomycotina-specific [<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. We found that DES1 is located in PS6. Taken together, these results suggest that our data is reliable and accurate enough for further analyses.</p><fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Estimation of gene emergence time through phylogenetic distribution of genes using BLASTP search. (A) Diagram summarizing the process of gene emergence time estimation. (B) Summary of phylogenetic distribution of genes according to BLASTP results. Nodes marked by gray circle represent evolutionary lineages leading to <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>. Phylostrata corresponding to fungal lineages were shaded with light blue. Horizontal bars represent number of genes that fall in the corresponding phylostrata.</p></caption><graphic content-type="colour" xlink:href="TMYB_A_1542970_F0001_C"/></fig><p>Our analysis shows that approximately 42% of annotated protein-coding genes in <italic>M. oryzae</italic> originated from prokaryotic and eukaryotic ancestors (PS1-2) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1(B)</xref>. The remaining genes emerged later in evolution of <italic>M. oryzae</italic>. Notably, we observed high peaks during split of eukaryotes to fungal lineages (PS2-3) and split of Ascomycota to Pezizomycotina (PS5-6). A high peak is also evident in PS7, which represents all genes that evolved in lineages leading to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> from Pezizomycotina ancestors. In particular, genes in PS7 might represent <italic>de novo</italic> evolved genes, since these genes are not found even in genomes of closely related plant pathogenic fungi such as <italic>M. poae</italic> and <italic>Gaeumannomyces graminis</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>The PS7 genes are <italic>M. oryzae</italic>-specific genes, of which orthologs cannot be found in database. Such genes are called orphans in many literatures. A previous study, where the same e-value threshold was applied for identification of orphan genes, reported that there are a total of 2,740 orphan genes in <italic>M. oryzae</italic> genome [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], in contrast to our estimation of 1,921 orphans. This discrepancy can be attributed to the size difference in the databases used for BLASTP search: NCBI nr vs. CFGP (Comparative Fungal Genomics Platform (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cfgp.riceblast.snu.ac.kr/">http://cfgp.riceblast.snu.ac.kr/</ext-link>)) [<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Since NCBI nr database covers much broader taxa and also contains meta-genomic sequences, it is likely that the estimation made in our study is much more accurate than the previous one.</p></sec><sec id="s0008"><label>3.2.</label><title>Distribution of genes across and within chromosomes</title><p>Following partitioning of protein-coding genes into the defined phylostrata, we asked if physical location of genes shows any correlation with phylostrata across and within chromosomes. Among seven chromosomes of <italic>M. oryzae</italic>, chromosome 2 is the longest (&#x0223c; 8.3&#x02009;Mb) and chromosome 7 is the shortest (3.4&#x02009;Mb). We found that genes in each phylostrata reside on seven chromosomes in proportion to the length of individual chromosomes <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2(A)</xref>, even though minor biases were detected in chromosome 2 and 7. For example, PS1 and PS7 genes were under-represented in chromosome 2, while PS7 genes were over-represented in chromosome 7.</p><fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Distribution of genes belonging to different phylostrata across and within seven chromosomes of <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>. (A) Distribution of genes across fungal chromosomes. Number of genes that correspond to individual phylostrata was marked by color codes. (B) Circular representation of gene distribution within chromosomes. Lines within each track represent genes in a particular phylostratum. The same color codes as in (A) were applied to the circular representation.</p></caption><graphic content-type="colour" xlink:href="TMYB_A_1542970_F0002_C"/></fig><p>We also checked if there are any biases in distribution of genes within individual chromosomes <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2(B)</xref>. However, we were not able to detect any large blocks enriched with genes from a particular phylostratum. This suggests that gene emergence appears to be randomly scattered across and within chromosomes regardless of their emergence time during evolution of <italic>M. oryzae</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s0009"><label>3.3.</label><title>Genomic features across ages</title><p>We used phylostratigraphic assignment to assess the trends over time for several physical, transcription- and/or translation-related features of genes and their protein products. With respect to physical features, gene length, GC content, hydrophobicity and amino acid composition were examined. Gene length and GC content showed tendency to decrease gradually from &#x0201c;old genes&#x0201d; (PS1-3) to &#x0201c;new genes&#x0201d; (PS7) with some exceptions (top panel in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>). However, hydrophobicity of protein products did not seem to be different among phylostrata. Unlike duplication-divergence model of gene birth, the <italic>de novo</italic> model predicts that younger genes should be shorter than older genes, since it is highly unlikely that proteins from new genes achieve high degree of complexity <italic>de novo</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In combination with the fact that genes are often characterized by having a higher GC content than the GC content of entire genome, observed length dependence over time suggests significant contribution of <italic>de novo</italic> gene birth to evolution of <italic>M. oryzae</italic> genome. Interestingly, we found that proteins encoded by orphan genes (PS7) have considerably higher cysteine residues than ones from other phylostrata (middle panel in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>). High cysteine content was reported in proteins that are secreted into extracellular milieu [<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], suggesting that orphan genes may be enriched with such secreted proteins. However, our analysis did not detect any particular enrichment of putative secreted proteins in PS7 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/12298093.2018.1542970">Figure 2 in Supplementary Material</ext-link>). It is worth noting that at least experimentally characterized secreted proteins were enriched in PS6 and PS7 (among 20 proteins, 11 and 3 were found in PS6 and PS7, respectively).</p><fig id="F0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Physical and functional features of genes across phylostrata. Top panels represent distributions of gene length, GC content and hydropathy index in different phylostrata. Middle panel shows amino acid composition in proteins according to phylostrata. Bottom panels represent distribution of codon adaptation index, transcript abundance and number of Interpro domains in proteins across phylostrata.</p></caption><graphic content-type="colour" xlink:href="TMYB_A_1542970_F0003_C"/></fig><p>CAI, which measures codon usage bias, exhibited no age dependence among phylostrata [<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Only PS7 has significantly lower CAI value distribution (bottom left panel in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>). Transcript abundance in hyphal tissue, however, again showed time-dependent trend: the older genes are, the more they tend to be expressed (bottom middle panel in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>). These observations may reflect degree of functional contributions that genes make to the cells. In line with this, older genes tend to have higher number of functional domains, while younger genes tend to have no or less number of domains (bottom right panel in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>3.4.</label><title>Functional implications of gene age</title><p>Given the observed trends across phylostrata, we then asked how emergence time of genes is related to their functionalities, using gene ontology (GO) analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>). During our analysis, we noticed that it is not practical to investigate and compare genes from all phylostrata, since there are too many combinations for comparisons, and PS5 contains too small number of genes to draw any statistically meaningful conclusion. Therefore, phylostrata were further grouped into three categories: ubiquitous, fungi, and orphan. We defined genes that are found in all cellular life forms and/or eukaryotes as ubiquitous (hereafter abbreviated as Ubi). Fungi group of genes is ones that are present only in fungal species. Orphans are <italic>M. oryzae</italic>-specific genes.</p><fig id="F0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Summary of GO enrichment analysis (biological process) for Ubi, Fungi, and Orphan groups. GO terms that are enriched with a particular group of genes are shown (Fisher&#x02019;s exact test, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). Area of circle represents the number of genes assigned to the particular GO term. Color of the circle indicates the proportion of genes assigned to the GO term in our data set among the total number of genes having that GO term in the genome.</p></caption><graphic content-type="colour" xlink:href="TMYB_A_1542970_F0004_C"/></fig><p>GO analysis showed that Ubi gene group is enriched with functions that are generally required for cells to be cells, such as single-organism cellular process, primary metabolic process, protein modification process, and macromolecule modification, just to name a few (top panel in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>). GO terms enriched in fungi gene group fall broadly under three categories: nucleotide acid metabolism process and gene expression, developmental processes such as mycelium development, and probably secondary metabolite-related processes (middle panel in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>). This might suggest that evolution of fungal species should involve expansion in metabolic capacities and gene expression regulation that are likely to be linked to fungal-specific developmental program. However, in orphan gene group, there is no enrichment of particular GO terms except single-organism process (note that p-value is greater than 0.01 in all cases but one), since orphan genes are usually lacking functional domain structures and rarely characterized so far, making it difficult for us to judge significance of our observation (bottom panel in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0011"><label>3.5.</label><title>Analysis of orphan genes in fungal pathogenesis</title><p>Most of published molecular genetics studies on pathogenicity genes in <italic>M. oryzae</italic> took reverse genetics approaches, where genes of well-characterized orthologs in other organisms are identified from <italic>M. oryzae</italic> genome and analyzed in the context of fungal development and pathogenesis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/12298093.2018.1542970">Figure 3 in Supplementary Material</ext-link>). As a result, orphan genes are rarely studied to date, although they accounts for considerable portion of current genome annotation. The fact that such biases are evident even in large-scale forward genetics studies (such as <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic>-mediated transformation (ATMT) project) [<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] suggests either that orphan genes are not actually genes encoding functional proteins or that lack of protein products encoded by orphan genes has negligible effects on overall fungal fitness. To eliminate the first possibility, we took advantage of some proteomic data that are publicly available [<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34&#x02013;37</xref>]. For translational evidence, we combined and used these multiple published proteomics data. For transcriptional evidence, we used RNA-seq data generated for mycelia tissue [<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. When we screened for orphan genes having translational evidences, we found seven genes from our orphan gene list (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/12298093.2018.1542970">Table 3 in Supplementary Material</ext-link>). Five among these seven genes showed no or little transcription in mycelia tissue (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/12298093.2018.1542970">Table 4 in Supplementary Material</ext-link>), which is consistent with their translational evidences being found in germinating conidia.</p><p>To delve into their roles during fungal development and pathogenesis, we attempted targeted gene knockout approach for all seven genes. For only four genes, however, we were able to successfully construct knockout vector and obtain candidate knockout mutants (data not shown). Subsequent phenotype screening revealed that deletion of one gene, which we designated <italic>MoHKR1</italic>, could cause detectable phenotypic changes. Although &#x00394;<italic>Mohkr1</italic> was comparable to the wild-type in radial growth <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0005">Figure 5(A)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0005">5(B)</xref>, the mutant was not able to produce as many conidia as the wild-type counterpart <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0005">Figure 5(C)</xref> and was much less virulent on its host plant, rice <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0005">Figure 5(D)</xref>. Such defects could be complemented by introduction of wild-type copy of gene back into the mutant. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report showing involvement of orphan genes in fungal pathogenesis. These data suggest that at least some orphan genes are likely to be <italic>bona fide</italic> protein-coding genes playing important, lineage-specific roles in the rice blast fungus.</p><fig id="F0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Characterization of an orphan gene, <italic>MoHKR1</italic> using gene knockout approach. (A) Comparison of vegetative growth among strains on oatmeal agar plates. (B) Bar graph showing colony diameter at 3-, 6-, and 9-day post inoculation. (C) Asexual reproduction of different strains measured by number of spores produced on oatmeal agar cultures. (D) Representative image of pathogenicity assay results. Pathogenicity assay was carried out by placing agar blocks containing fungal cultures on susceptible rice cultivar Nagdongbyeo.</p></caption><graphic content-type="colour" xlink:href="TMYB_A_1542970_F0005_C"/></fig></sec><sec id="s0012"><label>3.6.</label><title>Concluding remarks</title><p>In this study, we categorized entire genome into discrete classes, depending on their estimated emergence time. One major concern in our analysis is whether BLASTP is sensitive enough to detect most remote homologues. However, a previous study examining capacity of BLAST through simulation to detect proteins of diverse evolutionary rates showed that BLAST only misses homologues of extremely fast-evolving sequences [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Therefore, it is reasonable to assume that BLAST would not produce a particular bias toward certain phylostrata.</p><p>Our data suggested that emergence time of genes over evolutionary time scale is associated with physical and functional features of the genes. We argue that this type of analysis could be a potentially powerful tool to provide evolutionary insights into genetic basis of a particular trait such as fungal pathogenesis. Although studies of fungal pathogenesis so far are biased toward highly conserved genes, other data suggest ancient origin of gene functions involved in fungal development and pathogenesis. At the same time, our study illuminates the importance of monitoring new genes (orphan genes) in predicting evolutionary trajectory of fungal pathogenesis.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3679"><caption><title>Supplemental Material</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" xlink:href="TMYB_A_1542970_SM3679.zip" orientation="portrait" id="d37e121" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="s0013"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>On the trail of a cereal killer: exploring the biology of <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic></article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>202</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Kan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The top 10 fungal pathogens in molecular plant pathology</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>414</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>430</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22471698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Under pressure: investigating the biology of plant infection by <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Micro</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valent</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Breaking and entering: host penetration by the fungal rice blast pathogen <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic></article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>512</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8905089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kankanala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Czymmek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valent</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Roles for rice membrane dynamics and plasmodesmata during biotrophic invasion by the blast fungus</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>706</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>724</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17322409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gladieux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Condon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ravel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Gene flow between divergent cereal- and grass-specific lineages of the rice blast fungus <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title>. <source>mBio</source>. 2018;9:e01219&#x02013;17.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of the genomes of two field isolates of the rice blast fungus <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e1002869</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22876203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuzick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>PHI-base: a new interface and further additions for the multi-species pathogen-host interactions database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>D604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>DD10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27915230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuzick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Using the pathogen-host interactions database (PHI-base) to investigate plant pathogen genomes and genes implicated in virulence</article-title>. <source>Front Plant Sci</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>:605.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Domazet-Lo&#x00161;o</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brajkovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tautz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A phylostratigraphy approach to uncover the genomic history of major adaptations in metazoan lineages</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>539</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18029048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neme</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tautz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phylogenetic patterns of emergence of new genes support a model of frequent de novo evolution</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23433480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Domazet-Loso</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tautz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phylostratigraphic tracking of cancer genes suggests a link to the emergence of multicellularity in metazoa</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>66</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20492640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moyers</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluating phylostratigraphic evidence for widespread De Novo gene birth in genome evolution</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1256</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26758516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sipos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prasanna</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Genome expansion and lineage-specific genetic innovations in the forest pathogenic fungi <italic>Armillaria</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat Ecol Evol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1941</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29085064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conant</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Turning a hobby into a job: How duplicated genes find new functions</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>938</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>950</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tautz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Domazet-Loso</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The evolutionary origin of orphan genes</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>692</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>702</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21878963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Domazet-Loso</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tautz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An evolutionary analysis of orphan genes in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>2213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14525923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grigoriev</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikitin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haridas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>MycoCosm portal: gearing up for 1000 fungal genomes</article-title>. <source>Nucl Acids Res</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>D699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D704</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>215</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coordinators</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Database resources of the National Center for Biotechnology Information</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>D8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29140470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Team</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide profiling of DNA methylation provides insights into epigenetic regulation of fungal development in a plant pathogenic fungus</article-title>. <source><italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>. Sci Rep</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>8567</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25708804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Fungal secretome database: integrated platform for annotation of fungal secretomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20146824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>On homology searches by protein blast and the characterization of the age of genes</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17408474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Postberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forcob</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The evolutionary history of histone H3 suggests a deep eukaryotic root of chromatin modifying mechanisms</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20738881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brosch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loidl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graessle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Histone modifications and chromatin dynamics: a focus on filamentous fungi</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>439</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18221488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>A novel pathogenicity gene is required in the rice blast fungus to suppress the basal defenses of the host</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e1000401</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19390617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okagaki</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sailsbery</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Genome sequences of three phytopathogenic species of the Magnaporthaceae family of fungi</article-title>. <source>G3 (Bethesda)</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>2539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2545</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26416668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mir</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Analysis of in planta expressed orphan genes in the rice blast fungus <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Pathol J</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25506301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>CFGP: a web-based, comparative fungal genomics platform</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>D562</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D571</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Kingdom-wide analysis of fungal small secreted proteins (SSPs) reveals their potential role in host association</article-title>. <source>Front Plant Sci</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>186</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26925088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erill</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Relative codon adaptation: a generic codon bias index for prediction of gene expression</article-title>. <source>DNA Res</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20453079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide functional analysis of pathogenicity genes in the rice blast fungus</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>565</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17353894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franck</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gokce</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Temporal analysis of the <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> proteome during conidial germination and cyclic AMP (cAMP)-mediated appressorium formation</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2265</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23665591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gokce</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franck</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>In-depth analysis of the <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> conidial proteome</article-title>. <source>J Proteome Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>5827</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5835</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23039028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Proteome analysis of rice blast fungus (<italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic>) proteome during appressorium formation</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>3579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3587</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15378734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhadauria</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Proteomic changes associated with deletion of the <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> conidial morphology-regulating gene COM1</article-title>. <source>Biol Direct</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21040590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>