<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rice (N Y)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rice (N Y)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Rice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1939-8425</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1939-8433</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6081827</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30073557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">232</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12284-018-0232-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>OsRACK1A</italic>, encodes a circadian clock-regulated WD40 protein, negatively affect salt tolerance in rice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Dongping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yuzhu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Jinyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Jianfeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Dahong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Weifeng</given-names></name><address><email>wfxu@fafu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7080-9532</contrib-id><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Jiansheng</given-names></name><address><email>liangjs@sustc.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.268415.c</institution-id><institution>Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Crop Genetics and Physiology/Co-Innovation Center for Modern Production Technology of Grain Crop, </institution><institution>Yangzhou University, </institution></institution-wrap>Yangzhou, 225009 Jiangsu China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 2876</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256111.0</institution-id><institution>College of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, </institution></institution-wrap>Jinshan, Fuzhou, 350002 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1761 0120</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.459575.f</institution-id><institution>Department of Biological Engineering, </institution><institution>Huanghuai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Zhumadian, 463000 Henan China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Biology, Southern University of Science and Technology, Shenzhen, 518055 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>45</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The receptor for activated C kinase 1 (RACK1) is a WD40 type protein that is involved in multiple signaling pathways and is conserved from prokaryotes to eukaryotes. Here we report that rice <italic>RACK1A</italic> (<italic>OsRACK1A</italic>) is regulated by circadian clocks and plays an important role in the salt stress response. <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> was found to follow a rhythmic expression profile under circadian conditions at both the transcription and the translation levels, although the expression was arrhythmic under salt stress. Analysis of plant survival rates, fresh weight, proline content, malondialdehyde, and chlorophyll showed that suppression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> enhanced tolerance to salt stress. The ion concentration in both roots and leaves revealed that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-suppressed transgenic rice could maintain low Na<sup>+</sup> and high K<sup>+</sup> concentrations. Furthermore, <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-suppressed transgenic rice accumulated significantly more abscisic acid (ABA) and more transcripts of ABA- and stress-inducible genes compared with the wild-type plants. Real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction analysis revealed that many stress-related genes, including APETALA 2/Ethylene Responsive Factor (AP2/ERF) transcription factors, were upregulated in the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-suppressed transgenic rice line. We identified putative interactors of OsRACK1A, and found that OsRACK1A interacted with many salt stress-responsive proteins directly. These results suggest that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> is regulated by circadian rhythm, and involved in the regulation of salt stress responses.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12284-018-0232-3) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>OsRACK1A</kwd><kwd>Salt tolerance</kwd><kwd>Circadian</kwd><kwd>Rice</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31271622</award-id><award-id>31422047</award-id><award-id>31601230</award-id><award-id>31761130073</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Dongping</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Weifeng</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Jiansheng</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Natural Science Research Project for Colleges and Universities in Jiangsu Province </institution></funding-source><award-id>16KJB210013</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Dongping</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Jiangsu Province College Students Innovation Training Program in 2016</institution></funding-source><award-id>X20160741</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par22">The receptor for activated C kinase 1 (RACK1) is a member of the WD repeat-containing scaffold proteins and is conserved from prokaryotes to eukaryotes (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2013</xref>). As a scaffolding protein, RACK1 protein interacts with many proteins and is involved in multiple signaling pathways (McCahill et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2002</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2013</xref>). In plants, <italic>RACK1</italic> is involved in diverse biological processes, such as seed germination, organ development, hormones and stress responses (Nakashima et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>; Guo et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2011</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2014</xref>). Compared with the advances made from studies in metazoans and yeast, little is known about the molecular mechanisms of <italic>RACK1</italic> in plants.</p><p id="Par23">The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome contains three <italic>RACK1</italic> orthologues, <italic>RACK1A</italic>, <italic>RACK1B</italic> and <italic>RACK1C</italic>, which are ~&#x02009;78% similar to mammalian <italic>RACK1</italic> (Guo and Chen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>). Using loss-of-function mutants of <italic>RACK1A</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, Chen et al.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2006</xref>) found that <italic>AtRACK1A</italic> plays a role in several plant hormonal responses, including abscisic acid (ABA), gibberellin (GA), indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), and brassinosteroid (BR). There is direct and indirect evidence that <italic>RACK1s</italic> are involved in the regulation of plant tolerance to abiotic and biotic stresses (Kundu et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2013</xref>; Cheng et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2015</xref>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the <italic>rack1a</italic> mutant strongly tolerates soil drying, compared with the wild-type (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2013</xref>). Moreover, water loss in detached leaves and stomatal conductance of <italic>rack1</italic> mutants were significantly lower than in the wild-type, and the endogenous ABA content of <italic>rack1a</italic> mutants was higher than in the wild-type (Guo et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2009</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2013</xref>). In addition, <italic>rack1a</italic> mutants were hypersensitive to ABA in serval developmental processes, such as seed germination, cotyledon greening, and root growth, and some ABA-responsive marker genes were upregulated in <italic>rack1a</italic> mutants, while the <italic>RACK1</italic> genes were downregulated by ABA (Guo et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2009</xref>). These results suggest that <italic>RACK1</italic> functions as a negative regulator of ABA signaling and consequently enhances drought stress tolerance via ABA-dependent signaling in response to water stress in plants. Comparative proteomic analysis showed that the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RACK1C protein might play roles in regulating plant resistance to salt stress (Shi et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2011</xref>).</p><p id="Par24">The rice genome contains two <italic>RACK1</italic> homologous genes that are ~&#x02009;80% similar to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RACK1 proteins at the amino acid level: <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> and <italic>OsRACK1B</italic> (Nakashima et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>). Li et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2009</xref>) found that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-suppressed transgenic rice lines were more tolerant of soil drying, but the molecular mechanism remains unknown. Comparative phosphoproteomics studies revealed that the OsRACK1A protein is phosphorylated in response to exogenous ABA and drought treatment (He et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2008</xref>; Ke et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2009</xref>). These findings suggested that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> plays essential roles in ABA signaling and is involved in ABA-dependent stress responses. In addition to the involvement of <italic>RACK1</italic> in the regulation of plant responses to abiotic stresses, it has been reported to function in plant innate immunity. Overexpression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> enhanced the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) and increased resistance to blast fungus in rice (Nakashima et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>). <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> regulated ROS levels not only in abiotic stress responses but also in the seed germination process. Previously, we found that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> positively regulated seed germination by promoting H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production and enhancing ABA catabolism (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2014</xref>). Although <italic>RACK1</italic> functions in ABA signaling in both rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, it is still unclear whether <italic>RACK1</italic> is involved directly in ABA-dependent stress responses.</p><p id="Par25">Circadian clocks are 24-h biological oscillators, which generally enable organisms to coordinate their activities with the external light/dark cycles by anticipating the onset of dawn or dusk. In mammals, RACK1 protein plays a crucial role in circadian clocks by interacting with BMAL1, a component of the heterodimeric CLOCK:BMAL1 circadian complex. However, the expression of <italic>RACK1</italic> itself showed little or no circadian variation across the circadian cycle (Robles et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2010</xref>). In plants, no clock component has been reported to interact with RACK1 protein and whether plant <italic>RACK1</italic> is involved directly in circadian clock regulation has yet to be investigated. In this study, our results indicated that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> is a circadian rhythm gene and is involved in the response to salt stress. <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-suppressed transgenic plants were hyposensitive to salt stress, compared with wild-type Nipponbare. OsRACK1A plays an important role in the tolerance to high salinity by regulating many stress-related genes and interacting directly with many stress-response proteins.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant materials and stress treatment</title><p id="Par26">Rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. cv. Nipponbare) was used as the wild-type (non-transgenic line; NTL) and in the generation of all transgenic plants. All transgenic rice lines were generated and kept in our laboratory. An <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> over-expressing transgenic line, OeTL3&#x02013;8, and an RNA-interfered transgenic line, RiTL4&#x02013;2, were used as experimental materials (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2014</xref>). For NaCl treatment, 4-week-old hydroponic cultured rice plants were placed in different concentrations of NaCl solution (100, 150, 200&#x000a0;mM) for 10&#x02013;20 d and finally determined 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treated with 18 d and recovered for 10 d was the best condition for identifying stress phenotypes. All the plants grew in a plant growth chamber (Conviron atc26, 16&#x000a0;h light/ 8&#x000a0;h dark, 30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x000a0;day/ 22&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C night).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Measurements o<bold>f</bold> physiological index</title><p id="Par27">For the tolerance experiments, all rice plants were cultured in a plant growth chamber (Conviron atc26) (30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x000a0;day / 22&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C night). The survival rate and fresh weight were calculated after 18 d of treatment with 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl and recovery in normal conditions for another 10 d. Lipid peroxidation was determined by measuring the MDA content (Dhindsa and Matowe, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1981</xref>). The content of free proline in leaves was determined as described previously. (Bates et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1973</xref>) Chlorophyll was extracted from the leaves in 10&#x000a0;mL of 80% acetone for 16&#x000a0;h in the dark and was determined by measuring the absorbance at 652&#x000a0;nm (Arnon, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1949</xref>). To measure the Na<sup>+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> concentrations, 2-week-old hydroponic cultured rice seedlings were supplemented with 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 24, 48, or 72&#x000a0;h. Shoots and roots were harvested at the indicated times and all physiological measurements were based on the procedure described by Yang et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2015</xref>). Measurement of water loss form detached leaves was performed as previously described by Zhang et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2015</xref>). The detached leaves of non-transgenic and transgenic rice lines were weighed at room temperature (~&#x02009;23&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) with 35% relative humidity. The endogenous ABA levels of rice leaves were measured based on the procedures described by Zhang et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2014</xref>). All of the data were subjected to Student&#x02019;s t-test analysis using SPSS ver. 13.0 (SPSS Company, Chicago, IL).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p id="Par28">The RNAprep Pure Plant Kit (cat. no. DP441; Tiangen Biotech) was used to extract total RNA from rice. Single-strand cDNAs were synthesized by using the HiScript Q RT SuperMix for qPCR kit (cat. no. R123; Vazyme). Transcript-level expression of each gene were measured by quantitative RT-PCR using a 7300 Real-Time PCR system (ABI), with the iTaq universal SYBR Green SuperMix (Bio-Rad), and normalized against the values obtained for housekeeping gene <italic>OsActin1</italic> (LOC_Os03g50890). Three biological replicates were performed for each experiment. Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2 lists the qRT-PCR primer sequences. All of the data were subjected to Student&#x02019;s t-test analysis using SPSS ver. 13.0 (SPSS Company, Chicago, IL).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Protein blot analysis</title><p id="Par29">Rice leaves of seedlings were ground in liquid nitrogen and homogenized in PBS buffer (cat. no. CW0040S; CoWin Bioscience) containing complete protease inhibitor cocktail (cat. no. 04693132001; Roche). To prepare total protein, the homogenate was centrifuged (6000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic>, 30&#x000a0;min, 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) to remove cellular debris. Then, proteins were separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) on 10% gels and blotted onto polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membranes. The antibodies used were anti-&#x003b2;-actin antibody (cat. no. CW0264M; CoWin Bioscience), anti-green fluorescence protein (GFP) antibody (cat. no. ab290; Abcam), and anti-OsRACK1A antibody (cat. no. AbP80112-A-SE; Beijing Protein Innovation).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Co-IP assay</title><p id="Par30">To identify the OsRACK1A interaction proteins, <italic>UBI::GFP</italic> and <italic>UBI::GFP-OsRACK1A</italic> transgenic rice were used for co-IP assays. Leaves from 4-week-old plants were harvested and ground in liquid nitrogen. Proteins were extracted with the buffer containing 50&#x000a0;mM Tris (pH&#x000a0;7.5), 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 0.1% IGEPAL CA-630, Proteinase Inhibitor Cocktail (cat. no. 04693159001; Roche) and Phophatase Inhibitor Cocktail (cat. no. 04906845001). The samples were centrifuged at 12,000&#x000a0;g for 15&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and the supernatant was incubated with anti-GFP magnetic beads (catalog no. D153&#x02013;11; MBL) to overnight at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with gentle rotation. The beads were then washed four times with PBS. The immunoprecipitated proteins were eluted with 1&#x000a0;M glycine (pH&#x000a0;3.0). The presence of the corresponding proteins was detected by tandem liquid chromatograph-mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p id="Par31">Statistical analyses were performed using IBM SPSS Statistics 21 software (Chicago, IL, USA), and analyzed with one-way ANOVA. <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Expression of the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> gene is controlled in a circadian-clock like manner</title><p id="Par32">Information retrieved from the public microarray database (ArrayExpress, Accession: E-MTAB-275) showed that a circadian rhythm in <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> mRNA abundance occurred under photocycling (12&#x000a0;h light/12&#x000a0;h dark; 12&#x000a0;h hot/12&#x000a0;h hot; LDHH), thermocycling (12&#x000a0;h light/12&#x000a0;h light; 12&#x000a0;h hot/ 12&#x000a0;h cold; LLHC) or photocycling and thermocycling (12&#x000a0;h light/12&#x000a0;h dark; 12&#x000a0;h hot/12&#x000a0;h cold; LDHC) conditions (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1A). Another rice <italic>RACK1</italic> homolog, <italic>OsRACK1B</italic>, exhibited similar expression patterns (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1B). To confirm whether the expression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> was controlled by a circadian clock, the expression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> in a 24-h period was measured. Quantitative RT-PCR analysis showed that the transcript level of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> started accumulating with the onset of light and reached a maximum level 10&#x000a0;h after the lights were switched on (ZT0 and ZT24) and then the transcript level declined gradually and reached a minimum 6&#x000a0;h after the lights were switched off (ZT16 and ZT40, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). We also examined levels of OsRACK1A protein during the light/dark cycle using western blot analysis and the results revealed that OsRACK1A protein accumulated in the light (ZT0 to ZT14) and declined in the dark (ZT16 to ZT22, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). Moreover, we tested the expression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> under the constant light conditions and found that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> also displayed rhythmic expression (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1C).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Circadian clock-controlled <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> expression in rice. <bold>a</bold> Transcript analysis of the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> gene by qRT-PCR over a 48-h period. Rice plants were grown under 16&#x000a0;h light and 8&#x000a0;h dark in a growth chamber at a constant temperature of 28&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and sampled at regular intervals. <bold>b</bold> Immunoblot analysis of OsRACK1A protein over a 24-h period. <bold>c</bold>
<italic>OsRACK1A</italic> expression was monitored by immunoblot analysis in seedlings of a non-transgenic line (NTL), an <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-overexpressing transgenic line (OeTL3&#x02013;8), and an RNA-interfered transgenic line (RiTLs4&#x02013;2). <bold>d</bold> Protein levels of OsRACK1A in NTL, OeTL3&#x02013;8 and RiTLs4&#x02013;2 in light and dark. <bold>e</bold> Heading time distributions in transgenic rice plants grown in the field. During the heading period, the number of heading plants for each line was recorded every 3 days and compared. <bold>f</bold> Phenotypic comparison panicles during the heading period of transgenic plants. The rice plants had been grown in the field for 89 d. ZT, Zeitgeber Time. White and black rectangles indicate lights on and lights off, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_232_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Overexpression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> delays the time of heading</title><p id="Par33">Some circadian clock-controlled genes have been reported to be involved in photoperiodic flowering regulation (Xue et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2008</xref>; Ishikawa et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2011</xref>; Matsubara et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2011</xref>). To investigate whether <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> plays a role in photoperiod-controlled heading, we generated several <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> RNA-interference (RNAi) and overexpressing lines (Li et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2009</xref>). From these transgenic rice lines, we chose the stable downregulated RNA-interfered transgenic line RiTL4&#x02013;2, and the upregulated overexpressed transgenic line OeTL3&#x02013;8. Compared with the non-transgenic line (NTL), the OsRACK1A protein level was higher in OeTL3&#x02013;8 and lower in RiTL4&#x02013;2, measured by Western blot analysis using an OsRACK1A-specific antibody (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). This differential protein expression patterns of the three genotypes was occurred only in the light, whereas OsRACK1A protein was nearly undetectable in the dark (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). The heading date of field-grown plants was recorded and OeTL3&#x02013;8 had a heading date nearly 1 week later than NTL, whereas RiTL4&#x02013;2 showed a heading time approximately 1 week earlier than NTL (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>). The panicles phenotypes of field-grown plants at 95 d after germination are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>NaCl treatment affects expression of the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> gene</title><p id="Par34">To investigate the expression profile of the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> gene under salt stress, 2-week-old hydroponic cultured rice seedlings were exposed to 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for different times and the transcript-level expression of this gene was monitored using quantitative RT-PCR. The <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> expression pattern changed significantly in response to NaCl treatment. The transcript level of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> accumulated from ZT0 to ZT12 under both salt stress and control conditions, but expression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> was slightly higher under control than under salt stress conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Under normal conditions, the expression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> behaved like a circadian clock; when treated with NaCl, however, the transcription level of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> first increased to a relatively high level and then maintained this level throughout the experiment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>), which means that the circadian clock of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> expression disappeared when exposed to salt stress. The similar expression pattern of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> was shown under both light/dark cycle and constant light conditions with NaCl treatment (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1B). Interestingly, the protein level of OsRACK1A increased and was significantly higher than in the untreated control at 6, 12, 24, and 48&#x000a0;h after the onset of salt stress (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), whereas the transcript levels of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> were lower at ZT6 and ZT12 in the NaCl treatment than under control conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Salt stress-controlled <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> expression in rice. <bold>a</bold> Transcript analysis of the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> gene by qRT-PCR for a 48-h period under 0 and 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treatment. <bold>b</bold> Immunoblot analysis of OsRACK1A protein for a 24-h period under 0 and 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treatment. <bold>c</bold> GFP, OsRACK1A and a GFP-OsRACK1A fusion protein were monitored by immunoblot analysis in seedlings of <italic>UBI</italic>-promoted <italic>GFP</italic> and <italic>GFP-OsRACK1A</italic> transgenic rice. <bold>d</bold> GFP fluorescence was examined in roots of <italic>UBI</italic>-promoted <italic>GFP</italic> and <italic>GFP-OsRACK1A</italic> transgenic rice under 0 and 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treatment for 6&#x000a0;h. ZT, Zeitgeber Time. White and black rectangles indicate lights on and lights off, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_232_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par35">Therefore, we suspected that OsRACK1A protein levels were under post transcriptional and/or translational control. To test this, transgenic rice plants were generated that constitutively expressed GFP-OsRACK1A. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>, the GFP-OsRACK1A fusion protein was detected in ubiquitin-promoted <italic>GFP-OsRACK1A</italic> transgenic plants, whereas the GFP protein was detected in <italic>UBI::GFP</italic> transgenic plants. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref> shows fluorescence images of <italic>GFP-OsRACK1A</italic> transgenic plants in the presence or absence of 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 6&#x000a0;h. Control plants containing GFP alone showed no change in subcellular localization in response to salt stress (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). Furthermore, before salt treatment, plants containing GFP-OsRACK1A exhibited fluorescence that was detectable in the cytosolic fraction, as well as in the plasma membrane and nuclei. After treatment with 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl, GFP fluorescence from the GFP-OsRACK1A fusion was enhanced and appeared diffusely in the cytosol (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). These results supported the premise that OsRACK1A protein was controlled by post-transcriptional and/or translational regulation and accumulated under salt stress.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><italic>OsRACK1A</italic> negatively regulates salt tolerance</title><p id="Par36">Because both mRNA and protein levels of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> were induced by the high-salinity treatment, we used the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-overexpressing (OeTL3&#x02013;8) and RNAi (RiTL4&#x02013;2) lines to determine whether these different transgenic lines showed differences in performance under salt stress versus the NTL. Under normal conditions, transgenic plants showed no significant difference in growth versus the NTL. When 4-week-old plants were stressed with 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 18 d, the RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants had more green leaves than the OeTL3&#x02013;8 or NTL plants. After 18 d of high-salt treatment, all plants were subjected to normal irrigation (without salt stress) to allow recovery. Only RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants survived and resumed growth, forming new tillers, while OeTL3&#x02013;8 and NTL plants died during the 10-d recovery period (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). Twenty pots of plants were counted and the data showed that the survival rate of RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants was ~&#x02009;50%, whereas only ~&#x02009;20% of NTL plants survived. The lowest survival rate (&#x0003c;&#x02009;10%) was observed in OeTL3&#x02013;8 plants (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>). After 10 d of high-salinity treatment, the fresh weight of NTL was significantly higher than that of OeTL3&#x02013;8 and lower than that of RiTL4&#x02013;2 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). These results supported the notion that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> increases the salt stress response in rice.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><italic>OsRACK1A</italic> negatively regulates salt tolerance. <bold>a</bold> Comparison of the non-transgenic line (NTL), the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-overexpressing transgenic line (OeTL3&#x02013;8), and the RNA-interfered transgenic line (RiTLs4&#x02013;2) under 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 18 d (salt-stress recovery for 10 d). <bold>b</bold> Survival rate of plants after 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treatment and recovery. <bold>c</bold> Fresh weight of plants after 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treatment. <bold>d</bold> to <bold>f</bold> Contents of proline, MDA, and chlorophyll under 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 0, 24, 48 and 72&#x000a0;h. Sixty seedlings per genotype (twenty seedlings for each biological replicate) were used. Data shown are the means &#x000b1; SE of three biological replicates. An asterisk indicates a significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) versus stressed NTL</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_232_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par37">To evaluate the effects of salt stress on cell membranes, 4-week-old seedlings were treated with 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 24, 48, or 72&#x000a0;h and the malondialdehyde (MDA) content was measured. The RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants had lower MDA contents, whereas OeTL3&#x02013;8 contained more MDA than NTL under salt stress (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). The MDA contents indicated that cell membrane stability was reduced in the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-overexpressing line and increased in the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-RNAi line, versus the NTL under high-salinity stress. Most plants showed increased proline contents under salt-stress conditions, which was considered to be correlated with their stress resistance. In this study, the content of proline was increased after salt stress in plants. Compared with NTL plants, RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants accumulated higher levels of proline and OeTL3&#x02013;8 accumulated lower levels under 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treatment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e</xref>). It is known that salt stress causes chlorophyll degradation. We examined the chlorophyll content of rice plants exposed to 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3f</xref>, the chlorophyll content declined after salt stress. Compared with NTL plants, chlorophyll contents in RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants were higher, whereas those in OeTL3&#x02013;8 were lower under 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treatment. These results indicated that suppression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> enhanced salt-stress tolerance.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><italic>OsRACK1A</italic> regulates Na<sup>+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> levels under salt stress</title><p id="Par38">An important aspect of salt tolerance is the avoidance of Na<sup>+</sup> accumulation, and K<sup>+</sup> homeostasis is important for this process (Zhu, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2003</xref>). Four-week-old hydroponically grown transgenic and non-transgenic rice plants were subjected to 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 72&#x000a0;h. Subsequently, the leaves and roots were harvested at 0&#x000a0;h (before stress) and after 24, 48, and 72&#x000a0;h of salt stress, to measure Na<sup>+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> contents. Before the NaCl treatment, Na<sup>+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> levels in both shoots and roots of the plants with the three different genotypes were similar. The level of Na<sup>+</sup> increased continuously under salt stress in all plant lines tested. However, RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants accumulated significantly less Na<sup>+</sup> than the NTL, whereas OeTL3&#x02013;8 contained more Na<sup>+</sup> in both leaves and roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). In contrast to the Na<sup>+</sup> levels, the K<sup>+</sup> levels declined in the leaves and roots of all plant lines tested during salt stress. At 72&#x000a0;h of salt stress, the content of K<sup>+</sup> in RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants was higher than in NTL, whereas OeTL3&#x02013;8 contained less K<sup>+</sup> than NTL in leaves and roots (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). These results suggested that RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants might have the ability to avoid Na<sup>+</sup> accumulation and maintain K<sup>+</sup> homeostasis under high-salinity stress. It is generally accepted that the ability to maintain a high K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio contributes to salt tolerance in plants (Zhu, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2003</xref>). A decreasing K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio was detected in the roots and leaves of all plants under salt stress. However, a markedly higher K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio was observed in both shoots and roots of the RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants than those of the NTL and OeTL3&#x02013;8 plants, whereas no significant difference was observed under normal conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, b</xref>). These results imply that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> negatively regulates rice tolerance of NaCl largely by controlling the Na<sup>+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> accumulation in cells.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Na<sup>+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> contents in shoots and roots of various rice plants under salt stress. Ion content in leaf (<bold>a</bold>) and root tissue (<bold>b</bold>) of four-week-old NTL, OeTL3&#x02013;8 and RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants exposed to salt stress (150&#x000a0;mM NaCl) for 72&#x000a0;h. Values shown are for Na<sup>+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> together with changes in the K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio over time. Sixty seedlings per genotype (twenty seedlings for each biological replicate) were used. Data shown are the means &#x000b1; SE of three biological replicates. An asterisk indicates a significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) versus stressed NTL</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_232_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><italic>OsRACK1A</italic> regulates endogenous ABA content and ABA-responsive genes under salt stress</title><p id="Par39">The phytohormone ABA is a crucial regulator of plant growth and development, and plays a critical role in controlling adaptive plant responses to environmental stresses, such as drought, high salt stress, cold stress, and pathogen infection (Cutler et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2010</xref>; Umezawa et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2010</xref>). ABA accumulation and some ABA biosynthesis genes are upregulated by NaCl, drought, and cold stress (Cutler et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2010</xref>). We determined the endogenous ABA content of leaves under salt stress and found that the endogenous ABA content was significantly lower in OeTL3&#x02013;8, and significantly higher in RiTL4&#x02013;2 compared with that of NTL (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). The ABA content induced under stress conditions is regulated by the ABA biosynthesis 9-cis-epoxycarotenoid dioxygenase (<italic>NCED</italic>) genes (Xiong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2002</xref>). Our preliminary analysis showed that the transcript level of the <italic>OsNCED4</italic> and <italic>OsNCED5</italic> genes was dramatically induced under salt stress (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2). This study showed the transcript level of <italic>OsNCED4</italic> in RiTL4&#x02013;3 was ~&#x02009;1.5-fold those in NTL and OeTL3&#x02013;8, and the transcript level of <italic>OsNCED5</italic> was much higher in RiTL4&#x02013;3 than in NTL and OeTL3&#x02013;8 under stress conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><italic>OsRACK1A</italic> regulates ABA content and ABA-responsive genes under salt stress. <bold>a</bold> ABA content of various rice plants under normal and salt stress (150&#x000a0;mM NaCl). <bold>b</bold> Transcript level of ABA biosynthesis genes, <italic>OsNCED4</italic> and <italic>OsNCED5</italic> in various rice plants under normal and salt stress (150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 24&#x000a0;h). <bold>c</bold> Transcript level of ABA- and stress-inducible genes in various rice plants under normal conditions and salt stress (150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 24&#x000a0;h). <bold>d</bold> Water loss in various rice plants. Whole leaves of 14-d-old plants were cut off and used for the water loss assays. Sixty seedlings per genotype (twenty seedlings for each biological replicate) were used. Data shown are the means &#x000b1; SE of three biological replicates. An asterisk indicates a significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) versus stressed NTL</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_232_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">Next, we determined the transcript expression of three ABA response genes&#x02013; <italic>OsRAB16A</italic>, <italic>OsLEA3</italic> and <italic>OsLIP9</italic> &#x02013; under salt stress. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>, without NaCl treatment, the transcript levels of <italic>OsRAB16A</italic>, <italic>OsLEA3</italic> and <italic>OsLIP9</italic> showed no significant difference between wild-type and transgenic plants. Upon 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treatment, transcripts of these genes accumulated significantly in all three genotypes, while RiTL4&#x02013;3 accumulated more transcripts than NTL and OeTL3&#x02013;8 in response to salt stress (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). Because ABA is a key regulator of stomatal opening and closure, water loss from the detached leaves of NTL, OeTL3&#x02013;8 and RiTL4&#x02013;2 was compared. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>, water loss in RiTL4&#x02013;2 was much slower than in NTL and OeTL3&#x02013;8. These results suggested that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> negatively regulated the expression of ABA-dependent stress-inducible genes under salt treatment conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><italic>OsRACK1A</italic> significantly changes expression of salt stress-related genes in rice plants</title><p id="Par41">Next, we evaluated the expression of stress-related genes in NTL, OeTL3&#x02013;8, and RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants grown under both control and salt-stress conditions by real-time qPCR. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>, under control conditions, the dehydration-responsive element-binding protein 1 (DREB1) genes, <italic>OsDREB-A, -1B</italic>, <italic>-1C</italic>, <italic>&#x02212;1E</italic>, -<italic>1G</italic>and <italic>-1H</italic>, and the stress-related APETALA2/Ethylene Responsive Factor (AP2/ERF) gene AP59 were upregulated in RiTL4&#x02013;2 and downregulated in OeTL3&#x02013;8, in comparison with NTL. When treated with 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 24&#x000a0;h, the transcript levels of <italic>OsDREB1A, 1B</italic>, <italic>-1C</italic>, <italic>&#x02212;1E</italic>, <italic>&#x02212;1G</italic>, and <italic>OsAP59</italic> in RiTL4&#x02013;2 were higher than those in NTL, and the expression of OsDREB1A, -1C and OsAP59 was lower in OeTL3&#x02013;8 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><italic>OsRACK1A</italic> regulates the expression of stress-related genes. Expression of stress-related AP2/ERF genes (<bold>a</bold>) and other stress-related genes (<bold>b</bold>) in OeTL3&#x02013;8 and RiTL4&#x02013;2 compared with the NTL in both normal and salt-stress (150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 24&#x000a0;h) conditions by qRT-PCR. Data shown are the means &#x000b1; SE of four biological replicates. An asterisk indicates a significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) versus stressed NTL</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_232_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par42">We selected another seven salt stress-responsive genes (<italic>OsMYB2</italic>, <italic>SNAC1</italic>, <italic>OsTCP19</italic>, <italic>OsTPS1</italic>, <italic>OsMAPK5</italic>, <italic>OsSIK1</italic>, and <italic>OsCPK4</italic>) that have been reported to improve salt-stress tolerance (Xiong and Yang, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2003</xref>; Hu et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2006</xref>; Ouyang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2010</xref>; Li et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2011</xref>; Yang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2012</xref>; Campo et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2014</xref>; Mukhopadhyay and Tyagi, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2015</xref>). The expression levels of these genes were all upregulated significantly in RiTL4&#x02013;2, while the expression levels of <italic>OsMAPK5, OsMYB2</italic> and <italic>SNAC1</italic> were downregulated significantly in OeTL3&#x02013;8. <italic>OsRMC</italic> has been reported to be a negative regulator of the salt-stress response in rice (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2009</xref>; Serra et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2013</xref>) and the expression of <italic>OsRMC</italic> was downregulated in RiTL4&#x02013;2 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). Similar expression profile of these genes occurred under salt-stress conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). These results may partially explain the phenotype of RiTL4&#x02013;2 plants under stress conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>OsRACK1A interacts with salt-stress response proteins</title><p id="Par43">As a scaffold protein, RACK1 interacts with numerous proteins and plays a critical role in many fundamental physiological processes, including stress responses (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2013</xref>). In this study, we used co-immunoprecipitation (co-IP) to identify novel proteins that interact with OsRACK1A under both normal and salt-stress conditions. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1, 12 and 20 proteins were detected to interact with OsRACK1A directly or indirectly in normal and stress conditions, respectively. Of these 32 identified proteins, two (Os07g37760 and Os01g25610) interacted with OsRACK1A in both normal and salt-stress conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>). Nine of these genes responded to NaCl treatment (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3). We also used the yeast two-hybrid assay to confirm these interactions and ultimately found that six of the identified proteins interacted directly with OsRACK1A (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>). Interestingly, these six proteins were all identified in salt-stress conditions by co-IP assay and their mRNA levels were all downregulated with salt treatment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3). The mRNA expression of these six OsRACK1A interacting proteins was also detected in NTL, OeTL3&#x02013;8, and RiTL4&#x02013;2 under both normal and salt-stress conditions. The transcript levels of Os05g41640, Os07g04840, and Os01g31690, which encode phosphoglycerate kinase, PsbP, and oxygen-evolving enhancer protein 1, respectively, were lower in RiTL4&#x02013;2 compared with NTL and OeTL3&#x02013;8 in normal conditions, whereas no significant change in the expression of these genes was observed in NTL and transgenic plants after NaCl treatment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>). The Os09g36680, which encodes a ribonuclease T2 family domain containing protein, was downregulated in OeTL3&#x02013;8 with no treatment and up-regulated in RiTL4&#x02013;2 under salt treatment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>). These results indicated that OsRACK1A regulates stress responses by interacting directly with many stress related proteins.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>OsRACK1A directly interacts with stress-response proteins. <bold>a</bold> OsRACK1A interaction proteins screening using co-IP in both normal and salt stress (150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 24&#x000a0;h) conditions. <bold>b</bold> Verifying the protein interactions by yeast two hybrid assay. <bold>c</bold> Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of the expression of OsRACK1A interactors in response to salt stress (150&#x000a0;mM NaCl for 24&#x000a0;h). Data shown are the means &#x000b1; SE of four biological replicates. An asterisk indicates a significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) versus stressed NTL</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_232_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par44">RACK1 is a highly conserved scaffold protein that is expressed ubiquitously (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2013</xref>). <italic>RACK1</italic> is involved in multiple signaling pathways, including growth and development and responses to external environmental stresses (McCahill et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2002</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2013</xref>). However, the molecular mechanisms of RACK1 in plants is still in its infancy. In plant, <italic>RACK1</italic> is involved in the regulation of cell proliferation and elongation, and the responses to plant hormones and environmental factors (Chen et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2006</xref>; Nakashima et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>; Guo et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2009</xref>; Li et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2009</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2013</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2014</xref>). The rice genome contains two <italic>RACK1</italic> ortholog genes, <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> and <italic>OsRACK1B</italic> (Nakashima et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>). Although <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> and <italic>OsRACK1B</italic> are similar, <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> transcript levels are always significantly higher than those of <italic>OsRACK1B</italic> in leaves, roots, and mature seeds (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2014</xref>). Previously, we reported that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> negatively regulated the response of seed germination to exogenous ABA and the suppression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> improved drought tolerant in rice (Li et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2009</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2014</xref>). In the present study, we showed that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> negatively regulated salt stress tolerance and sought to explore the molecular mechanism(s) involved.</p><p id="Par45">A circadian oscillator controls the timing of several physiological functions in living organisms. In plants, processes controlled by a circadian clock include the photoperiodic induction of flowering, rhythmic leaf movements and stomatal opening (Thines and Harmon, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2011</xref>). Recent research also suggests that a circadian clock may contribute to plant fitness, enhancing their ability to tolerate abiotic stress (Grundy et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2015</xref>). In maize, transcripts of many stress related genes exhibits a diurnal cycling pattern (Hayes et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2010</xref>; Khan et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2010</xref>). Some salt stress-responsive genes, such as <italic>SOS1</italic>, <italic>RD29A</italic> and <italic>DREB2A</italic>, exhibit a 24-h period of expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, suggesting that salt tolerance may also be affected by the circadian clock (Park et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2016a</xref>). In some cases, other stress, such as cold and drought, modifies the transcription pattern of a major portion of genes showing diurnal oscillation (Wilkins et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2010</xref>; Jo&#x00144;czyk et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>). Resent evidence indicates that plants respond to salt stress more strongly during the day than at night and salt-induced expression of RD29A and SOS1 was much higher in the daytime than at night (Park et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2016b</xref>). We found that both mRNA and protein levels of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> exhibits a diurnal cycling pattern, and much higher during the day than at night (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a, b</xref>). However, expression of OsRACK1A increased under salt stress and remained high in both the light and dark (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref>). It might be that higher expression levels of OsRACK1A in day caused more damage under salt stress.</p><p id="Par46">In rice, OsRACK1A protein is phosphorylated under ABA and drought treatment, although the kinase responsible was not identified (He and Li, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2008</xref>; Ke et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2009</xref>). Recently, Urano et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2015</xref>) showed that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RACK1A (AtRACK1A) is also phosphorylated by an atypical serine/threonine protein kinase, WITH NO LYSINE 8 (WNK8), and phosphorylation of AtRACK1A rendered it unstable. Interestingly, in this present study, we found that OsRACK1A protein was controlled by post-transcriptional or translational regulation and consequently accumulated under salt stress. These results led us to the hypothesize that phosphorylation of OsRACK1A does not reduce the protein stability in rice and RACK1 protein may play distinct roles in different plant species. Guo and Sun (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2017</xref>) found that sumoylation of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RACK1B (AtRACK1B) increased AtRACK1B stability and its tolerance to ubiquitin-mediated degradation in the ABA response, and consequently enhanced the interaction between RACK1B and RAP2.6. Combined, these findings illustrate that protein stability controlled by post-transcriptional modification is a critical regulatory mechanism for RACK1 in both <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice.</p><p id="Par47">In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the clock component GIGANTEA (GI) is involved in salt-stress responses (Kim et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2013</xref>). Similar to <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>, <italic>GI</italic> transcription is under circadian control and peaked at 8&#x02013;10&#x000a0;h after the start of the day (Park et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1999</xref>). Under normal conditions, GI interacts with SOS2, a key component of the SOS pathway, preventing the interaction between SOS2 and SOS3. Under salt stress conditions, GI is degraded and the free SOS2/SOS3 complex activates SOS1, a Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter, to export sodium (Na<sup>+</sup>) ions from cells (Kim et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2013</xref>). In the present study<italic>, OsRACK1A</italic> also negatively regulated Na<sup>+</sup> accumulation and subsequently maintained a low K<sup>+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> ratio in rice seedlings under NaCl stress (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, b</xref>). We investigated the proteins that interact with OsRACK1A and identified six salt-stress suppressed proteins that interacted with OsRACK1A directly (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a, b</xref>). Unfortunately, none of these proteins were reported to be directly involved in salt-stress responses and the relationship between <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> and the Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter is still unclear. In eukaryotes, RACK1 regulates various signaling pathways and cellular processes through its interaction with numerous signaling proteins (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2013</xref>). For example, OsRACK1A binds the active form of Rac1 and interacts with the N terminus of Rboh, RAR1, and SGT1, to form a complex in rice innate immunity (Nakashima et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>). Similarly, OsRACK1A may form a complex with these salt-stress responses proteins, and active downstream molecules, such as salt-stress relative transcription factor. Future studies will reveal whether these OsRACK1A-interaction proteins are involved in salt-stress response.</p><p id="Par48">Under high-salt-stress conditions, a key plant stress-signaling hormone, ABA, and numerous ABA-induced stress-responsive genes products accumulate (Yoshida et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2014</xref>). The <italic>NCED</italic> genes are known to encode key enzymes in ABA biosynthesis in plants (Nambara and Marion-Poll, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2005</xref>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>AtNCED3</italic> is induced by drought and high salinity, and the overexpression of <italic>AtNCED3</italic> in transgenic plants enhanced dehydration stress tolerance (Iuchi et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2001</xref>). Five <italic>NCED</italic> genes (<italic>OsNCED1&#x02013;5</italic>) have been identified in the rice genome (Zhu et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2009</xref>). The qPCR analysis showed that the <italic>OsNCED4</italic> and <italic>OsNCED5</italic> were induced strongly under salt stress (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2), suggesting that transcriptional regulation of the <italic>OsNCED4</italic> and <italic>OsNCED5</italic> genes may be involved in salt-induced ABA accumulation in rice. Previous study has showed that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> negatively regulated the response of seed germination to exogenous ABA (Zhang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2014</xref>). Here we showed that the expression levels of <italic>OsNCED4</italic> and <italic>OsNCED5</italic> were higher in the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-suppressed line (RiTL4&#x02013;2) than the non-transgenic line and the <italic>OsRACK1A</italic>-expressing line (OeTL3&#x02013;8; Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). Additionally, the ABA content was higher in RiTL4&#x02013;2 than in NTL and OeTL3&#x02013;8 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>), suggesting that the OsRACK1A protein suppressed ABA accumulation under salt stress by regulating the expression of ABA biosynthesis genes. Some typical ABA-dependent stress-inducible genes, such as <italic>OsRAB16A</italic>, <italic>OsLEA3</italic> and <italic>OsLIP9</italic>, show higher mRNA levels in RiTL4&#x02013;2, indicating that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> is involved in ABA-dependent stress pathways.</p><p id="Par49">The AP2/ERF transcription factor superfamily is involved in responses to biotic and abiotic stresses, the regulation of metabolism, and developmental processes in various plant species (Dossa et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2016</xref>). We selected some <italic>AP2/ERF</italic> genes (<italic>OsDREB-1A</italic>, <italic>1B</italic>, <italic>-1C</italic>, <italic>&#x02212;1E</italic>, <italic>&#x02212;1G</italic>, <italic>-1H</italic> and <italic>OsAP59</italic>) and found that these <italic>AP2/ERF</italic> genes were all upregulated in RiTL4&#x02013;2 and some of them were downregulated in OeTL3&#x02013;8 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). Many of the upregulated <italic>AP2/ERF</italic> genes have been reported to play roles in salt-stress tolerance. Transgenic plants overexpressing <italic>OsDREB1B</italic> showed higher tolerances to drought, high salt, and freezing stresses (Dubouzet et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2003</xref>; Qin et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2006</xref>; Mao and Chen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2012</xref>). The <italic>OsAP59</italic> gene was found to be induced after exposure to drought and high-salt conditions, and constitutive expression of <italic>OsAP59</italic> in rice increased the tolerance to drought and high salinity during vegetative development (Oh et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2009</xref>). Some of these <italic>AP2/ERF</italic> genes, such as <italic>OsAP59</italic>, were not induced by ABA (Oh et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2009</xref>). These results suggested that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> is also involved in ABA-independent signaling in response to stress in rice. We found some other stress-related transcription factors, such as <italic>OsMYB2</italic>, <italic>SNAC1</italic> and <italic>OsTCP19</italic> were upregulated in <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> suppressed-expression plants in both normal and stress condition (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). OsMYB2-overexpressing plants were reported showing more tolerant to salt, cold, and dehydration stresses and more sensitive to abscisic acid than wild-type plants (Yang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2012</xref>). Interestingly, two core circadian clock components, CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED 1 (CCA1) and LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL 1 (LHY1), are also belone to MYB transcription factor family and involved in cold stress responses (Dong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2011</xref>), suggesting that MYB transcription factors might be molecular link between circadian clock and stress responses. We also showed that suppression of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> activated several known stress-related kinases, such as <italic>OsSIK1</italic>, <italic>OsMAPK5</italic>, and <italic>OsCPK4</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). These genes have been reported to be induced by cold, drought, salinity, ABA, and other abiotic stresses. Transgenic plants overexpressing these genes exhibited enhanced tolerance to various stresses (Xiong and Yang, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2003</xref>; Ouyang et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2010</xref>; Campo et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2014</xref>). In addition, we showed that expression of <italic>OsRMC</italic>, which negatively regulates salt-stress tolerance in rice (Serra et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2013</xref>), was suppressed in the RiTL4&#x02013;2 line (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). Although the signal transduction pathway involving these gene products is unclear, we suggest that <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> participates in abiotic stress pathways, directly or indirectly, by altering the expression of these stress-related genes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par50">In summary, results presented in this study demonstrate that OsRACK1A functions as a stress-responsive gene and <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> RNAi transgenic rice can significantly improve salt stress tolerance through ABA-dependent and -independent pathway. As a negative regulator of salt stress response, <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> expresses rhythmically under normal conditions and shows the loss of cycling under salt stress. Although OsRACK1A interacts with many salt-responsive proteins, no directly evidence links OsRACK1A protein to salt stress related transcription factors, such as DREB and AP2/ERF. Further investigations on the identification of the functions of OsRACK1A interaction proteins will be helpful to elucidate the mechanism of <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> in regulating salt stress tolerance.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec20"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_232_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S2.</bold> Primers used for the qRT-PCR analysis of various genes. <bold>Figure S1.</bold> Public microarray data showing <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> (A) and <italic>OsRACK1B</italic> (B) expression is controlled by a circadian clock (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/experiments/E-MTAB-275/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/experiments/E-MTAB-275/</ext-link>). <italic>OsRACK1A</italic> expression in rice leaves under 16&#x000a0;h light/ 8&#x000a0;h dark (LD) or constant light (LL) conditions and under NaCl treatment (C). <bold>Figure S2.</bold>
<italic>OsNCED</italic> gene expression in rice leaves under 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl treatment for 12&#x000a0;h. <bold>Figure S3.</bold> Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of the expression of OsRACK1 interactors in response to salt stress. (DOCX 356 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_232_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> Identification of OsRACK1A interacting proteins. (XLSX 22 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ABA</term><def><p id="Par2">Abscisic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AP2/ERF</term><def><p id="Par3">Apetala2/ethylene responsive factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMAL1</term><def><p id="Par4">Brain and muscle arnt-like protein-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BR</term><def><p id="Par5">Brassinosteroid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DREB</term><def><p id="Par6">Dehydration responsive element binding protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ERFs</term><def><p id="Par7">Ethylene response factors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GA</term><def><p id="Par8">Gibberellin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></term><def><p id="Par9">Hydrogen peroxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IAA</term><def><p id="Par10">Indole-3-acetic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDA</term><def><p id="Par11">Malondialdehyde</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NCED</term><def><p id="Par12">9-cis-epoxycarotenoid dioxygenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NTL</term><def><p id="Par13">Non-transgenic line</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OeTL</term><def><p id="Par14">Overexpressing-transgenic line</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qPCR</term><def><p id="Par15">Quantitative PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RACK1</term><def><p id="Par16">Receptor for activated C kinase 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RiTL</term><def><p id="Par17">RNA interference- transgenic line</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROS</term><def><p id="Par18">Reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SOS</term><def><p id="Par19">salt overly sensitive</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WD40</term><def><p id="Par20">Tryptophan-aspartic acid 40</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ZT</term><def><p id="Par21">Zeitgeber time</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><p>We acknowledge Miss Min Li and Dr. Yujie Fang (Yangzhou University) for their suggestions during this study.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par51">This work was supported by the National Science Foundation of China (31271622, 31422047, 31601230, and 31761130073), Natural Science Research Project for Colleges and Universities in Jiangsu Province (16KJB210013), the Jiangsu Province College Students Innovation Training Program in 2016 (X20160741).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par52">All data supporting the conclusions of this article are provided within the article (and its additional files).</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>JL, WX and DZ conceived and designed the experiments. DZ and YW performed plasmid construction and phenotypic analyses, quantitative real-time RT-PCR and western-blot assay. JS, JY and YG performed yeast two hybrid and co-immunoprecipitation (co-IP) experiment. DZ, YW, DL, and WX analyzed data. DZ, YW and JL wrote article. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par53">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par54">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par55">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par56">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnon</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copper enzymes in isolated chloroplasts</article-title><source>Polyphenoloxidase in Beta vulgaris Plant Physiol</source><year>1949</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16654194?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16654194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldren</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Teare</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid determination of free proline for water-stress studies</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><year>1973</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00018060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldrich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Messeguer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalanne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Coca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>San Segundo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of a calcium-dependent protein kinase confers salt and drought tolerance in Rice by preventing membrane lipid peroxidation</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.230268</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24784760?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24784760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Temple</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RACK1 mediates multiple hormone responsiveness and developmental processes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>2697</fpage><lpage>2708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erl035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16829549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16829549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>Woody</surname><given-names>OZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pathogen-secreted proteases activate a novel plant immune pathway</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>521</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14243</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25731164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25731164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkelstein</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abscisic acid: emergence of a core signaling network</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042809-112122</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20192755?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhindsa</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Matowe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drought tolerance in two mosses: correlated with enzymatic defence against lipid peroxidation</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>1981</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/32.1.79</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Farre</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomashow</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian Clock-Associated 1 and Late Elongated Hypocotyl regulate expression of the C-Repeat Binding Factor (CBF) pathway in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>7241</fpage><lpage>7246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1103741108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21471455?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21471455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dossa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonceka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insight into the AP2/ERF transcription factor superfamily in sesame and expression profiling of DREB subfamily under drought stress</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>171</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-016-0859-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27475988?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27475988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubouzet</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasuga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubouzet</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OsDREB genes in rice, Oryza sativa L., encode transcription activators that function in drought-, high-salt- and cold-responsive gene expression</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01661.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12609047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grundy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian regulation of abiotic stress tolerance in plants</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>648</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00648</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26379680?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26379680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RACK1 genes regulate plant development with unequal genetic redundancy in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>108</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-8-108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18947417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18947417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RACK1 is a negative regulator of ABA responses in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>3819</fpage><lpage>3833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19584117?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19584117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Involvement of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RACK1 in protein translation and its regulation by abscisic acid</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.160663</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21098678?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21098678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sumoylation stabilizes RACK1B and enhance its interaction with RAP2.6 in the abscisic acid response</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>44090</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep44090</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28272518?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28272518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Beatty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Habben</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Danilevskaya</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maize global transcriptomics reveals pervasive leaf diurnal rhythms but rhythms in developing ears are largely limited to the core oscillator</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e12887</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0012887</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20886102?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20886102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of phosphoproteins regulated by abscisic acid in rice leaves</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2008</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>883</fpage><lpage>888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2008.05.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18468508?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18468508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpressing a NAM, ATAF, and CUC (NAC) transcription factor enhances drought resistance and salt tolerance in rice</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>12987</fpage><lpage>12992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0604882103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16924117?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16924117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurotani</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phytochrome B regulates heading date 1 (Hd1)-mediated expression of rice florigen Hd3a and critical day length in rice</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-011-0621-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Taji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Naramoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of drought tolerance by gene manipulation of 9-cis-epoxycarotenoid dioxygenase, a key enzyme in abscisic acid biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2001</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.2001.01096.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11532178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11532178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jo&#x00144;czyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobkowiak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trzcinska-Danielewicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoneczny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Solecka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fronk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sowi&#x00144;ski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of gene expression in maize leaves treated with low temperature. II. Combined effect of severe cold (8 &#x000b0;C) and circadian rhythm</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-017-0651-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28828699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28828699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential regulation of proteins and phosphoproteins in rice under drought stress</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2009</year><volume>379</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2008.12.067</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19103168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19103168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordination of the maize transcriptome by a conserved circadian clock</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-126</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20576144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Hormaeche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Release of SOS2 kinase from sequestration with GIGANTEA determines salt tolerance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1352</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms2357</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23322040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23322040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dozier</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Deslandes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Somssich</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> scaffold protein RACK1A interacts with diverse environmental stress and photosynthesis related proteins</article-title><source>Plant Signal Behav</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e24012</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.24012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23435172?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23435172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Down-regulated expression of RACK1 gene by RNA interference enhances drought tolerance in rice</article-title><source>Rice Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1672-6308(08)60051-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of the trehalose-6-phosphate synthase gene OsTPS1 enhances abiotic stress tolerance in rice</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2011</year><volume>234</volume><fpage>1007</fpage><lpage>1018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-011-1458-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21698458?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21698458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colinearity and similar expression pattern of rice DREB1s reveal their functional conservation in the cold-responsive pathway</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e47275</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047275</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23077584?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23077584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanouchi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name><surname>Minobe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ehd3, encoding a plant homeodomain finger-containing protein, is a critical promoter of rice flowering</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2011</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04517.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21284756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21284756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCahill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Warwicker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Houslay</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yarwood</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RACK1 scaffold protein: a dynamic cog in cell response mechanisms</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>2002</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1261</fpage><lpage>1273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.62.6.1261</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12435793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12435793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OsTCP19 influences developmental and abiotic stress signaling by modulating ABI4-mediated pathways</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>9998</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep09998</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25925167?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25925167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Thao</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RACK1 functions in rice innate immunity by interacting with the Rac1 immune complex</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2265</fpage><lpage>2279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.107.054395</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18723578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18723578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nambara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marion-Poll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abscisic acid biosynthesis and catabolism</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.56.032604.144046</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15862093?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15862093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of the transcription factor AP37 in rice improves grain yield under drought conditions</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>1368</fpage><lpage>1379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.137554</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19429605?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19429605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Receptor-like kinase OsSIK1 improves drought and salt stress tolerance in rice (Oryza sativa) plants</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2010</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04146.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20128882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20128882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Soh</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of circadian rhythms and photoperiodic flowering by the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GIGANTEA gene</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>1579</fpage><lpage>1582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.285.5433.1579</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10477524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10477524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A New Insight of Salt Stress Signaling in Plant</article-title><source>Mol Cells</source><year>2016</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14348/molcells.2016.0083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27239814?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27239814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal and circadian regulation of salt tolerance in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>J Plant Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12374-016-0317-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation, optimization, and functional analysis of the cDNA encoding transcription factor OsDREB1B in Oryza Sativa L</article-title><source>Mol Breeding</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-006-9065-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyault</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Knutti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Weitz</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of RACK1 and protein kinase Calpha as integral components of the mammalian circadian clock</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>327</volume><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1180067</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20093473?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20093473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordeiro</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Louren&#x000e7;o</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abreu</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OsRMC, a negative regulator of salt stress response in rice, is regulated by two AP2/ERF transcription factors</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-013-0073-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23703395?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23703395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative proteomic analysis of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cbl1 mutant in response to salt stress</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4712</fpage><lpage>4725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.201100042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22002954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22002954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thines</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Four easy pieces: mechanisms underlying circadian regulation of growth and development</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2010.09.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20943429?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20943429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umezawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuromori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanokura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular basis of the core regulatory network in ABA responses: sensing, signaling and transport</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1821</fpage><lpage>1839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcq156</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20980270?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20980270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Czarnecki</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> receptor of activated c kinase1 phosphorylation by with no lysine8 kinase</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.247460</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25489024?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25489024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000e4;utigam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time of day shapes Arabidopsis drought transcriptomes</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2010</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04274.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20553421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20553421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumaker</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell signaling during cold, drought, and salt stress</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>S165</fpage><lpage>S183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.000596</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12045276?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12045276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disease resistance and abiotic stress tolerance in rice are inversely modulated by an abscisic acid-inducible mitogen-activated protein kinase</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.008714</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12615946?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12615946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Natural variation in Ghd7 is an important regulator of heading date and yield potential in rice</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.143</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18454147?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18454147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A R2R3-type MYB gene, OsMYB2, is involved in salt, cold, and dehydration tolerance in rice</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2012</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>2541</fpage><lpage>2556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err431</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22301384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22301384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>KX</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maohuzi6/Ethylene Insensitive3-Like1 and Ethylene Insensitive3-Like2 regulate ethylene response of roots and coleoptiles and negatively affect salt tolerance in Rice</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.00353</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25995326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25995326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogami</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ABA-dependent and ABA-independent signaling in response to osmotic stress in plants</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>21C</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2014.07.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OsRACK1 is involved in abscisic acid- and H2O2-mediated signaling to regulate seed germination in rice (Oryza sativa, L.)</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e97120</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097120</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24865690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24865690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rice G-protein subunits qPE9-1 and RGB1 play distinct roles in abscisic acid responses and drought adaptation</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2015</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>6371</fpage><lpage>6384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erv350</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26175353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26175353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The scaffolding protein RACK1: a platform for divers functions in the plant kingdom</article-title><source>Plant Biology Soil Health</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of an Apoplastic protein involved in the initial phase of salt stress response in Rice root by two-dimensional electrophoresis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>916</fpage><lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.131144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19036832?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19036832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose-induced delay of seed germination in rice is mediated by the suppression of ABA catabolism rather than an enhancement of ABA biosynthesis</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcp022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19208695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19208695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of ion homeostasis under salt stress</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(03)00085-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12972044?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12972044</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>