<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6093901</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">30632</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-30632-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Early molecular events associated with nitrogen deficiency in rice seedling roots</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>Ping-Han</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>Chia-Cheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Hsin-Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Hsiu-Chun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>Ming-Hsiun</given-names></name><address><email>ming@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2287 1366</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.28665.3f</institution-id><institution>Institute of Plant and Microbial Biology, Academia Sinica, </institution></institution-wrap>Taipei, 11529 Taiwan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>12207</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Nitrogen (N) deficiency is one of the most common problems in rice. The symptoms of N deficiency are well documented, but the underlying molecular mechanisms are largely unknown in rice. Here, we studied the early molecular events associated with N starvation (&#x02212;N, 1&#x02009;h), focusing on amino acid analysis and identification of &#x02212;N-regulated genes in rice roots. Interestingly, levels of glutamine rapidly decreased within 15&#x02009;min of &#x02212;N treatment, indicating that part of the N-deficient signals could be mediated by glutamine. Transcriptome analysis revealed that genes involved in metabolism, plant hormone signal transduction (e.g. abscisic acid, auxin, and jasmonate), transporter activity, and oxidative stress responses were rapidly regulated by &#x02212;N. Some of the &#x02212;N-regulated genes encode transcription factors, protein kinases and protein phosphatases, which may be involved in the regulation of early &#x02212;N responses in rice roots. Previously, we used similar approaches to identify glutamine-, glutamate-, and ammonium nitrate-responsive genes. Comparisons of the genes induced by different forms of N with the &#x02212;N-regulated genes identified here have provided a catalog of potential N regulatory genes for further dissection of the N signaling pathwys in rice.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Rice is a staple food for almost half of the world&#x02019;s population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. The production of rice, especially in Asian countries, is important in food security. The Green Revolution rice cultivars developed in 1960&#x02019;s, which constitute most of the rice varieties grown today, require large amounts of nitrogen (N) fertilizers to produce high yields<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. However, the production of N fertilizer requires a lot of energy. Furthermore, only 20&#x02013;30% of the applied N fertilizer is taken up by the rice plant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Most of the N fertilizers applied to rice are lost to the air or water, which causes substantial environmental problems. Thus, the use of N fertilizer is costly to farmers and the environment. The current agricultural practices are not enconomically and environmentally sustainable. Therefore, considerable efforts have been directed toward improvement of N management and development of new rice varieties with better N use efficiency in the past decades to ensure sustainable agriculture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Despite decades of study, the improvement of N use efficiency in crop plants is still one of the scientific &#x0201c;Grand Challenges&#x0201d; in the 21<sup>st</sup> century. To face this challenge, we need to have a better understanding of the genetics behind N uptake, transport, metabolism, and remobilization in crop plants, especially when N is limited in the environment. Since N is a major constituent of amino acids, nucleic acids, chlorophyll, ATP, coenzymes, plant hormones, and secondary metabolites, N deficiency affects all aspects of plant function, from metabolism to resource allocation, growth and development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. To cope with N deficiency, plants have evolved complex morphological, physiological, and biochemical adaptaions to the adverse environments. For instance, plants will increase its capacity to acquire N by stimulating root growth relative to shoot growth in response to N deficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The expression of high affinifity nitrate and ammonium transporter genes was induced by N starvation (&#x02212;N)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the remobilization of stored N and the release of ammonium via the biosynthesis of phenylpropanoids were stimulated by N deprivation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. It is evident that plants have evolved regulatory systems to adjust metabolism, conserve resources and activate the acclimatory pathways enabling them to adapt to N-deficient conditions. Nevertheless, the molecular mechanisms underlying the N-deficient responses are still largely unknown in plants.</p><p id="Par4">Global gene expression profiling using microarrays or RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) has been a successful approach to study the molecular aspects of nutrient and stress responses. For instance, microarrays were used in several studies to identify nitrate-responsive genes in Arabidopsis and rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Ammonium is believed to be the major N source for paddy rice. Transcriptome analysis using microarray or RNA-Seq has been applied to identify ammonium-responsive genes in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Similarly, &#x02212;N-responsive genes have been identified by transcriptome analyses in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. These studies have provided catalogs for the identification of potential N regulatory genes.</p><p id="Par5">Indeed, transcriptome analysis followed by reverse genetic study has successfully identified several N regulatory genes in plants. For instance, the <italic>LBD/37/38/39</italic> transcription factor genes were identified as nitrate-responsive genes in Arabidopsis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Further genetic studies demonstrated that LBD37/38/39 are regulators of N responses in Arabidopsis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. The expression of <italic>Os02g0325600</italic> encoding nitrate-inducible GARP (GOLDEN2, ARR-B, Psr1) transcriptional repressor 1 (NIGT1) was specifically induced by nitrate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The Arabidopsis NIGT1 homolog is involved in the integration of nitrate and phosphate signals at the root tip<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. More recently, the <italic>Os02g0120100</italic> gene encoding ACT domain-containing protein kinase 1 (ACTPK1), a homolog of Arabidopsis serine/threonine/tyrosine kinase 46 (STY46), was identified by transcriptome analysis of ammonium-responsive genes in rice roots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Further genetic and biochemical studies demonstrated that ACTPK1 can phosphorylate and inactivate AMT1;2, a major ammonium transporter, under ammonium-sufficient conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Since the availability of nutrients in the soil is directly perceived by roots, we aim to uncover the early molecular events associated with N deficiency in rice roots. This study primarily focused on the analysis of amino acids and identification of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in response to N deficiency. All of the DEGs identified by microarray analysis were verified by quantitative (q)RT-PCR, and only the verified genes were further used for Gene Ontology (GO) and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway enrichment analyses. Interestingly, these analyses revealed that genes involved in carbon (C) and N metabolism, &#x0201c;plant hormone signal transduction&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;transporter activity&#x0201d; were enriched in &#x02212;N-regulated genes. In addition, several novel N regulatory genes, including those encode transcription factors, protein kinases and protein phosphatases, were identified here. These newly identified N regulatory genes may play important roles in the regulation of N-deficient responses in rice roots.</p><p id="Par7">In addition to &#x02212;N, we previously used the same platform with similar criteria to identify ammonium nitrate (+N)-, glutamine (+Gln)-, and glutamate (+Glu)-regulated genes in rice roots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. These studies were conducted with similar setups, which allowed us to perform data comparisons across different experiments. We have identified at least 34 N-sensitive genes, whose expression was rapidly induced by +N and quickly repressed by &#x02212;N. In addition to genes involved in nitrate/nitrite assimilation, ferredoxin reduction, and the pentose phosphate pathway, the identified N-sensitive genes include several well-known N regulatory genes, such as <italic>LBD37</italic> (<italic>Os03g0445700</italic>, <italic>Os07g0589000</italic>), <italic>LBD38</italic> (<italic>Os03g0609500</italic>) and <italic>BT2</italic> (<italic>Os01g0908200</italic>, BTB/POZ and TAZ domain-containing protein 2)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. These results implicate that some of the novel N-sensitive genes may be involved in the regulation of N metabolism and/or responses in rice. Further studies on the &#x02212;N-regulated genes or N-sensitive genes identified here may provide new solutions to increase N use efficiency in rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Effects of N starvation on the growth of rice seedlings</title><p id="Par8">Compared with the green and healthy seedlings grown in +N hydroponic solution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, the 10-day-old rice seedlings grown in &#x02212;N medium have chlorotic leaves, thinner and longer roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). The shoot length, root length, and chlorophyll content of the +N- and &#x02212;N-treated rice seedlings are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B,C</xref>. The inhibition of shoot growth and promotion of root growth were also observed in 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with &#x02212;N for 2, 5, and 7 days (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). It is known that &#x02212;N can stimulate primary root growth by enhancing cell elongation as well as cell division<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. These results implicated that N deficiency could induce changes at cellular, biochemical, and molecular levels to affect plant growth and development.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effect of nitrogen starvation on the growth of rice seedlings. (<bold>A</bold>) Ten-day-old rice seedlings grown in hydroponic solutions containing 1.43&#x02009;mM NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub> (+N) or without nitrogen (&#x02212;N). Individual plants from +N and &#x02212;N were shown on the right. Root length, shoot length (<bold>B</bold>), and chlorophyll content (<bold>C</bold>) of rice seedlings from (<bold>A</bold>). Data are mean &#x000b1;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;15). ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005 represents the result of Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test. Scale bars are 3&#x02009;cm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e418"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Effects of N starvation on amino acid content in rice roots</title><p id="Par9">To examine the effects of &#x02212;N on amino acid content in 10-day-old rice seedlings, we measured the amounts of free amino acids in the roots after &#x02212;N treatment for 15&#x02009;min to 4&#x02009;h. Glutamine, glutamate, asparagine and aspartate are the most abundant amino acids in rice seedlings. Interestingly, levels of glutamine were rapidly reduced during the time course of N starvation. The amount of free glutamine was reduced approximately 50% during the first 15&#x02009;min of &#x02212;N treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Gln). By contrast, levels of glutamate were not reduced until 4&#x02009;h after &#x02212;N treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Glu). The amount of aspargine did not change significantly during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Levels of aspartate increased slightly within 1&#x02009;h, and started to decrease after 4&#x02009;h of &#x02212;N treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The amounts of the other amino acids did not change significantly during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of nitrogen starvation on contents of glutamine, glutamate, aspartate, and asparagine in rice roots. Amino acids extracted from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with nitrogen starvation for 0&#x02013;4&#x02009;h were analyzed. Data are mean &#x000b1;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Different lower-case letters indicate significant difference (ANOVA, post-hoc Tukey test, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e454"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Identification of genes rapidly respond to nitrogen starvation</title><p id="Par10">We used microarray analysis to identify DEGs in the roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with &#x02212;N for 1&#x02009;h. The expression of 288 genes were differentially regulated (&#x02212;N/+N, 144 up and 144 down) with 2-fold cutoff. Quantitative (q)RT-PCR analysis was used to examine the expression of all 288 genes identified by microarray analysis. The results confirmed that &#x02212;N induced the expression of 116 genes and repressed the expression of 98 genes within 1&#x02009;h with 2-fold cutoff. The expression patterns of these genes during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment are shown in Supplementary Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>. The &#x02212;N-induced 116 genes and the &#x02212;N-repressed 98 genes are listed in Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, respectively. These results revealed that approximately 81% of the up-regulated genes and 68% of the down-regulated genes identified by microarray analysis were reproducible in the independent qRT-PCR experiment. Most of the disqualified genes were up- or down-regulated by approximately 2-fold in the microarray analysis.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>List of genes rapidly induced by nitrogen starvation in rice roots.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>No.</th><th colspan="2">Locus ID</th><th>Fold change</th><th>Gene description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Os12g0189300</td><td>LOC_Os12g08760</td><td>9.5</td><td>Carboxyvinyl-carboxyphosphonate phosphorylmutase</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Os12g0156100</td><td>LOC_Os12g05990</td><td>5.5</td><td>NAC domain-containing protein 90 (NAC90)</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Os06g0725200</td><td>LOC_Os06g50950</td><td>5.5</td><td>GDSL esterase/lipase (GELP90)</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Os08g0137800</td><td>LOC_Os08g04340</td><td>5.1</td><td>Mavicyanin, phytocyanin</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Os07g0127500</td><td>LOC_Os07g03580</td><td>4.6</td><td>Pathogenesis-related protein PRB1-2</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>Os03g0667500</td><td>LOC_Os03g46470</td><td>4.1</td><td>Fe(II) transport protein 1 (OsIRT1)</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Os02g0626600</td><td>LOC_Os02g41670</td><td>4.1</td><td>Phenylalanine ammonia-lyase 3 (PAL3)</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Os09g0555500</td><td>LOC_Os09g38320</td><td>4.0</td><td>Phytoene synthase 3 (PSY3)</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Os09g0543900</td><td>LOC_Os09g37180</td><td>3.9</td><td>Agmatine coumaroyltransferase-2</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Os06g0587401</td><td>None</td><td>3.9</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>Os01g0595600</td><td>LOC_Os01g41240</td><td>3.7</td><td>Probable esterase KARRIKIN- INSENSITIVE 2 (KAI2)</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>Os12g0556300</td><td>LOC_Os12g36920</td><td>3.5</td><td>Calmodulin-binding protein 60&#x02009;A</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>Os03g0318400</td><td>LOC_Os03g20290</td><td>3.5</td><td>Aspartic proteinase nepenthesin-1</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>Os03g0183500</td><td>LOC_Os03g08520</td><td>3.5</td><td>Zinc-finger-FLZ domain-containing protein 24 (FLZ24)</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>Os09g0455300</td><td>LOC_Os09g28210</td><td>3.4</td><td>Basic helix-loop-helix transcription factor (bHLH120)</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>Os01g0666000</td><td>LOC_Os01g47580</td><td>3.4</td><td>Lipid phosphate phosphatase 2</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>Os07g0687900</td><td>LOC_Os07g48830</td><td>3.4</td><td>Galactinol synthase 2 (GolS2)</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>Os05g0161500</td><td>LOC_Os05g06920</td><td>3.3</td><td>GTP diphosphokinase; calcium-activated RelA-SpoT homolog 2 (CRSH2)</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>Os12g0478400</td><td>LOC_Os12g29430</td><td>3.2</td><td>Wall-associated receptor kinase 125 (WAK125)</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>Os01g0705200</td><td>LOC_Os01g50910</td><td>3.2</td><td>Late embryogenesis abundant protein, group 3</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>Os06g0521500</td><td>LOC_Os06g32990</td><td>3.1</td><td>Peroxidase 2-like</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>Os06g0218900</td><td>LOC_Os06g11520</td><td>3.0</td><td>LMBR1-like membrane protein</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>Os08g0470200</td><td>LOC_Os08g36630</td><td>3.0</td><td>Alpha carbonic anhydrase 7 (&#x003b1;-CA7)</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>Os07g0643700</td><td>LOC_Os07g44910</td><td>3.0</td><td>Probable carboxylesterase 18 (CXE18)</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>Os08g0353700</td><td>LOC_Os08g26520</td><td>3.0</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>Os07g0678300</td><td>LOC_Os07g48090</td><td>3.0</td><td>CBL-interacting protein kinase 29 (CIPK29)</td></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>Os02g0205200</td><td>LOC_Os02g11040</td><td>3.0</td><td>Protein of unknown function (DUF642)</td></tr><tr><td>28</td><td>Os03g0316200</td><td>LOC_Os03g20120</td><td>2.9</td><td>Galactinol synthase 1 (GolS1)</td></tr><tr><td>29</td><td>Os08g0540900</td><td>LOC_Os08g42800</td><td>2.9</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>Os07g0468100</td><td>LOC_Os07g28480</td><td>2.9</td><td>Glutathione S-transferase GSTU1</td></tr><tr><td>31</td><td>Os05g0135400</td><td>LOC_Os05g04490</td><td>2.9</td><td>Peroxidase 5</td></tr><tr><td>32</td><td>Os10g0391400</td><td>LOC_Os10g25230</td><td>2.8</td><td>TIFY 11e; jasmonate ZIM domain-containing protein 13 (JAZ13)</td></tr><tr><td>33</td><td>Os04g0605300</td><td>LOC_Os04g51580</td><td>2.8</td><td>Plant intracellular Ras-group-related LRR protein 1 (IRL1)</td></tr><tr><td>34</td><td>Os06g0522300</td><td>LOC_Os06g33100</td><td>2.8</td><td>Peroxidase 2-like</td></tr><tr><td>35</td><td>Os04g0308300</td><td>None</td><td>2.7</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>36</td><td>Os02g0646200</td><td>LOC_Os02g43170</td><td>2.7</td><td>B-box zinc finger protein 6 (BBX6)</td></tr><tr><td>37</td><td>Os08g0349300</td><td>LOC_Os08g26120</td><td>2.7</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>38</td><td>Os06g0142200</td><td>LOC_Os06g04990</td><td>2.7</td><td>Early nodulin 93 (ENOD93)</td></tr><tr><td>39</td><td>Os10g0488400</td><td>LOC_Os10g34700</td><td>2.7</td><td>Unknown, DUF761 containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>40</td><td>Os07g0582400</td><td>LOC_Os07g39350</td><td>2.7</td><td>Polyol/monosaccharide transporter 5 (PMT5)</td></tr><tr><td>41</td><td>Os04g0308401</td><td>None</td><td>2.7</td><td>Unknown, identical to Os04g0308300</td></tr><tr><td>42</td><td>Os01g0802700</td><td>LOC_Os01g58860</td><td>2.6</td><td>Auxin efflux carrier component 9 (PIN9)</td></tr><tr><td>43</td><td>Os05g0334400</td><td>LOC_Os05g26926</td><td>2.6</td><td>Chaperone protein DnaJ</td></tr><tr><td>44</td><td>Os12g0467700</td><td>LOC_Os12g28137</td><td>2.6</td><td>AAA-ATPase</td></tr><tr><td>45</td><td>Os10g0517500</td><td>LOC_Os10g37340</td><td>2.6</td><td>Methionine gamma-lyase (MGL)</td></tr><tr><td>46</td><td>Os03g0812400</td><td>LOC_Os03g59770</td><td>2.5</td><td>Calmodulin-like protein 2</td></tr><tr><td>47</td><td>Os06g0702000</td><td>LOC_Os06g48860</td><td>2.5</td><td>Auxin-responsive protein SAUR19</td></tr><tr><td>48</td><td>Os04g0308500</td><td>LOC_Os04g24328</td><td>2.5</td><td>23&#x02009;kDa jasmonate-induced protein</td></tr><tr><td>49</td><td>Os08g0190100</td><td>LOC_Os08g09080</td><td>2.5</td><td>Germin-like protein 8&#x02013;11</td></tr><tr><td>50</td><td>Os03g0180900</td><td>LOC_Os03g08320</td><td>2.5</td><td>TIFY 11c; jasmonate ZIM domain-containing protein 11 (JAZ11)</td></tr><tr><td>51</td><td>Os01g0895200</td><td>LOC_Os01g67010</td><td>2.5</td><td>Cytochrome b561 and DOMON domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>52</td><td>Os04g0469100</td><td>None</td><td>2.5</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>53</td><td>Os10g0523700</td><td>LOC_Os10g37980</td><td>2.5</td><td>Arogenate dehydratase/prephenate dehydratase 6 (ADT6)</td></tr><tr><td>54</td><td>Os08g0360300</td><td>LOC_Os08g27170</td><td>2.4</td><td>SAR DEFICIENT 1-like (SARD1)</td></tr><tr><td>55</td><td>Os02g0627100</td><td>LOC_Os02g41680</td><td>2.4</td><td>Phenylalanine ammonia-lyase 4 (PAL4)</td></tr><tr><td>56</td><td>Os08g0473900</td><td>LOC_Os08g36910</td><td>2.4</td><td>Alpha amylase isozyme 3D</td></tr><tr><td>57</td><td>Os07g0633400</td><td>LOC_Os07g43970</td><td>2.4</td><td>IQ domain-containing protein IQM2</td></tr><tr><td>58</td><td>Os04g0365100</td><td>LOC_Os04g29580</td><td>2.3</td><td>Wall-associated receptor kinase 37 (WAK37)</td></tr><tr><td>59</td><td>Os09g0325700</td><td>LOC_Os09g15670</td><td>2.3</td><td>Protein phosphatase 2&#x02009;C 68 (PP2C68)</td></tr><tr><td>60</td><td>Os12g0227500</td><td>LOC_Os12g12600</td><td>2.3</td><td>Dirigent-like protein</td></tr><tr><td>61</td><td>Os08g0347000</td><td>LOC_Os08g25850</td><td>2.3</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>62</td><td>Os12g0150200</td><td>LOC_Os12g05440</td><td>2.3</td><td>Cytochrome P450 94C1</td></tr><tr><td>63</td><td>Os04g0517500</td><td>LOC_Os04g43710</td><td>2.3</td><td>Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase kinase 3 (PPCK3)</td></tr><tr><td>64</td><td>Os12g0245700</td><td>LOC_Os12g14220</td><td>2.3</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>65</td><td>Os01g0826400</td><td>LOC_Os01g61080</td><td>2.3</td><td>WRKY transcription factor 33 (WRKY33)</td></tr><tr><td>66</td><td>Os08g0352100</td><td>LOC_Os08g26350</td><td>2.3</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>67</td><td>Os02g0699000</td><td>LOC_Os02g47090</td><td>2.3</td><td>NRT1/PTR FAMILY 8.3 (NPF)</td></tr><tr><td>68</td><td>Os04g0589800</td><td>LOC_Os04g49980</td><td>2.3</td><td>Late embryogenesis abundant (LEA) group 1</td></tr><tr><td>69</td><td>Os03g0860100</td><td>LOC_Os03g64260</td><td>2.3</td><td>Ethylene-responsive transcription factor 15 (ERF15)</td></tr><tr><td>70</td><td>Os04g0244800</td><td>LOC_Os04g17100</td><td>2.2</td><td>Heavy metal-associated isoprenylated plant protein 26</td></tr><tr><td>71</td><td>Os12g0518200</td><td>LOC_Os12g33300</td><td>2.2</td><td>WAT1-related protein, permease of the drug/metabolite Transporter (DMT) superfamily</td></tr><tr><td>72</td><td>Os09g0396900</td><td>LOC_Os09g23300</td><td>2.2</td><td>Vacuolar iron transporter 1.2</td></tr><tr><td>73</td><td>Os05g0332600</td><td>LOC_Os05g26840</td><td>2.2</td><td>Adenine/guanine permease AZG1</td></tr><tr><td>74</td><td>Os01g0736600</td><td>LOC_Os01g53500</td><td>2.2</td><td>RING-H2 finger protein ATL67</td></tr><tr><td>75</td><td>Os07g0461900</td><td>LOC_Os07g27780</td><td>2.2</td><td>Acetylornithine aminotransferase (ACOAT)</td></tr><tr><td>76</td><td>Os10g0508700</td><td>LOC_Os10g36500</td><td>2.2</td><td>21&#x02009;kDa protein; PMEI-like_3; Uncharacterized subfamily of plant Invertase/pectin methylesterase inhibitor domains</td></tr><tr><td>77</td><td>Os09g0572700</td><td>LOC_Os09g39940</td><td>2.2</td><td>Basic blue protein; phytocyanin</td></tr><tr><td>78</td><td>Os10g0576600</td><td>LOC_Os10g42610</td><td>2.2</td><td>TPR protein</td></tr><tr><td>79</td><td>Os05g0546400</td><td>LOC_Os05g46840</td><td>2.2</td><td>Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome protein homolog</td></tr><tr><td>80</td><td>Os07g0599500</td><td>LOC_Os07g40850</td><td>2.2</td><td>Pollen-specific leucine-rich repeat extensin-like protein 1</td></tr><tr><td>81</td><td>Os03g0131100</td><td>LOC_Os03g03900</td><td>2.2</td><td>Protein NLP1</td></tr><tr><td>82</td><td>Os02g0581200</td><td>LOC_Os02g37070</td><td>2.2</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>83</td><td>Os04g0608300</td><td>LOC_Os04g51890</td><td>2.2</td><td>Auxin-responsive protein SAUR36-like</td></tr><tr><td>84</td><td>Os04g0597600</td><td>LOC_Os04g50940</td><td>2.1</td><td>NRT1/PTR FAMILY 8.3 (NPF7.4)</td></tr><tr><td>85</td><td>Os08g0508800</td><td>LOC_Os08g39840</td><td>2.1</td><td>Lipoxygenase 7, chloroplastic; AtLOX2 homolog</td></tr><tr><td>86</td><td>Os04g0639000</td><td>LOC_Os04g54610</td><td>2.1</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>87</td><td>Os03g0184300</td><td>LOC_Os03g08600</td><td>2.1</td><td>UDP-glucuronate:xylan alpha-glucuronosyltransferase 2</td></tr><tr><td>88</td><td>Os09g0484800</td><td>LOC_Os09g31120</td><td>2.1</td><td>Pirin-like protein</td></tr><tr><td>89</td><td>Os01g0917900</td><td>LOC_Os01g68900</td><td>2.1</td><td>C3HC4 type zinc finger protein no-on-transient A (NONA)</td></tr><tr><td>90</td><td>Os02g0198200</td><td>LOC_Os02g10470</td><td>2.1</td><td>Calcium-binding protein CML21</td></tr><tr><td>91</td><td>Os07g0561300</td><td>LOC_Os07g37400</td><td>2.1</td><td>F-box protein</td></tr><tr><td>92</td><td>Os03g0738600</td><td>LOC_Os03g52860</td><td>2.1</td><td>Linoleate 9S-lipoxygenase 2; AtLOX1 homolog</td></tr><tr><td>93</td><td>Os03g0180800</td><td>LOC_Os03g08310</td><td>2.1</td><td>TIFY 11a; jasmonate ZIM domain-containing protein 9 (JAZ9)</td></tr><tr><td>94</td><td>Os12g0108500</td><td>LOC_Os12g01760</td><td>2.1</td><td>F-box/LRR-repeat protein 3</td></tr><tr><td>95</td><td>Os09g0442100</td><td>LOC_Os09g27010</td><td>2.1</td><td>Probable receptor-like protein kinase (RLK)</td></tr><tr><td>96</td><td>Os01g0882800</td><td>LOC_Os01g66010</td><td>2.1</td><td>Amino acid permease 8 (AAP8)</td></tr><tr><td>97</td><td>Os10g0521400</td><td>LOC_Os10g37710</td><td>2.1</td><td>MhpC; Pimeloyl-ACP methyl ester carboxylesterase</td></tr><tr><td>98</td><td>Os08g0398300</td><td>LOC_Os08g30770</td><td>2.1</td><td>ABC transporter A family member 7</td></tr><tr><td>99</td><td>Os09g0511300</td><td>LOC_Os09g33650</td><td>2.1</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>100</td><td>Os10g0459700</td><td>LOC_Os10g32170</td><td>2.1</td><td>Xyloglucan galactosyltransferase KATAMARI1 homolog</td></tr><tr><td>101</td><td>Os09g0543400</td><td>LOC_Os09g37120</td><td>2.1</td><td>Ornithine decarboxylase 1 (ODC1)</td></tr><tr><td>102</td><td>Os03g0194600</td><td>LOC_Os03g09880</td><td>2.1</td><td>Cytochrome b561 and DOMON domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>103</td><td>Os08g0550200</td><td>LOC_Os08g43654</td><td>2.1</td><td>Protein DETOXIFICATION 33; MATE efflux family protein</td></tr><tr><td>104</td><td>Os03g0125100</td><td>LOC_Os03g03370</td><td>2.1</td><td>Beta-carotene hydroxylase 1 (BCH1); HYD3</td></tr><tr><td>105</td><td>Os08g0472800</td><td>LOC_Os08g36860</td><td>2.1</td><td>Abscisic acid 8&#x02032;-hydroxylase 2; Cytochrome P450 707A6</td></tr><tr><td>106</td><td>Os11g0701100</td><td>LOC_Os11g47520</td><td>2.1</td><td>Xylanase inhibitor protein 2</td></tr><tr><td>107</td><td>Os01g0164100</td><td>LOC_Os01g07040</td><td>2.1</td><td>Non-classical arabinogalactan protein 30-like</td></tr><tr><td>108</td><td>Os07g0599300</td><td>LOC_Os07g40830</td><td>2.1</td><td>Pollen-specific leucine-rich repeat extensin-like protein 1</td></tr><tr><td>109</td><td>Os12g0484600</td><td>LOC_Os12g29950</td><td>2.0</td><td>Major Facilitator Superfamily (MFS) and nodulin-like domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>110</td><td>Os08g0200100</td><td>LOC_Os08g10010</td><td>2.0</td><td>Acyl-[acyl-carrier-protein] desaturase 7, AtSAD2 homolog</td></tr><tr><td>111</td><td>Os01g0138500</td><td>LOC_Os01g04590</td><td>2.0</td><td>Unknown, DUF789 domain-containing</td></tr><tr><td>112</td><td>Os02g0143400</td><td>LOC_Os02g05060</td><td>2.0</td><td>Auxin-induced protein X15</td></tr><tr><td>113</td><td>Os06g0142650</td><td>LOC_Os06g05070</td><td>2.0</td><td>Probable receptor-like protein kinase (RLK)</td></tr><tr><td>114</td><td>Os06g0292400</td><td>LOC_Os06g18900</td><td>2.0</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>115</td><td>Os04g0541700</td><td>LOC_Os04g45810</td><td>2.0</td><td>Homeobox-leucine zipper protein HOX22</td></tr><tr><td>116</td><td>Os05g0510100</td><td>LOC_Os05g43460</td><td>2.0</td><td>Protein LURP-one-related 5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Total RNA extracted from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings (+N) or treated with nitrogen starvation for 1&#x02009;h (&#x02212;N) was used for microarray analysis. Quantitative RT-PCR analysis was used to verify the expression of genes identified in the microarray data. The expression of genes listed here was up-regulated by nitrogen starvation (&#x02212;N/+N) for more than 2-fold in the qRT-PCR analysis.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>List of genes rapidly repressed by nitrogen starvation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>No.</th><th colspan="2">Locus ID</th><th>Fold change</th><th>Gene description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Os02g0770800</td><td>LOC_Os02g53130</td><td>&#x02212;16.7</td><td>Nitrate reductase [NAD(P)H]</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Os05g0114400</td><td>LOC_Os05g02390</td><td>&#x02212;13</td><td>Zinc finger transcription factor, ZOS5-02</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Os08g0468100</td><td>LOC_Os08g36480</td><td>&#x02212;7.5</td><td>Nitrate reductase [NADH] 1</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Os11g0184900</td><td>LOC_Os11g08210</td><td>&#x02212;7.4</td><td>NAC domain-containing protein 5 (NAC5)</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Os01g0631200</td><td>LOC_Os01g44050</td><td>&#x02212;7</td><td>Uroporphyrinogen-III C-methyltransferase</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>Os03g0684700</td><td>LOC_Os03g48030</td><td>&#x02212;6.8</td><td>Unknown, integral membrane HPP family protein</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Os08g0120600</td><td>LOC_Os08g02700</td><td>&#x02212;6.4</td><td>Fructose-bisphosphate aldolase</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Os05g0194900</td><td>LOC_Os05g10650</td><td>&#x02212;6.2</td><td>ATP-dependent 6-phosphofructokinase 4 (PFK04)</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Os03g0609500</td><td>LOC_Os03g41330</td><td>&#x02212;6.1</td><td>LOB domain-containing protein 38 (LBD38)</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Os09g0482800</td><td>LOC_Os09g30490</td><td>&#x02212;5.9</td><td>EF-hand domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>Os03g0126900</td><td>LOC_Os03g03520</td><td>&#x02212;5.8</td><td>Unknown, putative AtpZ domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>Os08g0113900</td><td>LOC_Os08g02200</td><td>&#x02212;5.7</td><td>Unknown, putative AtpZ domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>Os01g0860601</td><td>LOC_Os01g64120</td><td>&#x02212;5.6</td><td>Ferredoxin, root R-B1</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>Os04g0506800</td><td>LOC_Os04g42760</td><td>&#x02212;5</td><td>Sialyltransferase-like protein 3 (STLP3)</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>Os09g0484900</td><td>LOC_Os09g31130</td><td>&#x02212;5</td><td>Tonoplast dicarboxylate transporter (TDT)</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>Os07g0589000</td><td>LOC_Os07g40000</td><td>&#x02212;4.8</td><td>LOB domain-containing protein 37 (LBD37)</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>Os12g0198900</td><td>LOC_Os12g09710</td><td>&#x02212;4.6</td><td>NB-ARC and LRR domain-containing protein, RPM1-like</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>Os04g0665600</td><td>LOC_Os04g56990</td><td>&#x02212;4.5</td><td>Myb family protein</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>Os07g0147500</td><td>LOC_Os07g05360</td><td>&#x02212;4.5</td><td>Photosystem II 10&#x02009;kDa polypeptide; PsbR</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>Os05g0119000</td><td>LOC_Os05g02750</td><td>&#x02212;4.1</td><td>UPF0014 membrane protein STAR2; AtALS3 homolog</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>Os05g0360400</td><td>LOC_Os05g29710</td><td>&#x02212;4</td><td>RING-type E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase EL5-like</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>Os09g0545280</td><td>LOC_Os09g37330</td><td>&#x02212;3.8</td><td>OsSAUR39 - Auxin-responsive SAUR gene family member</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>Os01g0179600</td><td>LOC_Os01g08440</td><td>&#x02212;3.8</td><td>Crocetin glucosyltransferase; AtIAGLU homolog</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>Os09g0433800</td><td>LOC_Os09g26370</td><td>&#x02212;3.7</td><td>Zinc-finger-FLZ domain-containing protein 14 (FLZ14)</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>Os02g0620600</td><td>LOC_Os02g40730</td><td>&#x02212;3.6</td><td>Ammonium transporter 1 member 2 (AMT1;2)</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>Os02g0756600</td><td>LOC_Os02g52000</td><td>&#x02212;3.5</td><td>Protein EXORDIUM</td></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>Os02g0120100</td><td>LOC_Os02g02780</td><td>&#x02212;3.5</td><td>Serine/threonine-protein kinase STY46</td></tr><tr><td>28</td><td>Os02g0325600</td><td>LOC_Os02g22020</td><td>&#x02212;3.5</td><td>Nitrate-inducible, GARP-type transcriptional repressor 1 (NIGT1)</td></tr><tr><td>29</td><td>Os12g0113500</td><td>LOC_Os12g02200</td><td>&#x02212;3.5</td><td>CBL-interacting protein kinase 14 (CIPK14)</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>Os10g0578800</td><td>LOC_Os10g42780</td><td>&#x02212;3.3</td><td>Plastidal glycolate/glycerate translocator 1 (PLGG1)</td></tr><tr><td>31</td><td>Os01g0908200</td><td>LOC_Os01g68020</td><td>&#x02212;3.3</td><td>BTB/POZ and TAZ domain-containing protein 2 (BT2)</td></tr><tr><td>32</td><td>Os05g0111800</td><td>LOC_Os05g02110</td><td>&#x02212;3.3</td><td>Protein phosphatase 2&#x02009;C 46 (PP2C46)</td></tr><tr><td>33</td><td>Os11g0305400</td><td>LOC_Os11g20040</td><td>&#x02212;3.1</td><td>O-methyltransferase (OMT)</td></tr><tr><td>34</td><td>Os03g0764600</td><td>LOC_Os03g55590</td><td>&#x02212;3.1</td><td>MYB family protein</td></tr><tr><td>35</td><td>Os05g0401500</td><td>LOC_Os05g33310</td><td>&#x02212;3</td><td>2OG-Fe(II) oxygenase superfamily</td></tr><tr><td>36</td><td>Os05g0443700</td><td>LOC_Os05g37150</td><td>&#x02212;3</td><td>Unknown, syntaxin 6 N-terminal domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>37</td><td>Os05g0472400</td><td>LOC_Os05g39540</td><td>&#x02212;3</td><td>Zinc transporter 9 (ZIP9)</td></tr><tr><td>38</td><td>Os04g0280500</td><td>LOC_Os04g21130</td><td>&#x02212;2.9</td><td>Putative F-box protein PP2-B12</td></tr><tr><td>39</td><td>Os05g0506800</td><td>LOC_Os05g43120</td><td>&#x02212;2.9</td><td>GDSL esterase/lipase 72 (GELP72)</td></tr><tr><td>40</td><td>Os06g0535200</td><td>LOC_Os06g34430</td><td>&#x02212;2.9</td><td>RING-H2 finger protein ATL74</td></tr><tr><td>41</td><td>Os06g0566300</td><td>LOC_Os06g37010</td><td>&#x02212;2.9</td><td>Zinc transporter 10 (ZIP10)</td></tr><tr><td>42</td><td>Os05g0380250</td><td>None</td><td>&#x02212;2.9</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>43</td><td>Os01g0208700</td><td>LOC_Os01g11054</td><td>&#x02212;2.9</td><td>Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase 4 (PPC4), chloroplastic</td></tr><tr><td>44</td><td>Os07g0686300</td><td>LOC_Os07g48680</td><td>&#x02212;2.9</td><td>RING-H2 finger protein ATL45</td></tr><tr><td>45</td><td>Os02g0214900</td><td>LOC_Os02g12350</td><td>&#x02212;2.8</td><td>Histone deacetylase 3 (HDAC3)</td></tr><tr><td>46</td><td>Os01g0179800</td><td>LOC_Os01g08460</td><td>&#x02212;2.8</td><td>Probable serine incorporator (Serinc)</td></tr><tr><td>47</td><td>Os03g0784700</td><td>LOC_Os03g57120</td><td>&#x02212;2.8</td><td>Ferredoxin&#x02212;NADP reductase (FNR)</td></tr><tr><td>48</td><td>Os03g0445700</td><td>LOC_Os03g33090</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>LOB domain-containing protein 37 (LBD37)</td></tr><tr><td>49</td><td>Os04g0649500</td><td>LOC_Os04g55600</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>50</td><td>Os04g0649600</td><td>LOC_Os04g55610</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>51</td><td>Os04g0640900</td><td>LOC_Os04g54830</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>52</td><td>Os04g0475600</td><td>LOC_Os04g39980</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>Dioxygenase for auxin oxidation (DAO)</td></tr><tr><td>53</td><td>Os12g0204100</td><td>LOC_Os12g10280</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>Aquaporin nodulin 26-like intrinsic membrane protein NIP3;5</td></tr><tr><td>54</td><td>Os02g0807000</td><td>LOC_Os02g56310</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase kinase 1 (PPCK1)</td></tr><tr><td>55</td><td>Os04g0520700</td><td>LOC_Os04g43990</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Senescence regulator-like protein</td></tr><tr><td>56</td><td>Os06g0633100</td><td>LOC_Os06g42660</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Glutamine dumper 6 (GDU6)</td></tr><tr><td>57</td><td>Os06g0683800</td><td>LOC_Os06g46980</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>58</td><td>Os05g0472700</td><td>LOC_Os05g39560</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Zinc transporter 5 (ZIP5)</td></tr><tr><td>59</td><td>Os03g0823400</td><td>LOC_Os03g60840</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Bowman-Birk type trypsin inhibitor (BBTI)</td></tr><tr><td>60</td><td>Os02g0765600</td><td>LOC_Os02g52710</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Alpha-amylase 1 (AMY1)</td></tr><tr><td>61</td><td>Os05g0501600</td><td>LOC_Os05g42220</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Leucine rich repeat domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>62</td><td>Os01g0803300</td><td>LOC_Os01g58910</td><td>&#x02212;2.5</td><td>EamA domain-containig drug/metabolite transporter (DMT)</td></tr><tr><td>63</td><td>Os01g0383100</td><td>LOC_Os01g28600</td><td>&#x02212;2.5</td><td>Exocyst complex component EXO70A1</td></tr><tr><td>64</td><td>Os11g0484500</td><td>LOC_Os11g29400</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase (6PGDH)</td></tr><tr><td>65</td><td>Os11g0256900</td><td>LOC_Os11g15040</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>O-methyltransferase</td></tr><tr><td>66</td><td>Os06g0692600</td><td>LOC_Os06g47750</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>Tyrosine-sulfated glycopeptide receptor 1; leucine-rich repeat receptor-like protein kinase</td></tr><tr><td>67</td><td>Os01g0357100</td><td>LOC_Os01g25484</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>Nitrite reductase</td></tr><tr><td>68</td><td>Os05g0443500</td><td>LOC_Os05g37140</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>Ferredoxin-6, chloroplastic</td></tr><tr><td>69</td><td>Os04g0683700</td><td>LOC_Os04g58710</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>Oxalate&#x02013;CoA ligase; acyl-activating enzyme 3 (AAE3)</td></tr><tr><td>70</td><td>Os03g0599000</td><td>LOC_Os03g40194</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>Putative disease resistance protein RGA3</td></tr><tr><td>71</td><td>Os04g0561500</td><td>LOC_Os04g47360</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>Prolyl endopeptidase</td></tr><tr><td>72</td><td>Os07g0406300</td><td>LOC_Os07g22350</td><td>&#x02212;2.3</td><td>Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PDH)</td></tr><tr><td>73</td><td>Os04g0403701</td><td>LOC_Os04g33080</td><td>&#x02212;2.3</td><td>Protein phosphatase 2&#x02009;C 39 (PP2C39)</td></tr><tr><td>74</td><td>Os01g0621900</td><td>LOC_Os01g43370</td><td>&#x02212;2.3</td><td>Unknown, conserved peptide uORF-containing transcript</td></tr><tr><td>75</td><td>Os03g0190300</td><td>LOC_Os03g09070</td><td>&#x02212;2.3</td><td>Leucine rich repeat domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>76</td><td>Os08g0207500</td><td>LOC_Os08g10630</td><td>&#x02212;2.3</td><td>Zinc transporter 4 (ZIP4)</td></tr><tr><td>77</td><td>Os08g0465700</td><td>LOC_Os08g36310</td><td>&#x02212;2.2</td><td>Cytochrome P450 76M5-like</td></tr><tr><td>78</td><td>Os03g0838900</td><td>LOC_Os03g62240</td><td>&#x02212;2.2</td><td>Unknown, mTERF domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>79</td><td>Os04g0165200</td><td>LOC_Os04g08290</td><td>&#x02212;2.2</td><td>Zinc finger protein STAR3-like, ZOS4-04</td></tr><tr><td>80</td><td>Os09g0453300</td><td>LOC_Os09g27990</td><td>&#x02212;2.2</td><td>Annexin D8</td></tr><tr><td>81</td><td>Os02g0756200</td><td>LOC_Os02g51970</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Protein EXORDIUM</td></tr><tr><td>82</td><td>Os03g0854000</td><td>LOC_Os03g63700</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Putative gamma-glutamylcyclotransferase</td></tr><tr><td>83</td><td>Os01g0355100</td><td>LOC_Os01g25270</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Jacalin-like plant lectin domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>84</td><td>Os10g0554200</td><td>LOC_Os10g40600</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>NRT1/ PTR FAMILY 6.3 (NPF6.5)</td></tr><tr><td>85</td><td>Os10g0328400</td><td>LOC_Os10g18099</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>86</td><td>Os06g0323100</td><td>LOC_Os06g21820</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Indole-3-acetate O-methyltransferase 1 (IAMT1)-like</td></tr><tr><td>87</td><td>Os07g0119300</td><td>LOC_Os07g02800</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>MYB family protein</td></tr><tr><td>88</td><td>Os02g0306401</td><td>LOC_Os02g20360</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Nicotianamine aminotransferase A</td></tr><tr><td>89</td><td>Os09g0474000</td><td>LOC_Os09g29820</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>bZIP transcription factor 53</td></tr><tr><td>90</td><td>Os03g0243100</td><td>LOC_Os03g13950</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Actin-depolymerizing factor 5 (ADF5)</td></tr><tr><td>91</td><td>Os01g0747300</td><td>LOC_Os01g54340</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>PDDEXK nuclease-like family of unknown function</td></tr><tr><td>92</td><td>Os02g0525100</td><td>LOC_Os02g32450</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>93</td><td>Os01g0191700</td><td>LOC_Os01g09570</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>ATP-dependent 6-phosphofructokinase 6 (PFK01)</td></tr><tr><td>94</td><td>Os03g0228100</td><td>LOC_Os03g12690</td><td>&#x02212;2</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>95</td><td>Os05g0342000</td><td>LOC_Os05g27580</td><td>&#x02212;2</td><td>Wound-induced WI12 family protein</td></tr><tr><td>96</td><td>Os01g0888900</td><td>LOC_Os01g66544</td><td>&#x02212;2</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>97</td><td>Os04g0645500</td><td>LOC_Os04g55250</td><td>&#x02212;2</td><td>S-adenosylmethionine-dependent methyltransferase</td></tr><tr><td>98</td><td>Os05g0411100</td><td>LOC_Os05g34030</td><td>&#x02212;2</td><td>NRT1/PTR FAMILY 3.1-like (NPF)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Total RNA extracted from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings (+N) or treated with nitrogen starvation for 1&#x02009;h (&#x02212;N) was used for microarray analysis. Quantitative RT-PCR analysis was used to verify the expression of genes identified in the microarray data. The expression of genes listed here was down-regulated by nitrogen starvation (&#x02212;N/+N) for more than 2-fold in the qRT-PCR analysis.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>GO and KEGG enrichment analyses of early N starvation-induced genes</title><p id="Par11">AgriGO (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/">http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/</ext-link>) was used for GO enrichment analysis of the 116 genes induced by &#x02212;N. In biological process, the GO terms &#x0201c;cellular amino acid and derivative metabolic process&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;cellular ketone metabolic process&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;organic acid metabolic process&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;cellular nitrogen compound metabolic process&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;amine metabolic process&#x0201d; were significantly enriched (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). In molecular function, the GO terms &#x0201c;ion/cation/metal ion binding&#x0201d; were significantly enriched (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>). No GO terms were enriched in the category of cellular component. The information of genes enriched in GO analysis is provided in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>. In addition, KEGG pathway analysis of the 116 &#x02212;N-induced genes revealed that &#x0201c;plant hormone signal transduction (ko04075)&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;carotenoid biosynthesis (ko00906)&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;plant-pathogen interaction (ko04626)&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;linoleic acid metabolism (ko00591)&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;arginine and proline metabolism (ko00330)&#x0201d; were enriched. The information of genes enriched in these KEGG pathways is provided in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>. Together, the GO and KEGG enrichment analyses suggest that &#x02212;N rapidly induced the expression of genes involved in N remobilization and plant hormone signal transduction in rice roots.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Gene ontology (GO) analysis of nitrogen starvation (&#x02212;N)-induced genes. AgriGO (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/">http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/</ext-link>) was used to analyze the &#x02212;N-induced genes in 10-day-old rice seedling roots (false discovery rate, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Of the three structured networks, the &#x02212;N-induced genes are significantly enriched in the GO categories of biological process (<bold>A</bold>), and molecular function (<bold>B</bold>). The &#x02212;N-induced genes were not enriched in the GO categories of cellular component.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e4018"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Analysis of &#x02212;N-induced genes involved in metabolism, plant hormone signal transduction, and oxidative response</title><p id="Par12">In the category of biological process, GO enrichment analysis identified 9 genes encoding enzymes involved in metabolic processes. These enzymes are arogenate dehydratase/prephenate dehydratase 6 (ADT6, Os10g0523700) of phenylalanine biosynthesis, phenylalanine ammonia-lyase (PAL3, Os02g0626600 and PAL4, Os02g0627100) of the phenylpropanoid pathway, methionine gamma-lyase (MGL, Os10g0517500) of methionine catabolism, acetylornithine aminotransferase (ACOAT, Os07g0461900) and ornithine decarboxylase 1 (ODC1, Os09g0543400) of arginine biosynthesis, acyl-[acyl-carrier-protein] desaturase 7 (SAD, Os08g0200100, an Arabidopsis SAD2 homolog), &#x003b1;-carbonic anhydrase 7 (&#x003b1;-CA7, Os08g0470200), and GTP diphosphokinase (calcium-activated RelA-SpoT homolog 2 [CRSH2], Os05g0161500). CRSH2 is a Ca<sup>+2</sup>-activated (p)ppGpp synthetase that has been proposed to integrate the Ca<sup>+2</sup> and (p)ppGpp signaling pathways in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. The expression patterns of these metabolic genes during the time course (0&#x02013;24&#x02009;h) of &#x02212;N treatment are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Expression of metabolic genes rapidly induced by nitrogen starvation. Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of genes involved in small molecule metabolic process (<bold>A</bold>), abscisic acid and jasmonic acid metabolism (<bold>B</bold>), and oxidative stress response (<bold>C</bold>). RNA samples from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with nitrogen starvation for 0, 15&#x02009;min, 30&#x02009;min, 1&#x02009;h, 4&#x02009;h and 24&#x02009;h were analyzed by qRT-PCR. The expression level of each gene in the control sample (0&#x02009;h) was set at 1. Relative expression represents the fold change of the target gene relative to that of the control. Data are mean &#x000b1;SD of 3 biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e4054"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">The genes identified in the KEGG pathway &#x0201c;carotenoid biosynthesis (ko00906)&#x0201d;, <italic>Os09g0555500</italic> encoding phytoene synthase 3 (PSY3), <italic>Os03g0125100</italic> encoding beta-carotene hydroxylase 1 (BCH1), and <italic>Os08g0472800</italic> encoding abscisic acid 8&#x02032;-hydroxylase 2 (ABA8OX2), are also involved in the biosynthesis and metabolism of plant hormone ABA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The expression patterns of these genes during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>. The genes enriched in the KEGG pathway &#x0201c;linoleic acid metabolism (ko00591), including <italic>Os08g0508800</italic> encoding chloroplastic lipoxygenase 7, a homolog of Arabidopsis LOX2, and <italic>Os03g0738600</italic> encoding linoleate 9S-lipoxygenase 2, a homolog of Arabidopsis LOX1, are involved in the biosynthesis of plant hormone jasmonic acid (JA). The expression of these JA biosynthesis genes was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>).</p><p id="Par14">In addition, the expression of several genes related to oxidative stress was also rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). For instance, the expression of <italic>Os06g0521500</italic>, <italic>Os05g0135400</italic>, and <italic>Os06g0522300</italic> encoding peroxidase (POX) and <italic>Os07g0468100</italic> encoding glutathione S-transferase (GSTU1) was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>). Galactinol synthase (GolS) is the key enzyme for the synthesis of raffinose family oligosaccharide in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. In addition to their roles as osmoprotectants, galactinol and raffinose have been shown to protect plants from oxidative damage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Interestingly, we found that the expression of <italic>GolS1</italic> (<italic>Os03g0316200</italic>) and <italic>GolS2</italic> (<italic>Os07g0687900</italic>) was rapidly and strongly induced by &#x02212;N in rice roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>). These results implicated that oxidative stress might be one of the early events associated with N deprivation in the roots of rice seedlings.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Identifiction of early N starvation-induced transcription factor genes</title><p id="Par15">Of the 116 &#x02212;N-induced genes, at least 12 genes encode transcription factors. The expression patterns of these transcription factor genes during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>. The <italic>Os03g0183500</italic> gene encodes an uncharacterized plant-specific FCS-like zinc finger protein FLZ24<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. The expression of <italic>FLZ24</italic> was rapidly and strongly induced by &#x02212;N, which peaked at 15&#x02009;min during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The homeodomain-leucine zipper (HD-ZIP) gene <italic>HOX22</italic> (<italic>Os04g0541700</italic>) has been shown to affect ABA biosynthesis and regulate drought and salt responses through ABA-mediated signaling pathways in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. The basic helix-loop-helix transcription factor gene <italic>bHLH120</italic> (<italic>Os09g0455300</italic>) corresponds to the quantitative trait locus <italic>qRT9</italic> that controls root thickness and root length in upland rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. Previous studies revealed that the expression of <italic>HOX22</italic> and <italic>bHLH120</italic> was strongly induced by polyethylene glycol, salt, and ABA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the expression of <italic>HOX22</italic> and <italic>bHLH120</italic> was also rapidly and strongly induced by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The <italic>Os12g0156100</italic> gene encodes a homolog of Arabidopsis NAC90. The expression of <italic>Os12g0156100</italic> (<italic>NAC90</italic>) was strongly induced by &#x02212;N after treatment for 1&#x02013;4&#x02009;h (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Expression of transcription factor and protein kinase/phosphatase genes induced by nitrogen starvation. (<bold>A</bold>) Transcription factor genes. (<bold>B</bold>) Protein kinase/phosphatase genes. RNA samples from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with nitrogen starvation for 0, 15&#x02009;min, 30&#x02009;min, 1&#x02009;h, 4&#x02009;h and 24&#x02009;h were analyzed by qRT-PCR. The expression level of each gene in the control sample (0&#x02009;h) was set at 1. Relative expression represents the fold change of the target gene relative to that of the control. Data are mean &#x000b1;SD of 3 biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e4232"/></fig></p><p id="Par16">The plant-specific TIFY/JAZ (jasmonate-zim domain) transcription factors are key regulators of JA signaling pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. It has been demonstrated that the expression of <italic>TIFY11a</italic> (<italic>JAZ9</italic>, <italic>Os03g0180800</italic>), <italic>TIFY11c</italic> (<italic>JAZ11</italic>, <italic>Os03g0180900</italic>) and <italic>TIFY11e</italic> (<italic>JAZ13</italic>, <italic>Os10g0391400</italic>) was strongly induced by JA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Interestingly, &#x02212;N also rapidly induced the expression of these key transcription factor genes for JA signaling (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The expression patterns of <italic>TIFY11a</italic> (<italic>JAZ9</italic>, <italic>Os03g0180800</italic>), <italic>TIFY11c</italic> (<italic>JAZ11</italic>, <italic>Os03g0180900</italic>) and <italic>TIFY11e</italic> (<italic>JAZ13</italic>, <italic>Os10g0391400</italic>) during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>. The <italic>Os08g0360300</italic> gene encodes a homolog of Arabidopsis SYSTEMIC ACQUIRED RESISTANCE DEFICIENT 1 (SARD1) that is involved in salicylic acid (SA) signaling pathways. The expression of <italic>SARD1</italic> (<italic>Os08g0360300</italic>) was also induced by &#x02212;N in rice roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>).</p><p id="Par17">The <italic>Os03g0860100</italic> gene encodes ethylene-responsive transcription factor 15 (ERF15) of unknown function. The expression of <italic>Os03g0860100</italic> (<italic>ERF15</italic>) was rapidly and strongly induced by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The <italic>Os01g0826400</italic> gene encodes a homolog of Arabidopsis WRKY33 that plays an important role in defense response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. The expression of rice <italic>WRKY33</italic> (<italic>Os01g0826400</italic>) was also induced by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The <italic>Os02g0646200</italic> gene encodes B-box zinc finger protein 6 (BBX6), a homolog of Arabidopsis BBX20/21 that are involved in photomorphogenesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. The expression of <italic>Os02g0646200</italic> (<italic>BBX6</italic>) was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The Arabidopsis NIN-like proteins (NLPs) are key players in nitrate signaling pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. The <italic>Os03g0131100</italic> (<italic>NLP1</italic>) gene encodes a homolog of Arabidopsis NLPs. The expression of <italic>NLP1</italic> was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N in rice roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Identifiction of early N starvation-induced protein kinase/phosphatase genes</title><p id="Par18">Protien kinases and phosphatases are well known regulatory proteins involved in various signal transduction pathways. We have identified at least 6 protein kinase and one protein phosphatase genes that are rapidly induced by &#x02212;N in rice roots (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The cell wall-associated receptor kinases (WAKs) are primarily involved in the regulation of plant cell wall functions such as pathogen response, binding to pectin to control cell expansion, morphogenesis and development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. The expression of <italic>WAK125</italic> (<italic>Os12g0478400</italic>) and <italic>WAK37</italic> (<italic>Os04g0365100</italic>) was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N in rice roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>). Interestingly, <italic>WAK125</italic> was previously found to be an early glutamate-responsive gene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. In addition to <italic>WAK125</italic> and <italic>WAK37</italic>, the expression of <italic>Os09g0442100</italic> and <italic>Os06g0142650</italic>, encoding receptor-like protein kinase (RLK) homologs, was also rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>). The functions of these protein kinases have yet to be characterized in rice.</p><p id="Par19">The activity of phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase (PEPC), a key enzyme of primary metabolism of higher plants, is regulated by PEPC kinase (PPCK). The expression of <italic>PPCK3</italic> (<italic>Os04g0517500</italic>) was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N in rice roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>). The expression of <italic>Os07g0678300</italic> encoding calcineurin B-like protein (CBL) interacting protein kinase 29 (CIPK29) was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>). Interestingly, the expression of <italic>CIPK29</italic> was previously shown to be down-regulated by potassium (K) deficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. In addition, the <italic>Os12g0189300</italic> gene encoding carboxyvinyl-carboxyphosphonate phosphorylmutase was rapidly and strongly induced by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), but was also previously shown to be down-regulated by K deficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. These genes may be involved in the regulation of &#x02212;N and &#x02212;K responses, but in the opposite way.</p><p id="Par20">The only protein phosphatase gene found to be rapidly induced by &#x02212;N is <italic>Os09g0325700</italic> that encodes protein phosphatase 2&#x02009;C 68 (PP2C68). The rice PP2C68 is a homolog of Arabidopsis HAI1/2/3 (highly ABA-induced PP2C protein 1/2/3). It is not clear if ABA can induce the expression of <italic>PP2C68</italic>. Nevertheless, &#x02212;N can induce the expression of <italic>PP2C68</italic> in rice roots. The expression patterns of <italic>PP2C68</italic> during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Analysis of genes rapidly induced by &#x02212;N and +N</title><p id="Par21">We previously used microarray and qRT-PCR analyses to identify 158 genes that were rapidly induced by +N (1.43&#x02009;mM ammonium nitrate, 30&#x02009;min) in the roots of hydroponically grown rice seedlings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. We compared the 116 genes up-regulated by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) with the 158 genes induced by +N and found that the expression of 3 genes, <italic>Os01g0705200</italic> encoding a late embryogenesis abundant protein, <italic>Os08g0473900</italic> encoding an &#x003b1;-amylase, and <italic>Os10g0576600</italic> encoding a tetratricopeptide repeat (TPR) protein was induced by both &#x02212;N and +N treatments in rice roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6A</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). To verify this result, we used 10-day-old rice seedlings to conduct &#x02212;N and +N time course treatments. Total RNA extracted from roots of these samples was used for qRT-PCR analysis to examine the expression of <italic>Os01g0705200</italic>, <italic>Os08g0473900</italic>, and <italic>Os10g0576600</italic>. The results revealed that these genes responded to +N and &#x02212;N rapidly and transiently (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6B&#x02013;D</xref>). In general, the expression of these genes was induced by +N and &#x02212;N after 15&#x02009;min to 4&#x02009;h, and back to control levels after 24&#x02009;h (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6B&#x02013;D</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Identification of genes rapidly induced by the addition and deprivation of nitrogen. (<bold>A</bold>) Venn diagram of genes induced by nitrogen starvation (&#x02212;N) and ammonium nitrate supplementation (+N)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. RNA samples from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with &#x02212;N or +N for 0, 15&#x02009;min, 30&#x02009;min, 1&#x02009;h, 4&#x02009;h and 24&#x02009;h were used for qRT-PCR to analyze the expression of <italic>Os01g0705200</italic> encoding a late embryogenesis abundant protein (<bold>B</bold>), <italic>Os08g0473900</italic> encoding &#x003b1;-amylase isozyme 3D (<bold>C</bold>), and <italic>Os10g0576600</italic> encoding a TPR protein (<bold>D</bold>). The expression level of each gene in the control sample (0&#x02009;h) was set at 1. Relative expression represents the fold change of the target gene relative to that of the control. Data are mean &#x000b1;SD of 3 biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e4580"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>List of genes rapidly induced by nitrogen starvation and ammonium nitrate in rice roots.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="2">Locus ID</th><th colspan="2">Fold change</th><th rowspan="2">Gene description</th></tr><tr><th>&#x02212;N/+N</th><th>+N/&#x02212;N</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Os01g0705200</td><td>LOC_Os01g50910</td><td>3.2</td><td>3.0</td><td>Late embryogenesis abundant protein, group 3</td></tr><tr><td>Os08g0473900</td><td>LOC_Os08g36910</td><td>2.4</td><td>2.7</td><td>Alpha amylase isozyme 3D</td></tr><tr><td>Os10g0576600</td><td>LOC_Os10g42610</td><td>2.2</td><td>2.1</td><td>TPR protein</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>GO and KEGG enrichment analyses of early N starvation-repressed genes</title><p id="Par22">In addition to &#x02212;N-induced genes, we also performed GO and KEGG enrichment analyses on the 98 genes repressed by &#x02212;N. In biological process, the GO terms such as &#x0201c;metal ion transport&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;glucose metabolic process&#x0201d; were significantly enriched (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7A</xref>). In molecular function, the GO terms &#x0201c;transporter activity&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;inorganic cation transmembrane transporter activity&#x0201d; were significantly enriched (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7B</xref>). In cellular component, the GO term &#x0201c;membrane&#x0201d; was significantly enriched (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7C</xref>). These results suggest that rapid changes in glucose metabolism to decrease the amounts of C skeleton for N assimilation and the reduction of various transporter activities are among the early events of N deprivation in rice roots. The information of &#x02212;N-repressed genes enriched in GO analysis is provided in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Gene ontology (GO) analysis of nitrogen starvation-repressed genes. AgriGO (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/">http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/</ext-link>) was used to analyze nitrogen starvation-repressed genes in 10-day-old rice seedling roots, and significantly enriched GO categories in biological process (<bold>A</bold>), molecular function (<bold>B</bold>), and cellular component (<bold>C</bold>) are shown in orange and yellow boxes (false discovery rate, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e4700"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">KEGG pathway enrichment analysis of the 98 &#x02212;N-repressed genes indicated that &#x0201c;pentose phosphate pathway (ko00030)&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;photosynthesis (ko00195)&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;nitrogen metabolism (ko00910)&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;carbon metabolism (ko01200)&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;fructose and mannose metabolism (ko00051)&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms (ko00710)&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;glutathione metabolism (ko00480)&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;biosynthesis of amino acids (ko01230)&#x0201d; were enriched. These results suggest that the expression of genes involved in N assimilation and production of C skeletons for amino acid biosynthesis is rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N. The information of genes enriched in these pathways is provided in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>. These GO and KEGG enrichment analyses highlight the importance of coordinated regulation of C and N metabolism in response to changes of N nutrients in rice seedlings.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Analysis of metabolic and transporter genes rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N</title><p id="Par24">It is expected that &#x02212;N will repress the expression of genes related to nitrate/nitrite assimilation, ferredoxin reduction, and the pentose phosphate pathway. Indeed, we found that the expression of <italic>Os02g0770800</italic> and <italic>Os08g0468100</italic> encoding nitrate reductase (NIA), <italic>Os01g0357100</italic> encoding nitrite reductase (NIR), <italic>Os01g0860601</italic> encoding ferridoxin (Fd), and <italic>Os03g0784700</italic> encoding ferredoxin-NADP reductase (FNR) was rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8A</xref>). The major function of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PDH) and 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase (6PGDH) of the oxidative pentose phosphate pathway is to generate NADPH for the assimilation of inorganic N and fatty acid biosynthesis. The expression of <italic>G6PDH</italic> (<italic>Os07g0406300</italic>) and <italic>6PGDH</italic> (<italic>Os11g0484500</italic>) was also rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8A</xref>). In addition to <italic>G6PDH</italic> and <italic>6PGDH</italic>, genes involved in &#x0201c;cellular carbohydrate metabolic process (GO:0044262)&#x0201d; include <italic>Os05g0194900</italic> encoding ATP-dependent 6-phosphofructokinase 4 (PFK4), a key enzyme of the glycolysis pathway, <italic>Os08g0120600</italic> encoding fructose-bisphosphate aldolase (FBA), and <italic>Os04g0506800</italic> encoding sialyltransferase-like protein 3 (STLP3) (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). The expression patterns of these genes during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8A</xref>.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of genes repressed by nitrogen starvation (&#x02212;N) in rice roots. (<bold>A</bold>) Carbon and nitrogen metabolic genes. (<bold>B</bold>) Transporter genes. (<bold>C</bold>) Nitrate transporter genes. RNA samples from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with &#x02212;N for 0, 15&#x02009;min, 30&#x02009;min, 1&#x02009;h, 4&#x02009;h and 24&#x02009;h were used for qRT-PCR analysis. The expression of nitrate transporter genes <italic>Os10g0554200</italic> (<italic>NRT1.1B</italic>/<italic>NPF6.5</italic>) and <italic>Os05g0411100</italic> (<italic>NPF</italic>) was rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N, whereas the expression of <italic>Os02g0699000</italic> (<italic>NPF</italic>) and <italic>Os04g0597600</italic> (<italic>NPF7.4</italic>) was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N. The expression level of each gene in the control sample (0&#x02009;h) was set at 1. Relative expression represents the fold change of the target gene relative to that of the control. Data are mean &#x000b1;SD of 3 biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e4814"/></fig></p><p id="Par25">In addition to genes involved in C and N metabolism, the expression of genes involved in the transport and allocation of C and N metabolites was also rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). For instance, the expression of <italic>AMT1;2</italic> (<italic>Os02g0620600</italic>) encoding a key ammonium transporter was rapidly and strongly repressed by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8B</xref>). The expression of <italic>Os09g0484900</italic> encoding a tonoplast dicarboxylate transporter (TDT), <italic>Os12g0204100</italic> encoding an aquaporin nodulin 26-like intrinsic membrane protein (NIP3;5), <italic>Os06g0633100</italic> encoding glutamine dumper 6 (GDU6), <italic>Os10g0578800</italic> encoding plastidial glycolate/glycerate translocator 1 (PLGG1) and <italic>Os01g0803300</italic> encoding a drug/metabolite transporter (DMT) was also rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8B</xref>). Interestingly, we also found that the expression of four zinc transporter genes, <italic>ZIP4</italic> (<italic>Os08g0207500</italic>), <italic>ZIP5</italic> (<italic>Os05g0472700</italic>), <italic>ZIP9</italic> (<italic>Os05g0472400</italic>), and <italic>ZIP10</italic> (<italic>Os06g0566300</italic>), was rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N in rice roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8B</xref>).</p><p id="Par26">The rice nitrate transporter NRT1.1B/NPF6.5 has been demonstrated to play an important role in the regulation of N use efficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the expression of <italic>Os10g0554200</italic> (<italic>NRT1.1B</italic>/<italic>NPF6.5</italic>) and <italic>Os05g0411100</italic> (<italic>NPF</italic>) was rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8C</xref>). By contrast, the expression of another two nitrate transporter genes, <italic>Os02g0699000</italic> (<italic>NPF</italic>) and <italic>Os04g0597600</italic> (<italic>NPF7.4</italic>), was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8C</xref>). It has been demonstrated that &#x02212;N can induce the expression of high affinity nitrate transporter genes and repress the expression of low affinifity nitrate transporter genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. It is possible that Os02g0699000 (NPF) and Os04g0597600 (NPF7.4) have higher affinifity to nitrate than Os10g0554200 (NRT1.1B/NPF6.5) and Os05g0411100 (NPF). Nevertheless, the physiological and biochemical features of these nitrate transporters have yet to be further characterized.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Identification of genes that are sensitive to the availability of N in rice roots</title><p id="Par27">Venn diagram analysis of the 98 genes down-regulated by &#x02212;N and the 158 genes up-regulated by +N identified 34 overlapped genes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9A</xref>). The expression of these N-sensitive genes was rapidly induced by +N and quickly repressed by &#x02212;N. A complete list of these 34 genes is shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. As expected, genes related to nitrate/nitrite assimilation, ferredoxin reduction, and the pentose phosphate pathway are very sensitive to the availability of N in the growth medium (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The <italic>BT2</italic> (<italic>Os01g0908200</italic>) gene encoding a negative regulator of N use efficiency and several prominent candidate genes for the regulation of N response, including <italic>LBD37</italic> (<italic>Os03g0445700</italic>, <italic>Os07g0589000</italic>), and <italic>LBD38</italic> (<italic>Os03g0609500</italic>), are among the 34 genes identified here (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Still, we have identified several novel genes encoding potential N regulatory proteins, which may be involved in the regulation of N metabolism and/or signaling in rice roots.<fig id="Fig9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Identification of nitrogen-sensitive genes in rice seedling roots. (<bold>A</bold>) Venn diagram analysis of genes repressed by nitrogen starvation (&#x02212;N) and induced by ammonium nitrate supplementation (+N)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The expression of the 34 overlapped genes was rapidly induced by +N and quickly repressed by &#x02212;N. RNA samples from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with +N or &#x02212;N for 0, 15&#x02009;min, 30&#x02009;min, 1&#x02009;h, 4&#x02009;h and 24&#x02009;h were used for qRT-PCR to analyze the expression of <italic>BT2</italic> encoding a nitrogen regulatory protein (<bold>B</bold>), and transcription factor/protein kinase genes (<bold>C</bold>). The expression level of each gene in the control sample (0&#x02009;h) was set at 1. Relative expression represents the fold change of the target gene relative to that of the control. Data are mean &#x000b1;SD of 3 biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig9_HTML" id="d29e4996"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>List of nitrogen-sensitive genes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">No.</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="2">Locus</th><th colspan="2">Fold change</th><th rowspan="2">Gene description</th></tr><tr><th>+N/&#x02212;N</th><th>&#x02212;N/+N</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Os02g0770800</td><td>LOC_Os02g53130</td><td>65.8</td><td>&#x02212;16.7</td><td>Nitrate reductase [NAD(P)H]</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Os01g0860601</td><td>LOC_Os01g64120</td><td>42.2</td><td>&#x02212;5.6</td><td>Ferredoxin, root R-B1</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Os01g0631200</td><td>LOC_Os01g44050</td><td>32.3</td><td>&#x02212;7.0</td><td>Uroporphyrinogen-III C-methyltransferase</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Os03g0609500</td><td>LOC_Os03g41330</td><td>30.5</td><td>&#x02212;6.1</td><td>LOB domain-containing protein 38 (LBD38)</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Os03g0684700</td><td>LOC_Os03g48030</td><td>25.8</td><td>&#x02212;6.8</td><td>Integral membrane HPP family protein (HPP)</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>Os09g0484900</td><td>LOC_Os09g31130</td><td>15.7</td><td>&#x02212;5.0</td><td>Tonoplast dicarboxylate transporter (TDT)</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Os03g0445700</td><td>LOC_Os03g33090</td><td>15.0</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>LOB domain-containing protein 37 (LBD37)</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Os05g0114400</td><td>LOC_Os05g02390</td><td>14.0</td><td>&#x02212;13.0</td><td>Zinc finger transcription factor, ZOS5-02</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Os04g0640900</td><td>LOC_Os04g54830</td><td>13.4</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Os11g0184900</td><td>LOC_Os11g08210</td><td>11.5</td><td>&#x02212;7.4</td><td>NAC domain-containing protein 5 (NAC5)</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>Os07g0119300</td><td>LOC_Os07g02800</td><td>9.4</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>MYB family transcription factor</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>Os07g0589000</td><td>LOC_Os07g40000</td><td>8.5</td><td>&#x02212;4.8</td><td>LOB domain-containing protein 37 (LBD37)</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>Os03g0784700</td><td>LOC_Os03g57120</td><td>8.5</td><td>&#x02212;2.8</td><td>Ferredoxin&#x02212;NADP reductase (FNR)</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>Os03g0764600</td><td>LOC_Os03g55590</td><td>8.0</td><td>&#x02212;3.1</td><td>MYB family transcription factor</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>Os01g0357100</td><td>LOC_Os01g25484</td><td>8.0</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>Nitrite reductase</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>Os03g0243100</td><td>LOC_Os03g13950</td><td>6.5</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Actin-depolymerizing factor 5 (ADF5)</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>Os05g0360400</td><td>LOC_Os05g29710</td><td>5.9</td><td>&#x02212;4.0</td><td>RING-type E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase EL5-like</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>Os12g0113500</td><td>LOC_Os11g02240</td><td>5.4</td><td>&#x02212;3.5</td><td>CBL-interacting protein kinase 14 (CIPK14)</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>Os07g0406300</td><td>LOC_Os07g22350</td><td>5.1</td><td>&#x02212;2.3</td><td>Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PDH)</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>Os03g0823400</td><td>LOC_Os03g60840</td><td>5.0</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Bowman-Birk type trypsin inhibitor 13 (BBTI13)</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>Os06g0633100</td><td>LOC_Os06g42660</td><td>4.9</td><td>&#x02212;2.6</td><td>Glutamine dumper 6 (GDU6)</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>Os05g0443700</td><td>LOC_Os05g37150</td><td>4.8</td><td>&#x02212;3.0</td><td>Unknown, syntaxin 6 N-terminal domain protein</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>Os06g0566300</td><td>LOC_Os06g37010</td><td>4.5</td><td>&#x02212;2.9</td><td>Zinc transporter 10 (ZIP10)</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>Os11g0484500</td><td>LOC_Os11g29400</td><td>4.3</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase (6PGDH)</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>Os04g0475600</td><td>LOC_Os04g39980</td><td>3.1</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>Dioxygenase for auxin oxidation (DAO)</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>Os05g0194900</td><td>LOC_Os05g10650</td><td>2.9</td><td>&#x02212;6.2</td><td>ATP-dependent 6-phosphofructokinase 4 (PFK04)</td></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>Os01g0621900</td><td>LOC_Os01g43370</td><td>2.9</td><td>&#x02212;2.3</td><td>Unknown, conserved peptide uORF-containing transcript</td></tr><tr><td>28</td><td>Os03g0838900</td><td>LOC_Os03g62240</td><td>2.9</td><td>&#x02212;2.2</td><td>Unknown, mTERF domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>29</td><td>Os05g0443500</td><td>LOC_Os05g37140</td><td>2.9</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>Ferredoxin-6, chloroplastic</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>Os08g0207500</td><td>LOC_Os08g10630</td><td>2.6</td><td>&#x02212;2.3</td><td>Zinc transporter 4 (ZIP4)</td></tr><tr><td>31</td><td>Os01g0908200</td><td>LOC_Os01g68020</td><td>2.4</td><td>&#x02212;3.3</td><td>BTB/POZ and TAZ domain-containing protein 2 (BT2)</td></tr><tr><td>32</td><td>Os04g0649500</td><td>LOC_Os04g55600</td><td>2.3</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>33</td><td>Os04g0649600</td><td>LOC_Os04g55610</td><td>2.3</td><td>&#x02212;2.7</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>34</td><td>Os01g0747300</td><td>LOC_Os01g54340</td><td>2.2</td><td>&#x02212;2.1</td><td>Unknown, PDDEXK nuclease-like family protein</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Genes listed here are up-regulated by ammonium nitrate (+N/&#x02212;N)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> and down-regulated by nitrogen starvation (&#x02212;N/+N) for more than 2-fold after 30 min-1 h of treatments. Numbers of fold change are derived from the microarray data.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par28">To verify the expression of these 34 N-sensitive genes, total RNA extracted from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with +N or &#x02212;N for 0, 15&#x02009;min, 1&#x02009;h, 4&#x02009;h, and 24&#x02009;h was used for qRT-PCR analysis. The results of these +N and &#x02212;N time course experiments confirmed that the expression of these 34 genes was rapidly induced by +N and quickly repressed by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9B,C</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). For instance, the expression of the N regulatory gene <italic>BT2</italic> was rapidly regulated by +N and &#x02212;N, but in the opposite way (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9B</xref>). The 34 N-sensitive genes include at least 7 transcription factor genes, <italic>Os03g0609500</italic> (<italic>LBD38</italic>), <italic>Os03g0445700</italic> (<italic>LBD37</italic>), <italic>Os07g0589000</italic> (<italic>LBD37</italic>), <italic>Os05g0114400</italic> (<italic>ZOS5-02</italic>), <italic>Os11g0184900</italic> (<italic>NAC5</italic>), <italic>Os07g0119300</italic> (<italic>MYB</italic>) and <italic>Os03g0764600</italic> (<italic>MYB</italic>), and one protein kinase gene, <italic>Os12g0113500</italic> (<italic>CIPK14</italic>). The expression patterns of these genes during the time course of +N and &#x02212;N treatments are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9C</xref>.</p><p id="Par29">The expression patterns of genes related to nitrate/nitrite assimilation, ferredoxin reduction, and the pentose phosphate pathway during the +N and &#x02212;N time course treatments are shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>. The assimilation of N is highly dependent on the availability of C skeletons derived from glycolysis and the TCA cycle. In addition to N metabolic and regulatory genes, the expression of <italic>Os05g0194900</italic> encoding ATP-dependent 6-phosphofructokinase 4 (PFK04), a key enzyme of the glycolysis pathway, was rapidly induced by +N and quickly repressed by &#x02212;N (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). The expression of 5 transporter genes, including <italic>Os06g0633100</italic> encoding glutamine dumper 6 (GDU6), <italic>Os09g0484900</italic> encoding tonoplast dicarboxylate transporter (TDT), <italic>Os03g0684700</italic> encoding an integral membrane HHP family protein (HHP), <italic>Os08g0207500</italic> encoding zinc transporter 4 (ZIP4) and <italic>Os06g0566300</italic> encoding zinc transporter 10 (ZIP10), was up-regulated by +N and down-regulated by &#x02212;N (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>).</p><p id="Par30">The <italic>Os04g0475600</italic> gene encoding dioxygenase for auxin oxidation (DAO) is involved in catalyzing the irreversible oxidation of active indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) to biologically inactive 2-oxindole-3-acetic acid (oxIAA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the expression of <italic>DAO</italic> (<italic>Os04g0475600</italic>) was rapidly regulated by +N and &#x02212;N treatments (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Actin-depolymerizing factors (ADFs) are involved in the regulation of actin assembly, which affects cell growth, expansion, proliferation and differentiation. We have identified that one of the <italic>ADF</italic> genes, <italic>ADF5</italic> (<italic>Os03g0243100</italic>), is a N-sensitive gene (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). This implicates that the N status may rapidly and directly regulate cell growth and differentiation via the reorganization of cytoskeletons in rice roots. In addition to BT2, the ubiquitin-mediated proteolytic degradation machinery has been shown to modulate N responses in Arabidopsis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the expression of <italic>Os05g0360400</italic> encoding RING-type E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase EL5-like was rapidly regulated by the availability of N in the growth medium (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>).</p><p id="Par31">In addition, the expression of <italic>Os03g0823400</italic> encoding a Bowman-Birk type trypsin inhibitor (BBTI) was rapidly induced by +N and quickly repressed by &#x02212;N (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). We previously found that the expression of <italic>BBTI</italic> was also rapidly induced by glutamine and glutamate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Trypsin inhibitor is usually associated with defense response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. It is not clear why the expression of this particular <italic>BBTI</italic> (<italic>Os03g0823400</italic>) gene is tightly regulated by the availability of N in the growth medium. The <italic>Os05g0443700</italic> gene, one of the 7 unknown function genes identified here, encodes a syntaxin 6 N-terminal domain-containing protein, which is commonly found in various SNARE proteins involved in endosomal transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. The rapid response of <italic>Os05g0443700</italic> to +N and &#x02212;N treatments (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>) suggest that the encoded protein may be involved in cell trafficking associated with N metabolism and/or signaling. The expression patterns of the other 6 unknown function genes (<italic>Os04g0640900, Os01g0621900, Os03g0838900, Os04g0649500, Os04g0649600, Os01g0747300</italic>) during the time course of +N and &#x02212;N treatments are shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Analysis of &#x02212;N-repressed transcription factor genes</title><p id="Par32">In addition to the 7 N-sensitive transcription factor genes shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9C</xref>, we have identified at least 6 more genes encoding transcription factors or nuclear proteins, including <italic>Os04g0665600</italic> (<italic>MYB</italic>), <italic>Os02g0325600</italic> (<italic>NIGT1</italic>), <italic>Os02g0214900</italic> (<italic>HDAC3</italic>, <italic>HISTONE DEACETYLASE 3</italic>), <italic>Os04g0165200</italic> (<italic>ZOS4-04</italic>), <italic>Os09g0474000</italic> (<italic>bZIP53</italic>) and <italic>Os09g0433800</italic> (<italic>FLZ14</italic>), that were rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N. NIGT1 is a N regulatory protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. The enzyme histone deacetylase 3 (HDAC3) may have a global effect on gene expression via chromosome modification. The functions of <italic>Os04g0665600</italic> encoding a MYB family protein, <italic>Os04g0165200</italic> encoding a zinc-finger protein (ZOS4-04), <italic>Os09g0474000</italic> encoding basic leucine zipper 53 (bZIP53) and <italic>Os09g0433800</italic> encoding FCS-like zinc finger protein 14 (FLZ14) are unknown. The expression patterns of these 6 genes during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10A</xref>. The expression of <italic>Os04g0665600</italic> (<italic>MYB</italic>) and <italic>Os02g0325600</italic> (<italic>NIGT1</italic>) was strongly and continuously repressed by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10A</xref>). By contrast, the expression of <italic>Os09g0474000</italic> (<italic>bZIP53</italic>) and <italic>Os09g0433800</italic> (<italic>FLZ14</italic>) was only transiently repressed within 1&#x02009;h of &#x02212;N treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10A</xref>).<fig id="Fig10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Expression of transcription factor and protein kinase/phosphatase genes rapidly repressed by nitrogen starvation in rice roots. RNA samples from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with nitrogen starvation for 0, 15&#x02009;min, 30&#x02009;min, 1&#x02009;h, 4&#x02009;h and 24&#x02009;h were used for qRT-PCR to analyze the expression of genes encoding transcription factor/nuclear protein (<bold>A</bold>), and protein kinase/phosphatase (<bold>B</bold>). The expression level of each gene in the control sample (0&#x02009;h) was set at 1. Relative expression represents the fold change of the target gene relative to that of the control. Data are mean &#x000b1;SD of 3 biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_Fig10_HTML" id="d29e5996"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Analysis of &#x02212;N-repressed protein kinase/phosphatase genes</title><p id="Par33">We identified at least 4 protein kinase and 2 phosphatase genes that were rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N in rice seedling roots (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). <italic>CIPK14</italic> (<italic>Os12g0113500</italic>) is a N-sensitive gene that is rapidly regulated by +N and &#x02212;N treatments as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8B</xref>. The expression patterns of the other protein kinase/phosphatase genes, e.g. <italic>Os02g0120100</italic> (<italic>ACTPK1</italic>), <italic>Os02g0807000</italic> (<italic>PPCK1</italic>), <italic>Os06g0692600</italic> (<italic>RLK</italic>), <italic>Os04g0403701</italic> (<italic>PP2C39</italic>), and <italic>Os05g0111800</italic> (<italic>PP2C46</italic>), during the time course of &#x02212;N treatment are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10B</xref>. ACTPK1 (Os02g0120100) has been demonstrated to phosphorylate and inactivate the ammonium transporter AMT1;2 in rice seedling roots under sufficient ammonium conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. The <italic>Os02g0807000</italic> gene encodes phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase kinase 1 (PPCK1) that plays an important role in the regulation of phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase (PEPC) and plant metabolism. The functions of the other protein kinases/phosphatases and/or their roles in the regulation of N response have yet to be characterized in rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Genes rapidly regulated by N starvation, glutamine, and glutamate</title><p id="Par34">In addition to ammonium nitrate, we previously used transcriptome analysis followed by RT-PCR or qRT-PCR verification to identify genes that were rapidly regulated by glutamine (+Gln, 2.5&#x02009;mM, 30&#x02009;min) or glutamate (+Glu, 2.5&#x02009;mM, 30&#x02009;min) in rice roots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. In the +Gln study, we only identified 35 up-regulated genes, whereas 122 up- and 4 down-regulated genes were identified in the +Glu study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. None of the 35&#x02009;+&#x02009;Gln-induced genes were induced by &#x02212;N (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6A</xref>). By contrast, 10 of the 35 Gln-induced genes were rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6B</xref> and Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Interestingly, 5 of the 10&#x02009;+&#x02009;Gln-induced and &#x02212;N-repressed genes encode transcription factors, e.g. <italic>ZOS5-02</italic> (<italic>Os05g0114400</italic>), <italic>NAC5</italic> (<italic>Os11g0184900</italic>), <italic>LBD37</italic> (<italic>Os07g0589000</italic>), <italic>LBD37</italic> (<italic>Os03g0445700</italic>), and <italic>MYB</italic> (<italic>Os07g0119300</italic>) (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). The other 5&#x02009;+&#x02009;Gln-induced and &#x02212;N-repressed genes are <italic>CIPK14</italic> (<italic>Os12g0113500</italic>), <italic>GDU6</italic> (<italic>Os06g0633100</italic>), <italic>PFK04</italic> (<italic>Os05g0194900</italic>), <italic>BBTI13</italic> (<italic>Os03g0823400</italic>), and <italic>Os09g0482800</italic> encoding an EF-hand domain-containing protein (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>).</p><p id="Par35">Interestingly, the expression of 9 +Gln-induced and &#x02212;N-repressed genes, except <italic>Os09g0482800</italic> encoding an EF-hand domain-containing protein, was also rapidly induced by +N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. These results suggest that part of the inorganic N signaling pathways may be mediated via glutamine, and some of the transcription factors/regulatory proteins identified here may be involved in these processes in rice seedlings.</p><p id="Par36">Venn diagram analysis of genes induced by &#x02212;N and +Glu identified 12 overlapped genes (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7A</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>.). The &#x02212;N- and +Glu-induced genes include <italic>Os09g0455300</italic> (<italic>bHLH120</italic>), <italic>Os12g0478400</italic> (<italic>WAK125</italic>), <italic>Os08g0508800</italic> (<italic>LOX2</italic>), <italic>Os02g0627100</italic> (<italic>PAL4</italic>), <italic>Os01g0882800</italic> encoding amino acid permease 8, <italic>Os12g0518200</italic> encoding a drug/metabolite transporter (DMT), <italic>Os08g0473900</italic> (&#x003b1;-amylase isozyme 3D), <italic>Os01g0666000</italic> encoding lipid phosphate phosphatase 2, <italic>Os03g0318400</italic> encoding aspartic proteinase nepenthesin-1, <italic>Os01g0705200</italic>, encoding a late embryogenesis abundant protein, <italic>Os03g0194600</italic> encoding cytochrome b561 and DOMON domain-containing protein, and <italic>Os06g0292400</italic> encoding an unknown function protein. Exogenous Glu has been implicated to induce defense response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. It is possible that +Glu and &#x02212;N may share some components related to stress and/or defense response. For instance, the <italic>Os08g0508800</italic> gene encodes a LOX2 homolog that may play an important role in the biosynthesis of JA in rice. The expression of <italic>Os08g0508800</italic> (LOX2) was commonly induced by +Glu<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> and &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). It will be interesting to further investigate if JA, as well as the other +Glu- and &#x02212;N-induced genes, are involved in the interaction between +Glu and &#x02212;N signaling pathways.</p><p id="Par37">By contrast, comparison between the &#x02212;N-repressed and +Glu-induced genes revealed that the expression of <italic>NAC5</italic> (<italic>Os11g0184900</italic>), <italic>LBD37</italic> (<italic>Os07g0589000</italic>), <italic>MYB</italic> (<italic>Os07g0119300</italic>), <italic>BBTI13</italic> (<italic>Os03g0823400</italic>), <italic>TDT</italic> (<italic>Os09g0484900</italic>), and <italic>Os09g0482800</italic> encoding an EF-hand domain-containing protein was rapidly regulated by +Glu and &#x02212;N (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7B</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). Interestingly, 4 of the 6&#x02009;+&#x02009;Glu-induced and &#x02212;N-repressed genes, e.g. <italic>NAC5</italic> (<italic>Os11g0184900</italic>), <italic>LBD37</italic> (<italic>Os07g0589000</italic>), <italic>MYB</italic> (<italic>Os07g0119300</italic>) and <italic>BBTI</italic> (<italic>Os03g0823400</italic>), were also commonly induced by +N and +Gln<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The <italic>Os09g0482800</italic> gene encoding an EF-hand domain-containing protein is only shared by +Gln and +Glu, whereas the <italic>TDT</italic> (<italic>Os09g0484900</italic>) gene is commonly induced by +N and +Glu<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, these analyses futher support the notion that the transcription factors NAC5 (Os11g0184900), LBD37 (Os07g0589000) and MYB (Os07g0119300) are potential N regulatory proteins in rice. None of the 4 +Glu-repressed genes overlapped with the genes up- or down-regulated by &#x02212;N.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par38">Transcriptomic analysis using microarray or RNA-Seq has been applied to identify genes that are differentially regulated by &#x02212;N in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. However, these studies were either performed with a relatively long time of N deprivation or the identified genes were not verified by independent experiments. Here, we used a more stringent approach to identify genes that were rapidly regulated by &#x02212;N in rice roots. All genes identified by microarray analysis were further verified by qRT-PCR, and only those genes that had fold-change greater than 2 (&#x02212;N/+N) in both experiments were used for GO and KEGG enrichment analyses. Approximately 19% of the up-regulated and 32% of the down-regulated genes identified by microarray analysis did not pass the verification by qRT-PCR. In addition to genes involved in C and N metabolism, the expression of genes related to &#x0201c;plant hormone signal transduction&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;transporter activity&#x0201d; is rapidly regulated by &#x02212;N in rice roots.</p><p id="Par39">The expression of genes related to nitrate/ammonium uptake, nitrate/nitrite assimilation, ferredoxin reduction, the pentose phosphate pathway, and glucose metabolic process was rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). By contrast, the expression of genes involved in the release of ammonium, including <italic>PAL3</italic> (<italic>Os02g0626600</italic>), <italic>PAL4</italic> (<italic>Os02g0627100</italic>), and <italic>MGL</italic> (<italic>Os10g0517500</italic>) was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). These results suggest that the recycling of ammonium from amino acids is one of the early events during &#x02212;N in rice seedlings. The release of ammonium from amino acids may provide the initial demand of N during the sudden change from N sufficient to N deficient conditions.</p><p id="Par40">In bacteria, guanosine pentaphosphate and tetraphosphate (p)ppGpp play a major role in the stringent response such as nutrient starvation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Bacterial (p)ppGpp is synthesized from ATP and GTP/GDP by the RelA and SpoT enzymes, which modulates target enzymes to reduce cell proliferation to conserve resources and activates the acclimatory pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Genes encoding RelA and SpoT homologs (RSH) are widespread in plants and algae, which may play an important role in influencing plant growth and stress acclimation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the expression of <italic>Os05g0161500</italic> encoding chloroplastic GTP diphosphokinase/calcium-activated RelA-SpoT homolog 2 (CRSH2) was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N in rice roots (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref>). CRSH2 contains a central RelA-SpoT domain and two EF-hand motifs for calcium binding that may function as a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated (p)ppGpp synthetase to integrate the Ca<sup>2+</sup> and (p)ppGpp signaling pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. It will be interesting to investigate if CRSH2 and its product (p)ppGpp are involvled in the acclimatory responses during N deficiency in rice.</p><p id="Par41">The metabolism of C and N is highly interdependent as the assimilation of inorganic N requires C skeletons derived from glycolysis and the TCA cycle. Thus, the production and flux of C skeletons has to be regulated to match the demands under various N conditions. However, how the N status is perceived to regulate C metabolism and flux is unknown. Phosphofructokinase (PFK) catalyzes a key regulatory step of the glycolysis pathway. The expression of <italic>PFK04</italic> (<italic>Os05g0194900</italic>), one of the 15 <italic>PFK</italic> genes identified in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>, was rapidly induced by +N and quickly repressed by &#x02212;N in rice roots (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Dicarboxylate transporters play an important role in the transport and compartmentation of C metabolites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>. The expression of <italic>TDT</italic> (<italic>Os09g0484900</italic>) was co-regulated with <italic>PFK04</italic> and N assimilatory genes in response to the availability of N in the environment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). It is possible that PFK04 is one of the key enzymes that coordinately regulate C metabolism, and the intracellular dicarboxylate transporter TDT may modulate the levels of dicarboxylate in different cellular compartments in response to the demand of N assimilation in rice roots.</p><p id="Par42">The inter-dependency of C and N metabolism suggests that the signal transduction pathways underlying C and N deficiency may also interact with each other. The regulatory proteins CIPK14/CIPK15 have been shown to coordinate the responses to oxygen and sugar deficiency in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>. Interestingly, <italic>CIPK14</italic>/<italic>CIPK15</italic> are N-sensitive genes as the expression of <italic>CIPK14</italic>/<italic>CIPK15</italic> in rice roots was rapidly regulated by the availability of N in the growth medium (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). This finding further supports the notion that CIPK14/15 may coordinate the C and N signaling pathways in response to the relative C/N status in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par43">In addition to rapid changes in C and N metabolism, the homeostasis of plant homones such as IAA, JA, and ABA, and their signal transduction pathways may be associated with the early events of N deficiency in rice. It is known that auxin/IAA is involved in the regulation of root system archetiture in response to nitrate and N deficiency in Arabidopsis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>. By contrast, how auxin/IAA regulates the growth and development of rice roots in response to N deficiency is largely unknown. DAO (Os04g0475600) catalyzes the irreversible oxidation of IAA to oxIAA in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. The discovery that <italic>DAO</italic> is a N-sensitive gene provides insights into the involvement of IAA oxidation in the modulation of N responses in rice roots. In addition to IAA oxidation, the formation of IAA-glucose conjugate or IAA methyl ester (MeIAA) is one of the molecular modifications controlling IAA homeostasis and activity. Interestingly, the expression of <italic>Os01g0179600</italic> encoding indole-3-acetate beta-D-glucosyltransferase (IAGLU) and <italic>Os06g0323100</italic> encoding indole-3-acetate O-methyltransferase 1 (IAMT1) was rapidly repressed by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). These results suggest that N deficiency may increase the amount of IAA via decreasing the formation of oxidized- and conjugated-IAA, which in turn activates the IAA signaling pathway. In accordance with this hypothesis, the expression of <italic>PIN9</italic> (<italic>Os01g0802700</italic>), <italic>SAUR19</italic> (<italic>Os06g0702000</italic>), <italic>SAUR36</italic> (<italic>Os04g0608300</italic>) and <italic>Os02g0143400</italic> encoding auxin-induced protein X15 was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Thus, the oxidation and modifications of IAA may play a role in mediating N-deficient responses in rice roots.</p><p id="Par44">In addition to IAA, plant hormones JA and ABA may be also involved in the regulation of &#x02212;N responses in rice roots. The <italic>TIFY11a</italic> (<italic>JAZ9</italic>, <italic>Os03g0180800</italic>), <italic>TIFY11c</italic> (<italic>JAZ11</italic>, <italic>Os03g0180900</italic>), and <italic>TIFY11e</italic> (<italic>JAZ13</italic>, <italic>Os10g0391400</italic>) genes identified in the categories of &#x0201c;plant hormone signal transduction&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;plant-pathogen interaction&#x0201d; encode key components of the JA signaling pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. The <italic>Os08g0508800</italic> gene identified in the &#x0201c;linoleic acid metabolism&#x0201d; encodes a LOX2 homolog, which is a key enzyme of the JA biosynthesis pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>. The expression of these genes and <italic>Os04g0308500</italic> encoding a 23&#x02009;kDa jasmonate-induced protein was rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). These results indicate that the JA signal transduction pathways are among the early responses associated with N deficiency in rice roots.</p><p id="Par45">The plant hormone ABA is derived from the carotenoid biosynthesis pathway. The &#x02212;N-induced genes <italic>PSY3</italic> (<italic>Os09g0555500</italic>) and <italic>BCH1</italic> (<italic>Os03g0125100</italic>) are associated with ABA biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The rice <italic>PSY</italic> gene family consists of 3 members. <italic>PSY1</italic> and <italic>PSY2</italic> are involved in light-regulated carotenoid biosynthesis, whereas <italic>PSY3</italic> is devoted to abiotic stress-induced ABA formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The <italic>Os03g0125100</italic> gene encoding &#x003b2;-carotene hydroxylase 1 (BCH1) was shown to confer drought and oxidative stress resistance by increasing xanthophylls and ABA in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Moreover, the expression of <italic>PSY3</italic> and <italic>BCH1</italic> is induced by ABA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Interestingly, we found that &#x02212;N could rapidly and strongly induce the expression of <italic>PSY3</italic> and <italic>BCH1</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). The expression of ABA-responsive transcription factor genes <italic>HOX22</italic> and <italic>bHLH120</italic> was also rapidly and strongly induced by &#x02212;N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). These results suggest that ABA biosynthesis and signaling are among the early events induced by N deficiency in rice roots. Recently, ABA was shown to regulate auxin homeostais to promote root hair elongation in rice root tips<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup>. It is known that N deficiency will induce cell division as well as cell elongation to promote primary root growth in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. It is possible that these processes are governed by auxin and the interactions between auxin and ABA in rice.</p><p id="Par46">ROS production was shown to be associated with K, P, and N deficiencies in Arabidopsis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>. The rapid induction of genes encoding peroxidase or peroxidase-like proteins (<italic>Os06g0521500</italic>, <italic>Os05g0135400</italic>, and <italic>Os06g0522300</italic>) and <italic>Os07g0468100</italic> encoding GSTU1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>) indicates that N deficiency may also cause ROS production in rice roots. In addition, the expression of several oxidative stress-responsive genes was also rapidly induced by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). For instance, the expression of <italic>GolS1</italic> (<italic>Os03g0316200</italic>) and <italic>GolS2</italic> (<italic>Os07g0687900</italic>) encoding galactinol synthase, a key enzyme for the synthesis of raffinose family oligosaccharide to protect plants from oxidative damage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, was rapidly and strongly induced by &#x02212;N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>). These results implicate that the production of ROS and redox signaling pathways are among the early events associated with N deficiency in rice roots.</p><p id="Par47">We have identified several transcription factor genes, including <italic>NIGT1</italic>, whose expression is rapidly regulated by &#x02212;N (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref> and <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>). The functions of these genes in the regulation of N responses are mostly uncharacterized in rice. The Arabidopsis LBD/37/38/39 transcription factors have been demonstrated to regulate N responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the expression of <italic>Os07g058900</italic>, <italic>Os03g0445700</italic> and <italic>Os03g0609500</italic> encoding LBD37/38 homologs is co-regulated with <italic>NIA</italic> and <italic>NIR</italic> in response to changes of N availability (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). It is likely that the LBD37/38 homologs also play a key role in the regulation of N responses in rice. The NAC5 transcription factor is involved in stress tolerance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup>, but its role as a N regulatory protein has yet to be characterized. Further studies on NAC5 may provide insights into the interaction between the N response and stress signaling pathways in rice. In addition to transcription factor genes, we have also identified several protein kinase/phosphatase genes that are rapidly up- or down-regulated by &#x02212;N (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref> and <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>). The functions of these genes, except <italic>ACTPK1</italic>, in the regulation of N responses are unknown. Further studies on these potential N regulatory genes may provide a new solution to enhance N use efficiency in rice.</p><p id="Par48">Components of the ubiquitin-mediated proteolytic degradation machinery have been shown to modulate N responses in Arabidopsis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. The Arabidopsis BTB protein acts as a substrate-specific adapter of an E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase complex (CUL3-RBX1-BTB), which mediates the ubiquitination and subsequent proteasomal degradation of target proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>. One of the Arabidopsis BTB proteins, BT2, has been shown to mediate multiple responses to nutrients, stresses, and hormones<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup>. The rice BT2 homolog (Os01g0908200) functions as a negative regulator of nitrate transporter genes and N use efficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. It is possible that the ubiquitin-mediated proteolytic degradation machinery using BT2 as a hub may also interconnect N, hormone, and stress signaling pathways in rice. Interestingly, <italic>BT2</italic> and <italic>Os05g0360400</italic> encoding RING-type E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase EL5-like are N-sensitive genes. The expression of <italic>BT2</italic> and <italic>EL5-like</italic> was co-regulated with <italic>NIA</italic> and <italic>NIR</italic> in response to changes of N in the growth medium (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9B</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Ubiquitin ligase EL5 has been shown to maintain the viability of root meristems by influencing cytokinin-mediated nitrogen effects in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>. The function of EL5-like (Os05g0360400) protein has yet to be characterized. It is worthy to further investigate if BT2 and EL5-like (Os05g0360400) are involved in the regulation of N response and the crosstalk among multiple signaling pathways in rice.</p><p id="Par49">GO enrichment analysis revealed that transporter genes were enriched in &#x02212;N-repressed genes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Interestingly, some of the &#x02212;N-repressed transporter genes were also rapidly induced by +N (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). In addition to <italic>TDT</italic>, the expression of <italic>GDU6</italic>, <italic>ZIP4</italic>, <italic>ZIP10</italic> and <italic>Os03g0684700</italic> encoding an integral membrane HPP family protein was co-regulated with <italic>NIA</italic> and <italic>NIR</italic> in response to the availability of N (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Glutamine dumpers are plant-specific membrane proteins that are involved in nonselective amino acid export<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref></sup>. GDU6 may modulate the transport of amino acids in response to changes of N in the growth medium. Members of integral membrane HPP family are predicted to contain 4 transmembrane domains and a conserved HPP motif (Pfam: PF04982). Some of the Arabidopsis HPP family proteins are nitrate-inducible components of the nitrite transport system of plastids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref></sup>. It will be interesting to further study if HPP (Os03g0684700) is a nitrite transporter in rice. Zinc is an essential element that functions as a catalytic or structural co-factor in a large number of enzymes and regulatory proteins in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref></sup>. It has been shown that improved N nutrition can enhance zinc uptake and remobilization in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref></sup>. However, it is not clear if the uptake and remobilization of zinc will affect N metabolism. The discovery that <italic>ZIP4</italic> and <italic>ZIP10</italic> are N-sensitive genes raises an interesting question whether the homeostasis of zinc plays a role in the regulation of N response. Still, we cannot exclude the possibility that some of the zinc transporters may transport zinc as well as the other compounds associated with N metabolism.</p><p id="Par50">We previously used microarray analysis followed by RT-PCR or qRT-PCR verification to identify genes that were rapidly regulated by +N, +Gln, and +Glu in rice roots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Comparison of these results revealed that there were at least 7 genes that were commonly induced by +N, +Gln, and +Glu<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. We proposed that these genes may be involved in the regulation of general N responses in rice roots regardless the forms of N source<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Interestingly, 4 of these 7 genes, e.g. <italic>LBD37</italic> (<italic>Os07g058900</italic>), <italic>NAC5</italic> (<italic>Os11g0184900</italic>), <italic>MYB</italic> (<italic>Os07g0119300</italic>), and <italic>BBTI13</italic> (<italic>Os03g0823400</italic>), are among the N-sensitive genes identified here (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9C</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Previously, Gln was found to be rapidly accumulated in the roots of rice seedlings after 15&#x02013;30&#x02009;min of +N treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Similarly, Gln also rapidly accumulated after feeding of Glu in rice seedling roots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Here, we found that levels of Gln were rapidly reduced within 15&#x02009;min of &#x02212;N treatment in rice roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). These results suggest that the endogenous levels of glutamine are very sensitive to the availability of N in the environment. It is conceiveable that part of the general N signal may be mediated by Gln. Nonetheless, further studies on the putative N regulatory genes identified here may provide insights into the regulation of N signaling pathways in rice roots.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec19"><title>Plant material and growth conditions</title><p id="Par51">The rice plant <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> cv. TNG67 was used in all experiments. Rice seeds were surface-sterilized and placed in darkness at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 3 days. The germinated seedlings were transferred to 5-inch square pots filled with hydroponic solutions and placed in a growth chamber at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 7 days under a 12&#x02009;h light/12&#x02009;h dark cycle, 200 &#x000b5;mol photons m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> light intensity, and 70% relative humidity. The hydroponic solution recommended by the International Rice Research Institute containing 1.43&#x02009;mM NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub> was used as +N treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, and the same hydroponic solution without the addition of 1.43&#x02009;mM NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub> was used as &#x02212;N treatment in all experiments. For &#x02212;N treatment, 10-day-old rice seedlings grown in +N hydroponic solution were transferred to &#x02212;N hydroponic solution for 1&#x02009;h or the indicated time. The nutrient solution was completely renewed every 3 days.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Leaf chlorophyll measurement</title><p id="Par52">Leaf chlorophyll measurement was conducted with the Chlorophyll Content Meter (CCM-300, Opti-sciences, NH, USA) as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Fifteen leaves from 15 rice seedlings grown in +N or &#x02212;N hydroponic solution were used for the measurement.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Microarray analysis</title><p id="Par53">The GeneChip Rice Genome Array (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA, USA) was used for transcriptome analysis. The extraction of total RNA from roots of 10-day-old rice seedlings grown in +N or &#x02212;N (1&#x02009;h) was conducted as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref></sup>. RNA samples of three biological replicates from +N- or &#x02212;N-treated rice seedling roots were submitted to the Affymetrix Gene Expression Service Lab at Academia Sinica (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ipmb.sinica.edu.tw/affy/">http://ipmb.sinica.edu.tw/affy/</ext-link>) for microarray analysis. The experimental procesdures and criteria for selecting &#x02212;N-regulated genes were performed as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. AgriGO (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/">http://bioinfo.cau.edu.cn/agriGO/</ext-link>) and EXPath (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://expath.itps.ncku.edu.tw">http://expath.itps.ncku.edu.tw</ext-link>) were used for GO and KEGG enrichment analysis of the &#x02212;N-regulated genes, respectively. The nomenclature of genes listed in Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> is according to the annotation in NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/</ext-link>) or relevant literatures.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of genes responsive to &#x02212;N or +N treatment</title><p id="Par54">Total RNA extracted from 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with &#x02212;N or +N for the indicated time was used for qRT-PCR analysis with 3 biological replicates. The expression of nuclear genes <italic>UBC3</italic> (<italic>Os02g0634800</italic>) and <italic>UBQ10</italic> (<italic>Os02g 0161900</italic>) was used to normalize the qRT-PCR data. The primer sequences used in this study are listed in Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>. The sequences of <italic>CIPK14</italic> (<italic>Os12g0113500</italic>) and <italic>CIPK15</italic> (<italic>Os11g0113700</italic>) are highly identical. The expression of these two genes cannot be distinguished by qRT-PCR with the primers used in this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Analysis of free amino acids in rice roots</title><p id="Par55">The Waters Acquity UPLC system was used to analyze free amino acids extracted from 10-day-old rice seedlings treated with &#x02212;N for 0&#x02013;4&#x02009;h. Amino acid extraction and analysis were performed as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec24"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_30632_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Ping-Han Hsieh and Chia-Cheng Kan contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-30632-1.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Yan-An Juo for assistance in qRT-PCR analysis, Tsui-Yun Chung, Yi-Chieh Wang and Kuan-Lin Her for sample preparation. This research was supported by Sustainability Science Project AS-106-SS-A03 from Academia Sinica to M.H.H.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>M.H.H. conceived this research and designed experiments. P.H.H. C.C.K., H.Y.W. and H.C.Y. performed experiments. P.H.H., C.C.K. and M.H.H. analyzed data and prepared figures. M.H.H. wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The microarray datasets generated in this study are available in the NCBI GEO repository GSE109649 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE109649">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE109649</ext-link>). All other data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article and its Supplementary Information files.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seck</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Diagne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wopereis</surname><given-names>MCS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crops that feed the world 7: Rice</article-title><source>Food Sec.</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12571-012-0168-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khush</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green revolution: preparing for the 21st century</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>1999</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g99-044</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10464789?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10464789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strategies for overcoming low agronomic nitrogen use efficiency in irrigated rice systems in China</article-title><source>Field Crops Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2005.05.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reducing environmental risk by improving N management in intensive Chinese agricultural systems</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>3041</fpage><lpage>3046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0813417106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19223587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19223587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Socolow</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen management and the future of food: lessons from the management of energy and carbon</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>6001</fpage><lpage>6008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.11.6001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10339531?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10339531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Gouis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallais</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The challenge of improving nitrogen use efficiency in crop plants: towards a more central role for genetic variability and quantitative genetics within integrated approaches</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2007</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>2369</fpage><lpage>2387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erm097</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17556767?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17556767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitousek</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen in agriculture: Balancing the cost of an essential resource</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Env. Resour.</source><year>2009</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.environ.032108.105046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant nitrogen assimilation and use efficiency</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042811-105532</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22224450?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22224450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frink</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Waggoner</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen fertilizer: retrospect and prospect</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>1175</fpage><lpage>1180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.4.1175</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9989997?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9989997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giehl</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>von Wir&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Root nutrient foraging</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.245225</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25082891?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25082891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and physiological aspects of nitrate uptake in plants</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>1998</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(98)01311-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forde</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrate transporters in plants: structure, function and regulation</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta.</source><year>2000</year><volume>1465</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-2736(00)00140-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10748256?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10748256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Wiren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential regulation of three functional ammonium transporter genes by nitrogen in root hairs and by light in leaves of tomato</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.2000.00665.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10743657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richard-Molard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plant response to nitrate starvation is determined by N storage capacity matched by nitrate uptake capacity in two Arabidopsis genotypes</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erm363</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18304979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18304979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krapp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis roots and shoots show distinct temporal adaptation patterns toward nitrogen starvation</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>1255</fpage><lpage>1282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.179838</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21900481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21900481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Guegler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>LaBrie</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis of a nutrient response in Arabidopsis reveals diverse expression patterns and novel metabolic and potential regulatory genes induced by nitrate</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>1509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.12.8.1491</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10948265?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10948265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microarray analysis of the nitrate response in Arabidopsis roots and shoots reveals over 1,000 rapidly responding genes and new linkages to glucose, trehalose-6-phosphate, iron, and sulfate metabolism</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.021253</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12805587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12805587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis of the nitrate response using a nitrate reductase-null mutant of Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>2512</fpage><lpage>2522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.044610</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15333754?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15333754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palenchar</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouranov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lejay</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Coruzzi</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide patterns of carbon and nitrogen regulation of gene expression validate the combined carbon and nitrogen (CN)-signaling hypothesis in plants</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>R91</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2004-5-11-r91</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15535867?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15535867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide reprogramming of primary and secondary metabolism, protein synthesis, cellular growth processes, and the regulatory infrastructure of Arabidopsis in response to nitrogen</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>2483</fpage><lpage>2499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.047019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15375205?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15375205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased nitrogen-use efficiency in transgenic rice plants over-expressing a nitrogen-responsive early nodulin gene identified from rice expression profiling</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>2009</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1749</fpage><lpage>1760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2009.02032.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19682292?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19682292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obertello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katari</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Coruzzi</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-species network analysis uncovers conserved nitrogen-regulated network modules in rice</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>1830</fpage><lpage>1843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.255877</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26045464?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26045464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandran</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide transcriptome analysis of expression in rice seedling roots in response to supplemental nitrogen</article-title><source>J. Plant Physiol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>200</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2016.06.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27340859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27340859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNA-Seq analysis of differentially expressed genes in rice under varied nitrogen supplies</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2015</year><volume>555</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2014.11.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25447912?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25447912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome response to nitrogen starvation in rice</article-title><source>J. Biosci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12038-012-9242-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22922198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22922198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression profiles of 10,422 genes at early stage of low nitrogen stress in rice assayed using a cDNA microarray</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-005-5441-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16649102?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16649102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis of nitrogen starvation-responsive genes in rice</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-015-0425-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Members of the LBD family of transcription factors repress anthocyanin synthesis and affect additional nitrogen responses in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3567</fpage><lpage>3584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.067041</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19933203?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19933203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A nitrate-inducible GARP family gene encodes an auto-repressible transcriptional repressor in rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pct007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23324170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23324170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medici</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AtNIGT1/HRS1 integrates nitrate and phosphate signals at the Arabidopsis root tip</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>6274</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms7274</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25723764?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25723764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lack of ACTPK1, an STY kinase, enhances ammonium uptake and use, and promotes growth of rice seedlings under sufficient external ammonium</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2018</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>992</fpage><lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13824</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29356222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29356222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Juo</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glutamine rapidly induces the expression of key transcription factor genes involved in nitrogen and stress responses in rice roots</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>731</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1892-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26407850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26407850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Juo</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exogenous glutamate rapidly induces the expression of genes involved in metabolism and defense responses in rice roots</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>186</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-017-3588-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28212609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28212609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of early ammonium nitrate-responsive genes in rice roots</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>16885</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-17173-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29203827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29203827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araus</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Members of BTB gene family of scaffold proteins suppress nitrate uptake and nitrogen use efficiency</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1532</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27208309?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27208309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yoshida, S., Forno, D. A., Cock, J. H. &#x00026; Gomez, K. A. Laboratory manual for physiological studies of rice. In: The International Rice Research Institute. 3rd ed. p. 61&#x02013;66 (1976).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulating the root elongation by phosphate/nitrogen starvation in an OsGLU3 dependant way in rice</article-title><source>Plant Signal Behav.</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1144</fpage><lpage>1145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.21334</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22899054?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22899054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tozawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Calcium-activated (p)ppGpp synthetase in chloroplasts of land plants</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>35536</fpage><lpage>35545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M703820200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17938177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17938177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welsch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000fc;st</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;r</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Babili</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A third phytoene synthase is devoted to abiotic stress-induced abscisic acid formation in rice and defines functional diversification of phytoene synthase genes</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.117028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18326788?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18326788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallabhaneni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurtzel</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PSY3, a new member of the phytoene synthase gene family conserved in the Poaceae and regulator of abiotic stress-induced root carotenogenesis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>1333</fpage><lpage>1345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.107.111120</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18162592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18162592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the &#x003b2;-carotene hydroxylase gene DSM2 conferring drought and oxidative stress resistance by increasing xanthophylls and abscisic acid synthesis in rice</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>1304</fpage><lpage>1318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.163741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vallabhaneni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurtzel</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Timing and biosynthetic potential for carotenoid accumulation in genetically diverse germplasm of maize</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.137042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19346441?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Basak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Majumder</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significance of galactinol and raffinose family oligosaccharide synthesis in plants</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>656</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00656</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26379684?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26379684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishizawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yabuta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigeoka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Galactinol and raffinose constitute a novel function to protect plants from oxidative damage</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>1251</fpage><lpage>1263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.122465</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18502973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18502973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamsheer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Laxmi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DUF581 is plant specific FCS-Like zinc finger involved in protein-protein interaction</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e99074</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24901469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamsheer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannully</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gopan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Laxmi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive evolutionary and expression analysis of FCS-Like zinc finger gene family yields insights into their origin, expansion and divergence</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0134328</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26252898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Function of the HD-Zip I gene <italic>Oshox22</italic> in ABA-mediated drought and salt tolerances in rice</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-012-9967-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23109182?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23109182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>qRT9, a quantitative trait locus controlling root thickness and root length in upland rice</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2015</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>2723</fpage><lpage>2732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erv076</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25769309?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25769309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>JAZ repressors and the orchestration of phytohormone crosstalk</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2011.10.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22112386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22112386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and expression profiling analysis of TIFY family genes involved in stress and phytohormone responses in rice</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-009-9524-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19618278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19618278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birkenbihl</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Diezel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Somssich</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis WRKY33 is a key transcriptional regulator of hormonal and metabolic responses toward <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> infection</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.192641</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22392279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22392279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis B-box protein BZS1/BBX20 interacts with HY5 and mediates strigolactone regulation of photomorphogenesis</article-title><source>J. Genet. Genomics.</source><year>2016</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgg.2016.05.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27523280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27523280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The B-box domain protein BBX21 promotes photomorphogenesis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>2365</fpage><lpage>2375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.01305</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29259103?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29259103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis NIN-like transcription factors have a central role in nitrate signalling</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1617</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms2621</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23511481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23511481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>WAKs: cell wall-associated kinases linking the cytoplasm to the extracellular matrix</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1010691701578</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11554472?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11554472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>LFV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Wall-associated Kinase gene family in rice genomes</article-title><source>Plant Sci.</source><year>2014</year><volume>229</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2014.09.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25443845?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25443845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis of rice root responses to potassium deficiency</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>161</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-12-161</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22963580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22963580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression analysis of rice seedling under potassium deprivation reveals major changes in metabolism and signaling components</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e70321</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0070321</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23922980?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23922980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variation in NRT1.1B contributes to nitrate-use divergence between rice subspecies</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3337</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26053497?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26053497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A role for a dioxygenase in auxin metabolism and reproductive development in rice</article-title><source>Dev. Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2013.09.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24094741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24094741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mutation in NLA, which encodes a RING-type ubiquitin ligase, disrupts the adaptability of Arabidopsis to nitrogen limitation</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2007</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03050.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17355433?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17355433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilder</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatehouse</surname><given-names>AMR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheerman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel mechanism of insect resistance engineered into tobacco</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1987</year><volume>330</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/330160a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Inamdar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of intracellular membrane trafficking and cell dynamics by syntaxin-6</article-title><source>Biosci. Rep.</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20120006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22489884?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22489884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadotani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Akagi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exogenous proteinogenic amino acids induce systemic resistance in rice</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-016-0748-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26940322?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26940322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hauryliuk</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent functional insights into the role of (p)ppGpp in bacterial physiology</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3448</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25853779?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25853779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Field, B. Green magic: regulation of the chloroplast stress response by (p)ppGpp in plants and algae. <italic>J. Exp. Bot</italic>. 2017 Dec 21. 10.1093/jxb/erx485 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mustroph</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the phosphofructokinase gene family in rice and its expression under oxygen deficiency stress</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2013.00125</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23717315?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23717315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transport of primary metabolites across the plant vacuolar membrane</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>2007</year><volume>581</volume><fpage>2223</fpage><lpage>2226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2007.02.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17307167?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17307167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Coordinated responses to oxygen and sugar deficiency allow rice seedlings to tolerate flooding</article-title><source>Sci. Signal.</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>ra61</fpage><?supplied-pmid 19809091?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19809091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hormonal control of nitrogen acquisition: roles of auxin, abscisic acid, and cytokinin</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2011</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1399</fpage><lpage>1409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq410</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21196475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21196475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Auxin biosynthetic gene TAR2 is involved in low nitrogen-mediated reprogramming of root architecture in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12448</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24460551?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24460551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Creelman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A chloroplast lipoxygenase is required for wound-induced jasmonic acid accumulation in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>8675</fpage><lpage>8679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.92.19.8675</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7567995?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7567995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abscisic acid regulates auxin homeostasis in rice root tips to promote root hair elongation</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1121</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.01121</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28702040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28702040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schachtman</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactive oxygen species and root hairs in Arabidopsis root response to nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium deficiency</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1350</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pci145</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15946982?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15946982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The abiotic stress-responsive NAC-type transcription factor OsNAC5 regulates stress-inducible genes and stress tolerance in rice</article-title><source>Mol. Genet. Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-010-0557-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20632034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20632034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological mechanisms underlying OsNAC5-dependent tolerance of rice plants to abiotic stress</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2011</year><volume>234</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-011-1403-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21448719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21448719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OsNAC5 overexpression enlarges root diameter in rice plants leading to enhanced drought tolerance and increased grain yield in the field</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol. J.</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23094910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23094910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pintard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cullin-based ubiquitin ligases: Cul3-BTB complexes join the family</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1681</fpage><lpage>1687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600186</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15071497?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15071497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gingerich</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-scale, lineage-specific expansion of a bric-a-brac/tramtrack/broad complex ubiquitin-ligase gene family in rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2329</fpage><lpage>2348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.107.051300</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17720868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of telomerase in Arabidopsis by BT2, an apparent target of TELOMERASE ACTIVATOR1</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.044321</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17220202?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17220202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandadi</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McKnight</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BT2, a BTB protein, mediates multiple responses to nutrients, stresses, and hormones in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>1930</fpage><lpage>1939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.139220</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19525324?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19525324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitin ligase EL5 maintains the viability of root meristems by influencing cytokinin-mediated nitrogen effects in rice</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2014</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>2307</fpage><lpage>2318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eru110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24663342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24663342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of GLUTAMINE DUMPER1 leads to hypersecretion of glutamine from hydathodes of Arabidopsis leaves</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1827</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.021642</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15208395?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Voll</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frommer</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation of nonselective amino acid export by glutamine dumper proteins</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>762</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.151746</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20018597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20018597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Omata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrite transport activity of a novel HPP family protein conserved in cyanobacteria and chloroplasts</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1311</fpage><lpage>1324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcu075</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24904028?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24904028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broadley</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zelko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zinc in plants</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.01996.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17286818?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17286818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erenoglu</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutman</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceylan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved nitrogen nutrition enhances root uptake, root-to-shoot translocation and remobilization of zinc in wheat</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03488.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21029104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21029104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential regulation of Arabidopsis plastid gene expression and RNA editing in non-photosynthetic tissues</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-013-0069-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23645360?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23645360</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>