<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6279756</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">35939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-35939-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Nitrous oxide and nitric oxide emissions from lowland rice cultivation with urea deep placement and alternate wetting and drying irrigation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>S. M. Mofijul</given-names></name><address><email>mislambrri@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gaihre</surname><given-names>Yam Kanta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>Jatish Chandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Upendra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Md. Nayeem</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sanabria</surname><given-names>Joaquin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saleque</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Bangladesh Rice Research Institute, Soil Science Division, Gazipur, Bangladesh </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>International Fertilizer Development Center, Dhaka, Bangladesh </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>International Fertilizer Development Center, Muscle Shoals, Alabama USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>International Rice Research Institute, Dhaka, Bangladesh </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>17623</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Urea deep placement (UDP) and the alternate wetting and drying (AWD) irrigation method are two promising rice production technologies. However, studies on the impact of UDP under AWD irrigation on nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O) and nitric oxide (NO) emissions are limited. In this study, the effects of UDP with AWD irrigation on these emissions, nitrogen use efficiency (NUE), and rice yields are investigated, compared to conventional broadcast application. N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions from three fertilizer treatments &#x02013; no nitrogen, UDP, and broadcast application of prilled urea (PU) &#x02013; were measured. Measurements were taken using an automated gas sampling and analysis system continuously for two consecutive Boro (dry) rice seasons. N<sub>2</sub>O emission peaks were observed after broadcast application of PU but not after UDP. In contrast, large spikes in N<sub>2</sub>O emission were observed after UDP, compared to broadcast application, during dry periods. Despite differences in emission peaks, seasonal cumulative N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from UDP and broadcast treatments were similar. However, NO emissions were minimal and unaffected by UDP or AWD. UDP increased rice yields by 28% and N recovery efficiency by 167%, compared to broadcast urea. This study demonstrates that UDP with AWD irrigation can increase yields and NUE without increasing N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Agriculture is a significant anthropogenic source of nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O) and nitric oxide (NO), contributing up to 60% of total anthropogenic N<sub>2</sub>O emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. N<sub>2</sub>O emission is a major concern due to its increasing concentration in the atmosphere. N<sub>2</sub>O concentration has increased from 270 ppb during pre-industrial times to 328.9 ppb in 2016<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. The average annual carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>)-equivalent emission was 52 gigatons (Gt) in 2011. This is expected to almost double by 2050 if mitigation actions are not accelerated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. N<sub>2</sub>O is a strong greenhouse gas (GHG) that is 265 times more potent than CO<sub>2</sub> over a 100-year time horizon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. In addition to trapping heat in the atmosphere, N<sub>2</sub>O contributes to the destruction of the stratospheric ozone layer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. N<sub>2</sub>O alone contributed 6% to total anthropogenic GHG emissions in 2010<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Since both N<sub>2</sub>O and NO gases are produced in the soil through the biochemical process of nitrification and denitrification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, their emissions are highly variable with soil properties, climate, crops, irrigation regimes, and fertilizer sources and methods of application<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. NO contributes to acidification and eutrophication of ecosystems and plays an important role in the formation of ozone in the lower atmosphere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">In agriculture, N<sub>2</sub>O production is associated mainly with nitrogen (N) fertilizer application. Microbial nitrification and denitrification are major processes affecting N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions and N availability to plants. However, there are other processes producing N<sub>2</sub>O, such as chemical decomposition of hydroxylamine, chemodenitrification, and abiotic decomposition of ammonium nitrate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Nitrification is an aerobic oxidation of ammonium (NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) to nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>) in a two-step process in which NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> is oxidized to nitrite (NO<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>) by primary nitrifiers (<italic>Nitrosomonas sp</italic>.) and NO<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> is oxidized to NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> by secondary nitrifiers (<italic>Nitrobacter sp</italic>.). Alternatively, denitrification is the stepwise reduction of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> to N<sub>2</sub>, mediated by facultative anaerobic bacteria in an oxygen-limiting environment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Details of the nitrification and denitrification processes are given in Butterbach-Bahl <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. The magnitude of N<sub>2</sub>O emission from soil depends on the amount of N fertilizer applied, the availability of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> in soils, soil moisture, and temperature. In addition to the quantity of fertilizer applied, the N application method affects emissions. Nitrogen use efficiency (NUE) of broadcast-applied prilled urea (PU) in lowland rice fields is only 30&#x02013;40%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> due to losses through ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) volatilization, surface runoff, nitrification, denitrification, and leaching<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. The amount of N loss due to volatilization increases as long as the floodwater pH and temperature are favorable<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Broadcast application of PU produces higher floodwater NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N compared to deep placement of N<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. This increases the loss of N as NH<sub>3</sub> volatilization, which increases with increasing N rates. Therefore, the excessive use of N fertilizer via broadcast application has negative environmental consequences as a result of N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions, nitrate pollution of groundwater, and eutrophication<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Research in the past decades has focused on N management strategies, including the right fertilizer source, right rate, proper application timing, and methods of application, to increase crop productivity and NUE while reducing the negative environmental consequences. Increasing NUE has been achieved by using nitrification inhibitors, urease inhibitors, slow-release fertilizers, balanced crop nutrition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, and improved placement methods. Efficient fertilizer products and placement methods were found effective in mitigating N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Urea deep placement (UDP) is among the best N management strategies and a currently applicable technique, as it increases rice yields up to 20% and saves urea use up to 30%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, compared to surface application of PU.</p><p id="Par5">In addition to N management, water management plays an important role in N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions from rice fields<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. For example, continuous flooded rice cultivation emits less N<sub>2</sub>O<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, because in water-saturated and anaerobic conditions, much of the N<sub>2</sub>O is reduced to N<sub>2</sub> by denitrifiers before escaping from the soil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. In saturated soils, deep-placed N remains in the root zone as NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N, which is less subject to nitrification. This can ensure a continuous supply of N to plants throughout the growing season, depending on soil type. In contrast, alternate wetting and drying (AWD) irrigation triggers considerable N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The intermittent soil drying and wetting often produces cracks, particularly in clayey soil, in addition to changes in soil physicochemical properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. These cracks increase the oxygen content in the deeper soil layer, which in turn increases the rate of nitrification and, thus, N<sub>2</sub>O emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Unlike continuously flooded conditions, alternating the soil between dry and wet states makes soil N unstable, as it favors nitrification and subsequent denitrification, leading to more N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Therefore, the addition of N fertilizer, either as broadcast or deep placement, under AWD irrigation may increase the conversion rate of soil NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> to NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> as well as the rate of subsequent denitrification of the NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>, leading to more N<sub>2</sub>O emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">In Bangladesh, the groundwater table is depleting due to continuous pumping for Boro rice (dry season, between December/January and April/May) cultivation. This leads to increased irrigation water pumping costs for farmers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Adoption of the AWD irrigation practice has been shown to reduce water use by up to 38% without significant yield penalty<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Similarly, UDP has been gaining popularity for rice cultivation in some Asian countries due to saving fertilizer and increasing NUE and grain yields<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. In our previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, UDP significantly reduced N<sub>2</sub>O emissions compared to broadcast-applied PU, particularly when rice was cultivated with continuous flooding irrigation. Most previous studies with UDP have been conducted under conventional irrigation practices, i.e., continuous standing water (CSW) conditions. A limited number of studies have been performed with UDP under AWD conditions; these studies reported effects of UDP on grain yields and NUE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, indicating that UDP increases NUE and grain yields, compared to PU, in both AWD and CSW conditions. However, no studies have been conducted with UDP under AWD irrigation to determine the impact on N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions. UDP under AWD irrigation is hypothesized to be equally effective in terms of yield, NUE, and mitigation of emissions of N<sub>2</sub>O and NO as under CSW conditions. Therefore, the present field study was conducted to investigate the effects of UDP on N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions, grain yields, and NUE under AWD conditions during two consecutive Boro seasons.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Floodwater ammonium nitrogen (NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N)</title><p id="Par7">The dynamics of floodwater NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N were measured during seven consecutive days after N fertilizer application in two rice-growing seasons (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Deep placement of urea briquettes significantly reduced floodwater NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N, compared to broadcast PU. Peaks of floodwater NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N with the PU treatment were observed two to three days after fertilizer application, followed by a sharp decline, while treatment with urea briquettes showed floodwater NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N similar to the control treatment throughout the measurement period. The magnitudes of floodwater NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N were consistent in both years.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Dynamics of floodwater NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N in control, urea briquette, and PU treatments under alternate wetting and drying conditions in dry (Boro) season. TD-1, TD-2, and TD-3 represent first, second, and third topdressing of PU, respectively. Vertical bars indicate standard error of mean (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_35939_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e719"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Seasonal dynamics of N<sub>2</sub>O emissions</title><p id="Par8">The dynamics of N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from the control, UDP, and broadcast PU treatments are presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e,f</xref>. N<sub>2</sub>O emissions peaks were observed after topdressing of PU, during the drying period, or after re-flooding of dry soil. Except during the peak emission events, N<sub>2</sub>O emissions were within a range of &#x000b1;30&#x02009;&#x000b5;g&#x02009;N m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, irrespective of treatment and season.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Nitrous and nitric oxides emission rates, floodwater depth, air temperature, and rainfall under AWD conditions during Boro 2015 and Boro 2016 seasons at BRRI, Gazipur. T, TD-1, TD-2, TD-3, and H correspond to transplanting, first topdressing, second topdressing, third topdressing, and harvesting, respectively. The shaded area in the x-axis indicates the drying period.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_35939_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e755"/></fig></p><p id="Par9">In the Boro 2015 season, N<sub>2</sub>O emission peaks were observed after two to four days for each topdressing of PU and continued for up to eight days (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>). In contrast, emission peaks were not observed in the UDP treatment except during the dry period. Though large spikes of N<sub>2</sub>O-N emission were observed during the dry period in both treatments, the magnitudes of the emission were more prominent (466&#x02009;&#x000b5;g&#x02009;N m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and appeared for a longer time in the UDP treatment, compared to broadcast PU (324&#x02009;&#x000b5;g&#x02009;N m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). In Boro 2016, N<sub>2</sub>O emission peaks were observed with broadcast PU three days after the second topdressing and continued consistently for eight days. In contrast, the N<sub>2</sub>O emission peaks were very small to negligible after the first and third topdressing of PU (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f</xref>). As in Boro 2015, peaks of N<sub>2</sub>O emission were observed with both treatments during each dry period, but they were not as prominent as in Boro 2015. In general, drying-induced emissions were more prominent and prolonged compared to fertilizer-induced emissions. Occasional negative fluxes were observed with all treatments, but these did not show any consistent pattern.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Seasonal dynamics of NO emissions</title><p id="Par10">NO emission rates from all treatments are displayed in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2g,h</xref>. Occasional emission peaks were observed after topdressing of PU and during the drying period. The impacts of fertilizer placement methods on NO emission rates were not consistent. However, during dry episodes, the magnitudes of emission were slightly higher with the UDP treatment than broadcast PU, particularly in 2015. NO emissions were relatively higher in Boro 2015, compared to Boro 2016. Sporadic negative NO emissions were observed with all treatments, particularly during midnight through early morning periods. Irrespective of treatment, NO fluxes varied from &#x02212;7&#x02009;&#x000b5;g&#x02009;N m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 11&#x02009;&#x000b5;g&#x02009;N m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in Boro 2015 and from &#x02212;4&#x02009;&#x000b5;g&#x02009;N m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 7&#x02009;&#x000b5;g&#x02009;N m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in Boro 2016.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>N<sub>2</sub>O emissions: Seasonal total and yield-scaled emissions</title><p id="Par11">Fertilizer treatment had significant interaction effects with year on cumulative and yield-scaled emissions (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In 2015, cumulative and yield-scaled emissions ranged from 63&#x02009;g&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 732&#x02009;g&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and from 40&#x02009;g t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> grain to 153&#x02009;g t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. In Boro 2016, they ranged from 116&#x02009;g&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 209&#x02009;g&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and from 51&#x02009;g&#x02009;N t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> grain to 41&#x02009;g&#x02009;N t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> grain (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In 2015, the addition of N fertilizer, irrespective of method of application, increased cumulative emissions significantly (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), compared to the control treatment. However, the difference between UDP and PU was not significant. Similar results were observed for yield-scaled emissions. In 2016, no significant differences were observed on cumulative and yield-scaled N<sub>2</sub>O emissions among the treatments. Fertilizer-induced emission factors (EFs) were 0.42% and 0.86% in 2015 and 0.05% and 0.12% in 2016 for PU and UDP treatments, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The effects of fertilizer placement method on EF were insignificant (p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). The EFs were significantly higher in 2015 compared to 2016.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Seasonal N<sub>2</sub>O-N emissions, yield-scaled emissions, and emission factors with different N fertilizer treatments under AWD conditions, BRRI, Gazipur.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Treatment</th><th colspan="2">N<sub>2</sub>O-N emission<break/>(g ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> season<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th colspan="2">Yield-scaled N<sub>2</sub>O-N emission (g t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> grain)</th><th colspan="2">N<sub>2</sub>O-N emission factor (%)</th></tr><tr><th>2015</th><th>2016</th><th>2015</th><th>2016</th><th>2015</th><th>2016</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>63.30bA</td><td>115.94&#x02009;aA</td><td>40.17bA</td><td>51.34&#x02009;aA</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>Urea briquette</td><td>731.55&#x02009;aA</td><td>209.31aB</td><td>152.98&#x02009;aA</td><td>39.69aB</td><td>0.857&#x02009;aA</td><td>0.120aB</td></tr><tr><td>Prilled urea</td><td>500.96&#x02009;aA</td><td>162.31aB</td><td>136.61&#x02009;aA</td><td>40.72aB</td><td>0.421&#x02009;aA</td><td>0.045&#x02009;aA</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>Mean</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>431.94A</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>162.52B</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>109.91A</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>43.92B</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>0.639A</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>0.082B</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>Control</td><td colspan="2">89.62b</td><td colspan="2">45.75b</td><td colspan="2">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>Urea briquette</td><td colspan="2">470.43a</td><td colspan="2">96.33a</td><td colspan="2">0.488a</td></tr><tr><td>Prilled urea</td><td colspan="2">331.64a</td><td colspan="2">88.66a</td><td colspan="2">0.233a</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7">
<bold>ANOVA (p values)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>Year (Y)</td><td colspan="2">0.0022</td><td colspan="2">0.0014</td><td colspan="2">0.0036</td></tr><tr><td>Treatment (T)</td><td colspan="2">0.0036</td><td colspan="2">0.0326</td><td colspan="2">0.0994</td></tr><tr><td>Y&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;T</td><td colspan="2">0.0145</td><td colspan="2">0.0117</td><td colspan="2">0.2248</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: In a column, means followed by the same lowercase letters and, in a row for each response variable, means followed by the same uppercase letters are not significantly different at a 5% level of probability by Tukey&#x02019;s honest significant difference (HSD) test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>NO emissions: Seasonal total and yield-scaled emissions</title><p id="Par12">Cumulative and yield-scaled NO emissions were very low compared to N<sub>2</sub>O emissions. The effects of fertilizer treatments and their interaction with year were not significant (p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). Across the seasons, they ranged from 12.23&#x02009;g&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 14.73&#x02009;g&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and from 3.78&#x02009;g t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> grain to 6.80&#x02009;g t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> grain (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Similarly, the fertilizer-induced EF was not affected by the method of N fertilizer application or its interaction with year (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Across the seasons, fertilizer-induced EFs were 0.009% and 0.003%, respectively, for UDP and PU treatments (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). However, NO EF was significantly (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) higher in 2015 than in 2016.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Seasonal NO-N emissions, yield-scaled emissions, and emission factors (two-year average) with different N-fertilizer treatments under AWD conditions, BRRI, Gazipur.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treatment</th><th>NO-N emission<break/>(g ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> season<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th>Yield-scaled NO-N emission<break/>(g t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> grain)</th><th>NO-N emission factor (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>12.23a</td><td>6.80a</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>Urea briquette</td><td>18.08a</td><td>3.89a</td><td>0.009a</td></tr><tr><td>Prilled urea</td><td>14.72a</td><td>3.78a</td><td>0.003a</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: In a column, means followed by the same letters are not significantly different at a 5% level of probability by Tukey&#x02019;s honest significant difference (HSD) test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Grain yield and NUE</title><p id="Par13">Across the seasons, UDP significantly increased grain yield by 28% compared to broadcast PU (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Similarly, both agronomic use efficiency (AE<sub>N</sub>) and recovery efficiency (RE<sub>N</sub>) of N were significantly affected by method of N fertilizer application (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). UDP increased AE<sub>N</sub> and RE<sub>N</sub> by 109% and 167%, respectively, compared to broadcast PU. There were no significant interaction effects between treatment and year for studied variables (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of N application method on grain yields, agronomic use efficiency, and recovery efficiency of N (two-year average) under AWD conditions, BRRI, Gazipur.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treatment</th><th>Grain yield (t ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th>AE<sub>N</sub> (kg grain N kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th>RE<sub>N</sub> (kg N uptake N kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>1.91c</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>Urea briquette</td><td>4.95a</td><td>38.88a</td><td>0.56a</td></tr><tr><td>Prilled urea</td><td>3.86b</td><td>18.59b</td><td>0.21b</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">
<bold>ANOVA (P Values)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>Year (Y)</td><td>0.0024</td><td>0.2292</td><td>0.4280</td></tr><tr><td>Treatment (T)</td><td>&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td>Y&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;T</td><td>0.5174</td><td>0.6267</td><td>0.5512</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: In a column, means followed by the same letters are not significantly different at a 5% level of probability by Tukey&#x02019;s honest significant difference (HSD) test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par14">N fertilizer application method and water regime significantly influence N<sub>2</sub>O emissions. In this study, N<sub>2</sub>O emission from the UDP treatment tended to be higher (by an average of 37%) than broadcast PU, but this difference was below statistical significance (p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In contrast to these observations, Gaihre <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> reported that UDP reduced cumulative N<sub>2</sub>O emissions significantly, compared to broadcast PU; however, in that study, experiments were conducted under a CSW irrigation regime in which emissions from UDP were very low, relative to the present study in which experimental plots were maintained under AWD conditions. Higher emissions from the UDP treatment could be due to AWD irrigation. During the dry period, higher N<sub>2</sub>O emission peaks were observed with UDP compared to broadcast PU (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e,f</xref>). In general, the UDP plot retained more NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N in the soil (less in the floodwater) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Drying may have increased microbial nitrification, while re-flooding increased denitrification, resulting in more N<sub>2</sub>O emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Since UDP in flooded soils significantly reduces floodwater NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), most of the N is retained as NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> in a reduced zone for an extended period of time, and a very small amount of N is lost through NH<sub>3</sub> volatilization, nitrification, denitrification, and leaching<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. As a result, UDP can supply available N to the plant throughout the rice-growing season<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. With drying of the plot, NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> retained in the sub-surface layer could be oxidized to NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> (nitrification including chemical decomposition of hydroxylamine)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, resulting in greater N<sub>2</sub>O emissions.</p><p id="Par15">In the case of PU, application was broadcast; this led to more floodwater NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), which increased soil pH instantly. Subsequently, the NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N was rapidly lost through NH<sub>3</sub> volatilization, surface runoff, leaching, and nitrification-denitrification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. However, N<sub>2</sub>O emissions are not restricted to N fertilizer application sites (direct emissions); rather, N cascading from application sites (via volatilization, leaching, and erosion) to downwind and downstream ecosystems may result in natural ecosystem N enrichment, thereby creating new hot spots of N<sub>2</sub>O emissions, called indirect emissions. Therefore, comparatively lower N<sub>2</sub>O emission peaks were observed from broadcast PU during the dry period, due to less soil NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>. Nevertheless, the difference in cumulative N<sub>2</sub>O emissions between UDP and PU was not significant (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Except after topdressing of PU and during the dry period, N<sub>2</sub>O emissions were very low to negligible when the field was continuously flooded. In general, N<sub>2</sub>O emission is negligible in continuously flooded paddy fields<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, because N<sub>2</sub>O is further reduced to N<sub>2</sub> during denitrification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Occasional negative fluxes were observed in the present study, which is consistent with previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. The negative fluxes, essentially the uptake of N<sub>2</sub>O by soil, tend to occur under conditions of low soil inorganic N and high soil water content<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Under such conditions, N<sub>2</sub>O could be further reduced to N<sub>2</sub>, particularly during denitrification.</p><p id="Par16">Large seasonal variations in N<sub>2</sub>O emission were observed in this study (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), which is consistent with previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Higher N<sub>2</sub>O emission peaks and cumulative emissions, particularly in fertilized plots, were observed in 2015 compared to 2016 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e,f</xref>); these peaks were associated with the drying intensity of the soil. In 2015, when floodwater depth dropped close to or below 15&#x02009;cm from the soil surface, the upper layer of soil produced large cracks (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). This increased soil aeration, favoring microbial nitrification, and resulted in higher N<sub>2</sub>O emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. In contrast, in 2016, the water level did not drop as rapidly, and dry episodes were much shorter. These results suggest that variations in the magnitude of N<sub>2</sub>O emissions depend on the intensity of soil drying and wetting, rather than on season or year.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Soil cracks inside the gas chamber during the drying period.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_35939_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1670"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">The application of N fertilizer significantly increased yield-scaled N<sub>2</sub>O emissions, compared to the control treatment in 2015, but UDP and broadcast PU showed comparable yield-scaled N<sub>2</sub>O emissions in both seasons (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). However, UDP reduced emission intensity (g N<sub>2</sub>O t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> grain), compared to cumulative emissions, as UDP had significantly higher grain yields over broadcast PU (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Although there were no additional benefits by reducing significant amounts of cumulative N<sub>2</sub>O and yield-scaled N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from the UDP treatment over PU under AWD irrigation, UDP significantly increased rice grain yields and NUE. Previous studies reported that UDP with CSW irrigation significantly reduced cumulative N<sub>2</sub>O emissions and yield-scaled emissions, compared to broadcast PU<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Our results suggest that UDP under AWD irrigation is equally effective as under CSW, since it increased grain yields and NUE without increasing N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions.</p><p id="Par18">Across treatments and seasons, the fertilizer-induced N<sub>2</sub>O EF was 0.36% (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Similar EFs of N<sub>2</sub>O during the rice-growing season have been reported in previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. The mean fertilizer-induced EF of N<sub>2</sub>O for fertilized rice fields under midseason drainage was 0.37%, as reported by Akiyama <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, which is similar to findings in this study. The fertilizer-induced EF for UDP varied significantly with the season, which may be attributed to seasonal cumulative N<sub>2</sub>O emissions (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). However, our EF values are less than the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) default EF (1.0%)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup> for the entire rice-growing season.</p><p id="Par19">Emission peaks of NO were observed after N fertilizer application, but they were very small and inconsistent, compared to N<sub>2</sub>O peaks, even in the dry period (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2g,h</xref>). Increases in NO emissions after N fertilizer application have been observed not only in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> but also in vegetables<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. NO gas is produced mainly from oxidized soil through nitrification, although both nitrification and denitrification can produce NO<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. The effect of N fertilizer on the magnitude of NO emission peaks is largely influenced by soil type, soil moisture, soil temperature, fertilizer type, and ambient NO concentration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>, particularly under oxidized field conditions. Since dry-wet alternation favors both nitrification and denitrification, greater NO emission peaks were produced with the UDP treatment. The presence of more NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> with UDP in sub-surface soil, particularly during the dry period, may have provided more substrate for prolonged nitrification. Previous studies have also reported higher NO emission under AWD conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. In this study, although UDP showed large spikes of NO emission under wet-dry alternation compared to broadcast PU, cumulative emissions with UDP and broadcast PU were similar (p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). The lower NO emissions may be associated with its diffusion from production sites. NO is produced mainly in the fertilized layer and placement site but does not diffuse from the production sites because of its rapid uptake in the soil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, these results confirm that NO emission from rice fields with soil, climatic, and N management conditions similar to the present study site is negligible, regardless of irrigation regime and fertilizer placement method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par20">Significant variations in yield-scaled NO emissions between broadcast and deep-placed treatments were not observed; however, grain yields varied between application types (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Similarly, fertilizer-induced EFs were not affected by N placement method; EF values were very low, compared to 0.7% of applied N reported by Bouwman <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> and 0.04% in rice fields in China<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. The lower EF of NO in the present study is probably associated with higher background emissions due to the urban and industrial nature of the area surrounding the study site. Notably, our previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> in the same area under CSW conditions showed similar results.</p><p id="Par21">Application of N fertilizer significantly increased grain yields in both seasons (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The use of UDP with 25% less urea significantly improved rice yields and resulted in a marked increase in NUE (AE<sub>N</sub> and RE<sub>N</sub>), compared to broadcast PU. Ostensibly, UDP increased the contact of fertilizer molecules with soil particles and reduced NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-N in floodwater (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), while also reducing NH<sub>3</sub> volatilization. In general, UDP prolongs available N supply throughout the rice-growing season<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>, thereby promoting total N uptake and, ultimately, improving NUE and grain yield (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Results from this study are in close agreement with previous studies conducted under continuous flooding conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>, which reported that UDP significantly increased rice yield by 15&#x02013;20% and urea savings by 25&#x02013;50%, compared to broadcast application of PU. Therefore, these results confirm that UDP is effective under both CSW and AWD irrigation regimes.</p><p id="Par22">In addition to saving N fertilizer and increasing NUE and grain yields, UDP with AWD irrigation saves water by up to 38%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Adoption of AWD irrigation, however, increases N loss as N<sub>2</sub>O emissions, compared to continuous flooding irrigation. In this study, the average (two-year) N losses as N<sub>2</sub>O from UDP and broadcast PU treatments were 0.49% and 0.23% of applied N, respectively, which are higher compared to losses that occurred with continuous flooding irrigation (UDP: 0.11%; broadcast PU: 0.33%)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Despite the small increase in N<sub>2</sub>O emissions, the contribution of N<sub>2</sub>O (196 and 138&#x02009;kg CO<sub>2</sub> eq ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively) to total GHG emissions (methane [CH<sub>4</sub>] +N<sub>2</sub>O) from rice fields is fairly small (&#x0003c;5%) because of the higher (&#x0003e;95%) contribution of CH<sub>4</sub>, a major GHG emitted from rice fields (but not measured in this study)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. AWD irrigation can drastically reduce CH<sub>4</sub> emissions, which offsets increased N<sub>2</sub>O emissions. Overall, AWD irrigation reduces GHG (CH<sub>4</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O) emissions from rice fields by up to 40%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Therefore, efficient N management strategies, such as UDP with AWD irrigation, can contribute to mitigating the negative environmental effects of N fertilizer while permitting savings on fertilizers and increasing crop yields.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Experimental site and climate</title><p id="Par23">The field experiments were conducted at the Bangladesh Rice Research Institute (BRRI), Gazipur, Bangladesh (latitude: 23&#x000b0; 59&#x002b9; 25&#x002b9;&#x002b9;, longitude: 90&#x000b0; 24&#x002b9; 33&#x002b9;&#x002b9;), during Boro 2015 and Boro 2016 under an AWD irrigation regime. Boro is the dry season irrigated rice grown between December/January and April/May. The physicochemical properties of the soil before the start and after completion of the experiments are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. The daily average air temperature and rainfall throughout the rice-growing period in Boro 2015 and Boro 2016 are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a,b</xref>. The minimum air temperatures during both years were similar, ranging from 13.9&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (2015) to 15.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (2016) in January, while maximum air temperatures recorded in April were 29.3&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in 2015 and 32.5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in 2016. The mean annual air temperatures were 22.7&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and 24.5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in 2015 and 2016, respectively. During the experimental period, maximum rainfall occurred in March and April for both years (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a,b</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Physicochemical properties of soils before the experiment and after harvest of Boro 2016.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Soil properties</th><th>Initial soil (2013)</th><th>After harvest of Boro 2016</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>pH-H<sub>2</sub>O</td><td>5.8</td><td>6.2</td></tr><tr><td>Organic carbon (%)</td><td>1.27</td><td>1.26</td></tr><tr><td>Total N (%)</td><td>0.14</td><td>0.12</td></tr><tr><td>Available P (mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td>11.47</td><td>11.37</td></tr><tr><td>Available K (cmol<sub>c</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td>0.12</td><td>0.10</td></tr><tr><td>Texture</td><td colspan="2">Clay loam</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Experimental design and treatments</title><p id="Par24">The three N fertilizer treatments used in the studies were: (i) control, 0&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; (ii) UDP, deep placement of urea briquettes at 78&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; and (iii) PU, broadcast application of prilled urea at 104&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The N rates and placement methods selected for this study are based on existing N management practices in Bangladesh. UDP increases NUE by 30&#x02013;35% over broadcast application of PU and increases grain yield up to 20%. Therefore, the N rate for UDP was 25% less than with the broadcast PU (recommended dose)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Treatments were arranged in a randomized complete block design, with three replications. Each experimental plot was 4.8&#x02009;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3.2&#x02009;m. Urea briquettes of 2.7&#x02009;g were deep-placed in a reduced zone (7&#x02013;10&#x02009;cm depth) at 40&#x02009;cm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;40&#x02009;cm spacing between four hills of rice at each alternate row eight to 10 days after transplanting (DAT). A total of 62,500 briquettes per hectare were used, supplying 78&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Urea briquettes were applied as a single application during the first topdressing of PU, while PU was broadcast in three splits at 10 DAT, maximum tillering, and panicle initiation stages.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Crop management</title><p id="Par25">Phosphorus (triple superphosphate) and potassium (muriate of potash) fertilizers at 25&#x02009;kg&#x02009;P ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 85&#x02009;kg&#x02009;K ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively, were applied during final land preparation as basal applications to all plots. In addition, sulfur (S) and zinc (Zn) were applied to all plots as basal applications at the rate of 15&#x02009;kg&#x02009;S ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as gypsum and 3&#x02009;kg Zn ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as zinc sulfate. Two to three rice (variety: BRRI dhan 28) seedlings per hill were transplanted with a spacing of 20&#x02009;cm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;20&#x02009;cm.</p><p id="Par26">For irrigation, perforated PVC pipe was inserted (15&#x02009;cm depth) in each plot at 10 DAT. Floodwater depth inside the PVC pipe was monitored daily, and plots were irrigated when water depth in AWD pipes was 12&#x02013;15&#x02009;cm below the soil surface (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c,d</xref>). In 2015, AWD was successfully accomplished (&#x02212;15&#x02009;cm from the soil surface) four times, while in 2016 it was not successfully accomplished (&#x02212;5 to &#x02212;10&#x02009;cm) during each dry period due to the poor drainage system. However, in 2016, during two drying periods, a water table level very close to 15&#x02009;cm below the soil surface was accomplished immediately before harvesting (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c,d</xref>). During the rest of the drying period, the water table was 5&#x02013;10&#x02009;cm below the soil surface. AWD treatment started at 25 DAT and continued until two weeks before harvesting. However, irrigation was provided regularly during fertilizer application and during the flowering stage.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Measurement of N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions</title><p id="Par27">An automated closed chamber technique was used for the measurement of N<sub>2</sub>O and NO gases. A detailed description of this system was reported in our previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Briefly, the automated N<sub>2</sub>O and NO gas measurement system consists of 12 plexiglass gas chambers. Each chamber was installed in the respective plot between two rows of rice, leaving four border rows over a fixed aluminum base, which covered a surface area of 0.148&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup> and a headspace volume of 0.0578 m<sup>3</sup> (57.8 liters). In 2015, nine chambers were installed under AWD and three under CSW (non-replicated, not reported herein). In 2016, the three chambers used under CSW irrigation were moved to UDP plots. Each UDP plot had two chambers &#x02013; one in a fertilized row and another in an unfertilized row.</p><p id="Par28">Six air samples were taken at eight-minute intervals (0, 8, 16, 24, 32, and 40&#x02009;minutes [min]) in each three-hour sampling sequence. Within a three-hour cycle, a gas chamber was closed for 40&#x02009;min for gas sampling. One sample was collected just before closing the chamber, which represents the ambient air. Each gas chamber was sampled at three-hour intervals (i.e., eight samples per day). There were three sets of four chambers, one set for one replication (i.e., four chambers were sampled in a one-hour cycle). The three-hour interval consisted of three one-hour cycles: first one-hour cycle &#x02013; chambers 1&#x02013;4 (Rep 1); second one-hour cycle &#x02013; chambers 5&#x02013;8 (Rep 2); and third one-hour cycle &#x02013; chambers 9&#x02013;12 (Rep 3). Chambers 4, 8, and 12 represent the non-replicated treatments of the CSW experiment (for 2015).</p><p id="Par29">Gas samples collected from the chambers were passed to the analyzers using a Teflon tube with a 0.25-in diameter via a 13-port sample manifold (equipped with a solenoid valve, i.e., KIP valve). Of 13 valves in the sample manifold, 12 were used for air samples of the respective 12 chambers, while the last valve was used for the calibration gases (i.e., connected to the calibrator). Each sample valve in the manifold was controlled by a datalogger (Campbell Scientific CR3000) via 16-port (channel) relay controller (SDMCD16 AC/DC Relay Controller). The sample flow rate is determined by the vacuum pump and flow controller of the respective gas analyzers. The sample flow rates for NO and N<sub>2</sub>O measurements were ca. 450&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and ca. 750&#x02009;cm<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively. Air samples were filtered and dried before passing to the respective analyzers.</p><p id="Par30">N<sub>2</sub>O concentration of the air sample was measured by a Teledyne Advanced Pollution Instrumentation (API) T320U Gas Filter Correlation Analyzer, which uses the infrared absorption principle. NO concentration of the air sample was measured by a Teledyne API T200 Nitrogen Oxide Analyzer. Both N<sub>2</sub>O and NO analyzers were calibrated weekly using a Teledyne T700 Dynamic Dilution Calibrator. The NO and N<sub>2</sub>O analyzers were calibrated for two ranges of concentration (i.e., the low range for the NO and N<sub>2</sub>O analyzers was 40 ppb and 1,600 ppb, respectively, and the high range was 400 ppb and 8,000 ppb, respectively). T320U (N<sub>2</sub>O analyzer) can analyze N<sub>2</sub>O concentration up to 200 ppm, with a lower detection limit of 10 ppb. Similarly, the T200 (NO analyzer) can analyze NO concentration up to 20 ppm, with a lower detection limit of 0.4 ppb.</p><p id="Par31">The concentrations of N<sub>2</sub>O and NO increased or decreased during chamber closure time. Therefore, the N<sub>2</sub>O and NO fluxes were calculated from the slope of the linear regression curve on concentration of respective gases against chamber closure time. An emission event was considered significant when the slope was significant at P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and the R<sup>2</sup> value was 0.65 or higher. Hence, flux rates where R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.65 were not considered emission events and were discarded. The slope (ppb min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) from the significant emission events was corrected for air temperature, atmospheric pressure, and the ratio of chamber volume to surface area using the following formula:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{array}{c}{\rm{Emission}}\,{\rm{rate}}\,(\mu g\,{{\rm{N}}}_{{\rm{2}}}{\rm{O}}\mbox{--}{\rm{N}}\,{\rm{or}}\,{\rm{NO}}\mbox{--}{\rm{N}}\,{{\rm{m}}}^{\mbox{--}2}\,{{\rm{h}}}^{\mbox{--}1})\\ \,=\frac{ppb\,{\min }^{-1}\times V\times MW\times SP\times 60}{[0.08206\times {(273+T)}^{0}K]\times A\times 1,013.25\times 1,000}\end{array}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Emission</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">rate</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">O</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02013;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">or</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">NO</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02013;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02013;</mml:mo><mml:mi>2</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02013;</mml:mo><mml:mi>1</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>60</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.08206</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>273</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>013.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_35939_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Where,</p><p id="Par32">V is the volume of the gas chamber in L (57.8).</p><p id="Par33">MW is the molecular weight of the respective gas in ng nmol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p><p id="Par34">(NO&#x02013;N: 14, N<sub>2</sub>O&#x02013;N: 28).</p><p id="Par35">SP is the observed atmospheric pressure in millibars (mbar).</p><p id="Par36">60 is the conversion factor for time (min to h).</p><p id="Par37">0.08206 is the gas law constant (L atm mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x000b0;K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p><p id="Par38">T is the temperature inside the chamber (&#x000b0;C).</p><p id="Par39">A is the area covered by chamber (0.148&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>).</p><p id="Par40">1,013.25 is the standard pressure in mbar.</p><p id="Par41">1,000 is the conversion factor for mass (ng to &#x000b5;g).</p><p id="Par42">Cumulative seasonal total emissions (g N<sub>2</sub>O-N or NO-N) were calculated summing the hourly emission rates. Yield-scaled N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions (g N t<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> grain) were calculated from the ratio of seasonal total emissions to grain yields.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par43">Analysis of variance (ANOVA) of seasonal cumulative emissions, yield-scaled emissions, and EFs of N<sub>2</sub>O and NO gases, grain yield, total N uptake, and NUE was determined with SAS 9.3, Generalized Linear Mixed Models. Treatment, year, and their interaction (T&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Y) were handled as fixed effects and error term &#x02013; Rep (T&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Y) &#x02013; was considered a random effect. A pairwise comparison of treatment means was conducted with Tukey&#x02019;s honest significant difference (HSD) test at a 5% level of probability.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par44">UDP in rice fields under AWD irrigation increased NUE and grain yields significantly (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) compared to broadcast PU. UDP had discernible, but variable, effects on N<sub>2</sub>O emissions. N<sub>2</sub>O emission peaks were observed with both UDP and broadcast PU in each dry period. But under flooding conditions, N<sub>2</sub>O emission peaks were found only after broadcast application of PU. However, cumulative seasonal N<sub>2</sub>O emissions with UDP and broadcast PU were similar. Similarly, NO emissions were very minimal, compared to N<sub>2</sub>O emissions, and inconsistent for both UDP and PU treatments. Our results confirm that UDP with AWD irrigation is equally effective as UDP with CSW irrigation, since it increased grain yields and NUE compared to broadcast PU without significant (p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) effects on N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was financially supported by the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) through the project &#x0201c;Accelerating Agriculture Productivity Improvement &#x02013; Integrating Greenhouse Gas Emissions Mitigation into the Feed the Future Bangladesh Fertilizer Deep Placement Rice Intensification (cooperative agreement number AID-388-A-10-00002)&#x0201d; and Krishi Gobeshona Foundation (KGF), Bangladesh. The authors would like to thank Mr. Md. Sazzadur Rahman, Senior Scientific Officer, BRRI, for providing weather data.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>S.M.M.I., Y.K.G., and U.S. designed the experiments. S.M.M.I., Y.K.G., M.A.S., M.N.A. and J.C.B. conducted the experiments. J.S. performed statistical analysis of data. U.S. and all other authors substantially contributed to results interpretation and writing the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Smith, P. <italic>et al</italic>. Agriculture in Climate Change 2007: Mitigation. Contribution of Working Group III to the Fourth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (eds Metz, B., Davidson, O. R., Bosch, P. R., Dave, R. &#x00026; Meyer, L. A.)498&#x02013;540 (Cambridge University Press, 2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United Nations Environment Programme (UNEP). Drawing down N<sub>2</sub>O to protect climate and the ozone layer. A UNEP synthesis report. 57 (UNEP, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Meteorological Organization (WMO). WMO Greenhouse Gas Bulletin (GHG Bulletin) No. 13: The State of Greenhouse Gases in the Atmosphere Based on Global Observations through 2016, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://library.wmo.int/opac/doc_num.php?explnum_id=4022">https://library.wmo.int/opac/doc_num.php?explnum_id=4022</ext-link> (WMO, 2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC). <italic>Synthesis Report</italic>. Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (eds Pachuari, R. K. &#x00026; Meyer, L. A.) 151 (IPCC, 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crutzen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of nitrogen oxides on atmospheric zone content</article-title><source>Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc.</source><year>1970</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/qj.49709640815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Firestone, M. K. &#x00026; Davidson, E. A. Microbiological basis of NO and N<sub>2</sub>O production and consumption in soil in <italic>Exchange of Trace Gases between Terrestrial Ecosystems and the</italic> Atmosphere (eds Andreae, M. O. &#x00026; Schimel, D. S.) 7&#x02013;21 (John Wiley and Sons, Chichester, 1989).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Testing a conceptual model of soil emissions of nitrous and nitric oxides</article-title><source>BioSci.</source><year>2000</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1641/0006-3568(2000)050[0667:TACMOS]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impacts of population growth, changing food preferences and agricultural practices on the nitrogen cycle in East Asia</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><year>2008</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10705-007-9132-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lesschen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differentiation of nitrous oxide emission factors for agricultural soils</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut.</source><year>2011</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>3215</fpage><lpage>3222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2011.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21531058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Kessel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate, duration, and N placement determine N<sub>2</sub>O emissions in reduced tillage systems: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Glob. Chang. Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2012.02779.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23504719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crutzen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of NO and NO<sub>2</sub> in the chemistry of the troposphere and stratosphere</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Earth Pl. Sci.</source><year>1979</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ea.07.050179.002303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butterbach-Bahl</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baggs</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dannenmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiese</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zechmeister-Boltenstern</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrous oxide emissions from soils: how well do we understand the processes and their controls?</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2013</year><volume>368</volume><issue>1621</issue><fpage>20130122</fpage><lpage>20130122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2013.0122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savant</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Stangel</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deep placement of urea supergranules in transplanted rice: principles and practices</article-title><source>Fertil. Res.</source><year>1990</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01063765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang, W. F. <italic>et al</italic>. Chinese fertilizer development report (China Agricultural University Press, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of alternating wetting and drying versus continuous flooding on fertilizer nitrogen fate in rice fields in the Mekong Delta, Vietnam</article-title><source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2011.12.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ammonia volatilization from a paddy field following applications of urea: rice plants are both an absorber and an emitter for atmospheric ammonia</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2008</year><volume>390</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2007.10.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18054067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rice growth, grain yield, and floodwater nutrient dynamics as affected by nutrient placement method and rate</article-title><source>Agron. J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj2007.0007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Floodwater ammonium, nitrogen use efficiency and rice yields with fertilizer deep placement and alternate wetting and drying under triple rice cropping system</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><year>2016</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10705-015-9758-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>SMM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rice yields and nitrogen use efficiency with different fertilizers and water management under intensive lowland rice cropping systems in Bangladesh</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><year>2016</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10705-016-9795-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>SMM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Different nitrogen rates and methods of application for dry season rice cultivation with alternate wetting and drying irrigation: fate of nitrogen and grain yield</article-title><source>Agric. Water Manag.</source><year>2018</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agwat.2017.11.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deep placement of nitrogen fertilizers reduces ammonia volatilization and increases nitrogen utilization efficiency in no-tillage paddy fields in central China</article-title><source>Field Crop. Res.</source><year>2015</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2015.09.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dimkpa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Composite micronutrient nanoparticles and salts decrease drought stress in soybean</article-title><source>Agron. Sustain. Dev.</source><year>2017</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13593-016-0412-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of effectiveness of enhanced-efficiency fertilizers as mitigation options for N<sub>2</sub>O and NO emissions from agricultural soils: meta-analysis</article-title><source>Glob. Change Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1837</fpage><lpage>1846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2009.02031.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaihre</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitrous oxide and nitric oxide emissions and nitrogen use efficiency in lowland rice fields as affected by nitrogen placement in lowland rice fields</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><year>2018</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10705-017-9897-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miah</surname><given-names>MAM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fertilizer deep placement increases rice production: evidence from farmers&#x02019; fields in southern Bangladesh</article-title><source>Agron. J.</source><year>2016</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj15.0135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Direct emission factor for N<sub>2</sub>O from rice-winter wheat rotation systems in Southeast China</article-title><source>Atmos. Environ.</source><year>2005</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>4755</fpage><lpage>4765</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2005.04.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A 3-year field measurement of methane and nitrous oxide emissions from rice paddies in China: effects of water regime, crop residue, and fertilizer application</article-title><source>Glob. Biogeochem. Cycles.</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>GB2021</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2004GB002401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impacts of soil moisture on nitrous oxide emission from croplands: a case study on the rice-based agro-ecosystem in Southeast China</article-title><source>Chemosphere &#x02013; Glob. Change Sci.</source><year>2000</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1465-9972(99)00056-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide emissions from rice-wheat rotation fields in eastern China: effect of fertilization, soil water content, and crop residue</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><year>2010</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-010-0450-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of cracks and some key factors on emissions of nitrous oxide in paddy fields</article-title><source>J. Environ. Sci.</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitsch</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Creating riverine wetlands: ecological succession, nutrient retention, and pulsing effects</article-title><source>Ecol. Eng.</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoleng.2005.04.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Direct N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from rice paddy fields: summary of available data</article-title><source>Glob. Biogeochem. Cycles.</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>GB1005</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2004GB002378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantifying direct N<sub>2</sub>O emissions in paddy fields during rice growing season in mainland China: dependence on water regime</article-title><source>Atmos. Environ.</source><year>2007</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>8030</fpage><lpage>8042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2007.06.049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Methane and nitrous oxide emissions from rice paddy fields as affected by nitrogen fertilizers and water management</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><year>1997</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1004263405020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lampayan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adoption and economics of alternate wetting and drying water management for irrigated lowland rice</article-title><source>Field Crop. Res.</source><year>2015</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2014.10.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen deep-placement technologies for productivity, profitability, and environmental quality of rainfed lowland rice systems</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><year>1999</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1009731922431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaihre</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impacts of urea deep placement on nitrous oxide and nitric oxide emissions from rice fields in Bangladesh</article-title><source>Geoderma.</source><year>2015</year><volume>259&#x02013;260</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2015.06.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of ammonia volatilization on rice grown under different nitrogen application rates and its quantitative predictions in Erhai Lake Watershed</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><year>2015</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10705-014-9660-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapuis-Lardy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Soils, a sink for N<sub>2</sub>O? a review</article-title><source>Glob. Chang. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2006.01280.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Background nitrous oxide emissions in agricultural and natural lands: a meta analysis</article-title><source>Plant Soil.</source><year>2013</year><volume>373</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-013-1762-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arlene</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessing fertilizer N placement on CH<sub>4</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O emissions in irrigated rice systems</article-title><source>Geoderma.</source><year>2016</year><volume>266</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2015.11.034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen management to reduce yield-scaled global warming potential in rice</article-title><source>Field Crop. Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2013.03.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of water regimes on nitrous oxide emission from soils</article-title><source>Ecol. Eng.</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoleng.2007.04.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linquist</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fertilizer management practices and greenhouse gas emissions from rice systems: a quantitative review and analysis</article-title><source>Field Crop. Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2012.06.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sewage irrigation increased methane and nitrous oxide emissions from rice paddies in Southeast China</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><year>2009</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2008.11.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC). <italic>IPCC Guidelines for National Greenhouse Gas Inventories</italic> (eds Eggleston H. S., Buendia L., Miwa K., Ngara T. &#x00026; Tanabe K.) (Institute of Global Environmental Strategies, 2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide emissions from conventional vegetable fields in Southeastern China</article-title><source>Atmos. Environ.</source><year>2009</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2762</fpage><lpage>2769</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2009.02.040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouwman</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emissions of N<sub>2</sub>O and NO from fertilized fields: summary of available measurement data</article-title><source>Glob. Biogeochem. Cycles.</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>6-1</fpage><lpage>6-13.1058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2001GB001811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>N<sub>2</sub>O, NO, and NH<sub>3</sub> emissions from soil after the application of organic fertilizers, urea and water</article-title><source>Water Air Soil Pollut.</source><year>2004</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:WATE.0000036800.20599.46</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimation of nitrous oxide, nitric oxide and ammonia emissions from croplands in East, Southeast and South Asia</article-title><source>Glob. Chang. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1080</fpage><lpage>1096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2486.2003.00649.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide and nitrous oxide fluxes from typical vegetables cropland in China: effects of canopy, soil properties and field management</article-title><source>Atmos. Environ.</source><year>2009</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2571</fpage><lpage>2578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2009.02.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CH<sub>4</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>O and NO Emissions from a rice-wheat rotation cropping field in East China</article-title><source>Clim. Environ. Res. (in Chinese)</source><year>2007</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>760</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of deep application of urea on NO and N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from an Andisol</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><year>2002</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1021150808320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of urea placement on the time depth profile of NO, N<sub>2</sub>O and mineral nitrogen concentration in an Andisol during a Chinese cabbage growing season</article-title><source>Soil Sci. Plant Nutr.</source><year>2010</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1747-0765.2010.00519.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouwman</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modeling global annual N<sub>2</sub>O and NO from fertilized fields</article-title><source>Glob. Biogeochem. Cycles.</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>28-1</fpage><lpage>28-9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2001GB001812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil nitric oxide emissions from terrestrial ecosystems in China: a synthesis of modeling and measurements</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>7406</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep07406</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25490942?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25490942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rochette</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ammonia volatilization and nitrogen retention: how deep to incorporate urea?</article-title><source>J. Environ. Qual.</source><year>2013</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>1642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/jeq2013.05.0192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25602404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tirol-Padre</surname><given-names>Agnes</given-names></name><name><surname>Minamikawa</surname><given-names>Kazunori</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokida</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name><name><surname>Wassmann</surname><given-names>Reiner</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>Kazuyuki</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-specific feasibility of alternate wetting and drying as a greenhouse gas mitigation option in irrigated rice fields in Southeast Asia: a synthesis</article-title><source>Soil Science and Plant Nutrition</source><year>2017</year><volume>64</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00380768.2017.1409602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><italic>Fertilizer Recommendation Guide</italic> (Bangladesh Agricultural Research Council [BARC], 2012).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>