<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rice (N Y)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rice (N Y)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Rice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1939-8425</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1939-8433</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6093832</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">240</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12284-018-0240-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of the defense response to <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> in rice harboring the blast resistance gene <italic>Piz-t</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Dagang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Liu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Zaijie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Ziqiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Feng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Yuanchang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Yuming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Liming</given-names></name><address><email>yangliming@njfu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1500-2298</contrib-id><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Songbiao</given-names></name><address><email>songbiao_chen@hotmail.com</email><email>sbchen@fjage.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2229 4212</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418033.d</institution-id><institution>Biotechnology Research Institute, Fujian Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering for Agriculture, </institution><institution>Fujian Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Fuzhou, 350003 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410625.4</institution-id><institution>College of Biology and the Environment, </institution><institution>Nanjing Forestry University, </institution></institution-wrap>Nanjing, 210037 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.449133.8</institution-id><institution>Institute of Oceanography, Marine Biotechnology Center, </institution><institution>Minjiang University, </institution></institution-wrap>Fuzhou, 350108 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 2876</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256111.0</institution-id><institution>College of Crop Science, </institution><institution>Fujian Agricultural and Forestry University, </institution></institution-wrap>Fuzhou, 350002 China </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1804 2567</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410738.9</institution-id><institution>College of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Huaiyin Normal University, </institution></institution-wrap>Huaian, 223300 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>47</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Rice blast (caused by <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>) is one of the most destructive diseases of rice. While many blast resistance (<italic>R</italic>) genes have been identified and deployed in rice cultivars, little is known about the <italic>R</italic> gene-mediated defense mechanism. We used a rice transgenic line harboring the resistance gene <italic>Piz-t</italic> to investigate the <italic>R</italic> gene-mediated resistance response to infection.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">We conducted comparative proteome profiling of the <italic>Piz-t</italic> transgenic Nipponbare line (NPB-Piz-t) and wild-type Nipponbare (NPB) inoculated with <italic>M. oryzae</italic> at 24, 48, 72&#x000a0;h post-inoculation (hpi) using isobaric tags for relative and absolute quantification (iTRAQ) analysis. Comparative analysis of the response of NPB-Piz-t to the avirulent isolate KJ201 and the virulent isolate RB22 identified 114 differentially expressed proteins (DEPs) between KJ201-inoculated NPB-Piz-t (KJ201-Piz-t) and mock-treated NPB-Piz-t (Mock-Piz-t), and 118 DEPs between RB22-inoculated NPB-Piz-t (RB22-Piz-t) and Mock-Piz-t. Among the DEPs, 56 occurred commonly in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t. In a comparison of the responses of NPB and NPB-Piz-t to isolate KJ201, 93 DEPs between KJ201-Piz-t and KJ201-NPB were identified. DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t, RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t and KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB contained a number of proteins that may be involved in rice response to pathogens, including pathogenesis-related (PR) proteins, hormonal regulation-related proteins, defense and stress response-related proteins, receptor-like kinase, and cytochrome P450. Comparative analysis further identified 7 common DEPs between the comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB and KJ201-Piz-t/RB22-Piz-t, including alcohol dehydrogenase I, receptor-like protein kinase, endochitinase, similar to rubisco large subunit, NADP-dependent malic enzyme, and two hypothetical proteins.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">Our results provide a valuable resource for discovery of complex protein networks involved in the resistance response of rice to blast fungus.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12284-018-0240-3) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Proteomic analysis</kwd><kwd>Rice blast disease</kwd><kwd>Resistance gene</kwd><kwd><italic>Piz-t</italic></kwd><kwd>iTRAQ</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China (CN)</institution></funding-source><award-id>U1405212</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Songbiao</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31640006</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Liming</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003392</institution-id><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Fujian Province</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2014J07004</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Songbiao</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par15">Rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) is one of the most important food crops worldwide and is a major source of calories for half the world&#x02019;s population. Rice blast, caused by the ascomycete fungus <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>, is one of the most damaging diseases in rice. The blast fungus infects rice leaves, stems, nodes, panicles, and roots at all developmental stages (Wilson and Talbot <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2009</xref>), causing significant yield losses in rice production (Dean et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2005</xref>; Ebbole <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2007</xref>). The use of resistant cultivars is the most effective, economical, and environmentally friendly way of controlling rice blast (Tian et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2016</xref>). In recent decades, over 100 resistance (<italic>R</italic>) genes have been identified and at least 25 have been cloned (Singh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2015</xref>), providing an extensive genetic resource for breeding blast-resistant rice. However, little is known about the <italic>R</italic> gene-mediated defense mechanism in rice.</p><p id="Par16">Because of the high degree of pathogenic variability of <italic>M. oryzae</italic> (Dean et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2005</xref>), <italic>R</italic> gene-mediated resistance is prone to breakdown, making it difficult to breed durable blast resistance in rice. A better understanding of the <italic>R</italic> gene-mediated host defense mechanism may improve breeding for durable blast resistance. Over the past decade, high-throughput gene and protein profiling techniques have enabled investigation of the molecular processes involved in the defense responses of rice to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> infection (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>; Vergne et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2010</xref>; Bagnaresi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2012</xref>; Gupta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2012</xref>; Kim et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2013</xref>; Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2015</xref>; Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2016</xref>; Jain et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>). These large-scale transcriptomic and proteomic analyses have identified rice genes and/or proteins that were differentially expressed upon infection by <italic>M. oryzae</italic> and provided overviews of biological processes characterizing rice-<italic>M. oryzae</italic> interactions.</p><p id="Par17">The rice blast <italic>R</italic> gene <italic>Piz-t</italic>, which encodes a nucleotide-binding site-leucine-rich repeat protein, is a member of the <italic>Pi2/9</italic> multi-allelic gene family (Zhou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2006</xref>). <italic>Piz-t</italic> corresponds in a gene-for-gene fashion to the <italic>M. oryzae</italic> avirulence (<italic>Avr</italic>) gene <italic>AvrPiz-t</italic> (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2009</xref>). AvrPiz-t is a small, secreted protein that is translocated into the host cytoplasm. Recent studies have revealed that AvrPiz-t targets two rice ubiquitin E3 ligases, APIP6 (<underline>A</underline>vr<underline>P</underline>iz-t <underline>I</underline>nteracting <underline>P</underline>rotein 6) and APIP10, to suppress PAMP-triggered immunity in rice (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2016</xref>). AvrPiz-t also interacts with rice&#x02019;s bZIP-type transcription factor APIP5 (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2016</xref>), and its Nup98 family protein APIP12 (Tang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>), and K<sup>+</sup> channel protein OsAKT1 APIP7 (Shi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>) to suppress host basal defense. Conversely, Piz-t recognizes the AvrPiz-t signal through APIP5 and APIP10, and activates effector-triggered immunity in rice (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2016</xref>; Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2016</xref>). While the findings revealed aspects of the functions of AvrPiz-t/APIPs/Piz-t, the mechanisms underlying Piz-t-mediated rice resistance to blast fungus remain largely unknown.</p><p id="Par18">In this study, we performed isobaric tags for relative and absolute quantification (iTRAQ)-based proteomics analysis of rice in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> infection. We compared the protein expression profiles of Nipponbare and a transgenic Nipponbare line harboring the <italic>Piz-t</italic> gene inoculated with virulent and avirulent isolates at 24, 48, 72&#x000a0;h post-inoculation (hpi), respectively. A number of differentially expressed proteins (DEPs) that may be involved in rice response to pathogens were identified, including pathogenesis-related (PR) proteins, hormonal regulation-related proteins, defense and stress response-related proteins, receptor-like kinase, and cytochrome P450. We expected that our results would provide a valuable resource for the discovery of complex protein networks involved in the resistance response of rice to blast fungus.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Disease assessment and iTRAQ analysis</title><p id="Par19">To compare the responses of wild-type Nipponbare (NPB) and Nipponbare harboring the <italic>Piz-t</italic> gene (NPB-Piz-t) to infection with avirulent and virulent <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolates, we inoculated NPB and NPB-Piz-t with isolates KJ201 and RB22, respectively. An outline of the experimental design is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>. At 24, 48, and 72 hpi, no obvious symptoms of infection were observed on all tested rice seedlings. At 7&#x000a0;days post inoculation, while KJ201-inoculated NPB-Piz-t rice seedlings showed no disease symptoms, severe blast lesions were observed in NPB seedlings inoculated with KJ201 and RB22, and in NPB-Piz-t seedlings inoculated with RB22 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>), indicating the success of the inoculation experiment.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the experimental design. <bold>a</bold> The workflow for proteomic analysis of the defense response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> in rice harboring the blast resistance <italic>Piz-t</italic> gene using iTRAQ 2D LC-MS/MS technology. <bold>b</bold> Phenotypes of the wild-type rice cultivar Nipponbare (NPB) and transgenic Nipponbare line harboring the <italic>Piz-t</italic> gene (NPB-Piz-t) inoculated with <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolates KJ201 and RB22, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_240_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Proteins extracted from leaves of NPB and NPB-Piz-t inoculated with <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolates were subjected to iTRAQ analysis. After data filtering to eliminate low-scoring spectra (false discovery rate (FDR)&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), 2743, 1991, and 1839 proteins were identified from both mock-treated and <italic>M. oryzae</italic>-inoculated rice seedlings at 24, 48, and 72 hpi, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). DEPs between <italic>M. oryzae</italic>-inoculated and mock-treated leaves were identified according to the criteria of fold change &#x02265;1.5 or&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.67 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. In the NPB background, 85 proteins were identified as DEPs between the KJ201-inoculated sample (referred to as KJ201-NPB) and the mock-treated sample (referred to as Mock-NPB), including 11, 30, and 47 proteins at 24, 48, and 72 hpi, respectively; 120 proteins were identified as DEPs between the RB22-inoculated sample (referred to as RB22-NPB) and Mock-NPB, including 17, 41, and 67 proteins at 24, 48, and 72 hpi, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). In the NPB-Piz-t background, 114 proteins were identified as DEPs between the KJ201-inoculated sample (referred to as KJ201-Piz-t) and the mock-treated sample (referred to as Mock-Piz-t), including 23, 43, and 50 proteins at 24, 48, and 72 hpi, respectively; 118 proteins were identified as DEPs between the RB22-inoculated sample (referred to as RB22-Piz-t) and Mock-Piz-t, including 17, 37, and 65 proteins at 24, 48, and 72 hpi, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of spectra, peptide and protein identified at 24, 48 and 72 hpi</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">hpi</th><th rowspan="2">Spectra</th><th rowspan="2">Peptides</th><th rowspan="2">Proteins</th><th colspan="6">Differential expressed proteins</th></tr><tr><th>KJ201-NPB/Mock-NPB</th><th>RB22-NPB/Mock-NPB</th><th>KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t</th><th>RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Pizt</th><th>KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB</th><th>KJ201-Piz-t/RB22-Pizt</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>24&#x000a0;h</td><td>27133</td><td>16411</td><td>2743</td><td>11 (10&#x02191;, 1&#x02193;)</td><td>17 (4&#x02191;, 13&#x02193;)</td><td>23 (10&#x02191;, 13&#x02193;)</td><td>17 (8&#x02191;, 9&#x02193;)</td><td>40 (18&#x02191;, 22&#x02193;)</td><td>9 (7&#x02191;, 2&#x02193;)</td></tr><tr><td>48&#x000a0;h</td><td>27969</td><td>12125</td><td>1991</td><td>30 (21&#x02191;, 9&#x02193;)</td><td>41 (20&#x02191;, 21&#x02193;)</td><td>43 (35&#x02191;, 8&#x02193;)</td><td>37 (30&#x02191;,7&#x02193;)</td><td>32 (27&#x02191;, 5&#x02193;)</td><td>20 (8&#x02191;, 12&#x02193;)</td></tr><tr><td>72&#x000a0;h</td><td>29096</td><td>12593</td><td>1839</td><td>47 (29&#x02191;, 18&#x02193;)</td><td>67 (21&#x02191;,46&#x02193;)</td><td>50 (42&#x02191;, 8&#x02193;)</td><td>65 (50&#x02191;, 15&#x02193;)</td><td>24 (15&#x02191;, 9&#x02193;)</td><td>24 (7&#x02191;,17&#x02193;)</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td><td>85 (55&#x02191;, 27&#x02193;, 2&#x02191;&#x02191;, 1&#x02191;&#x02193;)</td><td>120 (42&#x02191;, 73&#x02193;, 1&#x02191;&#x02191;, 1&#x02191;&#x02193;, 3&#x02193;&#x02193;)</td><td>114 (83&#x02191;, 29&#x02193;, 2&#x02191;&#x02191;)</td><td>118 (87&#x02191;, 30&#x02193;, 1&#x02191;&#x02193;)</td><td>93 (57&#x02191;, 33&#x02193;, 1&#x02191;&#x02191;, 1&#x02191;&#x02193;, 1&#x02193;&#x02193;)</td><td>53 (22&#x02191;, 31&#x02193;)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>&#x02191; upregulated; &#x02193; downregulated; &#x02191;&#x02191; upregulated at two different hpi; &#x02193;&#x02193; downregulated at two different hpi; &#x02191;&#x02193; upregulated and downregulated at two different hpi; respectively; <italic>ND</italic> not determined</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Validation of differentially expressed proteins by qRT-PCR and western blotting</title><p id="Par21">Quantitative reverse-transcription PCR (qRT-PCR) and western blotting were used to validate the expression patterns of three proteins identified by iTRAQ. qRT-PCR results showed that the transcription level of OsGH1 (gi|218199777) in KJ201-Piz-t at 24 hpi was approximately 4.7 times that in KJ201-NPB at 24 hpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Western blot results showed that the accumulation of OsGH1 in KJ201-Piz-t at 24 hpi was obviously stronger than that in KJ201-NPB at 24 hpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). These results correlated with the iTRAQ data. Similarly, the results of qRT-PCR and western blotting revealed that the expression patterns of OsGH18 (gi|55168113) and OsCHIT7 (gi|20196) were consistent with the iTRAQ results (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>qRT-PCR (<bold>a</bold>) and western blot (<bold>b</bold>) confirmation of the three differentially expressed proteins identified by iTRAQ</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_240_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Differential proteomic profiles in NPB-Piz-t in response to virulent and avirulent <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolates</title><p id="Par22">We analyzed the proteomic profiles of NPB-Piz-t in response to the avirulent isolate KJ201 and the virulent isolate RB22. Compared with Mock-Piz-t, 10, 35, and 42 proteins were identified to be differentially upregulated in KJ201-Piz-t at 24, 48, and 72 hpi, and 13, 8, and 8 proteins were differentially downregulated in KJ201-Piz-t at 24, 48 and 72 hpi, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In RB22-Piz-t, 8, 30, and 50 proteins were differentially upregulated at 24, 48 and 72 hpi, and 9, 7 and 15 proteins were differentially downregulated at 24, 48 and 72 hpi, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In total, 85 proteins were differentially upregulated, and 29 proteins were downregulated in KJ201-Piz-t, and 87 and 30 proteins were differentially upregulated or downregulated, respectively, in BR22-Piz-t (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Among the upregulated proteins, 4, 18, and 30 were differentially upregulated in both KJ201-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t at 24, 48, and 72 hpi, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>-<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">c</xref>). While 4 proteins were differentially downregulated in both KJ201-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t at 24 hpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>), no proteins were shared between KJ201-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t at 48 or 72&#x000a0;hpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">c</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Venn diagrams of DEPs in NPB-<italic>Piz-t</italic> inoculated with <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolates at 24 (<bold>a</bold>), 48 (<bold>b</bold>), and 72 hpi (<bold>c</bold>), respectively. 116: mock-treated NPB-Piz-t; 117: KJ201-inoculated NPB-Piz-t; 118: RB22-inoculated NPB-Piz-t; Up: upregulated proteins; Down: Downregulated proteins</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_240_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">Using Gene Ontology (GO) analysis, DEPs were classified into biological process, cellular component, and molecular function terms (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). Analysis of DEPs specific to comparison KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t showed that the most common biological process categories were associated with metabolic and biosynthetic processes; the most common cellular component categories with cytoplasm and cytoplasmic parts; and the most common molecular function categories with binding and catalytic activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>, Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). In the case of DEPs specific to comparison RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t, the most common biological process categories were associated with metabolic process; the most common cellular component categories were cytoplasm and cytoplasmic parts; and the most common molecular function category was catalytic activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>, Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). For common DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t, the most common biological process categories were associated with the generation of precursor metabolites and protein folding; the most common cellular component categories were chloroplast, plastid, and mitochondrion; and the most common molecular function categories were catalytic activity and binding (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>, Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>GO analysis of DEPs in NPB-Piz-t in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> inoculation. <bold>a</bold> GO analysis of DEPs specific to comparison KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t. <bold>b</bold> GO analysis of DEPs specific to comparison RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t. <bold>c</bold> GO analysis of common DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t. The results are summarized in three main categories: biological process, cellular component, and molecular function</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_240_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par24">Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) analysis revealed that DEPs specific to comparison KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t were mainly involved in pathways related to photosynthetic antenna proteins; alanine, aspartate, and glutamate metabolism; phenylpropanoid biosynthesis; citrate (TCA) cycle; proteasome; and glyoxylate and dicarboxylate metabolism (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). DEPs specific to comparison RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t were mainly associated with the metabolism of carbon, glyoxylate and dicarboxylate; pyruvate and alpha-linolenic acid; and pathways related to metabolic, TCA cycle, oxidative phosphorylation, and biosynthesis of secondary metabolites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). The most highly enriched pathways in common DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t were associated with carbon metabolism, RNA degradation, metabolic pathways, photosynthesis, carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms, and biosynthesis of amino acids (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>KEGG classification of DEPs in NPB-Piz-t in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> inoculation. <bold>a</bold> KEGG classification of DEPs specific to comparison KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t. <bold>b</bold> KEGG classification of DEPs specific to comparison RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t. <bold>c</bold> KEGG classification of common DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_240_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par25">A Protein&#x02013;Protein Interaction (PPI) network of the identified DEPs was constructed using STRING (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). In NPB-Piz-t in response to KJ201, the DEPs were involved primarily in the biosynthesis of secondary metabolites. Specifically, ATP-citrate synthase beta chain protein 1 (ACLB-1) interacted with 15 proteins involved in secondary metabolite biosynthesis, carbon metabolism, cyanoamino acid metabolism, alpha-linolenic acid metabolism, carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms, TCA cycle, nitrogen metabolism, and glyoxylate and dicarboxylate metabolism. In NPB-Piz-t in response to RB22, the DEPs were involved mainly in carbon metabolism and the biosynthesis of secondary metabolites. Similarly, the common DEPs in NPB-Piz-t in response to both the two avirulent and virulent isolates, were mainly associated with secondary metabolite biosynthesis, carbon metabolism, and photosynthesis.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>PPI networks of DEPs in NPB-Piz-t in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> inoculation. Response to KJ201: DEPs specific to comparison KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t; Response to RB22: DEPs specific to comparison RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t; Co-Response: common DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t. <italic>P</italic>-values were calculated based on a -log scale. Fold change indicates the expression level of protein in the networks and are indicated in the white circle above each protein name</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_240_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par26">Based on GO and BLAST annotations, 33 DEPs that may be involved in rice response to pathogens were identified, including 10 PR proteins, 4 hormonal regulation-related proteins, 17 defense and stress-related proteins, 1 receptor-like kinase, and 1 cytochrome P450 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S3). Most of the proteins were upregulated in KJ201-Piz-t or in RB22-Piz-t, except for 1 PR protein gi|52353474 which was downregulated in RB22-Piz-t at 48 hpi, and 2 defense and stress-related proteins, gi|62733869 and gi|42408130, which were downregulated in KJ201-Piz-t at 24 hpi.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Expression patterns of DEPs may be involved in rice response to pathogens. <bold>a</bold> DEPs in NPB-Piz-t in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> inoculation. <bold>b</bold> DEPs in comparison between NPB-Piz-t and NPB in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolate KJ201. 114: KJ201-inoculated NPB; 116: mock-treated NPB-Piz-t; 117: KJ201-inoculated NPB-Piz-t; 118: RB22-inoculated NPB-Piz-t</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_240_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Differential proteomic profiles of NPB and NPB-Piz-t in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolate KJ201</title><p id="Par27">To obtain a more comprehensive profile of the proteome involved in <italic>Piz-t</italic>-mediated blast resistance, the proteomic profiles of KJ201-Piz-t and KJ201-NPB were compared. In total, 93 proteins were differentially expressed between KJ201-Piz-t and KJ201-NPB (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Table S4).</p><p id="Par28">GO analysis of DEPs in comparison KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB showed that the most common biological process categories were associated with metabolic and biosynthetic processes; the most common cellular component categories were associated with cytoplasm and cytoplasmic parts; and the most common molecular function categories were related to catalytic activity (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S1a, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Table S5). KEGG analysis revealed that the DEPs functioned mainly in carbon metabolism, metabolic pathways, biosynthesis of secondary metabolites, sulfur metabolism, porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism, biosynthesis of amino acids, and carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms (Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S1b, Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Table S5).</p><p id="Par29">PPI analysis revealed a complex network of the DEPs in comparison KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). At 24 hpi, while the proteins upregulated specifically in KJ201-Piz-t were involved primarily in fatty acid degradation; glycolysis/gluconeogenesis; and alanine, aspartate, and glutamate metabolism, a number of downregulated proteins were associated with porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism and ribosome. At 48 hpi, most of the DEPs were upregulated in KJ201-Piz-t, including proteins associated with cysteine and methionine metabolism, and phenylalanine, tyrosine, and tryptophan biosynthesis. Specifically, OSJNBb0042k11.2 (ribosomal protein L17-like protein) interacted with several downregulated proteins at 24 hpi and with 4 proteins up- or downregulated at 48 hpi. At 72 hpi, DEPs were mainly associated with carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms, glyoxylate and dicarboxylate metabolism, and sulfur metabolism. It is notable that several proteins related to RNA transport were linked to the nuclear pore complex (by network extension), suggesting that the activation of defense may be associated with gene regulation in the nuclei.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>PPI networks of DEPs in comparison between NPB-Piz-t and NPB in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolate KJ201. 24&#x000a0;h: 24 hpi; 48&#x000a0;h: 48 hpi; 72&#x000a0;h: 72 hpi</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_240_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p><p id="Par30">Twenty seven proteins that may be involved in rice response to pathogens were identified from DEPs in comparison KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB, including 6 PR proteins, 5 hormonal regulation-related proteins, 15 defense and stress-related proteins, and 1 receptor-like kinase (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S3). PR proteins and the receptor-like kinase were mainly upregulated in KJ201-Piz-t. In contrast, hormonal regulation-related proteins and defense and stress-related proteins displayed differential expression between KJ201-Piz-t and KJ201-NPB.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Identification of common DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB and KJ201-Piz-t/RB22-Piz-t</title><p id="Par31">The DEPs common to KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB and KJ201-Piz-t/RB22-Piz-t were identified. The KJ201-Piz-t interaction was incompatible, whereas the KJ201-NPB and RB22-Pizt interactions were compatible (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). Thus, the DEPs common to both comparisons may be strictly related to <italic>Piz-t</italic>-mediated rice blast resistance. In total, 9 proteins were differentially expressed between KJ201-Piz-t and KJ201-NPB and between KJ201-Piz-t and RB22-Piz-t (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). However, two proteins, gi|57900129 and gi|218188004, showed inconsistent patterns of expression; thus, seven proteins were identified as common DEPs between the two comparisons (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). One of the reasons for low common DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB and KJ201-Piz-t/RB22-Piz-t may be attributed to the differences of genetic background between <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolates KJ201 and RB22, and between NPB and NPB-Piz-t, although NPB-Piz-t was generated from NPB background. Among these common DEPs, alcohol dehydrogenase I (gi|34787317) and receptor-like protein kinase (gi|59800021) were upregulated in KJ201-Piz-t as compared with KJ201-NPB or RB22-Piz-t at 24 hpi; endochitinase (gi|20196) was upregulated in KJ201-Piz-t at 48 hpi, and similar to rubisco large subunit (gi|4680202) and hypothetical protein OsJ_24720 (gi|222637272) were upregulated in KJ201-Piz-t at 72&#x000a0;hpi. The two proteins, hypothetical protein OsJ_12578 (gi|222625800) and NADP-dependent malic enzyme (gi|54606800), were downregulated in KJ201-Piz-t as compared with KJ201-NPB or RB22-Piz-t at 48 and 72 hpi, respectively.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Common DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB and KJ201-Piz-t/RB22/Piz-t</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Accession no.</th><th rowspan="2">Protein description</th><th colspan="2">Fold change</th><th colspan="2">Differentially expression pattern</th></tr><tr><th>KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB</th><th>KJ201-Piz-t/RB22/Piz-t</th><th>KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB</th><th>KJ201-Piz-t/RB22/Piz-t</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>gi|34787317</td><td>Alcohol dehydrogenase I [<italic>Oryza rufipogon</italic>]</td><td>1.690</td><td>1.871</td><td>Up at 24 hpi</td><td>Up at 24 hpi</td></tr><tr><td>gi|59800021</td><td>Receptor-like protein kinase [<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> Japonica Group]</td><td>6.607</td><td>4.875</td><td>Up at 24 hpi</td><td>Up at 24 hpi</td></tr><tr><td>gi|20196</td><td>Endochitinase, OsCHIT7 [<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>]</td><td>2.089</td><td>4.920</td><td>Up at 48 hpi</td><td>Up at 48 hpi</td></tr><tr><td>gi|4680202</td><td>Similar to rubisco large subunit [<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>]</td><td>1.514</td><td>3.404</td><td>Up at 72 hpi</td><td>Up at 72 hpi</td></tr><tr><td>gi|222637272</td><td>Hypothetical protein OsJ_24720 [<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> Japonica Group]</td><td>2.421</td><td>3.221</td><td>Up at 72 hpi</td><td>Up at 72 hpi</td></tr><tr><td>gi|222625800</td><td>Hypothetical protein OsJ_12578 [<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> Japonica Group]</td><td>0.530</td><td>0.391</td><td>Down at 48 hpi</td><td>Down at 48 hpi</td></tr><tr><td>gi|54606800</td><td>NADP dependent malic enzyme [<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> Japonica Group]</td><td>0.637</td><td>0.619</td><td>Down at 72 hpi</td><td>Down at 72 hpi</td></tr><tr><td>gi|57900129</td><td>Putative transaldolase [<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> Japonica Group]</td><td>1.528</td><td>0.535</td><td>Up at 24 hpi</td><td>Down at 72 hpi</td></tr><tr><td>gi|218188004</td><td>Hypothetical protein OsI_01440 [<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> Indica Group]</td><td>0.366</td><td>1.675</td><td>Down at 48 hpi</td><td>Up at 48 hpi</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par32">We used iTRAQ to investigate proteome expression profiles during compatible and incompatible interactions of rice NPB and NPB-Piz-t lines with <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolates. Our analysis identified a number of DEPs that may be involved in rice-<italic>M. oryzae</italic> interactions and revealed common DEPs in NPB-Piz-t during the resistance reaction to <italic>M. oryzae</italic>.</p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Carbohydrate metabolism and energy production in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> infection</title><p id="Par33">Photosynthesis is one of the most fundamental physiological processes in plants. However, the photosystem is vulnerable to damage by plant pathogens, and if not repaired in time, it loses its function (Che et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>). Reducing the photosynthetic rate to allocate resources in defense against pathogens which compromise photosynthesis has been suggested as an effective defense mechanism in the early infection stages (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2015</xref>). Hanssen et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2011</xref>) showed that a number of photosynthesis-related genes were downregulated in tomato plants infected with <italic>Pepino mosaic virus</italic> during early stages of infection. Similarly, comparative phosphoproteomic analysis revealed that a number of photosynthesis-related phosphoproteins were downregulated in rice in both compatible and incompatible interactions with <italic>M. oryzae</italic> (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2015</xref>). In addition, our research showed that two important photosynthesis-related proteins, psaB (gi|42795618) and psbC (gi|68565738) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1) were downregulated in both compatible and incompatible interactions at 24 hpi. In contrast, at 48 or 72 hpi, a photosynthesis-related protein, P0463D04.20 (gi|52077301), and several proteins related to carbon fixation in photosynthesis, including Os03g0255500 (gi|291048382), OJ1484_G09.129&#x02013;1 (gi|257665951), OSJNBb0060J21.2 (gi|81686700), TPI (gi|385717670), Os10g0478200 (gi|75141370), and P0459B01.11 (gi|41052955), were found to be upregulated in both compatible and incompatible interactions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). The respiratory pathway of the TCA cycle is essential for energy production (Fernie et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2004</xref>). In the present study, six TCA cycle-related proteins, Os03g0255500 (gi|291048382), Os12g0616900 (gi|77557068), Os10g0478200 (gi|68565738), ACLB-1 (gi|75249275), P0038F12.18 (gi|81686717), and OSJNBa0072K14.5 (gi|21740743), were found to be upregulated in compatible or incompatible interactions at 48 or 72 hpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). The upregulation of photosynthesis-and TCA cycle-related proteins at late infection stages suggests that restoration of the photosynthetic system in rice promotes recovery from <italic>M. oryzae</italic> infection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Defense-related proteins involved in NPB and NPB-Piz-t responses to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> infection</title><p id="Par34">Plant PR proteins play an important role in defenses against pathogens (van Loon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2006</xref>). In this study, 12 PR proteins were identified as DEPs between the <italic>M. oryzae</italic>-inoculated NPB and/or NPB-Piz-t and the mock-treated rice leaves samples (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S3). While OsOC-2 (gi|52353474) exhibited less expression levels in KJ201-NPB (compared with Mock-NPB, at 48 hpi) and in RB22-Piz-t (compared with Mock-Pizt, at 48 hpi), respectively, the rest 11 PRs were expressed higher in the <italic>M. oryzae</italic>-inoculated samples than that in the mock-treated samples. In comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB and KJ201-Piz-t/RB22-Piz-t, 7 PRs were identified as DEPs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S3). Interestingly, compared with KJ201-NPB or RB22-Piz-t, 5 out of 7 PRs, OsCHIT7/endochitinase (gi|20196), BBTI-4/RBBI3&#x02013;1 (gi|53792234), OsCHIB1 (gi|55168113), Gns12 (gi|218199777), and OsLTP2 (gi|1667590) were identified to be differentially upregulated in KJ201-Piz-t. The results suggest that some PRs may be involved more specifically in Piz-t-mediated resistance response.</p><p id="Par35">The receptor-like kinases (RLKs) are key regulators of plant development and defense (Gao and Xue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2012</xref>). The rice genome contains more than 1131 RLKs that are involved in regulating various physiological processes, including defense and disease resistance (Shiu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2004</xref>). In this study, a receptor-like kinase protein (gi|59800021) was found to be differentially upregulated in <italic>M. oryzae</italic>-inoculated NPB and NPB-Piz-t at 24 hpi or 72 hpi, compared with the mock-treated NPB or NPB-Piz-t samples (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Table S6). gi|59800021 was also upregulated in KJ201-Piz-t when compared with KJ201-NPB or RB22-Piz-t (Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Table S6). gi|59800021 contains two salt stress response/antifungal domains. We speculate that this receptor-like kinase protein would be worthy of functional investigation as it may play an important role in rice defenses against blast fungus.</p><p id="Par36">Recent studies have revealed that AvrPiz-t function to suppress host basal defense (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2009</xref>; Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2012</xref>). By Y2H screening, 12 APIPs have been identified (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2012</xref>), and APIP5 (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2016</xref>), APIP6 (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2012</xref>), APIP7 (Shi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>), APIP10 (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2016</xref>), and APIP12 (Tang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>) have been functionally confirmed as targets of AvrPiz-t. Interestingly, in this study, we observed that a putative bowman birk trypsin inhibitor (gi|53792234) was induced to higher levels in KJ201-NPB than that in Mock-NPB at 72 hpi, in KJ201-Piz-t than that in Mock-Piz-t at 24 hpi, in RB22-Piz-t than that in Mock-Piz-t at 72 hpi, and in KJ201-Piz-t than that in KJ201-NPB at 24 hpi (Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Table S6). The bowman birk trypsin inhibitor was previously identified as APIP4 by Y2H (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2012</xref>). Taken together, the APIP4/bowman birk trypsin inhibitor might be involved in AvrPiz-t/Piz-t networks.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par37">In this study, comparative proteome profiling of the transgenic NPB-Piz-t and wild type NPB inoculated with an avirulent <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolate KJ201 and a virulent isolate RB22 at 24, 48, and 72 hpi were investigated using iTRAQ analysis. A total of 114 and 118 DEPs were identified in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Pizt and RB22-Piz-t/Mock-Pizt, respectively. A number of DEPs that may be involved in rice response to pathogens were identified, including PR proteins, hormonal regulation-related proteins, defense and stress response-related proteins, receptor-like kinase, and cytochrome P450. There were 7 common DEPs between the comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/RB22-Piz-t and KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB, including alcohol dehydrogenase I, receptor-like protein kinase, endochitinase, similar to rubisco large subunit, NADP-dependent malic enzyme, and two hypothetical proteins. These results provide a valuable resource for studying the mechanism of <italic>Piz-t</italic>-mediated defense in rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Plant materials, fungal isolates, and <italic>M. oryzae</italic> inoculation</title><p id="Par38">The rice cultivar Nipponbare (NPB), the transgenic Nipponbare line harboring the <italic>Piz-t</italic> gene (NPB-Piz-t) (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2016</xref>), and the <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolates KJ201 (avirulent to <italic>Piz-t</italic>) and RB22 (virulent to <italic>Piz-t</italic>) were used in this study. <italic>M. oryzae</italic> inoculations were performed in a greenhouse following a previously described procedure (Tian et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2016</xref>). Rice seedlings were grown in the greenhouse for approximately 2&#x000a0;weeks and were spray-inoculated with spores at a concentration of 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> spores mL<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>. The inoculated seedlings were maintained under high humidity, and leaves were collected at 24, 48, and 72&#x000a0;hpi, frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until protein extraction.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Protein extraction, digestion, and iTRAQ labeling</title><p id="Par39">Total protein was extracted from leaves of control and inoculated plants according to previously described procedures (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2013</xref>). The proteins were reduced using dithiothreitol and alkylated using iodoacetamide prior to trypsin digestion. The digested proteins were labeled using an iTRAQ Reagents 8PLEXKit (Applied Biosystems, FosterCity, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The samples of mock-treated NPB and NPB-Piz-t were labeled with iTRAQ tags 113 and 116; KJ201-inoculated NPB and NPB-Piz-t samples were labeled with iTRAQ tags 114 and 117; and RB22-inoculated NPB and NPB-Piz-t were labeled with iTRAQ tags 115 and 118, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). The samples of NPB and NPB-Piz-tat 24, 48, and 72&#x000a0;hpi were run in three independent experiments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>2D high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) separation, tandem mass spectrometry (MS/MS) analysis, protein identification, and relative quantification</title><p id="Par40">Strong cation exchange, reversed-phase nanoflow HPLC, and MS/MS measurements were performed as described previously (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2016</xref>). The MS/MS data were processed with ProteinPilot software (Applied Biosystems) against a local rice protein database from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) with parameter settings as described (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2016</xref>). Protein identification was based on a FDR of 1%, and proteins with a fold change value of &#x02265;1.5 or&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.67 and a <italic>P</italic>-value of &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were regarded as significantly differentially expressed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Bioinformatics analysis</title><p id="Par41">Biological processes, cellular components, and molecular functions of DEPs were determined by GO database annotation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org">http://www.geneontology.org</ext-link>/). Protein signaling pathways were elucidated using the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/pathway.html">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/pathway.html</ext-link>). Pathways enriched at <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were considered significant. Protein&#x02013;protein interaction (PPI) analysis was performed using STRING (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.string-db.org">www.string-db.org</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>qRT-PCR</title><p id="Par42">Total RNA was extracted from rice leaves using Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol, followed by DNase I (Takara, Dalian, China) treatment. First-strand cDNA was generated using a RevertAid First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). qRT-PCR was performed on an ABI Prism 7500 Detection System (Applied Biosystems) using a SYBR Green Real-time PCR Master Mix (Takara). The primers used for qRT-PCR are listed in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: Table S7.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p id="Par43">Total protein was extracted from rice leaves using an extraction buffer (50&#x000a0;mM Tris-MES, pH&#x000a0;8.0, 0.5&#x000a0;M Suc, 1 mMMgCl2, 10&#x000a0;mM EDTA, 5&#x000a0;mM DTT, 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M MG132), and plant protease inhibitor cocktail as described (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2012</xref>). The protein concentration was measured using a Bio-Rad protein assay kit (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). Proteins (30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g) were separated using 10% SDS-PAGE and then electrotransferred onto a polyvinylidene fluoride membrane (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). Immunoblotting was conducted using standard protocols. Anti-OsGH1, anti-OsGH18, and anti-OsCHIT7 (Beijing Protein Innovation, Beijing, China) were used at a dilution of 1:2000. Horseradish peroxidase-conjugated goat anti-rabbit antibody (Jackson ImmunoResearch, West Grove, PA, USA) was used at a dilution of 1:10,000. Chemiluminescence was detected using Pierce ECL substrate (Thermo Scientific) followed by exposure to hyperfilm.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec19"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_240_MOESM1_ESM.xls"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> DEPs in comparisons KJ201-NPB/Mock-NPB, RB22-NPB/Mock-NPB, KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t, and RB22-Piz-t//Mock-Piz-t. (XLS 152 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_240_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S2.</bold> GO and KEGG analyses of DEPs in comparisons KJ201-Piz-t/Mock-Piz-t, and RB22-Piz-t//Mock-Piz-t. (XLSX 84 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_240_MOESM3_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S3.</bold> Identification of DEPs that may be involved in rice response to pathogens. (DOCX 27 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_240_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S4.</bold> DEPs in comparison KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB. (XLSX 23 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_240_MOESM5_ESM.pptx"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> GO (a) and KEGG (b) analyses of DEPs in comparison between NPB-Piz-t and NPB in response to <italic>M. oryzae</italic> isolate KJ201. (PPTX 434 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_240_MOESM6_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S5.</bold> GO and KEGG analyses of DEPs in comparison KJ201-Piz-t/KJ201-NPB. (XLSX 47 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_240_MOESM7_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 7:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S6.</bold> Differentially expression pattern of receptor-like protein kinase (gi|59800021) and putative bowman birk trypsin inhibitor (gi|53792234). (DOCX 16 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_240_MOESM8_ESM.doc"><label>Additional file 8:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S7.</bold> Primers used for qRT-PCR analysis in this study. (DOC 30 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>APIPs</term><def><p id="Par4">AvrPiz-t interacting proteins</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DEPs</term><def><p id="Par5">Differentially expressed proteins</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FDR</term><def><p id="Par6">False discovery rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p id="Par7">Gene ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>hpi</term><def><p id="Par8">Hours post-inoculation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HPLC</term><def><p id="Par9">High-performance liquid chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>iTRAQ</term><def><p id="Par10">Isobaric tags for relative and absolute quantification</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p id="Par11">Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPI</term><def><p id="Par12">Protein&#x02013;protein interaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PR</term><def><p id="Par13">Pathogenesis-related</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qRT-PCR</term><def><p id="Par14">Quantitative reverse-transcription PCR</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This project is supported by grants from National Natural Science Foundation of China (U1405212, 31640006) and grant from Natural Science Foundation of Fujian Province, China (2014&#x000a0;J07004).</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par44">National Natural Science Foundation of China (U1405212, 31640006) and grant from Natural Science Foundation of Fujian Province, China (2014&#x000a0;J07004)&#x000a0;and&#x000a0;Natural Science Foundation&#x000a0;for&#x000a0;Higher Education Institutions of&#x000a0;Jiangsu Province (17KJA180002).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par45">The datasets supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the article and its additional files.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>DT, LY and SC conceived and designed the experiments. DT, LY, ZC, ZC, LY and SC performed the experiments. DT, LY, LY and SC analyzed the data. FW, YZ and YL contributed reagents and tools. DT, LY and SC wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagnaresi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Biselli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr&#x000f9;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Urso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Crispino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbruscato</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Piffanelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupotto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattivelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Val&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative transcriptome profiling of the early response to <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> in durable resistant vs susceptible rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) genotypes</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e51609</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051609</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23251593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23251593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Che</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C-terminal processing of reaction center protein D1 is essential for the function and assembly of photosystem II in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>16247</fpage><lpage>16252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1313894110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24043802?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24043802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebbole</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Farman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Orbach</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Donofrio</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soanes</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Djonovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolomiets</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehmeyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Coughlan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusbaum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Galagan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Birren</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genome sequence of the rice blast fungus <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>434</volume><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>986</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03449</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15846337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15846337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebbole</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Magnaporthe</italic> as a model for understanding host-pathogen interactions</article-title><source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.45.062806.094346</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17489691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17489691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweetlove</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory metabolism: glycolysis, the TCA cycle and mitochondrial electron transport</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2004.03.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15134745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15134745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of expression profiles of rice receptor like kinase genes</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssr062</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21765177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21765177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanwar</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The single functional blast resistance gene <italic>Pi54</italic> activates a complex defence mechanism in rice</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2012</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err297</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22058403?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22058403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanssen</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballester</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogewoning</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>NO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential tomato transcriptomic responses induced by Pepino mosaic virus isolates with differential aggressiveness</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.173906</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21427280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21427280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Solanke</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding host-pathogen interactions with expression profiling of NILs carrying rice-blast resistance <italic>Pi9</italic> gene</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>93</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00093</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28280498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28280498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakwal</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In-depth insight into in vivo apoplastic secretome of rice-<italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> interaction</article-title><source>J Proteome</source><year>2013</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2012.10.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression profiling of rice genes in early defense responses to blast and bacterial blight pathogens using cDNA microarray</article-title><source>Physiol Mol Plant Pathol</source><year>2006</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmpp.2006.06.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> avirulence gene <italic>AvrPiz-t</italic> encodes a predicted secreted protein that triggers the immunity in rice mediated by the blast resistance gene <italic>Piz-t</italic></article-title><source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><year>2009</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-22-4-0411</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19271956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19271956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative proteomic analysis of methyl jasmonate-induced defense responses indifferent rice cultivars</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1088</fpage><lpage>1101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.201300104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24505015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24505015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative phosphoproteome analysis of <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>-responsive proteins in susceptible and resistant rice cultivars</article-title><source>J Proteome</source><year>2015</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2014.12.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirsekar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Khang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Songkumarn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Afzal</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellizzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Valent</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> effector AvrPiz-t targets the RING E3 ubiquitin ligase APIP6 to suppress pathogen-associated molecular pattern-triggered immunity in rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>4748</fpage><lpage>4762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.105429</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23204406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23204406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirsekar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellizzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Songkumarn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Suttiviriya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Umemura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The E3 ligase APIP10 connects the effector AvrPiz-t to the NLR receptor Piz-t in rice</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e1005529</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1005529</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27031246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27031246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fungal pathogen <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> suppresses innate immunity by modulating a host potassium channel</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>e1006878</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006878</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29385213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29385213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlowski</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzeng</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of the receptor-like kinase family in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1220</fpage><lpage>1234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.020834</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15105442?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15105442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapila</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathour</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and physical mapping of a new allele of <italic>Pik</italic> locus from japonica rice &#x02018;Lijiangxintuanheigu&#x02019;</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2015</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-015-1437-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nup98 homolog APIP12 targeted by the effector AvrPiz-t is involved in rice basal resistance against <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title><source>Rice</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12284-017-0144-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28205154?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28205154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allele-specific marker-based assessment revealed that the rice blast resistance genes <italic>Pi2</italic> and <italic>Pi9</italic> have not been widely deployed in Chinese indica rice cultivars</article-title><source>Rice</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>19</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12284-016-0091-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27142801?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27142801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Loon</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rep</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significance of inducible defense-related proteins in infected plants</article-title><source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source><year>2006</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.44.070505.143425</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16602946?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16602946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vergne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidi Mammar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Droc</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>DeRose</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tharreau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Notteghem</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early and specific gene expression triggered by rice resistance gene <italic>Pi33</italic> in response to infection by ACE1 avirulent blast fungus</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2007</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.01971.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17335506?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17335506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vergne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grand</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalvon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Saindrenan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tharreau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nott&#x000e9;ghem</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preformed expression of defense is a hallmark of partial resistance to rice blast fungal pathogen <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>206</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-206</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20849575?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20849575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellizzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunity to rice blast disease by suppression of effector-triggered necrosis</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2399</fpage><lpage>2411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2016.06.072</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27641772?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27641772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Under pressure: investigating the biology of plant infection by <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19219052?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19219052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris-Shultz</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd-Allah</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dynamic changes of the plasma membrane proteins and the protective roles of nitric oxide in rice subjected to heavy metal cadmium stress</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>190</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26955374?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26955374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative proteome analyses reveal that nitric oxide is an important signal molecule in the response of rice to aluminum toxicity</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1316</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr300971n</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23327584?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23327584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis highlights defense and signaling pathways mediated by rice <italic>pi21</italic> gene with partial resistance to <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1834</fpage><?supplied-pmid 28008334?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28008334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellizzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The eight amino-acid differences within three leucine rich repeats between <italic>Pi2</italic> and <italic>Piz-t</italic> resistance proteins determine the resistance specificity to <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic></article-title><source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1216</fpage><lpage>1228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-19-1216</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17073304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17073304</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>