<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biotechnol Biofuels</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biotechnol Biofuels</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biotechnology for Biofuels</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1754-6834</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6319013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1340</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-018-1340-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>PLD&#x003b1;1-knockdown soybean seeds display higher unsaturated glycerolipid contents and seed vigor in high temperature and humidity environments</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Gaoyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bahn</surname><given-names>Sung-Chul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Geliang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yanrui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Beibei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yuliang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xuemin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4416-7334</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name><address><phone>+86-18674047685</phone><email>jianzhao@ahau.edu.cn</email><email>jzhao2@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 4804</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411389.6</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Tea Plant Biology and Utilization, College of Tea and Food Science and Technology, </institution><institution>Anhui Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Hefei, 230036 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000114809378</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266757.7</institution-id><institution>University of Missouri at St Louis, Donald Danforth Plant Science Center, </institution></institution-wrap>St. Louis, MO 63132 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 4137</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.35155.37</institution-id><institution>National Key Laboratory of Crop Genetic Improvement, </institution><institution>Huazhong Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, 430075 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9835 1415</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.453499.6</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Biology and Genetic Resources of Tropical Crops. Ministry of Agriculture, Institute of Tropical Bioscience and Biotechnology, </institution><institution>Chinese Academy of Tropical Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Haikou, Hainan 571101 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>9</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Soybean oil constitutes an important source of vegetable oil and biofuel. However, high temperature and humidity adversely impacts soybean seed development, yield, and quality during plant development and after harvest. Genetic improvement of soybean tolerance to stress environments is highly desirable.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">Transgenic soybean lines with knockdown of phospholipase D&#x003b1;1 (<italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic>) were generated to study <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1&#x02032;</italic>s effects on lipid metabolism and seed vigor under high temperature and humidity conditions. Under such stress, as compared with normal growth conditions, <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines showed an attenuated stress-induced deterioration during soybean seed development, which was associated with elevated expression of reactive oxygen species-scavenging genes when compared with wild-type control. The developing seeds of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> had higher levels of unsaturation in triacylglycerol (TAG) and major membrane phospholipids, but lower levels of phosphatidic acid and lysophospholipids compared with control cultivar. Lipid metabolite and gene expression profiling indicates that the increased unsaturation on phosphatidylcholine (PC) and enhanced conversion between PC and diacylglycerol (DAG) by PC:DAG acyltransferase underlie a basis for increased TAG unsaturation in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds. Meanwhile, the turnover of PC and phosphatidylethanolamine (PE) into lysoPC and lysoPE was suppressed in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds under high temperature and humidity conditions. <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds suffered lighter oxidative stresses than did wild-type developing seeds in the stressful environments. <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds contain higher oil contents and maintained higher germination rates than the wild-type seeds.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">The study provides insights into the roles of PLD&#x003b1;1 in developing soybean seeds under high temperature and humidity stress. <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> decreases pre-harvest deterioration and enhances acyl editing in phospholipids and TAGs. The results indicate a way towards improving production of quality soybean seeds as foods and biofuels under increasing environmental stress.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13068-018-1340-4) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Phospholipase D</kwd><kwd>Glycerolipid</kwd><kwd>Oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>Acyl editing</kwd><kwd>Unsaturation</kwd><kwd>High temperature and humidity</kwd><kwd>Oil content</kwd><kwd>Seed vigor</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Ministry of Science and Technology of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016YFD0100504</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Agriculture and Food Research Initiative (AFRI)</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016-67013-24429/project accession number 1007600</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xuemin</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31670294</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>The significances statement</title><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par4">Developing soybean seeds suffer from high temperature and humidity stress conditions that often occur in Southern China and cause oxidative stress and seed pre-harvest deterioration. Such soybean seed deterioration can be alleviated by seed-specific knockdown of <italic>phospholipase D&#x003b1;1</italic> (<italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic>). Thus, <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybeans have improved nutrition quality and seed vigor.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par5"><italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds have higher levels of unsaturation in triacylglycerol and phospholipids due to enhanced expression of desaturase genes and enhanced acyl editing and PC&#x02013;DAG conversion activities in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds compared with the wild-type seeds.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par6">The finding that <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds had improved seed vigor, nutrition quality, and tolerance to high temperature and humidity provides a molecular tool for genetic improvement of soybean for adaptation to wider growth conditions.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Background</title><p id="Par7">With global temperature increasing steadily in recent decades, high temperature conditions, accompanied either by drought or by humidity in different areas, caused damages and losses on crops and yield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. However, how high temperature and humidity affect crop growth, seed development, as well as yield is not well understood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The high temperature and humidity conditions adversely affect membrane lipids and storage triacylglycerol (TAG) in wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and oilseed crops, such as soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic>), particularly during seed development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. High temperatures impact developing soybean seeds&#x02019; sensitivity and vulnerability to stresses by causing seeds with poor germination, increased incidence of pathogen infection, and decreased economic value [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Previous studies indicated that phospholipase D&#x003b1; (PLD&#x003b1;1) is involved in seed naturally and artificially aging, by affecting both phospholipids and TAG of mature Arabidopsis and soybean seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. However, how PLD&#x003b1;1 affects lipid metabolism and storage nutrition of developing soybean seeds grown under high temperature and humidity conditions was unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Assembly of phospholipids and TAG occurs primarily in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and shares a common biosynthetic precursor phosphatidic acid (PA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Membrane phospholipid synthesis is active in young and green tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, in developing oilseeds, phospholipid metabolism is overwhelmingly directed to TAG accumulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], through two major pathways: the diacylglycerol acyltransferase (DGAT)-mediated Kennedy pathway that uses acyl-CoA and the diacylglycerol (DAG) to generate TAG, and phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase (PDAT)-mediated pathway that uses phosphatidylcholine (PC) and DAG to produce TAG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Overexpression of an A-type phospholipase, <italic>pPLAIII&#x003b4;</italic>, enhanced TAG production in Arabidopsis and Camelina seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. A-type phospholipase, PLA catalyzing the hydrolysis of PC to generate a free fatty acid and lysoPC (LPC), can also affect TAG production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Acyl-CoA:LPC acyltransferase (LPCAT) can modify PC saturation by introducing an acyl-CoA into a new PC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. De novo PC biosynthesis from choline by the actions of choline/ethanolamine kinase (CEK), choline-phosphate cytidylyltransferase (CCT), and DAG cholinephosphotransferase (DAG:CPT) is also important for phospholipid and TAG metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The interconversion between PC and DAG by PC:DAG cholinephosphotransferase (PDCT, also ROD1) can significantly affect TAG biosynthesis and unsaturation through above mentioned pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. PDCT transfers phosphocholine from PC to DAG actively during oil seed development, and edits TAG composition using PC that is also extensively modified by fatty acid desaturases (FADs) on their acyl chains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In the ER, the partitioning of PA, PC, and DAG precursors for TAG or phospholipid biosynthesis may be controlled by a unexplored complex network. For instance, it has been estimated that more than 70% PC-derived DAG is used to synthesize TAG in flax seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Thus, PC plays multiple roles in TAG and phospholipid biosynthesis by recycling or incorporation of the newly synthesized fatty acids in TAG acyl editing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">PLD may contribute to diurnal cycling of PA, and PC acyl editing and significantly affect PC pools and TAG production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. A study demonstrated that PC-derived DAG is the major source for TAG synthesis in <italic>Camelina</italic> seeds overexpressing <italic>PLD&#x003b6;1</italic> and <italic>PLD&#x003b6;2</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Recently, a genome-wide association study suggested a <italic>PLD&#x003b1;</italic> gene as a key locus affecting oil biosynthesis in soybean [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Studies indicated that PLD<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>1 is involved in the mature seed aging and deterioration stored under high temperature and humidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Two <italic>PLD&#x003b1;</italic>-<italic>RNAi</italic> knockdown (<italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic>) soybean lines had had altered unsaturation fatty acids in both phospholipids and TAG when grown in Kansas in the United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. However, it is still not understood why <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds have such changes in fatty acyl chains saturation.</p><p id="Par10">Although the anti-deterioration effects of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> mutation on naturally or artificially aging Arabidopsis and soybean seeds have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], the underlying molecular mechanism by which <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> mutation affects lipids metabolism and seed quality has not been explored [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Especially, how PLD&#x003b1;1 mutation affects soybean developing seeds under heat and humidity stresses is unknown. High temperature and humidity stresses occur frequently in southern China amid increasing global temperature in recent years and cause soybean pre-harvest deterioration and significant losses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. High temperature and humidity are major problems and limiting factors in soybean production area, and they not only caused soybean yield loss, but also affected adversely on seed storage and reduced nutrition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In the Mid-Yangzi River region of China, soybean seed development and ripening occur during the season of high precipitations (~&#x02009;more than 150&#x000a0;mm), high temperature (~&#x02009;34&#x02013;38&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C), and high humidity (~&#x02009;75&#x02013;80%) usually from the late June to the early September (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). The soybean seeds grown in these regions usually have pre-harvest deterioration, rapidly losing seed vigor, reducing nutrition quality severely, and are more vulnerable to pathogens during storage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. A better understanding of the mechanism by which high temperature and humidity impact developing soybean seeds will help design effective genetic strategies to improve soybean tolerance to these environmental stress conditions. Here, we generated <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean lines and investigated the <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean performance in such stressful environments. The data indicate a critical role of PLD&#x003b1;1 in lipid metabolism and stress response in developing soybean seeds under high temperature and humidity stress conditions, as compared in normal environments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Generation of transgenic soybean plants with seed-specific knockdown of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic></title><p id="Par11">Soybean <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> transgenic plants were generated by stable transformation of soybean cultivar Jack with a soybean <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1</italic> RNA interference (RNAi) construct under the control of the seed-specific promoter &#x003b2;-conglycinin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1). T0 and T2 transgenic plants were screened with qRT-PCR and immunoblotting with an antibody against Arabidopsis PLD&#x003b1;1. This antibody specifically recognized the ~&#x02009;92&#x000a0;kDa GmPLD&#x003b1;1 at both leaf and seed tissues of soybean (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The transgenic and background cultivar Jack seeds displayed different levels of PLD&#x003b1;1 accumulation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Immunoblotting screening for regenerated transgenic soybean lines showed that in the line #1020 (<italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD2</italic>), PLD&#x003b1;1 proteins in the developing and mature seeds were almost completely diminished by expression of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1RNAi</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b), whereas in another regenerated transgenic soybean line #1048 (<italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic>) displayed about 25% of that in wild-type soybean cultivar Jack (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). To confirm the seed specific expression of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1RNAi</italic> and seed-specific suppression of soybean PLD&#x003b1;1, proteins extracted from leaves and seeds of two <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines and wild-type control (Jack) were immunoblotted for PLD&#x003b1;1, and PLD&#x003b1;1 proteins remained in leaves of both transgenic lines, <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic> and <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD2</italic>, but was greatly diminished in their seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d). Assaying PLD&#x003b1;1 activity showed that PLD activity in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic> and <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD2</italic> was 23% and 10% of that in wild- type, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>e).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Generation of soybean <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown lines. Soybean <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> transgenic plants were generated by stable transformation of soybean cultivar Jack with a soybean <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> RNA interference (RNAi) construct. Transgenic soybean plants were used for analysis. <bold>a</bold> Construction of soybean <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic>. 1151bp one in forward and the other in reverse and separated by a DNA fragment of <italic>Pdk</italic>-<italic>I</italic> gene, is driven by a seed specific promoter for soybean <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>conglycinin</italic> gene encoding a major seed storage protein in seed, and terminated by a <italic>Phaseo</italic> gene terminator. <bold>b</bold> Immunoblotting screening PLD&#x003b1;1 in seeds of transgenic soybean plants 1020 (<italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic>). 1&#x02013;6 indicate individual plants from transgenic line or wild-type Jack (control). <bold>c</bold> Immunoblotting detection PLD&#x003b1;1 in seeds of another transgenic soybean line 1048 (<italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD2</italic>). 1&#x02013;3 indicate the individual plants from each transgenic line or wild-type Jack (control). <bold>d</bold> Immunoblotting of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> using proteins extracted from leaves and seeds from two <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines1. <bold>e</bold> PLD&#x003b1;1 activity in two <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines 1 and wild-type Jack line1 (control) developing seeds</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Effects of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> on the expression of other <italic>PLD</italic>s</title><p id="Par12">The soybean PLD family has 23 members (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2a, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2, Data S1). To evaluate the effect of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> on the expression patterns of different PLDs, developing seeds of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> from T3 and T5 generations of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> transgenic lines were tested (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Three <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;</italic>s are highly expressed (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S3) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> mutants, the expression of various <italic>PLD&#x003b1;</italic>s, including targeted <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic>s, was reduced significantly compared with that of control at different developmental stages (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2c, d). In control Jack seeds, <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;3</italic> is the most highly expressed, <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1</italic> is the second highest, and <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;4</italic> is the third most highly expressed <italic>PLD</italic> gene in developing seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2b, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. When using a pair of primers that amplify all <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;</italic>s, the total <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;</italic> expression displayed a similar pattern as that for the above major <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;</italic>s. <italic>GmPLD&#x003b2;3</italic> transcripts were lower in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> mutants than in wild-type during early stages of seed development, but higher than in Jack at late stages of seed development (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2c). Among <italic>GmPLD&#x003b2;</italic>s, <italic>GmPLD&#x003b2;4</italic> showed the highest expression level in developing seeds, and then <italic>GmPLD&#x003b2;1</italic>. Most other <italic>PLD&#x003b2;</italic>s were expressed at a low level in soybean developing seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2b, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Among two major <italic>GmPLD&#x003b4;s</italic> expressed in developing seeds, <italic>GmPLD&#x003b4;1</italic> was lower at the stages of 4 and 5, and <italic>GmPLD&#x003b4;2</italic> was lower at the satges 2 and 5 than those in the wild-type (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The results indicate that <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1</italic> RNAi also interfered with the transcripts of other <italic>PLD</italic> genes, likely due to the high sequence similarity among <italic>PLD</italic> genes.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Expression profiles of <italic>GmPLD</italic> genes in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type developing seeds. KD1<italic>: PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> line 1; KD2: <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> line 2. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 indicate different developing stages of seeds, corresponding to fresh weights: stage 1, 30&#x02013;70&#x000a0;mg; stage 2, 100&#x02013;150&#x000a0;mg; stage 3, 200&#x02013;250&#x000a0;mg; stage 4, 300&#x02013;350&#x000a0;mg; stage 5, 400&#x02013;480&#x000a0;mg. Data are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;S.D. (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). * and **Denote significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, compared with controls on Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test. <bold>a</bold> Appearances of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type Jack (WT) seeds at different developmental stages. <bold>b</bold> Expression profiles of major <italic>PLD</italic>s during seed development. Total RNA was extracted from developing seeds at different developmental stages</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds had elevated levels of ROS-scavenging genes</title><p id="Par13">Most plant tissues under abiotic stress conditions, such as drought, salinity, ozone, high temperature, and flooding, usually generate more reactive oxygen species (ROS), which is often associated with the synthesis of more enzymes involved in ROS-scavenging to reduce the oxidative damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Under high temperature and humidity, wild-type developing seeds displayed increased expression levels of ROS-scavenging related genes, indicating that seeds might be faced with elevated ROS production (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3). The expression of several genes, such as glutathione S-transferases (<italic>GST23</italic>), peroxidase (<italic>POD</italic>), catalase (<italic>CAT1</italic>), superoxide dismutase (<italic>SOD1</italic>), ascorbic acid peroxidase (<italic>APX</italic>), as well as a heat shock protein <italic>STI</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], were highly induced over the time during high temperature and humidity stress (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3). The level of <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1</italic> transcript also increased by ninefold at 6&#x000a0;h after heat treatment, compared with seeds under normal temperature (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3). Most stress-responsive and ROS-scavenging genes, such as <italic>GST23</italic>, <italic>POD</italic>, <italic>CAT1</italic>, <italic>SOD1</italic>, <italic>STI</italic>, and <italic>APX</italic>, in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic> and <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD2</italic> developing seeds displayed higher transcript levels than those in wild-type control under high temperature and humidity conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Weather conditions in Mid-Yangzi River regions and the heat stress-induced the oxidative stress and ROS-scavenging genes in developing seeds. <bold>a</bold> Temperature and humidity changes in Mid-Yangzi River in past 10&#x000a0;years. The data were downloaded from website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tianqi.911cha.com">https://tianqi.911cha.com</ext-link>. <bold>b</bold> Expression of the stress-related genes in wild-type Jack (WT) and <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1 KD</italic> seeds grown in high temperature and humility condition were examined with qRT-PCR. KD1: <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown line 1; KD2: <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown line 2. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 indicate different developing stages of seeds, corresponding to fresh weights, described as above. The values are the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). * and **Denote significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, compared with wild-type Jack (WT) based on Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Increased unsaturated fatty acids of TAG and phospholipids in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds</title><p id="Par14">We examined changes of TAG contents and fatty acid composition of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type soybean lines at different developmental stages. Total fatty acid content steadily increased over the seed filling during maturation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4). In addition, clear differences between <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type seeds in unsaturated fatty acids, 18:1, 18:2, and 18:3, were detected throughout the seed developmental stages. Wild-type soybean oil contains 13% palmitic acid (16:0), 4% stearic acid (18:0), 20% oleic acid (18:1), 55% linoleic acid (18:2), and 8% linolenic acid (18:3) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4). A higher content of unsaturated fatty acids in TAG was observed in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds than those in the wild-type Jack under normal conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4). The differences became bigger between <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD2</italic> and wild-type than those between <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic> and wild-type under stress conditions, suggesting that the degree of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> suppression may be proportional to the content of unsaturated fatty acids. To distinguish whether the difference in unsaturation resulted from fatty acids in TAG or phospholipids, we assayed fatty acid composition in TAG and phospholipids separated by TLC. The total TAG content in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> mutant seeds was higher than that in wild-type seeds at most developmental stages (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4). Correspondingly, the contents of total unsaturated fatty acids (mainly 18:1 and 18:2) in stage 5-seeds of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1 and 2</italic> mutant lines were comparable. Both were about two and tenfold higher than those of wild-type seeds under normal growth conditions and the high temperature and humidity conditions, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4). The total fatty acid content of WT under normal conditions was 1.5-fold higher than that under high temperature and humidity in stage-3 seeds. This result is consistent with a previous observation that high temperature decreased oil content of soybean seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. However, the total fatty acid content in developing <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds was almost unchanged, which could mean that the knockdown of <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1</italic> stabilizes the seed fatty acid contents under high temperature (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Heatmap analyses on fatty acid compositions of total lipids and TAGs from <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type developing seeds. Exact quantification data see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4 for details. The values represented are the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from at least three independent repeats. KD1-h, KD2-h and WT-h: <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown line 1, 2 and wild-type jack, respectively, under high temperature and humidity which used thick lines; KD1-n, KD2-n and WT-n: <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown line 1, 2 and wild-type Jack, respectively, under normal temperature and humidity. 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 indicate different developing stages of seeds, corresponding to fresh weights as described previously. The values are from the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Up-regulation of <italic>FAD</italic>s in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds as compared with wild-type</title><p id="Par15">In the ER, FAD2 synthesizes linoleic acid from oleic acid and FAD3 catalyzes the conversion of linoleic acid into &#x003b1;-linolenic acid on PC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). <italic>FAD2</italic>-<italic>2A</italic> (Glyma.19G147400), <italic>FAD2</italic>-<italic>2B</italic> (Glyma.19G147300), <italic>FAD2</italic>-<italic>2C</italic> (Glyma.15G195200), and <italic>GmFAD2</italic>-<italic>2D</italic> (Glyma.03G144500) were constitutively expressed in developing seeds and vegetative tissues of soybean [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] whereas <italic>FAD2</italic>-<italic>1A</italic> (Glyma.10G278000) and <italic>FAD2</italic>-<italic>1B</italic> (Glyma.20G111000) are specifically expressed in developing seeds, and play an essential role in controlling the oleic acid level in developing soybean seeds (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S5) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The low-linolenic acid trait in soybean requires the combination of up to three different recessive alleles of <italic>FAD3</italic> genes that encode omega-3 fatty acid desaturases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. <italic>GmFAD3</italic> includes <italic>GmFAD3A</italic> (Glyma.14G194300), <italic>GmFAD3B</italic> (Glyma.02G227200), and <italic>GmFAD3C</italic> (Glyma.18G062000).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Expression patterns of <italic>FAD</italic> genes in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type developing seeds. <bold>a</bold> FAD enzymes function in phospholipid desaturation with various PC molecules as preferred substrates. <bold>b</bold> Expression of <italic>FAD</italic> genes in soybean developing seeds of different genetic backgrounds under various growth conditions. FAD2, Microsomal &#x00394;12 desaturase; FAD3, Microsomal &#x003c9;3 desaturase; FAD6, Plastidial &#x00394;12 desaturase. The <italic>X</italic>-axis numbers indicated each development stage. KD1-h, KD2-h and WT-h: <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown line 1 and 2 and wild-type jack, respectively, under high temperature and humidity; KD1-n and KD2-n and WT-n: <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown line 1 and 2 and wild-type Jack, respectively, under normal temperature and humidity. 1&#x02013;5 indicate different developing stages of seeds corresponding to fresh weights as described in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec21" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>&#x0201d;. The values are the mean&#x02009;+&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). * and **Denote significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, compared with wild-type Jack (WT) based on Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par16">Quantitative RT-PCR results showed that the expression of <italic>FAD2</italic>-<italic>1B</italic> was much higher in developing seeds of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> than in wild-type under both normal and stress conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). Microarray data showed that <italic>FAD2</italic>s were highly expressed in seeds during development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. <italic>FAD2</italic>-<italic>1B</italic> and <italic>FAD2</italic>-<italic>1A</italic> were mainly expressed at the late stages of developing seeds, and their transcripts were higher in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> than wild-type under both conditions. The transcript levels of <italic>GmFAD3A</italic>, <italic>GmFAD3B</italic> and <italic>GmFAD3C</italic> were generally high in developing seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S5). Under high temperature, <italic>FAD3B</italic> expression levels increased to the highest level at the stage 4, and then decreased. However, under normal conditions, the <italic>FAD3B</italic> transcript level was higher at all developmental stages compared with that under stressed conditions. Furthermore, the <italic>FAD3B</italic> transcript level was much higher in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic> than wild-type seeds under normal conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). The expression levels of the major <italic>FAD</italic>s in seeds were higher under normal conditions than high temperature conditions, except for <italic>GmFAD2</italic>-<italic>2A</italic> and <italic>GmFAD3C</italic>, whose expression levels were generally low under normal conditions, and increased in response to elevated temperatures. The expression of chloroplast localized <italic>GmFAD6A</italic> was also higher in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KDs</italic> than in wild-type and up-regulated under stress conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Increased contents of PC and PE in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds</title><p id="Par17">The contents of PC and PE between wild-type and both PLD&#x003b1;1KDs lines were comparable under normal growth conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a), but they became different under high temperature and humidity conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). To compare the unsaturation status of phospholipids in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds with wild-type at different developmental stages under stress conditions, we profiled phospholipids at developmental stages 2, 3, and 4 as <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> expression was higher at these stages. The level of most phospholipids did not change substantially over these three stages (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). However, seeds from <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic> and <italic>2</italic> plants had averagely 132% PC and 47% PE higher than those from wild-type in stage-3 seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). The level of PC, particularly with unsaturated fatty acid acyl chains, was significantly higher in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds than wild-type. <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds had higher levels of PCs and PEs with 36:5, 36:6, 36:4, 36:3, 36:2 34:3, 34:2 (total acyl carbons: total acyl double bonds) acyl chains (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). The PA level in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds at all three stages was much lower than that in wild-type, with reduction of more than 81% (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). In addition, total levels of LPC, lysophosphatidylethanolamine (LPE), and lysophosphatidylglycerol (LPG) were lower in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds than in wild-type seeds, with LPC and LPE being decreased by 90%, in stage-3 seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Overall MGDG increased in both <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds compared to wild-type seeds, whereas DGDG content kept unchanged. The difference of PC contents between <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type seeds under high temperature and humidity was larger than those under normal conditions (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Phospholipid profiles in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type developing seeds. <bold>a</bold> Profiles of phospholipids in mature seeds of KD (<italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic>) and wild-type Jack (WT) by ESI-MS/MS. All seeds collected from soybean plants grown under normal conditions. <bold>b</bold> Total lipid contents of major lipids and the molecular species (total acyl chains: double bonds). All plants were grown under high temperature and humidity. All plants were grown under high temperature and humidity. The values are the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;S.D. (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 or 5). WT-2: wild-type Jack at stage 2; KD1-2: knockdown line 1 at stage 2; KD2-2: knockdown line 2 at stage 2; The rest can be explained in the same manner. All * and **denote significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, compared with wild-type Jack (WT) based on Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Lysophospholipid profiles in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type developing seeds. Total content of lysoPG, lysoPC, lysoPE and corresponding molecule species were measured by using ESI-MS/MS. All plants were grown under high temperature and humidity. The values are the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;S.D. (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 or 5). WT-2: wild-type Jack at stage 2; KD1-2: knockdown line 1 at stage 2; KD2-2: knockdown line 2 at stage 2; The rest can be explained in the same manner. All * and **denote significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, compared with wild-type Jack (WT) based on Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig7_HTML" id="MO61"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Decreased PA pools in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds</title><p id="Par18">We further investigated the expression of genes involved in PA biosynthesis- and catabolism in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a). <italic>LPAATs</italic> that produce PA from lysoPA, PA hydrolases (PAHs) that dephosphorylate PA to yield DAG, and PLDs that produce PA from hydrolysis of phospholipids, all contribute to the changes of PA levels. The soybean genome contains multiple genes encoding <italic>LPAATs</italic>, corresponding to Arabidopsis <italic>AtLPAAT</italic> 1&#x02013;5 that are essential enzymes for the de novo PA biosynthesis in both eukaryotic and prokaryotic pathways for glycerolipid biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. LPAAT function in TAG biosynthesis in soybean and Arabidopsis has been implicated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In soybean developing seeds, the major <italic>GmLPAAT</italic> transcripts, including <italic>GmLPAAT2&#x003b1;1</italic>, <italic>GmLPAAT2&#x003b1;2</italic>, accumulated in similar patterns compared with <italic>DGAT</italic>, <italic>PDAT</italic>, or other TAG biosynthesis-related genes, which fluctuated in developing seeds (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>, <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S6) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. These <italic>GmLPAAT</italic> transcripts increased more than 21% in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds compared to wild-type at developmental stage 5 under both conditions. Both <italic>LPAAT2&#x003b1;1</italic> and <italic>LPAAT2&#x003b1;2</italic> genes were down-regulated in wild-type, and in both <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines, the transcript level of <italic>LPAAT2&#x003b1;2</italic> was down-regulated but <italic>LPAAT2&#x003b1;1</italic> remained high in response to high temperature and humidity stress (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>b).<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p>Expression profiles of TAG biosynthesis genes in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type developing seeds. <bold>a</bold> Kennedy pathway for TAG biosynthesis in the ER. <bold>b</bold> Expression of major genes involved in the Kennedy pathway in soybean developing seeds of different genetic backgrounds under various growth conditions. The <italic>X</italic>-axis numbers indicated each development stage. KD1-h, KD2-h and WT-h: PLD&#x003b1;1 knockdown line 1, 2 and wild-type Jack, respectively, under high temperature and humidity which used thick lines; KD1-n, KD2-n and WT-n: PLD&#x003b1;1 knockdown line 1, 2 and wild-type Jack, respectively, under normal temperature and humidity which used thin lines. 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 indicate different developing stages of seeds, corresponding to fresh weights as described previously. The values are the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). * and **Denote significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, compared with wild-type Jack (WT) based on Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig8_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;9</label><caption><p>Differential expression patterns for genes involved in PC&#x02013;DAG conversion in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type developing seeds. <bold>a</bold> Acyl editing in phospholipid and TAG through PC&#x02013;DAG conversion. <bold>b</bold> Differential expression of genes involved in PC&#x02013;DAG conversion in developing seeds of different genetic backgrounds under various growth conditions. The <italic>X</italic>-axis numbers indicated each development stage. KD1-h, KD2-h and WT-h: PLD&#x003b1;1 knockdown line 1, 2 and wild-type Jack, respectively, under high temperature and humidity which used thick lines; KD1-n, KD2-n and WT-n: PLD&#x003b1;1 knockdown line 1, 2 and wild-type Jack, respectively, under normal temperature and humidity which used thin lines. 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 indicate different developing stages of seeds, corresponding to fresh weights as described previously. The values are the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). * and **Denote significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, compared with wild-type Jack based on Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig9_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;10</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic>PLAs</italic> and <italic>LPCATs</italic> involved in acyl editing in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic>KD and wild-type developing seeds. <bold>a</bold> Acyl editing in PC fatty acyl chains through PLA&#x02013;LPCAT cycle. <bold>b</bold> Expression of major <italic>PLA</italic> and <italic>LPCAT</italic> genes involved in developing seeds of different genetic backgrounds under various growth conditions. The <italic>X</italic>-axis numbers indicated each development stage. KD1-h, KD2-h and WT-h: PLD&#x003b1;1 knockdown line 1, 2 and wild-type Jack under high temperature and humidity which used thick lines; KD1-n, KD2-n and WT-n: PLD&#x003b1;1 knockdown line 1, 2 and wild-type Jack under normal temperature and humidity which used thin lines, respectively. 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 indicate different developing stages of seeds, corresponding to fresh weights as described previously. The values are the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). * and **Denote significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, compared with wild-type Jack (WT) based on Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig10_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par19">Three <italic>PAH</italic> genes, homologous to <italic>AtPAH1</italic> and <italic>AtPAH2</italic>, are present in the soybean genome. Two of them, <italic>Glyma.13G134500</italic> (<italic>GmPAH&#x003b2;1</italic>) and <italic>Glyma.10G046400</italic> (<italic>GmPAH&#x003b2;2</italic>), were highly expressed in developing seeds, in a trend coincident with seed oil accumulation (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S7) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The transcript levels for both <italic>GmPAH&#x003b2;1</italic> and <italic>GmPAH&#x003b2;2</italic> in PLD&#x003b1;1KD were one and twofold higher, respectively, than these in wild-type seeds at stages 4 under both conditions and the expression of <italic>GmPAHs</italic> was not affected at all by high temperature except <italic>GmPAH&#x003b2;1</italic> at stage 2 and <italic>GmPAH&#x003b2;2</italic> at stage 3 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>b). The combined effects of suppressed <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic>, and a markedly higher <italic>PAH</italic> expression level contributed to the decreased PA levels, which was confirmed by mature and developing seeds (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Altered transcript levels of <italic>DGATs</italic> and <italic>PDAT</italic>s for TAG biosynthesis in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds</title><p id="Par20">To explore how <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> affected TAG biosynthesis and phospholipid metabolism in soybean seeds, we examined several major genes involved in the Kennedy pathway (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>b). DGAT synthesizes TAG by transferring an acyl group to DAG from newly synthesized or recycled acyl-CoA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a). The DGAT family in the soybean genome has 10 members. Type 1 DGATs, <italic>Glyma.13G106100</italic>, <italic>Glyma.09G065300</italic>, and <italic>Glyma.17G053300</italic>, were highly expressed in seeds. Type 3 DGAT <italic>Glyma.17G041600</italic> was also highly expressed in seeds. Compared with type 1 and type 3 DGATs, type 2 DGAT, such as <italic>Glyma.16G115700</italic> and <italic>Glyma.09G195400</italic>, were expressed at a lower level in seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The transcript level of these genes increased steadily over seed development (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S8) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines have lower transcript levels for several seed-specific <italic>DGAT</italic>s, such as <italic>GmDGAT1A</italic> (Glyma.13G106100), <italic>GmDGAT1C</italic> (Glyma.09G065300) and <italic>GmDGAT3B</italic> (Glyma.17G041600), over all developmental stages under both conditions, indicating that <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines have reduced contributions through <italic>DGAT</italic> pathway towards TAG synthesis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>b). Meanwhile, the expression of <italic>GmDGAT1A</italic> and <italic>GmDGAT3B</italic> was increased whereas the expression of <italic>GmDGAT1C</italic> was suppressed in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines and wild-type under high temperature conditions compared with normal conditions.</p><p id="Par21">PDAT transfers the <italic>sn</italic>-2 acyl group from phosphatidylcholine or phosphatidylethanolamine to DAG for TAG production in plants and yeast (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], and in soybean seeds, DAG from PC is primarily used for TAG biosynthesis. PDAT and DGAT were shown to have overlapping functions in TAG biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The soybean genome contains 6 putative <italic>PDAT</italic> genes, and among them, <italic>Glyma.12G084000</italic>, <italic>Glyma.11G190400</italic>, and <italic>Glyma.13G108100</italic>, as well as <italic>Glyma.07G036400</italic>, were highly expressed in seeds. Transcripts of these <italic>PDATs</italic> increased steadily during seed development except <italic>Glyma.07G036400</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S9) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The transcript level of <italic>PDAT</italic> genes in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds was more than higher than those in wild-type seeds from stages 3 to 5 under both conditions, suggesting that <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds have increased PDAT-mediated, DAG-PC dependent TAG biosynthesis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>b). Meanwhile, high temperature and humidity suppressed the expression of <italic>GmPDAT1B</italic> in both <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type seeds.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Enhanced PC&#x02013;DAG conversion and acyl editing in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean seeds</title><p id="Par22">To test whether the active PC&#x02013;DAG&#x02013;PDAT pathway contributed to more TAG biosynthesis in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> than in wild-type, we compared the transcript levels of relevant genes. For PC synthesis, choline/ethanolamine kinase (CEK) produces phosphocholine that is used by CTP: phosphocholine cytidylyltransferase (CCT) to synthesize CDP- choline (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figures S10, S11). DAG: cholinephosphotransferase (CPT) then transfers choline form CDP-choline to DAG to generate PC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>a). The soybean genome has two CCT genes, <italic>CCT1</italic> (<italic>Glyma.09G051200</italic>) and <italic>CCT2</italic> (<italic>Glyma.15G157500</italic>), and their transcript levels fluctuated during seed development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>b, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S11) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. However, transcripts of <italic>CCT</italic>s in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines were down-regulated by approximately 18% at stage 3 under both conditions. The expression of <italic>GmCCTs</italic> was suppressed in both <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines and wild-type seeds under high temperature and humidity conditions.</p><p id="Par23">DAG-CPT and PDCT form an important PC&#x02013;DAG exchange/conversion cycle to enforce the acyl editing of TAGs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>a). In <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds, <italic>DAG:CPTs</italic> (also called AAPTs), <italic>DAG:CPT1</italic> and 2 (<italic>Glyma.12G081900</italic> and <italic>Glyma.02G128300</italic>, respectively), were up-regulated as compared with those in developing seeds of wild-type under both conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>b, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S12). The soybean genome contains two <italic>PDCT</italic> genes, <italic>GmPDCT1</italic> (<italic>Glyma.07G029800</italic>) and <italic>2</italic> (<italic>Glyma.08G213100</italic>). The two genes were highly expressed in developing soybean seeds (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S13) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The transcript of <italic>GmPDCT2</italic> was up-regulated at early developmental stages and then decreased during late seed stages under both conditions. <italic>GmPDCT1</italic> and <italic>2</italic> were significantly up-regulated at stages 2-3 in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds under both conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>b). The expression of <italic>GmPDCT1</italic> and <italic>GmDAG</italic>-<italic>CPT2</italic> was suppressed at stages 3-5 in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds under high temperature and humidity conditions. Other two genes <italic>GmPDCT2</italic> and <italic>GmDAG</italic>-<italic>CPT1</italic> displayed complicated expression patterns in wild-type and <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds in both environments. These data suggest that the activity of PC and DAG interconversion is increased when <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> was suppressed in developing soybean seeds.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Reduced transcript levels of <italic>PLA</italic>s but increased levels of <italic>LPCAT</italic> in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds</title><p id="Par24">Since pPLA affects TAG biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], we examined the expression of <italic>pPLAs</italic> that were either specifically or highly expressed in the developing soybean seeds. The soybean genome contains a large <italic>pPLA</italic> gene family, and several <italic>pPLA</italic>s were highly expressed in developing seeds, such as <italic>Glyma.08g028800</italic>, <italic>Glyma.11g036900</italic>, and <italic>Glyma.17G145900.</italic> The <italic>pPLA</italic>s, <italic>Glyma.18g251500</italic> and <italic>Glyma.09g243100</italic>, were expressed only in seeds (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S14) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The transcripts of <italic>pPLA</italic>s (<italic>Glyma01G.002400</italic> and <italic>Glyma08G.028800</italic>) in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean seeds were, on average, 44% lower than those in wild-type seeds at stage-4 under both conditions, which was consistent with higher levels of PCs in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean seeds and lower levels of lysophospholipids (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>b). Meanwhile, high temperature and humidity suppressed the expression of <italic>GmPLA2s</italic> in both <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines and WT seeds. The down-regulation of both <italic>PLD</italic> and <italic>PLA</italic> expression may explain the higher level of PCs in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds.</p><p id="Par25">As LPC and LPE content decreased significantly in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> than wild-type seeds by more than tenfold at stage 3, we examined the expression of genes involved in the LPC and PC cycle. LPC acyltransferases (<italic>LPCAT</italic>) catalyzes the synthesis of PC from LPC using a new fatty acyl-CoA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>a). <italic>AtLPCAT1</italic> and 2 in Arabidopsis control the acyl editing process by acting as the main entry of unsaturated FAs into PC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The <italic>lpcat1/lpcat2</italic> mutant showed decreased PUFA in seed TAG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Soybean genome contains two LPCATs, <italic>Glyma.17G131500</italic> (<italic>GmLPCAT1</italic>) and <italic>Glyma.05G049500</italic> (<italic>GmLPCAT2</italic>). Transcript levels of two genes increased to the highest levels at middle stages and then decreased at the later stage of seed development in both <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines under stress conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>b, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S15) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Both <italic>GmLPCAT</italic> transcripts were 17% higher in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds than in wild-type seeds at later stages under stress conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>b). Meanwhile, Both genes were up-regulated in both <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines and wild-type under stress conditions. The down-regulation of <italic>GmPLA</italic>s and up-regulation of <italic>GmLPCATs</italic> in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean seeds could lead to reduced contents of LPC and LPE, as compared with wild-type (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Higher germination rate of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds</title><p id="Par26">To address the effect of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> on soybean seed vigor after harvested from high temperature and humidity conditions, we tested the seed vigor and germination rate of these knockdown lines and wild-type after stored at high temperature and humidity for three months (28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in the dark and ~&#x02009;50% humidity). <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds displayed higher germination rates, than the wild-type seeds under high temperature and humidity conditions. Under stress conditions, the germination rates of wild-type, <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic>2 and <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic> seeds were 80%, 91%, and 95%, respectively, whereas they were 88%, 96%, and 96% under normal conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>a, b). However, the germination rate of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD1</italic> was lower than wild-type at an early stage but then caught up and became higher than wild-type at later stages. We further analyzed hormone levels in those germination seeds at different days after imbibitions. Higher ABA contents in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds than in wild-type seeds were detected, suggesting that <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds had deeper seed dormancy than wild-type seeds and less nutrient consumption in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> than in wild-type seeds during storage. Meanwhile, <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds had initially a lower level of indoleacetic acid (IAA), but later a higher IAA level than that did wild-type seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>c). Similarly, the seeds of two <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines showed difference in jasmonate (JA) and Ile-conjugated JA level from wild-type (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>c). <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> line 1 (KD1) seeds had lower total JAs and a lower germination rate, whereas <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> line 2 had higher total JAs and a higher germination rate than wild-type (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>c). The content of MDA was decreased in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds germinating for 1&#x000a0;day and had no significant difference within 2&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days compared with wild-type seeds. There was also no significant difference in the content of soluble sugar in both <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type germinating seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>d).<fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;11</label><caption><p>Germination rates and hormone levels of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic>- and wild-type-germinating seeds. <bold>a</bold> Germination rates of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type Jack (WT) seeds under normal conditions after maturation under high temperature (30&#x02013;36&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) and humidity (70&#x02013;85%) environments. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30 in one replications). <bold>b</bold> Germination seeds of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type Jack (WT) soybean for 3&#x000a0;days. <bold>c</bold> Hormone levels in germinating seeds of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type Jack (WT). <bold>d</bold> The contents of malonaldehyde and soluble sugars. KD1: <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown line 1; KD2: <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown line 2; WT: wild-type Jack. All data are e mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). * and **Denote significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, compared with wild-type Jack (WT) based on Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig11_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par27">Seed development is a temperature-sensitive process more vulnerable than vegetative tissues to high temperature stress; high temperature and humidity conditions reduce lipid contents in soybean seeds, as compared with normal growth conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. However, <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> attenuated the reduction in lipid contents of soybean developing seeds compared with wild-type under the stress conditions, as well as under normal growth conditions. We showed higher total TAG content in the <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> transgenic lines at most developmental stages, with higher proportion of polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) in TAG and PC as well. The higher levels of PCs are postulated as a consequence of down-regulation of <italic>PLD</italic>s and decreased transcripts of <italic>PLA</italic>s. The enhanced desaturation of PCs in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds is primarily attributable to increased <italic>FAD2</italic> and <italic>FAD3</italic> expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). The up-regulation of <italic>FAD</italic>s might further enhance acyl editing on PC or PE, which triggers an accelerated interconversion of PCs to DAGs in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> to drive metabolic flux toward unsaturated TAG biosynthesis. Up-regulated <italic>DAG:CPT</italic>s and <italic>PDCT</italic>s, as well as down-regulated <italic>CCT</italic> in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds indicate an enhanced metabolic flux or cross-talk between the acyl-editing and Kennedy pathways in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>). The <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown likely affected the responses of developing soybean seeds to high temperature and humidity conditions through modification of the levels of PAs and lysoPLs. These two signaling molecules accumulated to higher levels in developing wild-type seeds upon high temperature and humidity conditions, but significantly reduced in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds than wild-type. Levels of PAs and lysoPLs could be negatively related to seed viability and lipid stability, and lower levels of seed PAs and lysoPLs may have better seed viability and lipid stability in mature <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean seeds.<fig id="Fig12"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;12</label><caption><p>Schematic of the links between TAG and phospholipid metabolism involving <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1. CCT</italic> choline-phosphate cytidylyltransferase, <italic>DAG</italic> diacylglycerol, <italic>DAG-CPT</italic> diacylglycerol cholinephosphotransferase, <italic>DGAT</italic>, acyl-CoA: diacylglycerol acyltransferase, <italic>G3P</italic> glycerol-3-phosphate, <italic>GPAT</italic> glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase, <italic>LPA</italic> 2-lysophosphatidic acid, <italic>LPAAT</italic> 2-lysophosphatidic acid acyltransferase, <italic>LPC</italic> 2-lysophosphatidylcholine, <italic>LPCAT</italic> 2-lysophosphatidylcholine acyltransferase, <italic>PA</italic> phosphatidic acid, <italic>PDAT</italic> phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase, <italic>PDCT</italic> phosphatidylcholine:diacylglycerol cholinephosphotransferase, <italic>PLA2</italic> phospholipase A2, <italic>PAH</italic> phosphatidic acid phosphatase, <italic>PLD</italic> phospholipase D, <italic>PC</italic> phosphatidylcholine, <italic>TAG</italic> triacylglycerol</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_Fig12_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig>
</p><sec id="Sec16"><title><italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> knockdown promoted fatty acid unsaturation in both TAGs and phospholipids</title><p id="Par28">There are increases in the total contents of both TAGs and unsaturation fatty acids in the developing seeds of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> than wild-type cultivar under high temperature and humidity conditions. The desaturation of PCs is primarily attributable to FAD2 and FAD3 in the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. The increased transcripts of <italic>FAD2s</italic> and <italic>FAD3s</italic> in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds explain the increased unsaturated fatty acids in PCs and PEs, and TAG species, together with the decreased levels of PA, LPC, and LPE species in the <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds. The difference in lipid contents between <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type seeds under normal conditions was similar to that reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The high temperature and humidity decreased the contents of total lipids, especially fatty acid contents in seeds compared with these under normal conditions. However, our data showed that the differences in lipid contents between <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type seeds under the stress conditions became much bigger than those under normal conditions. Meanwhile, the high temperature and humidity conditions affected the expression of genes involved in PLs and TAG synthesis pathways, which may eventually result in decreased lipid contents. Consistently, under these stress conditions, developing seeds of <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> displayed higher gene expression levels and total lipid contents than those of wild-type seeds, e.g., <italic>GmFAD2</italic>-<italic>1A</italic> and <italic>GmFAD2</italic>-<italic>2A.</italic> Mature <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds also had better germination rates than did wild-type seeds. Therefore, suppression of <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1</italic> improved the expression of genes involved in PLs and TAG synthesis pathways under both high temperature and humidity stress and normal conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> enhanced the PDAT pathway and DAG-PC conversion toward TAG biosynthesis</title><p id="Par29">It has been proposed that the DAG:CPT-catalyzed reaction provides an acyl editing mechanism for the production of polyunsaturated TAGs containing 18:2 and 18:3 through PCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. The significant increases in unsaturation acyl chains of PCs in developing soybean seeds of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> plants were attributable to the higher expression levels of <italic>FAD</italic>s. Since both PC and DAG play essential roles in acyl editing on glycerolipids, their interconversion is important for TAG synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. The knockdown of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> in the developing soybean seeds affected expression of all genes involved in the acyl editing in soybean developing seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>). The up-regulation of both <italic>PDCT</italic>s and <italic>DAG:CPT</italic>s in consistent with an increased TAG contents in soybean developing seeds, since PCs are the major source of DAGs that further flux into TAGs by the action of PDATs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Since PA&#x02013;DAG&#x02013;PC&#x02013;DAG metabolic pathway primarily takes place in soybean developing seeds, PDCT thus becomes essential in determining the unsaturation of TAG. <italic>PDCT</italic> mutation results in a 40% decrease in polyunsaturated FAs in seed TAG without disrupting overall TAG levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. PDAT&#x02019;s substrate specificity on PC and DAG further enhanced the PC&#x02013;DAG conversion and resulted in higher levels of unsaturated fatty acids in TAGs of developing seeds. The markedly increased PC/PE accumulation coincides with up-regulated <italic>FAD2</italic> and <italic>3</italic>, <italic>PDCT</italic> and <italic>PDAT</italic> genes suggest PLD&#x003b1;1 negatively affects acyl editing and bridges the phospholipid turnover and TAG biosynthesis.</p><p id="Par30">PLA catalyzes PC or PE hydrolysis to generate free fatty acid and lysoPLs, such as LPC or LPE. PLAs and LPCATs can form a PC turnover cycle (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>). The lower transcripts of PLAs in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> are consistent with higher levels of PCs and lower levels of LPC and LPE in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> developing seeds, which is also consistent with previous report in Arabidopsis <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The down-regulation of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> and <italic>PLA</italic> genes may together lower PA, LPC and LPE levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In <italic>pah1pah2</italic> mutant, PC contents dramatically increased and TAG content decreased due to the increased PA contents through up-regulation of <italic>CCT1</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Our results suggest that PLA&#x02013;LPCAT, PLD, and PDCT&#x02013;DAG:CTP play important roles in acyl editing. <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> promotes the PDCT and DAG:CPT-catalyzed conversion between PCs and DAGs, through which extensive acyl desaturation on PCs by FADs is eventually reflected by the increased TAG unsaturation. Thus, the developing <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean seeds have higher levels of di18:2 than these non-transgenic lines.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Effects of high temperature and humidity on soybean seed development</title><p id="Par31">While high temperature and humidity can significantly affect membrane compositions, altering membrane physiological properties and functions, how the stress affects phospholipid and TAG metabolism in developing seeds is largely unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. High temperature stress causes significant increases in ROS-scavenging, lipid desaturating, oxidizing, and acylating genes, and in 18:3-TAG contents in wheat, while fatty acyl chain unsaturation in polar phospholipids decrease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. ROS plays various roles in regulating cell growth, development, and cell survival under stress. Generally, moderate levels of ROS may function as signals to promote plant growth and survival, whereas a large increase of ROS can induce plant cell death. Under physiologic conditions, the balance between generation and elimination of ROS maintains the proper function of redox-sensitive signaling proteins. However, under adversary environments, such as extreme heat, light, and cold conditions, plants produce more ROS or xenobiotics than normal levels, and activate ROS-scavenging enzymes and xenobiotics-detoxification enzyme GST to reduce ROS damage to plants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Possible mechanisms for the improvement of soybean seeds <italic>by knockdown of GmPLD&#x003b1;1</italic></title><p id="Par32"><italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> and its product PA and PLA and its product LysPLs, have been reported in other plants to function in plant stress response to salt and drought stresses, oxidative stresses, and hormones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Our study here indicates that high temperature and humidity environments significantly affect phospholipid and TAG metabolism in developing soybean seeds, and increase the contents of PAs and lysoPLs in wild-type seed, but the contents of PAs and lysoPLs were significantly reduced in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> mutant seeds (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The anti-deterioration effects of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> mutation on developing soybean seeds under high temperature and humidity conditions in our study were similar to the better oil storability and seed viability of these naturally or artificially aged Arabidopsis and soybean <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic>-antisense mutant seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Those results suggest that the lowered PAs and lysoPLs in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> or knockout mutant seeds might be the major causes. The higher PA and lysoPL contents may increase membrane permeability during seed development and storage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The variations in lipid contents and gene expression in two independent <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines may result from the variations of levels of PAs and lysoPLs because of different degrees of <italic>PLD</italic> suppression. It has been observed that different knockdown lines of <italic>AtPLD&#x003b1;1</italic> often showed variations in phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Besides its metabolic function, PLD&#x003b1;1 is also involved in plant responses to salinity, drought, cold, and heat stresses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>). The distinct responses of <italic>ROS</italic>-scavenging genes in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> and wild-type cultivars may also be associated to <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1/PLA</italic> and PA/lysPLs that could be critically involved in soybean adaptive response to high temperature and humidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. We posit that PA and lysoPLs generated by PLDs and PLAs under high temperature and humidity conditions could be the keys for the detrimental effects of high temperature and humidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> substantially decreases stress-induced production of PA and lysoPLs and thereby alleviates the negative impacts by these adverse conditions on developing soybean seeds.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par33">Genetically modified <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean seeds have improved oil content, seed vigor, and resistance against aging and deterioration under high temperature and humility environments. The mechanism behind the phenomena was explored by examination of relevant metabolites and transcripts of lipid metabolic genes in WT and <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean developing seeds grown under both stress and normal conditions. The higher TAG content with higher proportion of unsaturation degree in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> than wild-type at most developmental stages are attributable to the lower expression levels of <italic>PLDs</italic>, <italic>PLA2s</italic>, <italic>CCTs</italic>, and <italic>DGATs</italic> and higher expression levels of <italic>FADs</italic>, <italic>LPCAT</italic>, <italic>PDAT</italic>, <italic>PAH</italic>, <italic>PDCT</italic>, and <italic>DAG:CPT</italic> in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean. Higher levels of ROS-scavenging and xenobiotics-detoxifying genes (<italic>GST</italic>, <italic>SOD</italic>, <italic>CAT</italic>, <italic>POD</italic>, <italic>STI</italic>, and <italic>APX</italic>) in <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> soybean developing seeds and lower ROS level in germinated <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> seeds than those in wild-type seeds may explain their tolerance against high temperature and humility stress in preventing pre-harvest seed deterioration. This study presents a valuable model illustrating the role of <italic>PLD</italic> in TAG synthesis and provides novel insights into the mechanistic details of lipid metabolic pathway changes upon the knockdown of <italic>PLDs</italic> during seed development under stress. Despite of the biotechnological application potential in genetic improvement of soybean production under stress, the field trials may be required to validate the advantages for quality soybean production, especially under frequently occurred heatwaves.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec22"><title>Creation of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> transgenic soybean</title><p id="Par34">The forward and reverse sequences of 1151&#x000a0;bp from the conserved <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1</italic> cDNA in Williams 82 were used for making RNAi constructs, which were different from the forward 820&#x000a0;bp and reverse 1300&#x000a0;bp from conserved <italic>GmPLD&#x003b1;1</italic> sequence derived from cloning partial sequence in Fayette used previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The RNAi cassette was assembled into the <italic>Not</italic>I site of the soybean expression vector pBetaConSoyHyg, flanked on its 5&#x02032; end by the seed-specific promoter for the soybean &#x003b1;&#x02019; subunit of &#x003b2;-conglycinin gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] and on its 3&#x02032; end by the 3&#x02032;UTR of the phaseolin gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. The vector backbone, which was derived from pBluescript SK-(Stratagene), was engineered with a hygromycin B phosphotransferase gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] under control of the potato ubiquitin-3 promoter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>] for selection of transformed soybean embryos. Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1 illustrates the cloning strategy and details of the organization of gene cassettes generated in the vector pBetaConSoyHyg for soybean transformation. The construct was introduced into soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic> cv. Jack) somatic embryos using biolistic transformation as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Embryos were maintained after bombardment in SHaM media [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] with hygromycin selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Mature somatic embryos obtained following hygromycin selection were screened by immunoblotting analysis for PLD&#x003b1;1 levels. Embryos, representing independent transgenic events, that showed reductions in PLD&#x003b1;1 levels, were desiccated and used for regeneration of transgenic plants as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Regenerated plants were advanced to homozygosity (&#x0003e;&#x02009;<italic>T</italic><sub>3</sub> generation) for use in the described studies. One hundred forty-three putative tissues were recovered after selection. Ten transgenic soybean events were recovered and fully grown in the greenhouse. Using enzyme activity, PCR and western blotting, two successfully repressed transgenic soybean events (#1020 and #1048) were selected from ten transgenic events for analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Plant growth conditions and treatments</title><p id="Par35">Wild-type Jack and transgenic soybean <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic> lines were grown in a greenhouse with a normal (26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/18&#x000a0;h&#x000a0;day and 23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/6&#x000a0;h night photoperiod, 45&#x02013;65% humidity) or high temperature and high humidity (36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/18&#x000a0;h&#x000a0;day and 30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/6&#x000a0;h night photoperiod, 70&#x02013;85% humidity) conditions which were controlled by air condition and humidifier machine. The developing seeds were harvested at approximately 50&#x000a0;days after fertilization (DAF). The varieties for transcriptomic analyses at different developmental stages of soybean seeds were Williams 82 and Hokkaido Black 25- and 50-day seeds were collected and put into liquid nitrogen immediately after separating from plants. To test the suppression of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1</italic> in transgenic soybean seeds, qRT-PCR, western blotting with PLD&#x003b1;1 antibody, and PLD&#x003b1;1 activity assays were performed using developing staged 3 seeds of T3 and T5 lines. The presence of the transgene in T5 line seeds was confirmed by PCR. Monitoring soybean PLD proteins in the soybean extract used antibodies against <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> PLD&#x003b1;1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Analysis of seed total fatty acids</title><p id="Par36">Total fatty acids were extracted three times and analyzed with GC using triheptadecanoylglycerol as an internal standard using a method described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Analyses were carried out on an Agilent Technologies (USA) 7890A Network gas chromatograph, equipped with a flame-ionization detector (FID) and a split/splitless injector. Polyethylene glycerol:Agilent 19091&#x000a0;N-133 column (30&#x000a0;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x000a0;mm i.d. 0.25&#x000a0;m film thickness) was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. An HP ChemStation (Hewlett-Packard, Palo Alto, CA, USA) was used for instrument control and data analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Analysis of seed TAGs</title><p id="Par37">Seed TAG and its fatty acid compositions were analyzed as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Briefly, total seed lipids from developing seeds were separated into TAG, DAG, and free fatty acids on a TLC plate, and TAG spots were visualized with iodine vapor and identified by their migration. The spots of TAG were scraped off TLC plates for determination of fatty acid contents and compositions by GC as described above.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Immunoblotting and PLD activity assays</title><p id="Par38">Proteins were extracted from immature or mature soybean seeds with extraction buffer containing 50&#x000a0;mm Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 10&#x000a0;mm KCl, 1&#x000a0;mm EDTA, 0.5&#x000a0;mm&#x000a0;phenyl methylsulfonyl fluoride and 2&#x000a0;mm&#x000a0;DTT at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Proteins were incubated at boiling water bath for 10&#x000a0;min with a SDS-PAGE loading buffer containing 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 50&#x000a0;mm Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 6.8), 10&#x000a0;mm&#x000a0;DTT, 2% SDS, 0.01% bromophenol blue and 10% glycerol. Twenty micrograms of denatured proteins were fractionated by 10% SDS-PAGE and transferred to a membrane. The membrane was blotted with Arabidopsis PLD&#x003b1;1 antibodies as described by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Aliquots of 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of native protein were used for the PLD enzyme assay as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Phospholipid analysis</title><p id="Par39">Phospholipid profiling was performed on soybean developing seeds with ESI-MS/MS as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. In brief, five replicates of developing soybean seed samples were smashed in liquid nitrogen and transferred immediately to 3&#x000a0;mL of 85&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C hot isopropanol containing 0.01% butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) for 15&#x000a0;min. Then, adding 1.5&#x000a0;mL of chloroform and 1.5&#x000a0;mL of methanol for mixing well and extraction on shaker for 30&#x000a0;min, and then 1.8&#x000a0;mL of H<sub>2</sub>O were added to each sample separately. After mixing and centrifugation, lower layer solvent containing lipids was transferred to a new tube. Repeat the extraction with 3&#x000a0;mL of chloroform/methanol (2:1) containing 0.01% BHT for five times for 10&#x000a0;min each time. The combined solvent extracts were washed with 1&#x000a0;mL of 1&#x000a0;M KCl and 1&#x000a0;mL of sterile ddH<sub>2</sub>O, successively, and then concentrated with nitrogen gas. The total extracts were transferred to 2.0&#x000a0;mL vial with Teflon-lined screw cap and dried completely. The methanol solved lipids were detected followed the published protocol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Five duplicates for each genotype or treatments were analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Quantitative reverse transcriptase-PCR (qRT-PCR) for gene expression analysis</title><p id="Par40">qRT-PCR was done as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Briefly, total RNA was isolated from seeds with RNA isolation kit (Bioteke Corporation). The first strand of cDNA was synthesized according to the supplier&#x02019;s instructions (M-MLV First Strand kit, Life Technologies, Invitrogen, USA) and real-time RT-PCR was executed with primers listed as Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1 using the BioRad iQ5 (Bio-Rad, USA) with an SYBR green MIX (Premix system, NEWBIO INDUSTRY). Soybean <italic>ACTIN1</italic> (Glyma.15g034000) was used as the internal positive control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Seed germination assay</title><p id="Par41">After storing seeds for 3&#x000a0;months in high temperature and humidity conditions, seeds of <italic>PLD&#x003b1;1KD</italic>s and wild-type control harvested at the same time in same size were selected for assay. Seeds were sterilized with chloride gas and washed in distilled water three times before germinating in plates containing wet sterile filter papers. Seeds were germinated in an incubator at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in 16&#x000a0;h&#x000a0;day/8&#x000a0;h night. Seed germination was scored when the radical was elongated about 0.5&#x000a0;cm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Analysis of seed hormones</title><p id="Par42">Seed samples collected at different time during germination were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Hormones were measured according to the method described previously, with modifications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Briefly, the liquid nitrogen-frozen samples were lyophilized, and 0.1&#x000a0;g of samples was extracted with 750&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L methanol:ddH<sub>2</sub>O:acetic acid (80:19:1, v/v/v) for three times in the dark and 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The supernatants were combined and dried under stream of nitrogen. Prior to UPLC/ESI-MS/MS analysis, the extracts were suspended in 250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L methanol and sonicated for 10&#x000a0;min, and spun at 12,000&#x000a0;g for 10&#x000a0;min, and the supernatant was transferred into UPLC vials. Chromatographic separation was performed using the Agilent LC-20AD system (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) equipped with AB Sciex QTRAP<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> 5500 detector and a Zorbax&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;300 SB-C18 (4.6&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;150&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m) column (Agilent, Palo Alto, CA, USA), as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Bioinformatics&#x02019; analyses</title><p id="Par43">Soybean proteins involved in lipid metabolism and their expression data were retrieved from Phytozome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz">http://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz</ext-link>). For analyses, these genes were compared with homologues from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and other plant species retrieved from NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/</ext-link>). Phylogeny trees were constructed using the neighbor-joining tree method with MEGA6. The significance level of the neighbor-joining analysis was examined by bootstrap testing with 1000 repeats.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec32"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_MOESM1_ESM.ppt"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Figure S1.</bold> Schematic procedure for construction of soybean GmPLD&#x003b1;1RNAi vector for plant transformation. <bold>Figure S2.</bold> Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>PLD</italic> genes from the soybean genome and their expression patterns. <bold>Figure S3.</bold> Mechanism of plant resistant to stress and gene expression of GmPLD&#x003b1;s and stress-related genes under high temperature and humidity condition in comparison to under normal conditions. <bold>Figure S4.</bold> Analyses of lipids in PLD&#x003b1;1KD and wild-type developing seeds under different growth conditions. <bold>Figure S5.</bold> Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>FAD</italic> genes from the soybean genome and their expression patterns. <bold>Figure S6.</bold> Phylogenic analysis of Acyl-CoA:lysophosphatic acid acyltransferase (<italic>LPAAT</italic>) genes and their expression profiles. <bold>Figure S7.</bold> Phylogenic analysis of phosphatidic acid hydrolase (<italic>PAH</italic>) genes and their expression profiles. <bold>Figure S8.</bold> Phylogenic analysis of acyl-CoA:diacylglycerol acyltransferase (<italic>DGAT</italic>) genes and their expression profiles. <bold>Figure S9.</bold> Phylogenic analysis of phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase (<italic>PDAT</italic>) genes and their expression profiles. <bold>Figure S10.</bold> Phylogenic analysis of choline/ethylamine kinase (<italic>CEK</italic>) genes and their expression profiles. <bold>Figure S11.</bold> Phylogenic analysis of CTP: phosphocholine cytidylyltransferase (<italic>CCT</italic>) genes and the expression profiles. <bold>Figure S12.</bold> Phylogenic analysis of diacylglycerol:cholinephosphotransferase (<italic>DAG-CPT</italic> or <italic>AAAT</italic>) genes and their expression profiles. <bold>Figure S13.</bold> Phylogenic analysis of phosphatidylcholine:diacylglycerol cholinephosphotransferase (<italic>PDCT</italic>) genes and their expression profiles. <bold>Figure S14.</bold> Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>PLA</italic> genes from the soybean genome and their expression patterns. <bold>Figure S15.</bold> Phylogenic analysis of 2-lysophosphatidylcholine acyltransferase (<italic>LPCAT</italic>) genes and their expression profiles.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1340_MOESM2_ESM.doc"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2: Table S1.</bold> The Quantitative RT-PCR primers used in this study. <bold>Table S2.</bold>
<italic>PLD</italic> genes in soybean genome. <bold>Table S3.</bold> Expression pattern in different tissue. <bold>Table S4.</bold> Relative expression of <italic>GmPLD&#x00251;</italic>s in different developing seeds after fertilization. <bold>Data S1.</bold> Protein sequences for phylogenic tree construction.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>JZ planned and designed the research. GZ, SB, GW, YRZ, BC, YLZ performed the experiments and analyzed data. SB, GW, XW did soybean transformat screening. GZ, BC analyzed the data. JZ, GZ, XW wrote and edited the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par44">We thank Dr. Edgar B. Cahoon and Jamie Shipp (Center for Plant Science Innovation, University of Nebraska-Lincoln) for helps in generation of transgenic soybean plants and Dr. Ruth Welti (Kansas lipidomics center, Kansas State University) for parts of lipid analyses and critical reading the manuscript. The authors also thank lab members in Prof. Zhao&#x02019;s lab for all assistances in experiments and data analyses.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par45">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par46">All data supporting my findings can be available and found in the supplementary data; materials can be available for distribution upon request.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par47">The authors agree to the publication of this manuscript in the journal.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par48">No investigations were undertaken using humans/human samples in this study. No experimental animals were used to conduct any of the experiments reported in this manuscript. Our study did not involve endangered or protected species. No specific permits were required from the studies and Professor Jian Zhao should be contacted for future permissions.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par49">This project is support in part&#x000a0;by the Ministry of Science and Technology of China (2016YFD0100504), by Agriculture and Food Research Initiative (AFRI) Award No. [2016-67013-24429/project accession number 1007600] from the USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture, and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31670294).</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par50">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IPCC. Climate Change 2013: the physical science basis. Contribution of working group I to the fifth assessment report of the intergovernmental panel on climate change, Cambridge university press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA; 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate variation explains a third of global crop yield variability</article-title><source>Nat Commun.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>5989</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms6989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25609225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>PVV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of high night-time and high daytime temperature stress on winter wheat</article-title><source>J Agron Crop Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jac.12101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schauberger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Archontoulis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arneth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Balkovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciais</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Deryng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Consistent negative response of US crops to high temperatures in observations and crop models</article-title><source>Nat Commun.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>13931</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms13931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28102202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Welti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wheat leaf lipids during heat stress: I. High day and night temperatures result in major lipid alterations</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ</source><year>2016</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.12649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26436679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GmSBH1, a homeobox transcription factor gene, relates to growth and development and involves in response to high temperature and humidity stress in soybean</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1927</fpage><lpage>1937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-015-1840-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26205508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devaiah</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Welti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancing seed quality and viability by suppressing phospholipase D in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2007</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>950</fpage><lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03103.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17565616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Welti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schapaugh</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Trick</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced seed viability and lipid compositional changes during natural ageing by suppressing phospholipase Dalpha in soybean seed</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2012</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-7652.2011.00650.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21895945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Welti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schapaugh</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Trick</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phospholipid and triacylglycerol profiles modified by PLD suppression in soybean seed</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-7652.2010.00562.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20796246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phospholipase D and phosphatidic acid in plant defence response: from protein-protein and lipid-protein interactions to hormone signalling</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2015</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1721</fpage><lpage>1736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eru540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25680793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transport and transcriptional regulation of oil production in plants</article-title><source>Crit Rev Biotechnol</source><year>2017</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>641</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07388551.2016.1212185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27553510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tawfall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saettele</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of patatin-related phospholipase AIIIdelta altered plant growth and increased seed oil content in camelina</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25557877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incorporation of newly synthesized fatty acids into cytosolic glycerolipids in pea leaves occurs via acyl editing</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>31206</fpage><lpage>31216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M705447200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17728247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Durrett</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of acyl fluxes through multiple pathways of triacylglycerol synthesis in developing soybean embryos</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.137737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19329563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahn</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patatin-related phospholipase pPLAIIIdelta increases seed oil content with long-chain fatty acids in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.216994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23542150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatihi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Snapp</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlsson</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acyl editing and headgroup exchange are the major mechanisms that direct polyunsaturated fatty acid flux into triacylglycerols</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>1530</fpage><lpage>1539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.204438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22932756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazachkov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlsson</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metabolic interactions between the Lands cycle and the Kennedy pathway of glycerolipid synthesis in Arabidopsis developing seeds</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>4652</fpage><lpage>4669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.104604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23150634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The choline/ethanolamine kinase family in Arabidopsis: essential role of CEK4 in phospholipid biosynthesis and embryo development</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1497</fpage><lpage>1511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25966764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Miquel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An enzyme regulating triacylglycerol composition is encoded by the ROD1 gene of Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>18837</fpage><lpage>18842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0908848106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19833868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazachkov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deciphering the roles of Arabidopsis LPCAT and PAH in phosphatidylcholine homeostasis and pathway coordination for chloroplast lipid synthesis</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>965</fpage><lpage>976</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25268378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The phosphatidylcholine diacylglycerol cholinephosphotransferase is required for efficient hydroxy fatty acid accumulation in transgenic Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>1944</fpage><lpage>1954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.192153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22371508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickramarathna</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Siloto</surname><given-names>RMP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mietkiewska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Weselake</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterologous expression of flax phospholipid:diacylglycerol cholinephosphotransferase (PDCT) increases polyunsaturated fatty acid content in yeast and Arabidopsis seeds</article-title><source>BMC Biotechnol</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>63</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12896-015-0156-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26123542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Siloto</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickramarathna</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mietkiewska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Weselake</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a pair of phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferases from developing flax (<italic>Linum usitatissimum</italic> L.) seed catalyzing the selective production of trilinolenin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem.</source><year>2013</year><volume>288</volume><fpage>24173</fpage><lpage>24188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.475699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23824186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maatta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Levels of Arabidopsis thaliana leaf phosphatidic acids, phosphatidylserines, and most trienoate-containing polar lipid molecular species increase during the dark period of the diurnal cycle</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2012.00049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22629276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulatory functions of phospholipase D and phosphatidic acid in plant growth, development, and stress responses</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.068809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16219918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid signaling in plants</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>216</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23818891?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23818891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plant phospholipases D and C and their diverse functions in stress responses</article-title><source>Prog Lipid Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plipres.2016.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26783886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phospholipase Dzeta enhances diacylglycerol flux into triacylglycerol</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.00026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28325849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide association studies dissect the genetic networks underlying agronomical traits in soybean</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>161</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-017-1289-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28838319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Haq</surname><given-names>BU</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soybean LEC2 regulates subsets of genes involved in controlling the biosynthesis and catabolism of seed storage substances and seed development</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1604</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.01604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28979275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative proteomics analysis reveals the mechanism of pre-harvest seed deterioration of soybean under high temperature and humidity stress</article-title><source>J Proteomics.</source><year>2012</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>2109</fpage><lpage>2127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2012.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22270011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An integrated transcriptome atlas of the crop model <italic>Glycine max</italic>, and its use in comparative analyses in plants</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20408999?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20408999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Severin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woody</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolon</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Diers</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNA-Seq Atlas of Glycine max: a guide to the soybean transcriptome</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>160</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20687943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koester</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From climate change to molecular response: redox proteomics of ozone-induced responses in soybean</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2012</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2011.04037.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22272738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of proteins in soybean roots under flooding and drought stresses</article-title><source>J Proteomics.</source><year>2015</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2014.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25464361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noctor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichheld</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ROS-related redox regulation and signaling in plants</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2017.07.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28733165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heppard</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecca</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental and growth temperature regulation of two different microsomal [omega]-6 desaturase genes in soybeans</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.1.311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8587990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Novitzky</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Carol Griffin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oleate desaturase enzymes of soybean: evidence of regulation through differential stability and phosphorylation</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02535.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of a novel microsomal oleate desaturase gene from soybean</article-title><source>J Plant Physiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>1516</fpage><lpage>1526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2006.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17141918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilyeu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Palavalli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleper</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Beuselinck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in soybean microsomal omega-3 fatty acid desaturase genes reduce linolenic acid concentration in soybean seeds</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1830</fpage><lpage>1836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2004.0632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Karpova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilyeu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleper</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silencing of GmFAD3 gene by siRNA leads to low alpha-linolenic acids (18:3) of fad3-mutant phenotype in soybean [<italic>Glycine max</italic> (Merr.)]</article-title><source>Transgenic Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11248-008-9167-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18256901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plastid lysophosphatidyl acyltransferase is essential for embryo development in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>1206</fpage><lpage>1216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.035832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14976237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitous and endoplasmic reticulum-located lysophosphatidyl acyltransferase, LPAT2, is essential for female but not male gametophyte development in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.104.030403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15772283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Manan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two types of soybean diacylglycerol acyltransferases are differentially involved in triacylglycerol biosynthesis and response to environmental stresses and hormones</article-title><source>Sci Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>28541</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep28541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27345221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahlqvist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Banas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandager</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase: an enzyme that catalyzes the acyl-CoA-independent formation of triacylglycerol in yeast and plants</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>6487</fpage><lpage>6492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.120067297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10829075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oelkers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinkelenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdeniz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cromley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Billheimer</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturley</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A lecithin cholesterol acyltransferase-like gene mediates diacylglycerol esterification in yeast</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>15609</fpage><lpage>15612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C000144200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DGAT1 and PDAT1 acyltransferases have overlapping functions in Arabidopsis triacylglycerol biosynthesis and are essential for normal pollen and seed development</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3885</fpage><lpage>3901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.071795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20040537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlueter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasylenko-Sanders</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegfried</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FAD2 Gene family of soybean: insights into the structural and functional divergence of a paleopolyploid genome</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>47</volume><issue>S1</issue><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilyeu</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutant alleles of FAD2-1A and FAD2-1B combine to produce soybeans with the high oleic acid seed oil trait</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>195</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20828382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Clasen</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Demorest</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improved soybean oil quality by targeted mutagenesis of the fatty acid desaturase 2 gene family</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24851712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cholinephosphotransferase and diacylglycerol acyltransferase (substrate specificities at a key branch point in seed lipid metabolism)</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.3.923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12226231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compartmentation of triacylglycerol accumulation in plants</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>2288</fpage><lpage>2294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.R111.290072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22090025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant phospholipases</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.52.1.211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11337397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craddock</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurup</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eastmond</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphatidic acid phosphohydrolase regulates phosphatidylcholine biosynthesis in Arabidopsis by Phosphatidic acid-mediated activation of CTP:phosphocholine cytidylyltransferase activity</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1251</fpage><lpage>1264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25862304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Welti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of phospholipase Dalpha3 on Arabidopsis response to hyperosmotic stress and glucose</article-title><source>Plant Signal Behav.</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1099</fpage><lpage>1100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.3.12.7003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19704505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beachy</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name><surname>Horsch</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraley</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accumulation and assembly of soybean beta-conglycinin in seeds of transformed petunia plants</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1985</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>3047</fpage><lpage>3053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1985.tb04044.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16453646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuler</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Godette</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenger</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Beachy</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Slightom</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The glycosylated seed storage proteins of Glycine max and <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>. Structural homologies of genes and proteins</article-title><source>J Bio Chem.</source><year>1986</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>9228</fpage><lpage>9238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3013879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gritz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasmid-encoded hygromycin B resistance: the sequence of hygromycin B phosphotransferase gene and its expression in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1983</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1119(83)90223-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6319235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garbarino</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Belknap</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of a ubiquitin-ribosomal protein gene (ubi3) from potato and expression of its promoter in transgenic plants</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00040579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8111011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finer</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transformation of soybean via particle bombardment of embryogenic suspension culture tissue</article-title><source>Vitro Cell Dev Biol Plant.</source><year>1991</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02632213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahoon</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrott</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards normalization of soybean somatic embryo maturation</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-005-0950-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15856235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of multiple soybean phytonutrients by near-infrared reflectance spectroscopy</article-title><source>Anal Bioanal Chem</source><year>2017</year><volume>409</volume><fpage>3515</fpage><lpage>3525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00216-017-0288-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28424855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis phospholipase Dalpha1 interacts with the heterotrimeric G-protein alpha-subunit through a motif analogous to the DRY motif in G-protein-coupled receptors</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>1794</fpage><lpage>1800</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M309529200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14594812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Biesiada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Profiling membrane lipids in plant stress responses: role of phospholipase D&#x003b1; in freezing-induced lipid changes in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>31994</fpage><lpage>32002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M205375200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12077151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic engineering of proanthocyanidin production by repressing the isoflavone pathways and redirecting anthocyanidin precursor flux in legume</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2016</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1604</fpage><lpage>1618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26806316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedito</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diverse functions of multidrug and toxin extrusion (MATE) transporters in citric acid efflux and metal homeostasis in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2017</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>