<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5938817</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.00585</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Homoeologous Chromosomes From Two <italic>Hordeum</italic> Species Can Recognize and Associate During Meiosis in Wheat in the Presence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> Locus</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Calder&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>Mar&#x000ed;a C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/214296/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>Mar&#x000ed;a-Dolores</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/126995/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>Pilar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/104183/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Plant Breeding Department, Institute for Sustainable Agriculture, Agencia Estatal Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas (CSIC)</institution>, <addr-line>C&#x000f3;rdoba</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>John Innes Centre, Norwich Research Park</institution>, <addr-line>Norwich</addr-line>, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: M&#x000f3;nica Pradillo, Complutense University of Madrid, Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Eric Jenczewski, INRA Centre Versailles-Grignon, France; Pierre Sourdille, INRA Centre Auvergne Rh&#x000f4;ne Alpes, France</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Pilar Prieto <email>pilar.prieto@ias.csic.es</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Cell Biology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>585</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Calder&#x000f3;n, Rey, Mart&#x000ed;n and Prieto.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Calder&#x000f3;n, Rey, Mart&#x000ed;n and Prieto</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Understanding the system of a basic eukaryotic cellular mechanism like meiosis is of fundamental importance in plant biology. Moreover, it is also of great strategic interest in plant breeding since unzipping the mechanism of chromosome specificity/pairing during meiosis will allow its manipulation to introduce genetic variability from related species into a crop. The success of meiosis in a polyploid like wheat strongly depends on regular pairing of homologous (identical) chromosomes and recombination, processes mainly controlled by the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus. This means that pairing and recombination of related chromosomes rarely occur in the presence of this locus, making difficult wheat breeding trough the incorporation of genetic variability from related species. In this work, we show that wild and cultivated barley chromosomes associate in the wheat background even in the presence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus. We have developed double monosomic wheat lines carrying two chromosomes from two barley species for the same and different homoeology chromosome group, respectively. Genetic <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization revealed that homoeologous <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes recognize each other and pair during early meiosis in wheat. However, crossing over does not occur at any time and they remained always as univalents during meiosis metaphase I. Our results suggest that the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus does not prevent chromosome recognition and pairing but crossing over between homoeologous. The role of subtelomeres in chromosome recognition is also discussed.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>wheat</kwd><kwd>barley</kwd><kwd>homoeologous pairing</kwd><kwd>introgressions</kwd><kwd>meiosis</kwd><kwd>chromosome recognition</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="75"/><page-count count="15"/><word-count count="8697"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>More than two-thirds of global cropland features annual grain crops, which represent roughly 70% of humanity's food energy needs and typically grown in monoculture. Annual grain production, at its current scale, is fundamentally unsustainable. Thus, the growing human population demands greater crops, more productive and better adapted to specific agro-climatic conditions (Godfray et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Plant breeders are playing a major role in worldwide efforts to understand gene functions and interactions with the aim of increasing quality and productivity of major crops. Wide-crossing in plant breeding is an important tool and sometimes the results are the starting point for new crops (Omara, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">1953</xref>). For example, wide-crossing has been carried out in the Triticeae tribe, which includes wheat, to develop new plant species such as &#x000d7; <italic>Triticosecale</italic>, obtained after crossing wheat and rye, or &#x000d7; <italic>Tritordeum</italic>, an amphyploid between the wild barley <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> Roem. et Schult. and wheat (Omara, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">1953</xref>; Mart&#x000ed;n and Sanchez-Monge Laguna, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">1982</xref>). Breeders have also used related species as genetic donors for widening the genetic basis of wheat to get for example wheat cultivars better adapted to specific agro-climatic conditions, improving the quality or carrying resistance to diseases (Lukaszewski, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Liu et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Calder&#x000f3;n et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Rey et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>). In fact, there are many wild species carrying interesting traits that would be useful to be exploited in wheat breeding programmes, but unfortunately, hybridization between wheat and a wild related species produces only a low level of chromosome pairing and recombination. So understanding wheat genetics and genome organization is essential for plant breeding purposes.</p><p>Bread wheat is an hexaploid, which possesses three sets of related chromosomes because of doubling of chromosomes following sexual hybridization between closely related species. However, chromosomes associate regularly in pairs in wheat during meiosis, the cellular process to produce gametes in sexually reproducing organisms. Thus, at meiosis each chromosome only recognize and associate with its homologous and not with the related (homoeologous) chromosomes, which have a similar gene content and order but differ in repetitive DNA sequences. Several pairing homologous (<italic>Ph</italic>) genes control chromosome associations in wheat, although the major effect is due to the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus (Sears, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>). The efficiency of chromosome associations during meiosis have a big influence on the fertility of wheat plants, being crucial for success in breeding, but has a negative effect preventing pairing and recombination between wheat chromosomes and those from related species. Therefore, it seems reasonable to go deeper into the knowledge of the biology of chromosome associations during meiosis in wheat, which will be valuable for wheat breeding.</p><p>Chromosome dynamics during meiosis have been extensively studied in a polyploidy such as hexaploid wheat (Moore, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Corredor et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Colas et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Naranjo and Corredor, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). It is now well established that both interactions during recombination at the DNA level and assembly of a meiosis-specific proteinaceous structure known as the synaptonemal complex (SC) play roles in stabilizing associations between homologous chromosomes. However, how homologs became colocalized and how initial recognition is accomplished to establish chromosome associations remains poorly understood. When a chromosome recognizes its homolog (and not another chromosome) in wheat, a localized conformational change in adjacent chromatin is triggered in both partners. This process facilitates recognition and association of homologous versus homoeologous chromosomes and is affected by the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus (Prieto et al., <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Greer et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Thus, <italic>Ph1</italic> stabilizes wheat during meiosis by both, promoting homolog synapsis during early meiosis and preventing homoeologous recombination later in meiosis (Mart&#x000ed;n et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The effect on synapsis occurs during the telomere bouquet <italic>Ph1</italic> stage, when promotes more efficient homologous synapsis, thereby reducing the chance of homoeologous synapsis (Mart&#x000ed;n et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The effect on CO formation occurs later in meiosis, when <italic>Ph1</italic> prevents MLH1 sites (Double Holliday Junctions marked to become COs) on synapsed homoeologues from becoming COs. In addition, it has been also described that the level of a ZIP4 paralog included within the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus alters the number of CO between homoeologous chromosomes (Rey et al., <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).</p><p>Efforts focused on centromeres and telomeres behavior during meiosis have been also made (Martinez-Perez et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Naranjo et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Telomeres, which are highly conserved structures among plants, including wheat (Simpson et al., <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Ganal et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Schwarzacher and Heslop-Harrison, <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>), play an important role on initial chromosome associations at the onset of meiosis. In this stage, the association of telomeres in a bouquet facilitates the search and recognition of homologous chromosomes by bringing chromosomes closer (Corredor and Naranjo, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Koszul et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Moore and Shaw, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) and its formation is affected by the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus (Richards et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Subtelomeres, which are the telomere associated sequences (TAS), are highly polymorphic and extraordinarily dynamic sequences (Eichler and Sankoff, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The complex and variable nature of subtelomeres has made difficult to assess the possible functions(s) of these regions so far, but studies on <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and <italic>Hordeum</italic> subtelomeres might suggest a possible role on chromosome specificity between homolog chromosomes at the onset of meiosis (Kotani et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Heacock et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Calder&#x000f3;n et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In fact, subtelomeres in <italic>Hordeum</italic> showed high variability not only from different chromosomes but also among chromosome arms within the same chromosome (Schubert et al., <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Prieto et al., <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2004b</xref>). Thus, the copy number of the subtelomeric HvT01 sequence was variable among chromosomes in both <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic>. Since chromosome associations are initiated at the distal regions of the chromosomes and homologous chromosomes are zipping up from those to the centromeres (Prieto et al., <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2004a</xref>; Corredor et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), it seems reasonable to go deeper into the role of the subtelomeric regions on homolog chromosome associations, rather than focusing on features that are common to all chromosomes like telomeres.</p><p>The addition of a pair of &#x0201c;alien&#x0201d; chromosomes to the full genome complement of a crop species is commonly used as a first step for accessing genetic variation from the secondary gene pool, but addition lines are also relevant for understanding meiotic pairing behavior and chromosome structure (Friebe et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Lukaszewski, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Sets of both cultivated (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) and wild (<italic>H. chilense</italic>) barley addition lines in a hexaploid wheat background were developed (Islam et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">1978</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>; Miller et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">1982</xref>) and have potential in plant meiosis studies. Certainly, it allows tracking one specific pair of chromosomes or chromosome segments within the wheat background using genomic <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (GISH) and study chromosome rearrangements and associations exclusively in a pair of homologs (Naranjo et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Rey et al., <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2015b</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we have developed double monosomic addition lines of wild and cultivated barley in wheat for the same and for different homoeology group to go deeper into the knowledge of chromosome associations during meiosis. These double monosomic addition lines enabled to distinguish chromosomes from two different barley species in the wheat background, observe conformational changes during meiosis and analyze whether subtelomeres might play a role on chromosome recognition/pairing at early meiosis in the absence of homologs. Results showed that homoeologous chromosomes can recognize each other to associate correctly in pairs, even in the presence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus, although crossing over does not occur as they remained as univalents during metaphase I.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Plant material</title><p>Crosses between <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> addition lines in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> cv. Chinese Spring; AABBDD + pair of H<sup>ch</sup>H<sup>ch</sup> and AABBDD + pair of H<sup>v</sup>H<sup>v</sup>, respectively) for the same and for different homoeology group were made to obtain double monosomic wheat lines carrying one <italic>H. chilense</italic> and one <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosome for the same and for different homoeology group. <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> addition lines were kindly provided by Steve Reader, JIC, Norwich, UK. The presence of each <italic>Hordeum</italic> sp. chromosome in parental and F1 wheat lines used in this work was confirmed by both PCR assays previously described (Liu et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Hagras et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) and <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization.</p><p>Seeds obtained from genetic crosses were germinated on wet filter paper in the dark for 5 days at 4&#x000b0;C, followed by a period of 24h at 25&#x000b0;C. Plants were then growth in the greenhouse at 26&#x000b0;C during the day and 18&#x000b0;C during the night (16 h photoperiod).</p></sec><sec><title>Fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization</title><p>Fluorescence genomic <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (GISH) was used to study chromosome associations between <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes in the wheat background as described previously (Prieto et al., <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2004b</xref>). Root tips were collected from germinating seeds and were pre-treated for 4 h in a 0.05% colchicine solution at 25&#x000b0;C and fixed in 100% ethanol-acetic acid, 3:1 (v/v), for at least a week at room temperature. Spikes in meiosis were collected from mature plants and preserved in 100% ethanol-acetic acid, 3:1 (v/v) until were used to characterize chromosome associations. Chromosome spreads were prepared from both root tips cells and pollen mother cells (PMCs) at meiosis. Root tips and anthers were macerated in a drop of 45% glacial acetic acid on ethanol-cleaned slides, squashed under a cover slip and dipped in liquid nitrogen in order to fix the plant material on the slide. The cover slip was removed and the slides were air-dried and stored at 4&#x000b0;C until used.</p><p>Both total genomic <italic>H. vulgare</italic> and <italic>H. chilense</italic> DNA were labeled by nick translation with biotin-11-(Boehringer Mannheim Biochemicals, Germany) and digoxigenin-11-dUTP (Roche Applied Science, Indianapolis, IN, USA), respectively, and used as probes. Both probes were mixed to a final concentration of 5 ng/&#x003bc;l in the hybridization mixture. The hybridization mixture consisted of 50% formamide, 2 &#x000d7; SCC, 5 ng of biotin-labeled or digoxigenin-labeled probe, 10% dextran sulfate, 0.14 &#x003bc;g of yeast tRNA, 0.1 &#x003bc;g of sonicated salmon sperm DNA and 0.005 &#x003bc;g of glycogen. Biotin-labeled <italic>H. vulgare</italic> DNA and digoxigenin-labeled <italic>H. chilense</italic> DNA were detected with a streptavidin- Cy3 conjugate (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) and antidigoxigenin-FITC (Roche Diagnostics, Meylan, France), respectively. Chromosomes were counterstained with DAPI (4&#x02032;, 6-diamidino-2-phenylindole) and mounted in Vectashield (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA).</p><p>Chromosome spreads from somatic cells and anthers of the F1 wheat lines were reprobed with the barley subtelomeric tandem repeat HvT01, which was obtained by amplification by the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) from genomic DNA from the barley cv. Betzes using primers made according to the published sequence (Belostotsky and Ananiev, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>). PCR conditions were previously described by Prieto et al. (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2004b</xref>). The PCR product corresponding to this barley satellite HvT01 probe was labeled with digoxigenin-11-dUTP, (Roche Applied Science, Indianapolis, IN, USA) by nick translation and detected with antidigoxigenin-FITC (Roche Diagnostics, Meylan, France). Meiosis metaphase samples were also reprobed to label centromeres using the RT sequence included in the barley centromeric BAC7 (Hudakova et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>), amplified by PCR following the same conditions as the amplification of the CCS1 centromeric repeat (Arag&#x000f3;n-Alcaide et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>), labeled with biotin-11-(Boehringer Mannheim Biochemicals, Germany) and detected with the streptavidin- Cy3 conjugate (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Fluorescence microscopy and image processing</title><p>Hybridization signals were visualized using a Nikon Eclipse 80i epifluorescence microscope. Images were captured with a Nikon CCD camera using the Nikon 3.0 software (Nikon Instruments Europe BV, Amstelveen, The Netherlands) and processed with Photoshop 11.0.2 software (Adobe Systems Inc., San Jose, California, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analyses were performed using STATISTIX 10.0 software (Analytical Software, Tallahassee, FL, USA). Anaphase I combinations were evaluated by an analysis of variance (ANOVA) as a completely randomized design. This analysis included a tangent transformation in the anaphase I combination where only one pole of the meiocytes showed <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> signals. Tetrad combinations were analyzed by the Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test (nonparametric one-way analysis of variance).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Development of double monosomic <italic>H. vulgare-H</italic>. chilense addition lines in wheat</title><p>Crosses between disomic <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> addition lines in bread wheat carrying chromosomes 7H<sup>ch</sup> and 7H<sup>v</sup>, respectively, were made to obtain double monosomic barley additions in wheat carrying homoeologous <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosome 7. Similarly, genetic crosses between disomic <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> addition lines in bread wheat for chromosomes 7H<sup>ch</sup> and 5H<sup>v</sup>, respectively, were made to obtain double monosomic wheat lines carrying non-homoeologous chromosomes 7H<sup>ch</sup> and 5H<sup>v</sup>. Finally, to corroborate observations on chromosome associations in a different homoeology group, we also developed genetic crosses between disomic <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> addition lines in bread wheat for chromosomes 5H<sup>ch</sup> and 5H<sup>v</sup>, respectively, to obtain double monosomic barley additions in wheat lines carrying homoeologous <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes for group 5. The F<sub>1</sub> hybrid progeny from each genetic cross was analyzed by GISH to ensure that they retained the expected both <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). All the plants from all the genetic crosses carried both barley chromosomes. In addition, fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) was also performed in these wheat lines using the barley subtelomeric HvT01 repeat as a probe to label polymorphisms between the subtelomeric regions from the <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes added to the wheat background (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Chromosome 7H<sup>v</sup> had two strong signals for the barley subtelomeric HvT01 sequence on both chromosome arms meanwhile there was only a weaker signal on the short arm of chromosome 7H<sup>ch</sup>. Both 5H<sup>ch</sup> and 5H<sup>v</sup> chromosomes had a signal on the short arm for the HvT01 probe, which was stronger in the case of 5H<sup>v</sup> chromosome, and only a weak signal on the subtelomeric region of the long arm of chromosome 5H<sup>v</sup> was detected, which sometimes cannot be clearly seen and depended on the FISH experiment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). No HvT01 subtelomeric signals were detected on the wheat chromosomes. The F1 progeny from each genetic cross was also growth until meiosis with the aim of studying the meiotic behavior of both <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization in PMCs in the wheat background.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> double monosomic addition lines in wheat and physical location of the HvT01 subtelomeric repeat on barley chromosomes. <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> (green) and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> (red) chromosomes were detected in GISH experiments in somatic chromosome spreads. In addition, the HvT01 subtelomeric sequence from barley was also detected (green). Total genomic DNA was counterstained with DAPI (blue). <bold>(a)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line, including a diagram showing the HvT01subtelomeric signals in all barley chromosome arms, except in 7H<sup>ch</sup>L arm. <bold>(b)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line, including a diagram showing the subtelomeric barley sequence in all barley chromosome arms except in 7H<sup>ch</sup>L arm. <bold>(c)</bold> Double monosomic 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line, including a diagram showing the subtelomeric barley sequence in all barley chromosome arms, except in 5H<sup>ch</sup>L arm. Bar represents 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Homoeologous wild and cultivated barley chromosomes can fully associate in pairs in wheat in the presence of the Ph1 locus</title><p>Chromosome pairing was analyzed during early meiosis by GISH in F<sub>1</sub> plants carrying one copy of <italic>H. chilense</italic> and one copy of <italic>H. vulgare</italic> homoeologous chromosomes (7H<sup>ch</sup> and 7H<sup>v</sup>) and it was compared to those carrying non-homoeologous <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes (7H<sup>ch</sup> and 5H<sup>v</sup>, respectively). Experiments were developed in around a 100 cells of each genomic combination in prophase I of meiosis. Both wild and cultivated barley chromosomes were visualized simultaneously in the wheat background (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). In both cases, <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes were in proximity in the nucleus in early prophase (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a,c</xref>). As meiosis progressed, GISH experiments showed homoeologous <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes always fully-associated in pairs along the whole chromosome (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>). In contrast, non-homoeologous <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes 7H<sup>ch</sup> and 5H<sup>v</sup> were not observed associated at this meiotic stage at any time, remaining always un-associated (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2d</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Behavior of homoeologous and non-homoeologous barley chromosomes during early meiosis in wheat. <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> chromosomes are visualized in green and <italic>H. vulgare chromosomes</italic> are visualized in red. <bold>(a)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line showing both barley chromosomes un-associated at early pachytene. <bold>(b)</bold> Homoeologous barley chromosomes are fully associated at late pachytene in the double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line. <bold>(c)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line showing both barley chromosomes un-associated at early pachytene. <bold>(d)</bold> Non-homoeologous 7H<sup>ch</sup> and 5H<sup>v</sup> chromosomes remained un-associated at late pachytene. <bold>(e)</bold> Double monosomic 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line showing homoeologous wild and cultivated barley chromosomes half-paired at early pachytene. <bold>(f)</bold> Double monosomic 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line showing both homoeologous <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes fully associated. Bar represents 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-g0002"/></fig><p>GISH experiments were also carried out in cells in prophase I of meiosis in F<sub>1</sub> plants carrying homoeologous chromosomes from <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> for another homoeology group (group 5), with the aim of confirming the observations on chromosome associations between homoeologous chromosomes 7H<sup>ch</sup> and 7H<sup>v</sup> in the wheat background. Results showed that homoeologous <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes 5H<sup>ch</sup> and 5H<sup>v</sup> did also associate in pairs during early meiosis in the wheat background, even in the presence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2e,f</xref>), suggesting that chromosome pairing between homoeologous chromosomes from two different <italic>Hordeum</italic> species is not hampered by the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus. In addition, results suggested that homoeologous barley chromosomes shared enough similar DNA sequences to recognize each other, a conformational chromatin change is observed in both homoeologues and chromosomes are finally associated completely in pairs.</p></sec><sec><title>Subtelomeres might hamper chromosome associations between non-homologous hordeum chromosomes in the wheat background</title><p>We have described that in the absence of homologous chromosomes, wild and cultivated barley homoeologous chromosomes can still recognize each other and associate completely in pairs during early meiosis. In addition, we have observed that, in these cases, initial chromosome recognition occurred by the chromosome ends where none or little copy number of the subtelomeric HvT01 repeat were detected, i.e., the long arm of homoeologous chromosomes 5H<sup>ch</sup> and 5H<sup>v</sup> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Thus, homoeologous <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes did recognize and associate in pairs by these chromosome ends, which made chromosome recognition less restrictive and allowed homoeologous to recognize and associate in pairs. These observations were similar in the cells detected at the same stage from the double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line in wheat (data not shown). Moreover, the observations were consistent in all the cells detected at the initiation of pairing (26 and 18 cells from the double monosomic 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> and 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition lines in wheat, respectively). Once homoeologous chromosomes had associated by these chromosome ends, a conformational change was observed along both homoeologous <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes and pairing progressed along both chromosomes allowing a complete chromosome association between them (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Detection of the subtelomeric HvT01 sequence in the wild and cultivated barley chromosomes in the 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> double monosomic addition line. DNA was counterstained with DAPI (blue). <bold>(a)</bold> GISH of both <italic>H. chilense</italic> (green) and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> (red) homoeologous chromosomes initiating pairing during early pachytene. <bold>(b)</bold> Detection of the subtelomeric HvT01 probe (green) on the same cell. <bold>(c)</bold> Merge image showing the subtelomeric HvT01 signal (overlay in white) on the terminal region of the unpaired homoeologous wild and cultivated barley chromosome arms (arrowed). Bar represents 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-g0003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Crossing over does not occur between wild and cultivated barley chromosomes in wheat although they previously associated in early meiosis</title><p>Once we observed full chromosome associations between homoeologous <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes during early meiosis in the wheat background, we also analyzed chromosome behavior of both wild and cultivated barley chromosomes during metaphase I of meiosis in PMCs from double monosomic <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> additions in wheat lines, both for the same and different homoeologous chromosomes. Meiosis metaphase I was also checked in the disomic <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> addition lines in wheat used as parental lines for the genetic crosses developed in this work, to obtain the double <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> double monosomic addition lines. Chromosome stability of the parental lines was confirmed as the homologous barley chromosomes carried in the <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> disomic addition lines were always observed associated in pairs, indicating that crossing over occurred between homologous barley chromosomes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Similarly, wheat chromosomes associated correctly in bivalents at meiosis metaphase I and orientated by centromeres properly in double monosomic <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> additions in wheat lines, both for the same and different homoeologous chromosomes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). In contrast, <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes remained always un-associated in all the cells analyzed for the three different genetic combinations analyzed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>), despite the fact that homoeologous <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes (7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> and 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup>, respectively) did completely associate in pairs in early meiosis. These observations suggested that, although wild and cultivated barley homoeologous chromosomes can fully associate during pachytene, crossing over did not occur later between these chromosomes. Consequently, <italic>Hordeum</italic> homoeologous chromosomes were never observed associated by chiasmata during metaphase I and always remained as univalent (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>), suggesting other requirements for crossing over rather than full previous chromosome associations or similarities in the DNA sequence.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosome behavior during metaphase I in parental <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> disosomic addition lines in wheat. <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> (green) and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> (red) chromosomes were observed always associated in pairs in all the cells in metaphase I in each <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> disomic addition line. DNA was counterstained with DAPI (blue). <bold>(a)</bold>
<italic>H. chilense</italic> chromosome 7H<sup>ch</sup> disomic addition line. <bold>(b)</bold>
<italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosome 7H<sup>v</sup> disomic addition line. <bold>(c)</bold>
<italic>H. chilense</italic> chromosome 5H<sup>ch</sup> disomic addition line. <bold>(d)</bold>
<italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosome 5H<sup>v</sup> disomic addition line. Bar represents 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-g0004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosome behavior in double monosomic barley addition lines in wheat during metaphase I. <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> (green) and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> (red) chromosomes remained unassociated in all the cases. DNA was counterstained with DAPI (blue). Centromeres (red) were labeled with RT sequence to show the correct orientation of wheat chromosomes during metaphase I. Subtelomeres on barley chromosomes were labeled in green. <bold>(a)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line. <bold>(b)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line. <bold>(c)</bold> Double monosomic 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line. Bar represents 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-g0005"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Chromosome segregation does not depend on previous chromosome associations during early meiosis</title><p>Each PMC analyzed at the MI stage was characterized by the presence of two barley univalents in double monosomic <italic>H. chilense-H. vulgare</italic> addition lines. Around 300 cells were observed in meiosis anaphase I. GISH analysis showed that both wild and cultivated barley univalents segregated simultaneously with wheat bivalents at stage anaphase I (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). All the different possible situations for chromosome segregation of the unpaired <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes were identified (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a&#x02013;e</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>): (i) both barley chromosome were detected in both nuclei; (ii) only <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosome was detected in both nuclei; (iii) only <italic>H. chilense</italic> chromosome was detected in both nuclei; (iv) each barley chromosome was detected in each daughter nucleus; and (v) both barley chromosomes were detected in the same anaphase/telophase pole. These different situations for chromosome segregation of both barley chromosomes were found in all the genetic combinations (7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup>, 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup>, and 7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> double monosomic addition lines) in the wheat background, although the ratio between them varied depending on the genetic stock (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Nevertheless, no significant differences were found for <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosome segregation between the different genetic combinations (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), despite the fact that the most frequent observation for the segregation of the wild and cultivated barley chromosomes was different in 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line compared to 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup>, and 7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition lines (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Moreover, no significant differences were found on the behavior of the <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes within the same F1 line. These results suggest that chromosome segregation in double <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> monosomic addition lines in wheat occurred randomly, regardless the barley chromosomes added to the wheat background and whether or not chromosome associations took place previously in early meiosis.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Behavior of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes in double monosomic barley addition lines in wheat during anaphase I of meiosis. Examples of barley chromosome segregation after metaphase I. <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> were visualized in green and red, respectively. DNA was counterstained with DAPI (blue). <bold>(a)</bold> Double monosomic 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line, <bold>(b)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line, <bold>(c)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line; <bold>(d)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line. <bold>(e)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line. <bold>(f)</bold> Both 7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> barley chromosomes remained delayed. <bold>(g)</bold> Both 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> barley chromosomes remained delayed and a misdivision of chromosome 7H<sup>v</sup> was also observed. One or both barley micronuclei were positioned in the equatorial region on telophase I in <bold>(h)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line, <bold>(i)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line, and <bold>(j)</bold> Double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition line. The subtelomeric HvT01 probe was used in GISH experiments performed in cells in telophase I from the double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition line to visualize <bold>(k)</bold> 5H<sup>v</sup> chromosome misdivision or <bold>(l)</bold> 5H<sup>v</sup> chromosome segregation. Bar represents 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-g0006"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Total number of PMCs scored at anaphase I showing the different combinations observed for both <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes added to the wheat background. The most frequent observation per line and the total number of meiocytes examined are shown in bold. <bold>(B)</bold> Quantification of meiocytes (%) for each observation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>(A)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Wheat lines</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Number of PMCs scored in Anaphase I</bold></td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0001.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0002.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0003.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0004.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0005.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7H<sup>ch</sup> 7H<sup>v</sup> addition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>49</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>24</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>35</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>291</bold></td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>(B)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0006.jpg"/></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Chromosomes delay was usually observed in double monosomic <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> addition lines in late anaphase I/telophase I (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6f,g</xref>), and the presence of chromatin across the equator during phragmoplast formation either from <italic>H. chilense, H. vulgare</italic> or both species was also observed (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6h&#x02013;j</xref>). Missegregation or chromosome breaks that occurred in anaphase I in the double monosomic <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> addition lines cannot be distinguished from sister chromatids segregation unless using, among others, the HvT01 subtelomeric probe (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6k,l</xref>).</p><p>Depending on chromosome segregation of both wild and cultivated barley univalents during meiosis I, the number of different genetic combinations in the PMC increased during MII, resulting in a wide range of meiotic phenotypes observed (nineteen different cases; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The most frequent <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosome combination observed for each genetic combination during telophase II was different depending on whether <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes were included in the same or in different homoeology group (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), but no significant differences were found. Results suggested that both sister chromatids separation and misdivision did occur randomly independently of the barley chromosome combination.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Number of meiocytes showing the different combinations for both <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes added to the wheat background. The most frequent observation per line and the total number of PMCs examined are shown in bold. <bold>(B)</bold> Quatification of meiocytes (%) for each observation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="21" rowspan="1"><bold>(A)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Wheat lines</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="20" rowspan="1"><bold>Number of PMCs scored in tetrads</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0007.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0008.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0009.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0010.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0011.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0012.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0013.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0014.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0015.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0016.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0017.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0018.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0019.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0020.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0021.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0022.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0023.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0024.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0025.jpg"/></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> addition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> addition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>91</bold></td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="21" rowspan="1"><bold>(B)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="20" rowspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-i0026.jpg"/></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Behavior of <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes in double monosomic <italic>Hordeum</italic> addition lines in wheat after the second meiosis division. Examples of the most frequent observations for both <italic>H. chilense</italic> (green) and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> (red) chromosomes are shown. DNA was counterstained with DAPI (blue). <bold>(a)</bold>
<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> and <italic>H. chilense</italic> chromatin detected in four and two PMCs, respectively, in the double monosomic 7H<sup>ch</sup>7H<sup>v</sup> wheat line. <bold>(b)</bold>
<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> and <italic>H. chilense</italic> chromatin detected in four and in two PMCs, respectively, in the double monosomic 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> wheat line. <bold>(c)</bold> Four <italic>H. chilense</italic> signals and two <italic>H. vulgare</italic> signals were observed in the double monosomic 5H<sup>ch</sup>5H<sup>v</sup> wheat line at the same frequency as reported in <bold>b</bold>. <bold>(d)</bold> Wild and cultivated barley signals are present in the same nucleus and only one each in another two different nucleus. Bar represents 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00585-g0007"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Little is known about how chromosomes recognize each other to correctly associate in pairs at early meiosis and recombine. This is a key question for plant breeders to transfer genetic variability from related species into a crop like wheat. The lack of recombination between cultivated wheat and alien chromosomes limits the transfer of novel traits from relatives to wheat because <italic>Ph1</italic> suppresses homoeologous recombination between wheat and related species (Riley and Chapman, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">1958</xref>; Sears, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>). Different meiosis studies on chromosome pairing have been developed using wheat lines carrying an addition of one pair of homologous chromosomes or chromosome segments from one related species into wheat (Mikhailova et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Maestra et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Prieto et al., <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2004a</xref>) or hybrids between wheat and relatives (Moln&#x000e1;r-L&#x000e1;ng et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Rey et al., <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In this work, we have developed wheat lines carrying double monosomic chromosome additions for wild and cultivated barley for the same and for different homoeology group, respectively, which allowed us to track simultaneously by GISH a couple of extra homoeologous and non-homoeologous chromosomes from two different <italic>Hordeum</italic> species during early meiosis. These double monosomic addition lines can contribute to go deeper into the knowledge of how chromosomes recognize and associate in pairs in the wheat background in the presence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus. In addition, most of the works carrying alien chromosomes in the wheat background are focused in meiosis metaphase I or later stages (Moln&#x000e1;r-L&#x000e1;ng et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Silkova et al., <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The analysis of chromosome pairing focused only in metaphase I can result in an underestimation of homoeologous associations that might occur earlier in meiosis, as chromosomes might remain mostly as univalents due to the lack of homoeologous recombination. Few works analyzed the behavior of an extra pair of chromosomes at early stages of meiosis (Arag&#x000f3;n-Alcaide et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Prieto et al., <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2004a</xref>; Valenzuela et al., <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>, <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Koo et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Homologous barley chromosomes have been previously observed associated during early meiosis and metaphase I in disomic addition lines in wheat (Arag&#x000f3;n-Alcaide et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Calder&#x000f3;n et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In this study we have reported by GISH analysis that homoeologous wild and cultivated barley chromosomes can also fully associate in pairs in the wheat background during early meiosis and that such chromosome pairing occurred even in the presence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus, although homoeologous barley chromosomes did not cross over and were always observed as univalent in metaphase I. The role of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus was recently narrowed down preventing recombination between related chromosomes in interspecific hybrids (Moore, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Mart&#x000ed;n et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Our results clearly showed that the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus does not hamper homoeologous chromosome associations but crossing over. Nevertheless, homoeologous recombination between related <italic>Aegilops geniculata</italic> and <italic>Ae. searsii</italic> has been detected in the wheat background in the presence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus due to the presence of chromosome 5 Mg of <italic>Ae. geniculata</italic>, which harbors a homoeologous recombination promoter factor (Koo et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Recombination frequencies between <italic>H. vulgare</italic> and <italic>H. bulbosum</italic> homoeologues have been previously detected but are lower than association frequencies (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>), probably because of non-chiasmate associations (Orellana, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>). Homologous pairing has been also described in the absence of synapsis and meiotic recombination in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (Dernburg et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). Our results showed that homoeologous <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes associated in pairs in wheat in the absence of crossing over and that the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus does not prevent such chromosome recognition and association between homoeologues. It is also worthy to mention that, although <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> are phylogenetically quite distant, even included in two different sections among the <italic>Hordeum</italic> genus (Blattner, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), both species share a high degree of similarities at the chromosomal level, as it has been reported between them and other species within this genus (Hern&#x000e1;ndez et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Aliyeva-Schnorr et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Thus, other elements such as cohesins or the DNA sequence itself might play a major role on chromosome recognition and pairing at the onset of meiosis in a polyploidy like wheat.</p><p>So far, it is unclear whether initial recognition is mediated through protein-protein interactions, DNA base-pairing, or other chromosomal features. For example, a noncoding RNA (meiRNA-L) is responsible for the recombination-independent pairing of homologous loci in <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> (Ding et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Other chromosomal features different from DNA/DNA recombinational interactions or RNA-mediated pairing have been proposed to be involved in the homologous recognition such as the pattern of cohesins distribution in the axial elements of unmatched meiotic chromosomes in mice and <italic>S. pombe</italic> (Ishiguro et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Ding et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Subtelomeres have been also reported as crucial to promote chromosome recognition and pairing between homologous chromosomes (Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Garc&#x000ed;a et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Calder&#x000f3;n et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In our study, variability for the HvT01 subtelomeric sequence was found between <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> chromosomes 5 and 7, particularly for the long arm of both chromosomes. We observed that although homoeologous chromosomes can potentially associate by the telomeres, subtelomeric DNA blocks might hamper homoeologous chromosome to correctly associate in pairs and thus, in the absence of homologs, chromosome recognition and association between homoeologues can occurred by the chromosome end where the subtelomeric repeats are shorter or absent. However, as meiosis progressed, the pairing signal initiated at these chromosome ends can be propagated along the whole chromosome, so that the homoeologues became fully associated by late pachytene. Thus, our results might suggest that subtelomeres can play a key role in the specificity of chromosome recognition, restricting chromosome recognition to true homologs and therefore hampering homoeologous chromosomes to recognize each other and associate. The implication was that DNA sequence(s) within the subtelomeric region must be important for the process of initial homolog recognition and pairing, although further studies are required to reveal how subtelomeres take part in such important meiosis processes.</p><p>The peculiarities of univalent behavior in meiosis have been extensively studied in wheat aneuploids, particularly for the relation between the means of a chromosome segregation and its inclusion into a microspore (Sears, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">1952</xref>; Marais and Marais, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Friebe et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Lukaszewski, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The knowledge about univalent behavior in meiosis is necessary for the directed development of wheat lines carrying alien introgressions since univalent are subjected of incorrect division and segregation. Thus, abnormities in meiosis result in various modifications and/or in the loss of a transferred chromosome (Silkova et al., <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Univalents in meiosis have a tendency to misdivide (break) across their centromeres producing telocentric. This process has been deeply described in wheat (Sears, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">1952</xref>; Steinitz-Sears, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">1966</xref>; Friebe et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), and used to generate different cytogenetic stocks (Sears and Sears, <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">1978</xref>; Lukaszewski, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). The most common alien introgression in wheat, chromosome translocations, is the result of centric misdivision and fusion of misdivision products. Translocations between <italic>H. chilense</italic> and <italic>H. vulgare</italic> have been detected previously when the genomes of these species are in the same background (Prieto et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Our results overview the univalent behavior of two homoeologous and non-homoeologous barley chromosomes in the wheat background. We observed that chromosome misdivisions and sister chromatids segregated randomly at anaphase I similarly to previous works (Friebe et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), and independently of whether or not related chromosomes associate in pairs in early meiosis.</p><p>In summary, homoeologous wild and cultivated barley chromosomes were observed fully associated in pairs in early meiosis in the presence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> although crossing over did not occur at any time, as both chromosomes were always visualized as univalents during metaphase I. Whether or not homoeologous <italic>Hordeum</italic> chromosomes can crossover in the absence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> locus remains to be elucidated. In addition, the role of the terminal chromosome regions in chromosome recognition and paring and the proteins interacting with these chromosomes ends will be key questions to shed light in future works.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Human and animal rights and informed consent</title><p>This article does not contain any studies with human participants or animals.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Authors contributions</title><p>All authors contributed to this manuscript. MC and PP designed the research and performed the experiments. MC, MR, AM, and PP analyzed, discussed the results. PP and MC wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research was supported by grants AGL2015-64833R from Spanish Ministerio de Econom&#x000ed;a y Competitividad (MINECO) and ERC-StG- 243118 from the FP7 and The European Regional Development Fund (FEDER) from the European Union. Authors deeply appreciate the comments from the independent reviewers during the revision of the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aliyeva-Schnorr</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houben</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Collinearity of homoeologous group 3 chromosomes in the genus <italic>Hordeum</italic> and <italic>Secale cereale</italic> as revealed by 3H-derived FISH analysis</article-title>. <source>Chromosome Res.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>242</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10577-016-9518-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26883649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26883649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arag&#x000f3;n-Alcaide</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzacher</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reader</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A cereal centromeric sequence</article-title>. <source>Chromosoma</source>
<volume>105</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02524643</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8939818?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8939818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arag&#x000f3;n-Alcaide</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reader</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beven</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Association of homologous chromosomes during floral development</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>905</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>908</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9382806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9382806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belostotsky</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ananiev</surname><given-names>E. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Characterization of relic DNA from barley genome</article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet</source>. <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>374</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>380</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00210075</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24220972?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24220972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blattner</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Progress in phylogenetic analysis and a new infrageneric classification of the barley genus <italic>Hordeum</italic> (Poaceae: Triticeae)</article-title>. <source>Breed. Sci.</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>480</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1270/jsbbs.59.471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calder&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Development of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> introgression lines in durum wheat: a tool for breeders and complex trait analysis</article-title>. <source>Plant Breed.</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>738</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0523.2012.02010.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calder&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M.-D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The subtelomeric region is important for chromosome recognition and pairing during meiosis</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>6488</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep06488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25270583</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colas</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanous</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spielmeyer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mago</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Effective chromosome pairing requires chromatin remodeling at the onset of meiosis</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>105</volume>, <fpage>6075</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6080</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0801521105</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18417451?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corredor</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukaszewski</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Terminal regions of wheat chromosomes select their pairing partners in meiosis</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>177</volume>, <fpage>699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>706</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.107.078121</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17720899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corredor</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Effect of colchicine and telocentric chromosome conformation on centromere and telomere dynamics at meiotic prophase I in wheat-rye additions</article-title>. <source>Chromosome Res.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10577-006-1117-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17308890?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17308890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dernburg</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulder</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barstead</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dresser</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villeneuve</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Meiotic recombination in <italic>C. elegans</italic> initiates by a conserved mechanism and is dispensable for homologous chromosome synapsis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>398</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81481-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9708740?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9708740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>D. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamasa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagahama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haraguchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiraoka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Meiotic cohesin-based chromosome structure is essential for homologous chromosome pairing in <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic></article-title>. <source>Chromosoma</source>
<volume>125</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>214</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00412-015-0551-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26511279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26511279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>D. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamasa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haraguchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Meiosis-specific noncoding RNA mediates robust pairing of homologous chromosomes in meiosis</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>336</volume>, <fpage>732</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>736</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1219518</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22582262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22582262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eichler</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankoff</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Structural dynamics of eukaryotic chromosome evolution</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>301</volume>, <fpage>793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>797</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1086132</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12907789?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12907789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friebe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linc</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Robertsonian translocations in wheat arise by centric misdivision of univalents at anaphase I and rejoining of broken centromeres during interkinesis of meiosis II</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet. Genome Res</source>. <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000082412</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15753589?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganal</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapitan</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Macrostructure of the tomato telomeres</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.3.1.87</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1668615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1668615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crute</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nisbett</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The future of the global food system</article-title>. <source>Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</source>. <volume>365</volume>, <fpage>2769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2777</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2010.0180</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20713383?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20713383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puertas</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The high variability of subtelomeric heterochromatin and connections between nonhomologous chromosomes, suggest frequent ectopic recombination in rye meiocytes</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet. Genome Res</source>. <volume>115</volume>, <fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000095240</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17065801?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17065801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pendle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colas</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A. M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The Ph1 locus suppresses Cdk2-type activity during premeiosis and meiosis in wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.094771</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22274628?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22274628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagras</surname><given-names>A. A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masahiro</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsujimoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Genomic differentiation of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> from <italic>H. vulgare</italic> as revealed by repetitive and EST sequences</article-title>. <source>Genes Genet. Syst.</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1266/ggs.80.147</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16172528?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16172528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heacock</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spangler</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riha</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puizina</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shippen</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Molecular analysis of telomere fusions in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>: multiple pathways for chromosome end-joining</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2313</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600236</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15141167?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorado</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A core genetic map of <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> and comparisons with maps of barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) and wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet</source>. <volume>102</volume>, <fpage>1259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1264</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220000514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hudakova</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michalek</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Presting</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>ten Hoopen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jasencakova</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Sequence organization of barley centromeres</article-title>. <source>Nucleid Acids Res</source>. <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>5029</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5035</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/29.24.5029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11812833?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11812833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishiguro</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiyama-Nakamura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A new meiosis-specific cohesin complex implicated in the cohesin code for homologous pairing</article-title>. <source>EMBO Rep.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>275</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/embor.2011.2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21274006?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21274006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>A. K. M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>D. H. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Production and characterization of wheat-barley addition lines,</article-title> in <source>Proceedings 5th International Wheat Genetics Symposium</source> (<publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>), <fpage>365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>371</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>A. K. M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>D. H. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of euplasmic wheat-barley chromosome addition lines</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hdy.1981.24</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friebe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Homoeologous recombination in the presence of Ph1 gene in wheat</article-title>. <source>Chromosoma</source>
<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>540</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00412-016-0622-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27909815?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27909815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koszul</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prentiss</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleckner</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kameoka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Meiotic chromosomes move by linkage to dynamic actin cables with transduction of force through the nuclear envelope</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>1188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.04.050</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18585353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18585353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kotani</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosouchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuruoka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Structural Analysis and Complete Physical Map of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> Chromosome 5 Including Centromeric and Telomeric Regions</article-title>. <source>DNA Res.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>386</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/6.6.381</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10691131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10691131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Molecular cytogenetic identification of a wheat-<italic>Thinopyron intermedium</italic> (Host) Barkworth &#x00026; DR Dewey partial amphiploid resistant to powdery mildew</article-title>. <source>J. Integr. Plant. Biol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>726</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>733</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2005.00051.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Biyashev</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saghai Maroof</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Development of simple sequence repeat DNA markers and their integration into a barley linkage map</article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source>
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>869</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>876</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00224088</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24162420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24162420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukaszewski</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Reconstruction in wheat of complete chromosome-1B and chromosome-1R from the 1RS.1BL translocation of Kavkaz origin</article-title>. <source>Genome</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>824</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g93-109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18470029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukaszewski</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Further manipulation by centric misdivision of the 1RS.1BL translocation in wheat</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>261</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1002916323085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukaszewski</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Manipulation of the 1RS.1BL translocation in wheat by induced homoeologous recombination</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2000.401216x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukaszewski</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Behavior of centromeres in univalents and centric misdivision in wheat</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet. Genome Res</source>. <volume>129</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000314108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20551608?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maestra</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Chromosome arrangement and behaviour of two rye homologous telosomes at the onset of meiosis in disomic wheat-5RL addition lines with and without the Ph1 locus</article-title>. <source>Chromosome Res</source>. <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>655</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>667</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1021564327226</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12575794?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12575794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>The derivation of compensating translocations involving homoeologous group-3 chromosomes of wheat and rye</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>
<volume>79</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00023578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Dual effect of the wheat <italic>Ph1</italic> locus on chromosome synapsis and crossover</article-title>. <source>Chromosoma</source>
<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>680</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00412-017-0630-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28365783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28365783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reader</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Licensing MLH1 sites for crossover during meiosis</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>4580</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms5580</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25098240?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25098240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Monge Laguna</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Cytology and morphology of the amphiploid <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> x <italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> conv. durum</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>267</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00028329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Perez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aragon-Alcaide</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Chromosomes form into seven groups in hexaploid and tetraploid wheat as a prelude to meiosis</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01853.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12974808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12974808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Perez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Polyploidy induces centromere association</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>148</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.148.2.233</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10648555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10648555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Perez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The <italic>Ph1</italic> locus is needed to ensure specific somatic and meiotic centromere association</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>411</volume>, <fpage>204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35075597</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11346798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11346798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mikhailova</surname><given-names>E. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyting</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The effect of the wheat Ph1 locus on chromatin organization and meiotic chromosome pairing analysed by genome painting</article-title>. <source>Chromosoma</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>350</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004120050316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9880767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reader</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>The addition of Hordeum chilense chromosomes to wheat,</article-title> in <source>Paper Presented at the Proceedings of the International Symposium Eucarpia on Induced Variability in Plant Breeding</source>. (<publisher-loc>Pudoc, Wageningen</publisher-loc>), <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moln&#x000e1;r-L&#x000e1;ng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linc</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Logojan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Production and meiotic pairing behaviour of new hybrids of winter wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) x winter barley(<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Genome</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1045</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1054</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g00-079</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11195337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11195337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moln&#x000e1;r-L&#x000e1;ng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linc</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szak&#x000e1;cs</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Wheat&#x02013;barley hybridization: the last 40 years</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>
<volume>195</volume>, <fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>329</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-013-1009-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Meiosis in allopolyploids - the importance of &#x02018;Teflon&#x02019; chromosomes</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source>. <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>463</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9525(02)02730-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12175806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12175806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The control of recombination in wheat by Ph1 and its use in breeding,</article-title> in <source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name>), <fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Improving the chances of finding the right partner</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev</source>. <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gde.2009.02.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19327980?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19327980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corredor</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Nuclear architecture and chromosome dynamics in the search of the pairing partner in meiosis in plants</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet. Genome Res</source>. <volume>120</volume>, <fpage>320</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>330</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000121081</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18504361?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18504361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maestra</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corredor</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The search of the homologous partner at early meiosis in wheat</article-title>. <source>Chromosome Res.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15791408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Chiasma frequency is region specific and chromosome conformation dependent in a rye chromosome added to wheat</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet. Genome Res.</source>
<volume>129</volume>, <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000314029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20551607?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omara</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1953</year>). <article-title>The cytogenetics of Triticale</article-title>. <source>Bot. Rev.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>605</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02861827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orellana</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Most of the homoeologous pairing at metaphase-i in wheat-rye hybrids is not chiasmatic</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>917</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>931</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17246307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004b</year>). <article-title>Chromosomal distribution of telomeric and telomeric-associated sequences in <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization</article-title>. <source>Hereditas</source>
<volume>141</volume>, <fpage>122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>127</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1601-5223.2004.01825.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15660972?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15660972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reader</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Control of conformation changes associated with homologue recognition during meiosis</article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>510</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-005-2040-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15895201?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15895201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballesteros</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Identification of intergenomic translocations involving Wheat, <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> and <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> chromosomes by FISH</article-title>. <source>Hereditas</source>
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1601-5223.2001.t01-1-00171.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12152330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12152330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004a</year>). <article-title>Homologue recognition during meiosis is associated with a change in chromatin conformation</article-title>. <source>Nature Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>906</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>908</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb1168</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15340450?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15340450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calder&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015b</year>). <article-title>The use of the <italic>ph1b</italic> mutant to induce recombination between the chromosomes of wheat and barley</article-title>. <source>Front. Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00160</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25852713?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25852713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calder&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacar&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al&#x000f3;s</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015a</year>). <article-title>Novel bread wheat lines enriched in carotenoids carrying <italic>Hordeum chilense</italic> chromosome arms in the ph1b background</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0134598</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134598</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26241856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26241856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swarbreck</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uauy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Exploiting the ZIP4 homologue within the wheat <italic>Ph1</italic> locus has identified two lines exhibiting homoeologous crossover in wheat-wild relative hybrids</article-title>. <source>Mol. Breed.</source>
<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-017-0700-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28781573?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28781573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Quantitative dynamics of telomere bouquet formation</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e1002812</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002812</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23236272?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23236272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>). <article-title>Genetic control of the cytologically diploid behaviour of hexaploid wheat</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>182</volume>, <fpage>713</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>715</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/182713a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>An efficient screening for terminal deletions and translocations of barley chromosomes added to common wheat</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>495</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1998.00125.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarzacher</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heslop-Harrison</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title><italic>In situ</italic> hybridization to plant telomeres using synthetic oligomers</article-title>. <source>Genome</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>323</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g91-052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1952</year>). <article-title>Misdivision of univalents in common wheat</article-title>. <source>Chromosoma</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>550</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14945063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14945063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>Genetic control of chromosome pairing in wheat</article-title>. <source>Ann. Rev. Genet</source>. <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ge.10.120176.000335</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 797311?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">797311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>L. M. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>The telocentric chromosomes of common wheat,</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of 5th International Wheat Genetics Symposium</source> (<publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>), <fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>407</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silkova</surname><given-names>O. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabanenko</surname><given-names>Y. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loginova</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The effect of wheat-rye substitution on chromosome elimination: an analysis of univalents' behavior in wheat meiosis with dimonosomy and tetramonosomy</article-title>. <source>Russ. J. Genet.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1134/S102279541402015X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25438548?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25438548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noel Ellis</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Identification of translocations in pea by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization with chromosome-specific probes</article-title>. <source>Genome</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>749</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g90-112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinitz-Sears</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>). <article-title>Somatic instability of telocentric chromosomes in wheat and the nature of the centromere</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>248</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17248316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17248316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Identifying crossover-rich regions and their effect on meiotic homologous interactions by partitioning chromosome arms of wheat and rye</article-title>. <source>Chromosome Res</source>. <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>445</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10577-013-9372-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23843032?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23843032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Dynamics of rye chromosome 1R regions with high and low crossover frequency in homology search and synapsis development</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e36385</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036385</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22558456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22558456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Direct measurement of recombination frequency in interspecific hybrids between <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> and <italic>H. bulbosum</italic> using genomic <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.hdy.6885710</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10504428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10504428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>