<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Psychol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Psychol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Psychol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Psychology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-1078</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6057114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2018.01200</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Psychosocial and Sociocultural Factors Influencing Antenatal Anxiety and Depression in Non-precarious Migrant Women</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharapova</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/545153/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goguikian Ratcliff</surname><given-names>Betty</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Faculty of Psychology and Educational Sciences, University of Geneva</institution>, <addr-line>Geneva</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Drozdstoy Stoyanov Stoyanov, Plovdiv Medical University, Bulgaria</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Massimiliano Aragona, Societ&#x000e0; Italiana di Medicina Migratoria, Italy; Liang Gong, Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Anna Sharapova, <email>anna.sharapova@unige.ch</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Psychopathology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1200</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Sharapova and Goguikian Ratcliff.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sharapova and Goguikian Ratcliff</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The aims of this paper are (1) to assess the role of sociodemographic and psychosocial risk factors on antenatal anxiety (AA) and antenatal depression (AD) in first-generation migrant women in Geneva, as compared to a control group of native Swiss women, and (2) to examine the role of acculturation and other sociocultural factors in the development of antenatal distress in migrant women. A sample of 43 migrant and 41 Swiss pregnant women were recruited during the third trimester of pregnancy. AA was assessed by using the State Trait Anxiety Inventory, and AD by using the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale. Acculturation was assessed as a bidimensional process comprising <italic>attachment to the heritage culture</italic> and <italic>adaptation to the local Swiss culture</italic>, using the Vancouver Index of Acculturation. AA in migrant women was mainly predicted by psychosocial factors, namely socioeconomic status, marital support, family presence in Geneva and parity, while AD was predicted by one dimension of acculturation, i.e., attachment to the heritage culture. Our study can inform perinatal health care professionals about some specific risk factors for antenatal distress in migrant women in order to increase systematic screening procedures.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>depression</kwd><kwd>anxiety</kwd><kwd>pregnancy</kwd><kwd>migrant</kwd><kwd>acculturation</kwd><kwd>culture</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="69"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Transition to motherhood constitutes a profound existential crisis in a woman&#x02019;s life and may lead to increased vulnerability to mental health problems (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Heron et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Nanzer, 2009</xref>). Antenatal depression (AD) is recognized as a major public health issue (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Austin, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2009</xref>), with about 12&#x02013;20% of pregnant women presenting depressive symptoms (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Marcus et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Rich-Edwards et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Leigh and Milgrom, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Brittain et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>Solid evidence has shown that AD can lead to adverse obstetrical and neonatal outcomes (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Marcus et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Brittain et al., 2015</xref>). It may impact fetal development directly (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Field et al., 2003</xref>) and later affect the quality of the mother-infant relationship, leading to unforeseen difficulties in the child&#x02019;s cognitive and emotional development (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Foss et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Goodman et al., 2011</xref>). In addition, AD represents a major risk factor for postpartum depression, with about 50% of antenatally depressed women presenting elevated depressive scores in the postpartum period (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Heron et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Robertson et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Austin et al., 2007</xref>). This continuity between antenatal and postpartum depression stresses the importance of early detection and treatment of AD in order to reduce psychological morbidity during pregnancy and after birth (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Leigh and Milgrom, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Lefkovics et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Risk factors for AD overlap with those for postpartum depression, namely, past history of psychopathology, poor marital and social support, stressful life events, low self-esteem, and unwanted pregnancy (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Robertson et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Biaggi et al., 2016</xref>). Some specific risk factors have been identified for AD, however, such as unemployment, low socioeconomic status, young age, domestic violence, and physical health problems during pregnancy (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Robertson et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Rich-Edwards et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Leigh and Milgrom, 2008</xref>).</p><p>Increasing evidence suggests that comorbid antenatal anxiety (AA) may be a significant feature of AD (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Heron et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Teixeira et al., 2009</xref>). Anxiety is also known to occur as an independent condition during pregnancy but it has been less studied than depression (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Matthey et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Dunkel Schetter and Tanner, 2012</xref>). In fact, studies show that many women suffer from new onset or aggravation of their anxiety symptoms during pregnancy (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Ross and McLean, 2006</xref>). Different authors evaluated the prevalence of AA as high as 21&#x02013;50% (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Heron et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Faisal-Cury and Rossi Menezes, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2007</xref>). This high prevalence might be due to pregnant women&#x02019;s increased vulnerability to stress (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Biaggi et al., 2016</xref>). In addition, pregnant women, especially primiparas, report pregnancy-specific anxiety, such as worries about coping with delivery, pain of childbirth, parenting concerns, bodily changes, and a safe outcome for the infant (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">&#x000d6;hmann et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Faisal-Cury and Rossi Menezes, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Lobel et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Koleva et al., 2011</xref>). AA has important negative consequences: it not only represents an independent risk factor for the occurrence of postpartum depression (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Heron et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Austin et al., 2007</xref>), but it has also been associated to negative obstetrical and neonatal outcomes, such as small gestational age, low birth weight, slow fetal growth and development (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">DiPietro et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Dole et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Orr et al., 2007</xref>), and behavior/emotional problems in the child (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Connor et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Foss et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Ronald et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, assessment of both anxiety and depression appears to be a clear clinical need during pregnancy, with the objective of early identification and treatment (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Matthey et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Austin, 2004</xref>).</p><sec><title>AA and AD in Migrant Women</title><p>Migrant women are at higher risk than native women for developing AD, with the prevalence of the disorder ranging from 25 to 42% (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Lara et al., 2009</xref>). They also seem to be at higher risk for AA but research on the subject is lacking. This high prevalence might be due to various environmental and contextual stressors associated with migration. The risk for AA and AD increases in migrant women who have been exposed to pre- or post-migratory traumatic events (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Foss et al., 2004</xref>) and in those who have a precarious or no legal status and who thus face housing or financial difficulties (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Bollini et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Gagnon et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015b</xref>). The lack of local language proficiency has been identified as another risk factor for AA and AD, as it may lead to social isolation and a feeling of discomfort and incompetence (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz et al., 2004</xref>). Last but not least, it has been shown that the lack of marital and social support, in particular the lack of the mother (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015a</xref>), was related to high levels of antenatal distress (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bina, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Bollini et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Most studies on antenatal distress in migrant women focus on disadvantaged populations, such as women from low-income background (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015b</xref>). Little is known about the transition to motherhood in non-precarious migrant women. The few existing studies have shown that migrant women in general, even those living in non-precarious socioeconomic conditions and speaking the local language, are at particularly high risk of developing depression and/or anxiety during the perinatal period (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed et al., 2008</xref>). This suggests that the migration experience is associated with a set of sociocultural factors influencing the psychological well-being of migrant mothers during pregnancy.</p><sec><title>Sociocultural Transition and Acculturation</title><p>In addition to the environmental risk factors associated with the resettlement process, migration involves the move from one political, socioeconomic and cultural system to another (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Team et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015a</xref>). Culture here is considered as a set of practices executed in a tangible and observable way by a social group, as well as internal patterns and belief systems, each level mutually reinforcing the other. Furthermore, culture is not a static characteristic of an individual who continually adapts to ever-changing environments. Human development is thus embedded in social networks, interpersonal relations, and local environment. Therefore, culture plays an important role in shaping our identity, and constructs our reality via a process of cultural representations within a specific historical and cultural context. Migrant women, who move from one cultural context to another, have to go through the process of acculturation or adjustment to the host culture, in terms of values, behavior, character, and language skills, with subsequent changes in self-identity (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Ryder et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Berry, 2003</xref>).</p><p>Acculturation is a process of cultural modification of an individual or a group by adapting to or borrowing traits from another culture. However, acculturation is not a unidimensional process because it does not necessarily result in assimilation and loss of a person&#x02019;s ethnic identity. It is a dynamic, ongoing process (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Berry, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Beck, 2006</xref>). Acculturation has long been viewed as a unidimensional process in which migrants move along the continuum toward the acquisition of the host culture, while losing features of their original culture (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Cabassa, 2003</xref>). However, it has recently been shown that individuals have multiple independent cultural identities. Thus, acculturation is nowadays defined and measured as a bi- or multidimensional process in which individuals may maintain their heritage culture and at the same time participate in the host culture (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Berry, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Ryder et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Gibson, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Tadmor et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>The relationship between acculturation and mental health is complex. Multiple studies have shown that assimilation or acculturation to the host culture is associated with better adjustment in the host country and mental health (see <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Berry, 1994</xref>, for an overview). Furthermore, it has been argued that the biculturalism (successful adaptation to two or more cultures) reflects cognitive flexibility and is thought to be potential resilience factor (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Kim and Omizo, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Spiegler and Leyendecker, 2017</xref>).</p><p>Pregnant migrant women, especially primiparas, are experiencing overlapping life transitions: a sociocultural transition calling for acculturation process and a developmental transition to motherhood (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Foss et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015a</xref>). During pregnancy, culture determines how the future mother will perceive her pregnancy and prepare for her motherhood. It links the woman to her social group, providing her with contextual cues, resources, and a sense of family continuity (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">DeSouza, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015a</xref>). Far from their extended families, women cannot turn to older female relatives and friends who can provide a sense of belonging to a family and transmit maternal know-how (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bina, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Baubet and Moro, 2013</xref>). This lack of family and cultural resources can become a source of uncertainty, a feeling of maternal incompetence, and emotional distress (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Berry, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Koneru et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Baubet and Moro, 2013</xref>).</p><p>The role of acculturation process in the development of AA and AD has so far received scarce attention (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Beck, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Fung and Dennis, 2010</xref>). The existing studies mainly focused on <italic>postpartum</italic> depression in <italic>second-generation</italic> migrant women (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Martinez-Schallmoser et al., 2003</xref>). They showed that women born in the host country and highly acculturated to the local culture reported higher postpartum depressive symptomatology, as they were more involved in health risk behaviors (smoking, bad eating habits) and had poorer perinatal outcomes than their less acculturated counterparts. The few studies in first-generation women showed inconsistent results. Some of them reported that the lack of acculturation to the host culture was not related to postpartum depression (see <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Beck, 2006</xref>, for a review), while others concluded that higher levels of acculturation to the host culture was associated with fewer depressive symptoms after birth (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz and Millet, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Foss, 2001</xref>). The heterogeneity of experimental designs and the variables used to define acculturation limit the conclusions that can be drawn.</p><p>In perinatal research, most studies on first-generation migrant women adopt the unidimensional model of acculturation and use various unidimensional scales or proxy measures of assessment. For example, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz and Millet (1995)</xref> used language proficiency as a proxy measure of acculturation to the Canadian culture. They concluded that the lack of local language proficiency resulted in social isolation and thus led to postpartum depressive symptoms in migrant women. However, studies using the unidimensional measures of acculturation do not inform about the role of maintaining one&#x02019;s heritage culture in the development of depressive symptoms during pregnancy and after birth. One study (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abbott and Williams, 2006</xref>) measured acculturation as a bidimensional process and showed that migrant women in New Zealand were at risk of postpartum depression if they rejected the values of both their heritage and host cultures. Women who maintained their heritage culture and at the same time participated in the host culture were less likely to suffer from depression. Therefore, cognitive flexibility, openness to the host culture, but also preservation of traditional cultural practices in the migratory context, might represent protective factors against postpartum depression (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Kim and Omizo, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bina, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Moro and Drain, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015a</xref>). More research using the bidimensional model of acculturation is necessary, however, to confirm these results and understand how the adaptation to the host culture and the conservation of the heritage culture act as protective factors against depression and anxiety during the entire perinatal period (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Beck, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Fung and Dennis, 2010</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Aims of the Study</title><p>The aim of the study was to disentangle sociodemographic, psychosocial and sociocultural risk factors for AA and AD in migrant women in Geneva. The transition to motherhood and antenatal distress in non-precarious migrant women have received scarce attention so far, as most of the studies have focused on disadvantaged populations (refugees, undocumented, or low-income migrant women). In this study, migrant women were compared to native Swiss women of the similar socioeconomic status in terms of sociodemographic and psychosocial risk factors (age, employment status, social and marital support, presence of family members in Geneva, parity) for AA and AD. Further, in migrant women, the role of acculturation in the development of AA and AD was examined. More specifically, the predictive role of the two dimensions of acculturation, namely, <italic>attachment to the heritage culture</italic> and <italic>adaptation to the Swiss culture</italic>, were independently assessed. The role of other sociocultural risk factors (French proficiency and length of stay in Geneva) on AA and AD was also examined.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Participants and Procedure</title><p>Participants were primipara and multipara mothers recruited through flyers and while attending birth preparation classes at the Maternity Unit of the Geneva University Hospitals and the Arcade des Sages-femmes (a collective of independent midwives). Data were collected between January 2015 and March 2016. Consenting women were contacted by phone to set up an interview date. Migrant women were first-generation migrants, defined as foreign-born women who moved to Switzerland during adulthood (at 18 years old or later). The inclusion criteria were as follows: in the third trimester of pregnancy; aged 18 years and older; English- or French-speaking; married or in a cohabiting relationship. The exclusion criteria were fetal malformation or current diagnosis of a severe psychiatric pathological condition.</p><p>Of the 89 women who agreed to participate, two did not meet the inclusion criteria, one woman met the exclusion criteria, and two other women were no longer interested in participating when contacted by phone. The final sample consisted of 84 women, 43 of whom were migrants. The study procedure was approved by the Faculty of Psychology Ethical Committee at the University of Geneva.</p></sec><sec><title>Measures</title><p>A 21-item sociodemographic questionnaire was used to obtain sociodemographic data (age, country of birth, education level, length of stay in Geneva, type of residence permit, French language proficiency) and psychosocial living conditions (housing, work rate, presence of family members in Geneva). Educational levels of women and their partners were added together (1 = primary education, 2 = secondary education, and 3 = higher education), as well as their work rates (1 = not working, 2 = part-time job, and 3 = full-time job), in order to obtain an indirect measure of their <italic>socioeconomic status</italic>.</p><p>The <italic>Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale</italic> (EPDS; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Cox et al., 1987</xref>) was used to screen for AD. It is a 10-item self-report psychometric measure for antenatal and postpartum depression, an instrument of choice in international perinatal research (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Cox and Holden, 1994</xref>). There is some controversy as to the appropriate cutoff point to use during pregnancy. <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Murray and Cox (1990)</xref> recommended using a cutoff point of 12/13 to screen for both major and minor depression. In this study, we chose to use a cutoff of 10/11, as recommended by the American Pediatric Association, in order to identify women <italic>at risk</italic> for AD. The French version used in this study was validated in France by <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Guedeney and Fermanian (1998)</xref> for the detection of postpartum depression. In the current sample, the Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha of the scale was 0.77.</p><p>The <italic>State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</italic> (STAI; <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Spielberger, 1983</xref>) was used as it allows to assess two distinct anxiety concepts: anxiety as an emotional state (<italic>state anxiety subscale</italic>) and proneness to anxiety as a personality trait (<italic>trait anxiety subscale</italic>), with 20 items on both subscales. Items were scored on a four-point scale (from 1 to 4) with general scores varying from 20 to 80. It is acknowledged that anxiety is low up to a score of 45, moderate between 46 and 55, and high when the score is 56 or more. In French-speaking women, a French version of the STAI validated by <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Bruchon-Schweitzer and Paulhan (1993)</xref> was used. In the current sample, the scale showed good internal consistency, with Cronbach&#x02019;s alphas of 0.91 and 0.89 for <italic>state anxiety subscale</italic> and <italic>trait anxiety subscale</italic>, respectively.</p><p>The <italic>Short-Form Social Support Questionnaire</italic> (SSQ-6; <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Sarason et al., 1987</xref>) was used to measure perceived social support. Two scores were obtained: the extent of social support, i.e., the number of people available in case of need, and the degree of satisfaction with the available support scored on a four-point scale with scores ranging from 6 to 36 points. The French version used was translated and validated by <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Bruchon-Schweitzer and Paulhan (1993)</xref>. Coefficient alphas for the current sample were 0.91 for the subscale of the extent of social support and 0.89 for the subscale of satisfaction with the available support.</p><p><italic>Marital support</italic> was measured with two questions: (1) Does your husband/partner provide you with practical and emotional support during pregnancy? (2) How satisfied are you with your husband&#x02019;s/partner&#x02019;s support during pregnancy? The second question was rated on a 10-point Likert scale ranging from 0 (not at all satisfied) to 10 (extremely satisfied). The score was used in its continuous form for the analyses.</p><p><italic>Vancouver Index of Acculturation</italic> (VIA; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Ryder et al., 2000</xref>) was used to access acculturation. It is a 20-item self-report scale that comprises two orthogonal dimensions of acculturation: the extent of attachment to individual&#x02019;s heritage culture and the extent of adaptation to Swiss mainstream culture. Items have response formats of 1 (disagree) to 9 (agree), addressing several domains of cultural identification, such as social and leisure activities, humor, and adherence to cultural traditions. Scores range from 10 to 90 on each subscale, with higher scores indicating greater identification with each domain. The items of the VIA were adapted to the present sample by replacing the term &#x0201c;American&#x0201d; by &#x0201c;Swiss.&#x0201d; The French version used in this study was created in Belgium by <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Friedman and Saroglou (2010)</xref>. In this study, Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha coefficients were 0.76 for the heritage culture subscale and 0.82 for the Swiss culture subscale.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Analysis</title><p>Mean-level differences between migrant and Swiss women for all scales were tested using ANOVAs in Statistica, release 11. Multiple regression analyses were performed to test if different sociodemographic, psychosocial and sociocultural factors predicted AA and AD in the two groups. For migrant women, the role of acculturation was assessed by introducing into the regression analysis the two independent subscales of the VIA, namely, attachment to the heritage culture and adaptation to the Swiss culture. The other sociocultural factors examined were French proficiency and length of stay in Geneva. The scores of the scales were used in their continuous form for the analyses. Multicollinearity was not found to be present in any of the analyses. All analyses were conducted with a significance threshold of &#x003b1; = 0.05, two-tailed.</p><p>AA significantly correlated with AD (<italic>r</italic> = 0.70; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) in all women. AA (measured by <italic>state anxiety subscale</italic> of the STAI) was controlled for in all analyses where AD represented the outcome variable. Proneness to anxiety (measured by <italic>trait anxiety subscale</italic> of the STAI) was controlled for in all analyses where AA represented the outcome variable.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Sample Description</title><p>A total of 84 women participated in the study. Descriptive analyses revealed that participants ranged in age from 21 to 42 years (<italic>M</italic> = 32.7, <italic>SD</italic> = 4.3). The majority of women were married (<italic>n</italic> = 63, 75%) and the others were in a cohabiting relationship. For most women, the current pregnancy was their first (<italic>n</italic> = 66, 79%) and for 92% of women (<italic>n</italic> = 77), the pregnancy was voluntary. The level of education of participants was high (12% with a Ph.D. or postgraduate degree, 51% with a master&#x02019;s degree, 20% with a bachelor&#x02019;s degree). The majority of women (<italic>n</italic> = 66, 79%) were employed, and most of them (<italic>n</italic> = 53, 63%) worked at least 4 days a week. Of the women&#x02019;s partners, 94% of them were employed.</p><p>Migrant women (<italic>n</italic> = 43) did not significantly differ from native women in terms of age, education level, social support, or employment status (see <bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>). However, migrant women were more likely to be married (91 vs. 56%, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 13.42, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) and expecting their first baby (91 vs. 68%, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 6.84, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Not surprisingly, they were less likely to have family members in Geneva (7 vs. 88%, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 55.13, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). They had been living in Switzerland for an average of 5 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 3.9; minimum 5 months and maximum 15 years). Eleven women (26%) had been living in Geneva for less than 2 years, 17 (40%) between 2 and 5 years, and 15 (35%) for 5 years or more. Nearly half of the migrant women (<italic>n</italic> = 18, 42%) came from Western European countries, 10 (23%) came from other OECD countries, such as Canada, Japan, United States; and 15 (35%) came from non-OECD countries, such as Russia, Ukraine, India, Taiwan, and Kenya. Nearly half of the migrant women spoke fluent French (47%), 12% reported limited French proficiency, and 41% had little or no French proficiency. Most migrant women (71%) had a long-term residence permit; 2% had received Swiss nationality; 25% possessed a special permit related to their workplace, such as international and intergovernmental organizations; and 2% had a short-term work permit of less than 1 year.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of demographic information for native and migrant participants.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographic variable</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Migrant (<italic>N</italic> = 43)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native (<italic>N</italic> = 41)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age of participants (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.5 (4.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7 (4.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primiparity (%)<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;PhD or postgraduate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Master&#x02019;s degree</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Bachelor&#x02019;s degree</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;High school diploma</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Civil status: married (%)<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of women employed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have friends in Geneva (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have family in Geneva (%)<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean EPDS score (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 (3.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 (3.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean STAI state anxiety score (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3 (8.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.6 (8.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean STAI trait anxiety score (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (6.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8 (9.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean SSQ score</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Number of people available (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6 (14)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6 (11.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Satisfaction with social support (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9 (4.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2 (2.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean satisfaction with marital support (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4 (1.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8 (1.3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>EPDS, Edinburgh Prenatal Depression Scale; <italic>STAI</italic>, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory <italic>SSQ</italic>, Short-Form Social Support Questionnaire. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001</italic>.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Mean Scores</title><p>For the current sample, the EPDS and the STAI scores were normally distributed (Skewness &#x0003c; 1, Kurtosis &#x0003c; 1). The mean EPDS score was 5.8 (<italic>SD</italic> = 3.7). Fifteen women (18%) presented a score equal to or more than 10 and were considered at risk for AD. The mean score of the STAI state anxiety was 36 (<italic>SD</italic> = 8.7), and the mean score of the STAI trait anxiety was 34.9 (<italic>SD</italic> = 6.8). Sixteen women (19%) scored 46 or above and thus were experiencing a moderate to high level of anxiety during pregnancy. There was no significant difference in the mean scores of the EPDS or the STAI between migrant and native women (see <bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>).</p><p>The majority of migrant women were highly attached to their heritage culture, with the mean score of 72.64 (<italic>SD</italic> = 10.7) on the corresponding VIA subscale. They also demonstrated relatively high adaptation to the Swiss culture, with the mean score of 62 (<italic>SD</italic> = 13.2). The attachment to the heritage culture decreased with time spent in Geneva (<italic>b</italic> = 0.32, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Unexpectedly, the adaptation to the Swiss culture did not increase over time.</p></sec><sec><title>Sociodemographic and Psychosocial Predictors of AA and AD</title><p><italic>In migrant women</italic>, AA was significantly predicted by a set of sociodemographic and psychosocial factors [<italic>F</italic>(4,38) = 11.18, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001] provided in <bold>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></bold>. The significant predictor variables were trait anxiety (<italic>b</italic> = 0.59, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), primiparity (<italic>b</italic> = -0.33, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), satisfaction with marital support (<italic>b</italic> = -0.29, <italic>p</italic> = 0.030), and socioeconomic status of the couple (<italic>b</italic> = 0.30, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). These four factors predicted 49% of the AA variance. AD was significantly predicted only by state anxiety (<italic>b</italic> = 0.68, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), predicting 39% of its variance [<italic>F</italic>(1,42) = 28.75, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001]. Age, education level and social support were not found to be predictive of AA and AD. However, migrant women who had family members in Geneva reported less anxiety symptoms (<italic>b</italic> = -0.33, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), independently of the available social support.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Results of multiple regression analysis for sociodemographic and psychosocial predictors of AA in migrant women.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predictor variables</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>b</italic><sup>&#x02217;a</sup></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SE</italic><sup>b</sup></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic>(38)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primiparity</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait anxiety</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Satisfaction with marital support</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socioeconomic status</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>AA, antenatal anxiety. <sup><italic>a</italic></sup>Standardized regression coefficients. <sup><italic>b</italic></sup>Standard errors of <italic>b<sup>&#x02217;</sup></italic>. <italic>R</italic> = 0.74, <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 0.54, adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 0.49, standard error = 0.17. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001</italic>.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><italic>In native women</italic>, AA was significantly predicted only by trait anxiety (<italic>b</italic> = 0.73, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), even when controlling for other sociodemographic and psychosocial factors. AD was significantly predicted by state anxiety (<italic>b</italic> = 0.78, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and socioeconomic status (<italic>b</italic> = -0.22, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), predicting 69% of the variation of AD [<italic>F</italic>(2,38) = 48.54, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001]. In other words, women who presented a lower socioeconomic status and those who were feeling anxious during pregnancy also presented more depressive symptoms.</p></sec><sec><title>Sociocultural Predictors of AA and AD in Migrant Women</title><p>When the two independent subscales of the VIA were added to the regression analysis, AA in migrant women was still significantly predicted by trait anxiety (<italic>b</italic> = 0.57, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and <italic>psychosocial</italic> factors, namely satisfaction with marital support (<italic>b</italic> = -0.39, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), and by socioeconomic status (<italic>b</italic> = -0.27, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Adaptation to the Swiss culture and attachment to the heritage culture were not found to be predictive of AA, nor was length of stay in Geneva.</p><p>As for AD, once the two VIA subscales were added to the regression analysis, it was still significantly predicted by state anxiety (<italic>b</italic> = 0.60, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), but also by attachment to the heritage culture (<italic>b</italic> = 0.23<italic>, p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), independently of the adaptation to the Swiss culture (see <bold>Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref></bold>). That is, independently of being an anxious person, migrant women presented more depressive symptoms when they were attached to their heritage culture. Both state anxiety and attachment to the heritage culture altogether explained 49% of AD variance [<italic>F</italic>(4,39) = 11.52, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001]. Attachment to the heritage culture predicted 10% of AD variance. Adaptation to the Swiss culture did not predict AD in migrant women.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Results of multiple regression analysis for psychosocial and sociocultural predictors of AD in migrant women.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predictor variables</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>b</italic><sup>&#x02217;a</sup></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SE</italic><sup>b</sup></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic>(37)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">State anxiety</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socioeconomic status</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attachment to heritage culture</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adaptation to Swiss culture</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>AD, antenatal depression. <sup><italic>a</italic></sup>Standardized regression coefficients. <sup><italic>b</italic></sup>Standard errors of <italic>b<sup>&#x02217;</sup></italic>. <italic>R</italic> = 0.75, <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 0.57, adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 0.52, standard error = 2.55. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001</italic>.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The length of stay in Geneva tended to predict AD, but did not reach statistical significance (<italic>b</italic> = -0.21, <italic>p</italic> = 0.069), suggesting that women living in Geneva for a longer period of time tended to present less depressive symptoms, which may be due to the decrease in the attachment to the heritage over time (<italic>b</italic> = 0.32, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05).</p><p>French proficiency did not predict AA or AD in migrant women.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, first-generation, non-precarious migrant women were first compared to a control group of Swiss women of the similar socioeconomic status in terms of sociodemographic and psychosocial risk factors for AA and AD, such as age, parity, employment status, social and marital support. Second, the role of acculturation in the development of AA and AD in migrant women was assessed. Acculturation was considered as a bidimensional process that included <italic>attachment to the heritage culture</italic> and <italic>adaptation to the Swiss culture</italic>. The influence of other sociocultural factors, such as French proficiency and length of stay in Geneva, on the development of AA and AD was also examined. The novel feature of this study is the disentanglement of sociodemographic and psychosocial risk factors for AA and AD in migrant women on one hand, and sociocultural risk factors on the other hand.</p><p>Migrant women in our sample did not differ from native women in terms of age, education, employment status, socioeconomic environment, or availability of social support. The majority of them came from Western European countries and had a long-term residence permit. The present sample seems to be representative of the general migrant population in Geneva, with two-thirds of permanent migrants coming from Western Europe Federal Statistical (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Office of Statistics of the City of Geneva [OCSTAT], 2013</xref>). In this study, migrant women were more likely to be married and expecting their first child. The high marriage rates in this sample might be explained, partially at least, by its practical utility in simplifying legal procedures when migrating as a family. As for the delay in transition to motherhood, it might reflect the challenge of becoming a mother while dedicating themselves to their careers in a foreign land (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Nunes-Reichel and Santiago-Delefosse, 2015</xref>). Not surprisingly in this context, almost all pregnancies were voluntary.</p><sec><title>AA and AD</title><p>The rates of AA and AD symptoms in the current sample of migrant women were lower than in those reported in other studies (18 vs. 25&#x02013;42%) (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed et al., 2008</xref>). Native women presented similar AA and AD rates as reported in other studies on general population (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Faisal-Cury and Rossi Menezes, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Lara et al., 2009</xref>). Contrary to our expectations, migrant women did not differ from Swiss women in terms of rates of depression symptoms and anxiety symptoms. In fact, numerous studies in North American and European literature indicate a higher prevalence of AA and AD among migrants (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Foss et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Lara et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015a</xref>). This difference has been explained by the fact that migrant women usually face multiple stressors such as low socioeconomic position, poor social support, and/or difficulties in adaptation to the host culture (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Gagnon et al., 2010</xref>). In our sample, women did not face any of these factors. Most of them were employed and had high socioeconomic status. Women also benefitted from a solid social network, which constitutes a protective factor against antenatal distress (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Martinez-Schallmoser et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015b</xref>). This result is surprising, as the majority of similar studies show that migrant women often lack social support and report a feeling of isolation (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bina, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Goguikian Ratcliff et al., 2015b</xref>). The strong social network of migrant women in our sample could be explained by their length of stay in Geneva (the majority of women had been living in Geneva for more than 2 years), their employment status, and the international environment where they lived. In fact, Geneva hosts more than 20 international and intergovernmental organizations, and one third of the active population in the city speak English at work (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Office of Statistics of the City of Geneva [OCSTAT], 2013</xref>). Thus, even women who did not speak French could create a solid network, often consisting of colleagues or a foreign community. As for acculturation to the local culture, it seems that migrant women in our sample who lived in such an international environment did not feel the need to engage in profound adaptation of the Swiss traditions and values. This result will be further discussed in the following section.</p><p>Antenatal anxiety was highly comorbid with AD, in consonance with the conclusions of prior studies (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Austin, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Heron et al., 2004</xref>). It is still unclear if anxiety and depression constitute clearly separate disorders during pregnancy (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Matthey et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Dunkel Schetter and Tanner, 2012</xref>). In this study, although AA and AD were highly correlated, they might be seen as separate phenomena, as they were predicted by different sociodemographic, psychosocial and sociocultural factors. Again it seems important to separately screen for AA and AD, as they have been shown to independently predict postpartum depression and adverse neonatal outcomes (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Foss et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Heron et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Orr et al., 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Sociodemographic, Psychosocial and Sociocultural Risk Factors in Migrant Women</title><p>Compared to native women in whom AD was predicted by lower socioeconomic status, migrant women were at risk for AD when they were strongly attached to their heritage culture, after controlling for their socioeconomic status and AA. The predictive role of the attachment to the heritage culture in the development of AD is an important finding of this study because it contributes to a better understanding of migrant women&#x02019;s increased vulnerability to antenatal distress. This result is inconsistent with the findings of <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abbott and Williams (2006)</xref> in New Zealand, who showed that the integrative or bicultural acculturation strategy (attachment to the heritage culture <italic>and</italic> adaptation to the host culture) represented a <italic>protective</italic> factor against postpartum depression. However, it is difficult to compare results of the present study with those of the study by <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abbott and Williams (2006)</xref>, as the attachment to the heritage culture in their study was assessed only with regard to adaptation to the local culture, but not independently. Thus the interdependent nature of the two subscales did not permit to access the particular role of each acculturation dimension separately. Moreover, the authors focused on postpartum depression in Pacific mothers of low socioeconomic status, thus confounding socioeconomic and sociocultural factors.</p><p>The result of our study underlines the fact that for the first-generation, non-precarious migrant women in our sample, attachment to their heritage culture represented a source of increased vulnerability, as their transition to motherhood occurred far from their families and cultural framework. In a new cultural and social context, their sense of belonging might have been undermined, especially since they experienced overlapping transitions (migration and pregnancy). Pregnancy is a period when the need to belong to a family system and to continue its heritage is absolutely crucial (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bina, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Baubet and Moro, 2013</xref>). Migrant women are far from their mothers and larger family, and from the usual intergenerational transmission and guidance practices, which may lead to a loss of the sense of family anchorage. Migrant mothers have to reconcile the two cultures during the acculturation process, and come up with a new, bicultural identity (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Koneru et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">DeSouza, 2014</xref>). In this context, the strong attachment to the heritage culture in migrant women in our sample might reflect their longing for the lost familiar cultural context and family ties. This hypothesis is further supported by the fact that migrant women who had family members living in Geneva reported significantly less anxiety symptoms than women who did not. Women who kept their cultural traditions and beliefs might have also faced some discrepancies between their cultural practices related to pregnancy (breastfeeding, sleeping routines, and child rearing practices) and local guidelines given by health care professionals. In her literature review on the impact of cultural factors on postpartum depression, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bina (2008)</xref> concluded that the maintenance of cultural traditions in the host country could be at the same time a risk factor and a protective factor against depressive symptoms; therefore, the role of attachment to the heritage culture varies among individuals and contexts.</p><p>As for AA in migrant women, it was mainly predicted by trait anxiety (proneness to anxiety as a personality trait), and sociodemographic and psychosocial variables, namely primiparity, low satisfaction with marital support, and low socioeconomic status. These results confirm the findings of prior studies, stressing that in the context of migration, partner&#x02019;s support takes on even greater significance (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zelkowitz et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bina, 2008</xref>). Low socioeconomic status represents a major risk factor for antenatal distress (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Robertson et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Bollini et al., 2009</xref>). Migrant women in our sample often expressed fears of losing their position after the birth of the baby, and thus encounter financial difficulties. This was particularly true for women whose legal permit in Switzerland was related to their workplace (a quarter of migrant women).</p><p>Even though most migrant women in our sample adapted to the Swiss culture, those women who were less integrated or had little French proficiency did not report higher anxiety or depression symptoms. Lack of knowledge about the host culture can be stressful and a few existing studies on the subject have shown that acculturation to the host culture and higher language proficiency in migrants reduced acculturation stress, depressive symptoms and anxiety (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Foss, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Foss et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abbott and Williams, 2006</xref>). It should be noted that we used the VIA scale, in which adaptation to the Swiss culture was assessed by one&#x02019;s knowledge of different areas of local culture, such as cuisine, films, music, and national holidays, as well as socializing with Swiss people. Similarly, in their study on the experience of skilled migrant women in Switzerland, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Nunes-Reichel and Santiago-Delefosse (2015)</xref> showed that expatriates only spoke English at work and socialized mostly with their colleagues, which constituted at the same time a comfort and an important obstacle to the integration of local practices.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The present study expands our understanding of the specific role of sociodemographic, psychosocial and sociocultural risk factors on antenatal distress in migrant women. More research is needed to better understand the role of the attachment to the heritage culture and the adaptation to the host culture, assessed separately, in the antenatal distress of migrant women.</p><sec><title>Limitations of the Study</title><p>Several limitations of the study need to be highlighted. First, the voluntary nature of participation may have induced a selection bias, as women who decided to participate might be those who felt more satisfied with the pregnancy experience. Second, the sample consisted of women who were married or in couple, with high levels of education and high socioeconomic status, which limits the generalization of the results to all migrant women. Third, we used self-report questionnaires to measure anxiety and depressive symptoms. These are convenient and easy-to-use methods, but they are not appropriate for establishing a diagnosis of depression and anxiety, as they are not designed to do so. The STAI was used to measure anxiety symptoms, as it allows to assess anxiety as an emotional state and proneness to anxiety as a personality trait. Pregnancy specific anxiety scale might have better reflected pregnancy related worries. A psychiatric diagnosis based, for example, on DSM-IV criteria would allow a more accurate estimate of the rates of AA and AD, but the establishment of diagnoses was beyond the purpose of this study.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>This study was carried out in accordance with the recommendations of the Ethical Committee of the Faculty of Psychology and Educational Sciences of the University of Geneva. The protocol was approved by the Ethical Committee of the Faculty of Psychology and Educational Sciences. All subjects gave written informed consent in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>This study has been conducted in the context of AS&#x02019;s doctoral thesis. AS participation included the project preparation and elaboration, the obtention of the Ethical Committee agreement, recruitment of participants, antenatal interviews and administration of the questionnaires, data entry and statistical analyses, and article writing and editing. BGR elaboration of the study project, supervision of the study procedure, methods, as well as the article writing; participation in the interpretation of the results and discussion writing.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by the Ernst et Lucie Schmidheiny Foundation.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Postnatal depressive symptoms among Pacific mothers in Auckland: prevalence and risk factors.</article-title>
<source><italic>Aust. N. Z. J. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1614.2006.01779.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16476150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahoush</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Experiences of immigrant new mothers with symptoms of depression.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Womens Ment. Health</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>303</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00737-008-0025-6</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18677438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18677438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>M.-P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Antenatal screening and early intervention for &#x0201c;perinatal&#x0201d; distress, depression and anxiety: where to from here?</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Womens Ment. Health</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00737-003-0034-4</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 14963727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14963727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>M.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Examining the relationship between antenatal anxiety and postnatal depression.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Affect. Disord.</italic></source>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2006.11.015</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17196663?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17174405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baubet</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moro</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <source><italic>Psychopathologie Transculturelle.</italic></source>
<publisher-name>Paris</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Elsevier-Masson</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Acculturation: implications for perinatal research.</article-title>
<source><italic>MCN Am. J. Matern. Child Nurs.</italic></source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005721-200603000-00011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16523037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Acculturation and psychological adaptation,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Journeys into Cross-Cultural Psychology</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bouvy</surname><given-names>A.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Vijver</surname><given-names>F. J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-name>Lisse</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Swets &#x00026; Zeitlinger Publishers</publisher-loc>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Immigration, acculturation and adaption.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Appl. Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Conceptual approaches to acculturation,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Acculturation: Advances in Theory, Measurement, and Applied Research</italic></source>
<role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Organista</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>), <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/10472-004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biaggi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conroy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pawlby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pariante</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Identifying the women at risk of antenatal anxiety and depression: a systematic review.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Affect. Disord.</italic></source>
<volume>191</volume>
<fpage>62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2015.11.014</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26650969?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26650969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bina</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The impact of cultural factors upon postpartum depression: a literature review.</article-title>
<source><italic>Health Care Women Int.</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>568</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>592</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07399330802089149</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18569045?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18569045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bollini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pampallona</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kupelnick</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Pregnancy outcome of migrant women and integration policy: a systematic review of the international literature.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soc. Sci. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>452</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>461</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2008.10.018</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19042065?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19042065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brittain</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koopowitz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Risk factors for antenatal depression and associations with infant birth outcomes: results from a South African birth cohort study.</article-title>
<source><italic>Paediatr. Perinat. Epidemiol.</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>514</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppe.12216</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26236987?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26236987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruchon-Schweitzer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulhan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source><italic>Adaptation Fran&#x000e7;aise de L&#x02019;inventaire d&#x02019;Anxi&#x000e9;t&#x000e9; Trait-Etat. Forme Y (STAI Y).</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Les Editions du Centre de Psychologie Appliqu&#x000e9;e</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cabassa</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Measuring acculturation: where we are and where we need to go.</article-title>
<source><italic>Hisp. J. Behav. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>146</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0739986303025002001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source><italic>Perinatal Psychiatry: Use and Misuse of the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Royal College of Psychiatrists</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagovsky</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Detection of postnatal depression: development of the 10-item Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale.</article-title>
<source><italic>Br. J. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>150</volume>
<fpage>782</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>786</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.150.6.782</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 3651732?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3651732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeSouza</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>One woman&#x02019;s empowerment is another&#x02019;s oppression: Korean migrant mothers on giving birth in Aotearoa New Zealand.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Transcult. Nurs.</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>356</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1043659614523472</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24583877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24583877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiPietro</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilton</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costigan</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pressman</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Maternal stress and affect influence fetal neurobehavioural development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Dev. Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>659</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>668</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0012-1649.38.5.659</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12220045?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12220045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dole</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savitz</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hertz-Picciotto</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siega-Riz</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buekens</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Maternal stress and preterm birth.</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. J. Epidemiol.</italic></source>
<volume>157</volume>
<fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwf176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12505886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunkel Schetter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Anxiety, depression and stress in pregnancy: implications for mothers, children, research, and practice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Opin. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/YCO.0b013e3283503680</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22262028?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faisal-Cury</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi Menezes</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of anxiety and depression during pregnancy in a private setting sample.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Womens Ment. Health</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00737-006-0164-6</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17187166?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17187166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diego</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Reif</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schanberg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yando</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Pregnancy anxiety and comorbid depression and anger: effects on the fetus and neonate.</article-title>
<source><italic>Depress. Anxiety</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>151</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/da.10071</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12768648?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12768648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foss</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Maternal sensitivity, posttraumatic stress, and acculturation in Vietnamese and Hmong Mothers.</article-title>
<source><italic>MCN Am. J. Matern. Child Nurs.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005721-200109000-00009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11552576?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11552576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foss</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andjukenda</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Maternal depression and anxiety and infant development: a comparison of foreign-born and native mothers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Public Health Nurs.</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0737-1209.2004.21306.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15144368?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15144368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saroglou</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Religiosity, psychological acculturation to the host culture, self-esteem and depressive symptoms among stigmatized and nonstigmatized religious immigrant groups in Western Europe.</article-title>
<source><italic>Basic Appl. Soc. Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01973531003738387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Postpartum depression among immigrant women.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Opin. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>342</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/YCO.0b013e32833ad721</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20495458?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20495458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimbeck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeitlin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Migration and perinatal health surveillance: an international survey.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>149</volume>
<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2009.12.002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20074849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20074849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Immigrant adaptation and patterns of acculturation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Hum. Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000057037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goguikian Ratcliff</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharapova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gakuba</surname><given-names>T.-O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015a</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Antenatal depression in immigrant women: a culturally sensitive prevention program in Geneva (Switzerland),&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Women&#x02019;s Mental Health</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Khanlou</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilkington</surname><given-names>F. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>343</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goguikian Ratcliff</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharapova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suardi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015b</year>). <article-title>Factors associated with antenatal depression and obstetric complications in immigrant women in Geneva.</article-title>
<source><italic>Midwifery</italic></source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>871</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>878</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.midw.2015.04.010</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26026198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26026198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouse</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Deconstructing antenatal depression: What is it that matters for neonatal behavioral functioning?</article-title>
<source><italic>Infant Ment. Health J.</italic></source>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>361</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/imhj.20300</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28520144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28520144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guedeney</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fermanian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Validation study of the French version of the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (EPDS): new results about use and psychometric properties.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0924-9338(98)80023-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19698604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The course of anxiety and depression through pregnancy and the postpartum in a community sample.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Affect. Disord.</italic></source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2003.08.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15094259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15094259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Omizo</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Behavioural acculturation and enculturation and psychological functioning among Asian American college students.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cultur. Divers. Ethnic Minor. Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>258</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/1099-9809.12.2.245</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16719575?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16719575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koleva</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Hara</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman-Reif</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Risk factors for depressive symptoms during pregnancy.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Womens Ment. Health</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00737-010-0184-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20872153?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20872153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koneru</surname><given-names>V. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisman</surname></name><name><surname>de Mamani</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Betancourt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Acculturation and mental health: current findings and recommendations for future research.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Prev. Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.appsy.2007.07.016</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12064428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12064428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lara</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>H. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Letechipia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochhausen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Prenatal depression in Latinas in the U.S. and Mexico.</article-title>
<source><italic>Matern. Child Health J.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>576</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10995-008-0379-4</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18581222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18581222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keung Lam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sze Mun</surname><given-names>Lau</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiu Yin</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Prevalence, course, and risk factors for antenatal anxiety and depression.</article-title>
<source><italic>Obstet. Gynecol.</italic></source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>1102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1112</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.AOG.0000287065.59491.70</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17978126?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17978126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lefkovics</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baji</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rig&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Impact of maternal depression on pregnancies and on early attachment.</article-title>
<source><italic>Infant Ment. Health J.</italic></source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>354</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>365</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/imhj.21450</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25798487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25798487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leigh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milgrom</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Risk factors for antenatal depression, postnatal depression and parenting stress.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>24</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-244X-8-24</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18412979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18412979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lobel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannella</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeVincent</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Pregnancy-specific stress, prenatal health behaviors, and birth outcomes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Health Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>615</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0013242</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18823187?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18823187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Depressive symptoms among pregnant women screened in obstetrics settings.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Womens Health</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>380</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/154099903765448880</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12804344?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12804344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Schallmoser</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Telleen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macmullen</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The effect of social support and acculturation on postpartum depression in Mexican American women.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Transcult. Nurs.</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>338</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1043659603257162</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 14535154?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14535154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matthey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howie</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Diagnosing postpartum depression in mothers and fathers: whatever happened to anxiety?</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Affect. Disord.</italic></source>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-0327(02)00012-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12706515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12706515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moro</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drain</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Parentalit&#x000e9; en exil [Parenthood in exile].</article-title>
<source><italic>Soins P&#x000e9;diatr. Pueric.</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Screening for depression during pregnancy with the Edinburgh Depression Scale (EPDS).</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Reprod. Infant Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02646839008403615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nanzer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source><italic>La D&#x000e9;pression Postnatale, Sortir du Silence [Postpartum Depression, Break the Silence].</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Editions Favre</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunes-Reichel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santiago-Delefosse</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The experience of skilled migrant women in Switzerland: challenges for social and professional integration.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Human. Soc. Sci. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>
<comment>The Alspac Study Team</comment>. (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Antenatal anxiety predicts child behavioural/emotional problems independent of postnatal depression.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>1470</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1477</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004583-200212000-00019</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12447034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12447034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Office of Statistics of the City of Geneva [OCSTAT]</collab> (<year>2013</year>). <source><italic>Religion et Langue Dans le Canton de Gen&#x000e8;ve en 2010 [Religions and Languages Spoken in Geneva in 2010].</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>OCSTAT</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;hmann</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunewald</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walndenstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Women&#x02019;s worries during pregnancy: testing the Cambridge Worry Scale on 200 Swedish women.</article-title>
<source><italic>Scand. J. Caring Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>152</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-6712.2003.00095.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blazer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Maternal prenatal pregnancy-related anxiety and spontaneous preterm birth in Baltimore, Maryland.</article-title>
<source><italic>Psychosom. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0b013e3180cac25d</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17636150?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17636150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rich-Edwards</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleinman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harlow</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joffe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Sociodemographic predictors of antenatal and postpartum depressive symptoms among women in a medical group practice.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Epidemiol. Community Health</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech.2005.039370</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16476752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16476752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallington</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Antenatal risk factors for postpartum depression: a synthesis of recent literature.</article-title>
<source><italic>Gen. Hosp. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>295</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2004.02.006</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15234824?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15234824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ronald</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennell</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Prenatal maternal stress associated with ADHD and autistic traits in early childhood.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>:<issue>223</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2010.00223</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21833278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21833278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Anxiety disorders during pregnancy and the postpartum period: a systematic review.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Clin. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>1285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1298</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/JCP.v67n0818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryder</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delroy</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Is acculturation unidimensional or bidimensional? A head-to-head comparison in the prediction of personality, self-identity, and adjustment.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Pers. Soc. Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037//0O22-3514.79.1.49</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10909877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarason</surname><given-names>I. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarason</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shearin</surname><given-names>E. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plerce</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>A brief measure of social support: practical and theoretical implications.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Soc. Pers. Relat.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>510</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5172/conu.2011.157</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22551428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22551428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spiegler</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyendecker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Balanced cultural identities promote cognitive flexibility among immigrant children.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>1579</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2017.01579</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28970811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28970811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spielberger</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source><italic>Manual for the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Palo Alto, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Consulting Psychologists Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tadmor</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetlock</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Acculturation strategies and integrative complexity the cognitive implications of biculturalism.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Cross Cult. Psychol.</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>139</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022022108326279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Team</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasey</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manderson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source><italic>Cultural Dimensions of Pregnancy, Birth and Post-Natal Care.</italic></source> Avaialable at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.health.qld.gov.au/multicultural/support_tools/14MCSR-pregnancy.pdf">http://www.health.qld.gov.au/multicultural/support_tools/14MCSR-pregnancy.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conde</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Anxiety and depression during pregnancy in women and men.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Affect. Disord.</italic></source>
<volume>119</volume>
<fpage>142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2009.03.005</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19346001?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab> (<year>2009</year>). <source><italic>Mental Health Aspect&#x02019;s on Women&#x02019;s Reproductive Health: A Global Review of the Literature.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zelkowitz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>La sant&#x000e9; mentale des immigrantes enceintes [Mental health of pregnant immigrant women].</article-title>
<source><italic>Psychol. Qu&#x000e9;bec</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>80</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zelkowitz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Screening for postpartum depression in a community sample.</article-title>
<source><italic>Can. J. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/070674379504000205</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17319890?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17319890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zelkowitz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saucier</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katofsky</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westreich</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Stability and change in depressive symptoms from pregnancy to two months postpartum in childbearing immigrant women.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Womens Ment. Health</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00737-008-0219-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18270652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18270652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zelkowitz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schinazi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katofsky</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saucier</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westreich</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Factors associated with depression in pregnant immigrant women.</article-title>
<source><italic>Transcult. Psychiatry</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>464</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1363461504047929</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15709645?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15709645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>