<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Plant Methods</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Plant Methods</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Plant Methods</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-4811</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6114889</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">344</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13007-018-0344-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Estimation of area- and mass-based leaf nitrogen contents of wheat and rice crops from water-removed spectra using continuous wavelet analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Dong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Hengbiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Xia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Yongchao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Weixing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Tao</given-names></name><address><phone>+86 25 8439 6565</phone><email>tcheng@njau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9750 7019</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27871.3b</institution-id><institution>National Engineering and Technology Center for Information Agriculture (NETCIA), Key Laboratory of Crop System Analysis and Decision Making, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Jiangsu Key Laboratory for Information Agriculture, Jiangsu Collaborative Innovation Center for Modern Crop Production, </institution><institution>Nanjing Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>One Weigang, Nanjing, Jiangsu 210095 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>76</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The visible and near infrared region has been widely used to estimate the leaf nitrogen (N) content based on the correlation of N with chlorophyll and deep absorption valleys of chlorophyll in this region. However, most absorption features related to N are located in the shortwave infrared (SWIR) region and the physical mechanism of leaf N estimation from fresh leaf reflectance spectra remains unclear. The use of SWIR region may help us reveal the underlying mechanism of casual relationships and better understand the spectral responses to N variation from fresh leaf reflectance spectra. This study combined continuous wavelet analysis (CWA) and water removal technique to improve the estimation of N content and leaf mass per area (LMA) by reducing the effect of water absorption and enhancing absorption signals in the SWIR region. The performance of the wavelet-based method was evaluated for estimating leaf N content and LMA of rice and wheat crops from fresh leaf reflectance spectra collected over a 2-year field experiment and compared with normalization difference (ND)-based spectral indices.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">The LMA and area-based N content (N<sub>area</sub>) exhibited better correlations with the determined wavelet features derived from the water-removed (WR) spectra (LMA: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71, N<sub>area</sub>: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77) than those from the measured reflectance (MR) spectra (LMA: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.62, N<sub>area</sub>: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.64). The wavelet features performed remarkably better than the optimized ND indices for the estimations of LMA and N<sub>area</sub> with MR spectra or WR spectra. Based on the best estimations of LMA and N<sub>area</sub> with wavelet features from WR spectra, the mass-based N content (N<sub>mass</sub>) could be retrieved with a high accuracy (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.82, RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32%) in the indirect way. This accuracy was higher than that for N<sub>mass</sub> obtained in the direct use of a single wavelet feature (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.68, RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.42%).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">The enhancement of absorption features in the SWIR region through the CWA applied to water-removed (WR) spectra was able to improve the spectroscopic estimation of leaf N content and LMA as compared to that obtained with the reflectance spectra of fresh leaves. The success in estimating LMA and N with this method would advance the spectroscopic estimations of grain quality parameters for staple crops and individual dry matter constituents for various vegetation types.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Nitrogen content</kwd><kwd>Water-removed</kwd><kwd>Wavelet analysis</kwd><kwd>Shortwave infrared</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>The National Key R&#x00026;D Program</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016YFD0300601</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Tao</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>The Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</institution></funding-source><award-id>KYLH201603</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Tao</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>The National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>31470084</award-id><award-id>31725020</award-id><award-id>31671582</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Xia</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Tao</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Jiangsu Distinguished Professor Program</institution></funding-source><award-id>N/A</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Tao</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>The Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions (PAPD).</institution></funding-source><award-id>N/A</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par15">Rice and wheat are two major staple crops in the world and provide primary dietary calories and protein for the global population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Leaf nitrogen (N) content is an important indicator of crop photosynthetic capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] and is needed by agronomists for making fertilization recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Quantification of leaf N content could provide valuable information for monitoring crop physiology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], and practicing precise farming [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] so as to improve the use efficiency of nitrogen fertilizers. Remote sensing has been widely used as a non-destructive approach for estimating leaf N content in the past few decades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The common practice is to establish linear or nonlinear relationships between leaf N content and spectral features derived from leaf reflectance spectra.</p><p id="Par16">Curran [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] listed 42 absorption features caused by bending and stretching of foliar chemical bonds in the 400&#x02013;2400&#x000a0;nm range and identified many of them related to N in the shortwave infrared region (SWIR) region (1000&#x02013;2400&#x000a0;nm). Based on a number of N-sensitive wavelengths in the SWIR region, leaf N can be estimated accurately from the reflectance spectra of dried and ground leaves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, these absorption features are masked by water absorption and hence not clearly visible in the SWIR reflectance spectra of fresh leaves, thereby leading to weaker signals of N in the entire spectra [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. This has been proven by the findings that the accuracy of N estimation from the reflectance spectra of fresh leaves is lower than that of dry leaves or dried and ground leaves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Therefore, the SWIR region in the reflectance spectra of fresh leaves has seldom been used for N estimation. Instead, the visible and near infrared (VNIR) region has been widely used for this purpose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] because nitrogen and chlorophyll are well related [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and the latter has deep absorption valleys in this region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. To date, most studies built N estimation models with the spectral information of fresh leaves in the VNIR region alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] or VNIR and SWIR regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. A few studies made use of SWIR reflectance alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] but their focus was on the spectra of dried leaves or leaf powder, rather than fresh leaves that are easier to handle for reflectance measurements. How accurately the N content could be estimated from reflectance spectra of fresh leaves in the SWIR region alone is poorly understood.</p><p id="Par17">As a group of N-containing compounds in fresh leaves, chlorophylls account for only a portion of the total nitrogen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The physical mechanism underlying the spectroscopic estimation of leaf N content remains unclear due to the use of indirect N-sensitive wavelengths in the VNIR region. The use of SWIR region may help us reveal the mechanism and better understand the spectral responses to N variation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. A major problem constraining the satisfactory estimation of N content is the effect of leaf water absorption on reflectance spectra, which was claimed to be removed to within 10% by Kokaly and Clark [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Recently, a few studies adopted a water removal technique originally proposed by Gao and Goetz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] to remove the effect of water absorption so as to improve the estimation of N content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] and N to phosphorous ratio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. These studies compared water removal to traditional spectral transformation techniques, but did not decompose the water removal process for understanding the underlying mechanism of this technique. To make use of the spectral information in the SWIR region, they applied traditional methods such as stepwise multiple linear regression and partial least-squares regression to the spectra after the water removal process. Based on these methods, some of the selected wavelengths were not related to the absorption features of the chemical being examined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and the regressions were often faced with model overfitting and indirect relationships [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In addition, how to enhance the causal absorption features in WR spectra for the improved estimation of leaf N content is poorly understood.</p><p id="Par18">Recently, continuous wavelet analysis (CWA) has been widely used to estimate chlorophyll content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], water content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], dry matter content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], and leaf area index [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] from leaf and canopy reflectance spectra. After the application of continuous wavelet transform, a reflectance spectrum is decomposed into a number of scale components, which have the same length as the reflectance spectrum and are composed of wavelet features as a function of wavelength and scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Wavelet features have been proven to be superior to vegetation indices (VIs) in the characterization of absorption by foliar chemicals in reflectance spectra [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. However, none of previous studies have used CWA and water removal techniques collectively and have investigated the application of CWA to WR spectra for examining dry matter and nitrogen related absorption characteristics. In contrast to the continuum removal operation used in Schlerf et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and Ramoelo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], the continuous wavelet transform (CWT) is a linear operation and enables us to decompose the CWT of WR spectra into that of spectral addition or subtraction. Combining CWA and water removal has the potential to improve the estimation of N content by reducing the effect of water absorption and enhancing N absorption signals.</p><p id="Par19">Common measures for expressing leaf N content are either area-based (N<sub>area</sub>, g/m<sup>2</sup>) or mass-based (N<sub>mass</sub>, %). Because of its tight correlation with photosynthetic capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] and the widespread use in fertilization management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], N<sub>mass</sub> has been extensively studied and estimated from remotely sensed data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Both N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> can be directly obtained in a destructive way, but remote sensing usually works better for estimating N<sub>area</sub>. The leaf biochemistry for dried ground samples is usually expressed as concentration (mass-based, mass per unit dry weight). For intact fresh leaves, the biochemistry is often expressed as content (area-based, mass per unit leaf area) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The use of chemical content may be more suitable for remote sensing applications because it is a better representation of the interaction between matter and light per unit surface area. For example, the units of biochemical parameters used in PROSPECT model are all area-based [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. It may be proven by the higher correlations of many VIs with N<sub>area</sub> than N<sub>mass</sub> documented in Hansen and Schjoerring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and Jay et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Although the interaction of leaves with light per unit leaf area is directly related to such area-based traits as N<sub>area</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], few studies paid attention to the estimation of N<sub>area</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. As pointed out by Wright et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], N<sub>mass</sub> and N<sub>area</sub> are interconverted via leaf mass per area (LMA, g/m<sup>2</sup>). To the best of our knowledge, only one study made use of this connection and derived N<sub>area</sub> indirectly from estimated N<sub>mass</sub> and LMA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Based on our understanding of N<sub>mass</sub> and N<sub>area</sub>, this study will investigate first estimating the two area-based factors (N<sub>area</sub> and LMA) and then indirectly estimating N<sub>mass</sub> instead. The SWIR region encompasses all of the major absorption features of dry matter and N and may provide sufficient spectral information to estimate LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub>.</p><p id="Par20">Therefore, the objectives of this study were (1) to determine the wavelet features most sensitive to LMA and N<sub>area</sub> from both leaf reflectance spectra and WR spectra in the SWIR region, (2) to evaluate the feasibility of improving LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> estimations with the integration of CWA and the water removal technique, and (3) to compare the CWA and normalization difference (ND) index approaches in the performance of LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> estimations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Experimental design</title><p id="Par21">Four experiments were conducted at the experimental station in Rugao, Jiangsu of eastern China (120&#x000b0;45&#x02032;E and 32&#x000b0;16&#x02032;N) with two for rice and two for wheat. Both crops were chosen as they were grown in rotation in this experimental area. We intended to develop robust models for both of them despite their differences in biochemical parameters and surface properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The pooled data represented a wider range of samples and were beneficial to test the stability of the method proposed in this study. The treatment in each experiment represented variations in cultivar type, nitrogen fertilization rate and planting density with three replications. These treatments were applied to create wide ranges for N<sub>mass</sub>, N<sub>area</sub> and LMA, which includes the extremely high and low values. There were a total of 36 plots with the same size of 5&#x000a0;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;6&#x000a0;m for each experiment. Details about the experiments and sampling dates are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Rice was transplanted and grown in a grid pattern with a plant spacing of 15&#x000a0;cm and two row spacings of 30 and 50&#x000a0;cm. Wheat was sowed in drill with different row spacings and the rows were oriented in a south-north direction. The 2-year experimental data for rice and wheat were combined to form RICE and WHEAT datasets, respectively.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Summary of designs and ground samplings periods of the field plot experiments</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Dataset</th><th align="left">Year of data collection</th><th align="left">Cultivar</th><th align="left">Nitrogen rate (kg&#x000a0;hm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)</th><th align="left">Planting density (cm)</th><th align="left">Growth stages for sampling</th><th align="left">Number of samples</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Rice</td><td align="left">2015</td><td align="left">Yliangyou 1*<break/>Wuyunjing 24**</td><td align="left">0, 100, 200, 300</td><td align="left">30&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;15, 50&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;15</td><td align="left">Jointing, booting, heading</td><td char="." align="char">95</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2016</td><td align="left">Yliangyou 1*<break/>Wuyunjing 24**</td><td align="left">0, 150, 300</td><td align="left">30&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;15, 50&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;15</td><td align="left">Jointing, booting</td><td char="." align="char">74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Wheat</td><td align="left">2016</td><td align="left">Yangmai 18*</td><td align="left">0, 80, 150, 220</td><td align="left">20, 30, 40</td><td align="left">Jointing, booting, heading</td><td char="." align="char">127</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2017</td><td align="left">Yangmai 15*<break/>Yangmai 16**</td><td align="left">0, 150, 300</td><td align="left">25, 40</td><td align="left">Late-jointing, heading, anthesis</td><td char="." align="char">104</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*, **Denote erect-leaf and drooping-leaf cultivars, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Measurements of reflectance spectra and chemical constituents</title><p id="Par22">Three leaves per plot were collected and each leaf made a sample. Their reflectance spectra were measured using an ASD FieldSpec Pro spectrometer (Analytical Spectral Devices, Boulder, CO, USA) assisted with a leaf clip accessory. Reflectance spectra were taken per leaf for three leaf positions and these spectra were averaged to represent the leaf sample spectrum. The spectrometer collects data at 1.4&#x000a0;nm and 2&#x000a0;nm sampling interval in the 350&#x02013;1000&#x000a0;nm and 1000&#x02013;2500&#x000a0;nm spectral regions, respectively. The spectral data were obtained at a 1&#x000a0;nm spectral interval.</p><p id="Par23">After collection of reflectance spectra, the surface area (A, m<sup>2</sup>) and fresh weight (FW, g) were measured immediately for every leaf sample. The leaf area (A, m<sup>2</sup>) was determined with a HP G4050 scanner (HP Development Company, L.P., USA) and calculated as the product of pixel count per leaf and the actual area represented by each pixel. The leaf dry weight (DW, g) was measured after the leaves were dried in the oven at 80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 48&#x000a0;h. Finally, equivalent water thickness (EWT, g/m<sup>2</sup>), leaf mass per area (LMA, g/m<sup>2</sup>) and area-based leaf nitrogen content (N<sub>area</sub>, g/m<sup>2</sup>) were calculated with the equations below:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{EWT}} = \left( {{\text{FW}} - {\text{DW}}} \right)/{\text{A}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>EWT</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>FW</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>DW</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{LMA}} = {\text{DW}}/{\text{A}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>LMA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>DW</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{N}}_{\text{area}} = {\text{N}}_{\text{mass}} \times {\text{LMA}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>area</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>mass</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>LMA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where mass-based leaf nitrogen content (N<sub>mass</sub>, %) was determined using Kjeldahl method with SEAL AutoAnalyzer 3 HR (SEAL Analytical, Ltd., German). Note that the unit g/m<sup>2</sup> of EWT can be interconverted to cm (1&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>&#x000a0;g/cm<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>&#x000a0;cm) via the density of water (1&#x000a0;g/cm<sup>3</sup>: 1&#x000a0;g water&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x000a0;cm<sup>3</sup> water) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>The adjusted water-removal technique</title><p id="Par24">The water removal technique was originally proposed by Gao and Goetz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] with the assumption that there is a linear spectral background level and a nonlinear combination of a reflectance spectrum of leaf water and that of leaf dry matter for fresh leaves. However, the assumption of linear spectral background is only valid for small wavelength regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] and this technique is often performed on spectral segments, such as 1500&#x02013;1780&#x000a0;nm and 2100&#x02013;2200&#x000a0;nm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The use of narrow and discrete spectral segments may limit the utility of full-range spectral information. Therefore, this technique was adjusted in this study to obtain full-range water removed (WR) spectra by adopting PROSPECT-5B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] for modeling leaf reflectance spectra. The input parameters of PROSPECT-5B include chlorophyll content (C<sub><italic>ab</italic></sub>), carotenoid content (C<sub><italic>xc</italic></sub>), EWT, LMA, and structural parameter (<italic>N</italic><sub><italic>struc</italic></sub>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. To estimate the WR spectra, the first step was to find the best combination of input parameters for PROSPECT-5B by minimizing the following merit function:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$min = \mathop \sum \limits_{\lambda = 1}^{n} \left( {R_{\lambda } - \widetilde{{R_{\lambda } }}} \right)^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">~</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>&#x003bb;</italic></sub> and <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\widetilde{{R_{\lambda } }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">~</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the measured reflectance (MR) and modeled reflectance values of a spectrum at wavelength <italic>&#x003bb;</italic>, respectively. The mathematical optimization was performed with the &#x02018;CONSTRAINED_MIN&#x02019; function in IDL 8.3 (Exelis Visual Information Solutions, Boulder, CO, USA), which gives the best combination of parameters that minimizes the difference between modeled and measured reflectance for the specified spectral range. Since most nitrogen and dry matter related absorption features are located in the shortwave infrared (SWIR) region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], the spectral range 1000&#x02013;2400&#x000a0;nm was used in this study for implementing PROSPECT model inversion as well as the determination of WR spectra. In addition, the <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>ab</italic></sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>xc</italic></sub> were fixed at 30 and 3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup>, respectively, because these pigments have no absorption in this spectral region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">After the PROSPECT model inversion process, the second step was to model the leaf water reflectance spectra by inputting the inverted parameters into PROSPECT-5B with zero LMA values. Since pigments have no influences on the reflectance in this spectral region, the parameters C<sub>ab</sub> and C<sub>xc</sub> were fixed at 30 and 3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup>, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. As water was the only absorbing chemical left in fresh leaves for this purpose, the modeled leaf water reflectance spectra were named as water-only (WO) spectra. The residual spectra, namely the WR spectra, were estimated as below:<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$WR_{\lambda } = \left( {R_{\lambda } - R_{\lambda }^{wo} } \right)/\bar{R}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">wo</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>R</italic><sub arrange="stack"><italic>&#x003bb;</italic></sub><sup arrange="stack"><italic>wo</italic></sup> was the reflectance of a WO spectrum at wavelength &#x003bb;. <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\bar{R}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> was the mean reflectance of a MR spectrum over all wavelengths.</p><p id="Par26">After the absorption of dry matter was removed, the amplitude of modeled leaf water reflectance increased for all wavelengths except for the strong water absorption region around 1900&#x000a0;nm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Many nitrogen-related absorption features that were not obvious in the MR spectrum became visible in the WR spectrum, such as the feature at 2180&#x000a0;nm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). Note that the reflectance values have physical meanings and cannot be negative, but the amplitudes of WR spectra were relative values estimated from MR spectra and the negative MR values only meant the negative differences between a reflectance spectra and the corresponding water-only spectrum. Similar terminology is also seen in &#x0201c;derivative spectra&#x0201d;, which represents the derivative data of reflectance spectra and encompasses negative and positive values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Represents a measured reflectance spectrum and the modeled water-only spectrum for a fresh leaf and <bold>b</bold> represents the corresponding water-removed spectrum. The vertical dashed lines correspond to the absorption features of nitrogen centered at 1510&#x000a0;nm, 1690&#x000a0;nm, 2060&#x000a0;nm, 2180&#x000a0;nm, and 2300&#x000a0;nm. In addition, three scaled and shifted mother wavelets (labeled as S3, S4, and S5) at scales 3&#x02013;5 with the shifting factor of 2180&#x000a0;nm are presented in (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig1_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Continuous wavelet analysis (CWA)</title><p id="Par27">Mathematically, continuous wavelet transform (CWT) is a linear operation that performs the convolution of reflectance spectrum with a scaled and shifted mother wavelet. The realization process is shown as below:<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\psi_{a,b} \left( {{\uplambda }} \right) = \frac{1}{\sqrt a }\psi \left( {\frac{\lambda - b}{a}} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c8;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msqrt></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x003c8;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$W_{r} ( {a,b}) = \int\limits_{- \infty }^{+\infty } r(\lambda )\psi_{a,b} ( \uplambda)d\lambda$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c8;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\psi \left( {{\uplambda }} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c8;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the mother wavelet function and <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\psi_{a,b} \left( {{\uplambda }} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c8;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the scaled and shifted version of <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\psi \left( {{\uplambda }} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c8;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. <italic>W</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub>(<italic>a</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>b</italic>) is the wavelet coefficient (or wavelet feature, denoted as WF<sub>b,a</sub>) for the scaling factor <italic>a</italic> and the shifting factor <italic>b</italic>. The scaling factor indicates the width of the scaled mother wavelet, which can be comparable with the width of an absorption feature. Narrow absorption features can be captured by a low scaling factor while broad features need high scaling factors. The scaling factor used in this study is at dyadic scales 2<sup>3</sup> (scale 3), 2<sup>4</sup> (scale 4), 2<sup>5</sup> (scale 5), and 2<sup>6</sup> (scale 6). The shifting factor determines the central wavelength of shifted mother wavelet, which is used to capture the peak or valley of an absorption feature. Taking the absorption feature of nitrogen at 2180&#x000a0;nm as an example, the three scaled and shifted mother wavelets (Scale 3, Scale 4, and Scale 5) are displayed in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b. The spectral width of the corresponding wavelet feature increases with the scaling factor. Different with a spectral index calculated with two discrete wavelengths, a wavelet feature represents the information for a continuous spectral sub-region that determined by scaling and shifting factors. Although CWA is known to be resistant to signal noise, noise reduction is not the focus of this study. Rather, we took the advantage of CWA in capturing and enhancing the absorption features by nitrogen and dry matter. The multiscale property of CWA is well suited for characterizing the absorption changes that may occur in different widths over different wavelength ranges.</p><p id="Par28">The one-dimensional reflectance spectra are converted into two-dimensional wavelet power (magnitude of wavelet coefficient) datasets after the application of CWT. Hence, a scalogram of coefficients of determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) was obtained at all wavelengths and scales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Moreover, the regions that compromised the top 1% <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> values were extracted from the comprised scalograms and finally the wavelet feature with the highest <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> was selected. In this study, the mother wavelet function was determined as the second derivative of the Gaussian function because of its similarity to the shapes of leaf absorption features [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. CWT was conducted using the &#x02018;WV_CWT&#x02019; function in IDL 8.3 (Exelis Visual Information Solutions, Boulder, CO, USA). Since the wavelet is linearly additive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], the wavelet power derived from a WR spectrum equals the difference in wavelet power between the MR spectrum and the WO spectrum divided by the mean of reflectance over all wavelengths as follows:<disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$WP(WR_{\lambda } ) = WP\left( {R_{\lambda } )/\bar{R} - WP(R_{\lambda }^{wo} } \right)/\bar{R}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">wo</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where WP represents the wavelet power and other symbols are the same as in Eq.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Evaluation of estimation accuracy</title><p id="Par29">The widely used normalization difference (ND) indices were calculated in this study for comparison with the wavelet features in the evaluation of estimation accuracy. The ND index wavelengths were determined as the best band combination from <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> scalograms except these combinations with difference between two wavelengths within 10&#x000a0;nm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Since the aim of this study was to build a robust model across rice and wheat crops, the most sensitive wavelet features and ND indices to LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> were determined separately from pooled data. These spectral features were used to represent their regression relationships and generate direct estimates of those traits. Since area-based foliar traits are directly related to the interaction of foliar constituents with light and can be more easily estimated with spectral features than mass-based traits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], N<sub>mass</sub> was also estimated in an indirect way as the ratio of estimated LMA and N<sub>area</sub> values as below:<disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{Estimated }}\,{\text{N}}_{\text{mass}} = \frac{{{\text{Estimated }}\,{\text{N}}_{\text{area}} }}{{{\text{Estimate}}\, {\text{LMA}}}} \times 100{{\% }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Estimated</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>mass</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Estimated</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msub><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>area</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Estimate</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mtext>LMA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ9.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>The indirect estimation of N<sub>mass</sub>, based on two wavelet features separately sensitive to N<sub>area</sub> and LMA, might outperform the direct estimation with a single wavelet feature.</p><p id="Par30">The estimation accuracies were evaluated with the metrics <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and root mean square root (RMSE):<disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R^{2} = 1 - \frac{{\mathop \sum \nolimits_{i} \left( {y_{i} - y_{i}^{\prime } } \right)^{2} }}{{\mathop \sum \nolimits_{i} \left( {y_{i} - \bar{y}} \right)^{2} }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ10.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$RMSE = \sqrt {\frac{{\mathop \sum \nolimits_{i} \left( {y_{i} - y_{i}^{\prime } } \right)^{2} }}{n}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_Equ11.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$y_{i}^{\prime }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the measured and estimated trait values for sample <italic>i</italic>. <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\bar{y}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the arithmetic mean of trait and n is the number of samples. Due to the intrinsic discrepancy between rice and wheat leaves, the best feature for rice may not be exactly the same as that for wheat and vice versa. A generic model that would work best across rice and wheat samples was preferred over that specific to one crop alone. Therefore, the selected features were determined from the pooled data of rice and wheat. These evaluation metrics were calculated from two commonly used validation processes. One is a 10-fold cross validation procedure applied to the pooled data, and the other is the leave-one-out (LOO) method. In the LOO process, three sub-datasets were used for model calibration and the left one was used for validation. This validation process was repeated for the every one of the four sub-datasets (Rice 2015, Rice 2016, Wheat 2016, and Wheat 2017) in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Since many studies also used the VNIR region to calculate the Red-Edge Chlorophyll Index (CI<sub>red edge</sub>) for leaf N content estimation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], a brief comparison between SWIR and VNIR regions was presented.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Descriptive statistics of foliar traits</title><p id="Par31">Differences in foliar traits between the two datasets could be observed in terms of range and magnitude (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Compared with RICE, the WHEAT dataset exhibited a higher mean and a wider range for EWT, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) but a lower mean and a narrower range for LMA (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). In addition, N<sub>area</sub> was positively correlated with N<sub>mass</sub> for both RICE (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.79, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) and WHEAT (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.92, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). N<sub>area</sub> was positively correlated with LMA for WHEAT (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.65, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) but not correlated with EWT for both datasets. N<sub>mass</sub> was correlated with LMA for RICE (<italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.56, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) and WHEAT (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.31, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) but correlated with EWT only for RICE (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.30, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Stacked frequency distributions of <bold>a</bold> EWT, <bold>b</bold> LMA, <bold>c</bold> N<sub>area</sub>, and <bold>d</bold> N<sub>mass</sub> for the two datasets RICE and WHEAT. The statistics before and after slash (/) in each distribution plot are shown for RICE and WHEAT, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig2_HTML" id="MO13"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Pearson&#x02019;s correlation matrix for EWT, LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> (top-right triangle for RICE and bottom-left triangle for WHEAT)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Tab2_HTML" id="MO14"/><table-wrap-foot><p>**Significant correlations with <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par32">As one of the most important factors in this experiment, the effect of N treatment on leaf reflectance spectra is displayed in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> by taking the WHEAT 2017 samples as an example. The N<sub>mass</sub>, N<sub>area</sub>, and LMA values for WHEAT 2017 increased with the N fertilization rate, and EWT was almost invariant for N1 and N2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a&#x02013;d). The leaf reflectance spectra under three N treatments exhibited marginal differences in the SWIR region (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>e). This phenomenon was expected for fresh leaves, which demonstrated the need of water removal technique to remove the water absorption and CWA to enhance the absorption features of nitrogen and dry matter.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>The boxplots of <bold>a</bold> N<sub>mass</sub>, <bold>b</bold> N<sub>area</sub>, <bold>c</bold> EWT and <bold>d</bold> LMA as well as <bold>e</bold> averaged leaf reflectance spectra under three nitrogen treatments (N0: 0&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;hm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, N1: 150&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;hm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, N2: 300&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;hm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) for WHEAT 2017 samples</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig3_HTML" id="MO15"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Relationships of N<sub>area</sub> with optimal wavelet features and ND indices</title><p id="Par33">The highest <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> values between N<sub>area</sub> and wavelet features for pooled data were 0.64 and 0.77 for MR and WR spectra, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a, b). The two feature regions determined for MR spectra were centered at 2060&#x000a0;nm and 2180&#x000a0;nm, and both of them matched up with the absorptions of protein and nitrogen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. As for the WR spectra, a similar feature region with longer wavelengths was found, and a minor one exhibited much shorter wavelengths than the counterpart for the MR spectra.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Coefficients of determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) for the relationships of N<sub>area</sub> with <bold>a</bold> MR spectra and <bold>b</bold> WR spectra derived wavelet features, and <bold>c</bold> MR spectra and <bold>d</bold> WR spectra derived ND indices. Regions highlighted in red on the scalograms represent the top 1% <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> for wavelet features or ND indices. The downward arrows on the top of the figure indicate the wavelength locations of absorption features with both 2060&#x000a0;nm and 2180&#x000a0;nm for protein and nitrogen</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig4_HTML" id="MO16"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par34">The <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> contour maps for the relationship between N<sub>area</sub> and ND indices are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c, d for MR (maximum <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40) and WR (maximum <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.37) spectra, respectively. Seven wavelength regions most sensitive to N<sub>area</sub> were observed for the MR spectra and five of them were close to the diagonal line, which indicates the presence of similar wavelengths in an ND index. As for the WR spectra, the majority of wavelength combinations were located in the 1700&#x02013;1800&#x000a0;nm region in which both <italic>&#x003bb;</italic><sub><italic>1</italic></sub> and <italic>&#x003bb;</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub> fall.</p><p id="Par35">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> shows the relationships of N<sub>area</sub> with four optimal spectral features (WF<sub>2060,3</sub>, WF<sub>2181,4</sub>, ND<sub>2192,2202</sub> and ND<sub>1749,1773</sub>) determined from the top 1% correlations in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. The two optimal wavelet features (WF<sub>2060,3</sub> and WF<sub>2181,4</sub>) used the spectral information over two spectral sub-regions that matched well with the absorption features centered at 2060&#x000a0;nm and 2180&#x000a0;nm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a, b). Nevertheless, the two optimal ND indices (ND<sub>2192,2202</sub> and ND<sub>1749,1773</sub>) used the spectral information at four individual wavelengths 1749&#x000a0;nm, 1773&#x000a0;nm, 2192&#x000a0;nm and 2202&#x000a0;nm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c, d). All of the relationships for WHEAT, RICE and pooled data were linear. After the application of the WR process, the N<sub>area</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;WF correlation exhibited a pronounced improvement (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> increased from 0.71 to 0.83) over that from the MR spectra for the WHEAT dataset but a slight increase for RICE dataset (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a, b). Overall, this caused an increase of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> from 0.64 to 0.77 for the pooled data. For N<sub>area</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;ND correlations, the combination of an increase for RICE and a decrease for WHEAT resulted in an overall decrease in <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c, d).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Relationships of N<sub>area</sub> with wavelet features (top row) and ND indices (bottom row) derived from MR spectra (left column) and WR spectra (right column). Red, blue and black lines represent linear fits on RICE, WHEAT and pooled data, respectively. All regressions are statistically significant (<italic>p&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig5_HTML" id="MO17"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par36">Because of the linearly additive property of CWT, the final regressions from the WR spectra could be decomposed into intermediate regressions to understand how the effect of water absorption was removed. Taking the N<sub>area</sub> estimation as an example, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> shows the intermediate and final regressions based on Eq.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="">8</xref>) to illustrate the advantages of the water removal technique. N<sub>area</sub> was well correlated to the WF<sub>2181,4</sub> derived from the MR spectra (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a) but not to the WF<sub>2181,4</sub> derived from the WO spectra for both RICE and WHEAT datasets (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). The WF<sub>2181,4</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;N<sub>area</sub> relationship in the MR spectra was weaker than that in the WR spectra (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c, d). After the removal of water absorption information in the WO spectra (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>e), the WR-derived WF<sub>2181,4</sub> that equaled the difference between MR-derived and WO-derived WF<sub>2181,4</sub> values contained no more water information (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>f). Clearly, the WR-derived WF<sub>2181,4</sub> showed improved relationships with N<sub>area</sub> with increases of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> values by 0.23 and 0.18 for RICE and WHEAT datasets, respectively.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Relationships between WF<sub>2181,4</sub> and (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold>) N<sub>area</sub> and (<bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold>, <bold>f</bold>)&#x000a0;EWT derived from MR spectra (left column), WO spectra (middle column) and WR spectra (right column). Particularly, the WF<sub>2181,4</sub> at right column was equal to the difference between WF<sub>2181,4</sub> at left column and middle column. Red and blue lines represent linear fits on RICE and WHEAT, respectively. All regressions are statistically significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) except for that in (<bold>b</bold>, <bold>f</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig6_HTML" id="MO18"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Relationships of N<sub>mass</sub> with optimal wavelet features and ND indices</title><p id="Par37">The highest <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> between N<sub>mass</sub> and wavelet features for pooled data were 0.71 and 0.68 for MR and WR spectra, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a, b). The three feature regions determined for MR spectra were centered at 2050&#x000a0;nm, 2120&#x000a0;nm and 2170&#x000a0;nm, all of which corresponded to the absorption wavelengths of protein and nitrogen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] but showed an offset about 10&#x000a0;nm. As for the WR spectra, only one feature region sensitive to N<sub>mass</sub> was found and its center wavelength (2110&#x000a0;nm) was 20&#x000a0;nm off the known absorption feature.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Coefficients of determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) for the relationships of N<sub>mass</sub> with <bold>a</bold> MR spectra and <bold>b</bold> WR spectra derived wavelet features and <bold>c</bold> MR spectra and <bold>d</bold> WR spectra derived ND indices. Regions highlighted in red on the scalograms represent the top 1% <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> for wavelet features or ND indices. The downward arrows on the top of the figure indicate the wavelength locations of absorption features with both 2060&#x000a0;nm and 2180&#x000a0;nm for protein and nitrogen and 2130&#x000a0;nm for protein</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig7_HTML" id="MO19"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par38">The <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> contour maps for the relationships between N<sub>mass</sub> and ND indices are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c, d for MR (maximum <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32) and WR (maximum <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.37) spectra, respectively. Regardless of MR and WR spectra, wavelength regions sensitive to N<sub>area</sub> were dispersed on the contour map and a majority of them were close to the diagonal line.</p><p id="Par39">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> shows the linear relationships of N<sub>mass</sub> with four optimal spectral features (WF<sub>2053,3</sub>, WF<sub>2113,4</sub>, ND<sub>2281,2291</sub> and ND<sub>2147,2161</sub>) determined from the top 1% regions in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>. With the WR technique, the N<sub>mass</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;WF correlation exhibited a decrease over that from the MR spectra for the individual datasets and for the pooled data (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a, b). N<sub>area</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;ND correlations increased from MR spectra to WR spectra but the <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> values were still substantially lower than those for the N<sub>mass</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;WF correlations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>c, d).<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p>Relationships of N<sub>mass</sub> with (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>)&#x000a0;wavelet features and (<bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>)&#x000a0;ND indices derived from MR spectra (left column) and WR spectra (right column). Red, blue and black lines represent linear fits on RICE, WHEAT and pooled data, respectively. All regressions are statistically significant (<italic>p&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig8_HTML" id="MO20"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Relationships of LMA with optimal wavelet features and ND indices</title><p id="Par40">The highest <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> between LMA and wavelet features for pooled data were 0.62 and 0.71 for MR and WR spectra, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>a, b). The two feature regions determined for MR spectra were centered at 2210&#x000a0;nm and 2270&#x000a0;nm. The former did not coincide with any known absorption feature but the latter matched up with the absorption features of cellulose, sugar and starch [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. After the water removal process, a similar feature region was found with longer wavelengths and a narrower range of scales. In addition, a new feature region with shorter wavelengths was found and exhibited a wavelength centered at 1580&#x000a0;nm that was associated with the absorptions of starch and sugar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;9</label><caption><p>Coefficients of determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) for the relationships of LMA with <bold>a</bold> MR spectra and <bold>b</bold> WR spectra derived wavelet features and <bold>c</bold> MR spectra and <bold>d</bold> WR spectra derived ND indices. Regions highlighted in red on the scalograms represent the top 1% <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> for wavelet features or ND indices. The downward arrows on the top of the figure indicate the wavelength locations of absorption features reported in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] with 1580&#x000a0;nm for starch and sugar and 2270&#x000a0;nm for cellulose, sugar and starch</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig9_HTML" id="MO21"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par41">The <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> contour maps for the correlations between LMA and ND indices for pooled data are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>c, d for MR (maximum <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60) and WR (maximum <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60) spectra, respectively. Three wavelength regions most sensitive to LMA for the MR spectra were represented by center wavelengths <italic>&#x003bb;</italic><sub>1</sub> at 1450&#x000a0;nm, 1870&#x000a0;nm and 2230&#x000a0;nm, and <italic>&#x003bb;</italic><sub>2</sub> at 2240&#x000a0;nm. As for the WR spectra, the most significant wavelength combinations were located in the regions with both <italic>&#x003bb;</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>&#x003bb;</italic><sub>2</sub> shorter than 1800&#x000a0;nm. The ND index regions representing the top 1% <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> with LMA were generally more scattered than the wavelet feature regions, and therefore more difficult to relate with major absorption features documented in the literature.</p><p id="Par42">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref> shows the relationships of LMA with four optimal spectral features (WF<sub>2273,4</sub>, WF<sub>1578,4</sub>, ND<sub>2236,2247</sub> and ND<sub>1716,1727</sub>) determined as the best candidates from the top 1% correlations in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>. These relationships were linear for WHEAT, RICE and pooled data. With the WR technique, the LMA&#x02009;~&#x02009;WF correlation exhibited a pronounced improvement (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> increased from 0.45 to 0.66) over that from the MR spectra for the RICE dataset but did not change for WHEAT (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>a, b). This caused an increase of <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> from 0.62 to 0.71 for the pooled data. For LMA&#x02009;~&#x02009;ND correlations, the combination of a decrease for RICE and an increase for WHEAT led to no change in <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> for the pooled data (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>c, d).<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;10</label><caption><p>Relationships of LMA with (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>)&#x000a0;wavelet features and (<bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>)&#x000a0;ND indices derived from MR spectra (left column) and WR spectra (right column). Red, blue and black lines represent linear fits on RICE, WHEAT and pooled data, respectively. All regressions are statistically significant (<italic>p&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig10_HTML" id="MO22"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Assessment for the estimations of LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub></title><p id="Par43">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> shows the estimation accuracy for LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> over the pooled data with the 10-fold cross-validation. In particular, N<sub>mass</sub> was estimated with the determined wavelet features as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref> (the direct way) and with the ratio of estimated N<sub>mass</sub> and LMA values (the indirect way). In all cases, wavelet features outperformed ND indices substantially in the estimations of N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> for both MR and WR spectra. For the estimation of N<sub>area</sub>, the accuracy with the best correlated wavelet features was improved from MR spectra (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.64 and RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.22&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup>) to WR spectra (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77 and RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.18&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup>), but that with ND indices even decreased slightly. For the direct estimation of N<sub>mass</sub> with the best correlated wavelet features and ND indices, there was no significant difference in estimation accuracy before and after the application of water removal. As the ratio of wavelet-derived N<sub>area</sub> and LMA, N<sub>mass</sub> could be better estimated from WR spectra (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.82 and RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32%) than from MR spectra (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71 and RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40%). As can be seen in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>, the scatter plot of estimated versus measured N<sub>mass</sub> is closer to the 1:1 line, especially for samples in the WHEAT dataset. This indirect estimation of N<sub>mass</sub> from WR spectra was also more accurate than the direct estimation. The improvement in the indirect estimation of N<sub>mass</sub> from MR spectra to WR spectra was not seen for ND indices. The performance of these wavelet features derived from the SWIR region (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77 and 0.82 for N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub>, respectively) was better than CI<sub>red edge</sub> from the VNIR region (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.76 and 0.71 for N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub>, respectively), especially for N<sub>mass</sub>.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Assessment of LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> estimations generated with the direct and indirect ways</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Dependent variables</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Explanatory variables</th><th align="left" colspan="2">MR spectra</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Explanatory variables</th><th align="left" colspan="2">WR spectra</th></tr><tr><th align="left">
<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</th><th align="left">RMSE</th><th align="left">
<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</th><th align="left">RMSE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">LMA</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2273,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td><td char="." align="char">4.95</td><td align="left">WF<sub>1578,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.70</td><td char="." align="char">4.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ND<sub>2236,2247</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.60</td><td char="." align="char">5.12</td><td align="left">ND<sub>1716,1727</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.59</td><td char="." align="char">5.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">N<sub>area</sub></td><td align="left">WF<sub>2060,3</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.64</td><td char="." align="char">0.22</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2181,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.77</td><td char="." align="char">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ND<sub>2192,2202</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.39</td><td char="." align="char">0.29</td><td align="left">ND<sub>1749,1773</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.36</td><td char="." align="char">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">N<sub>mass</sub>-direct</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2053,3</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.71</td><td char="." align="char">0.40</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2113,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.68</td><td char="." align="char">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ND<sub>2283,2286</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.31</td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td><td align="left">ND<sub>2153,2154</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.36</td><td char="." align="char">0.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">N<sub>mass</sub>-indirect</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2273,4</sub>, WF<sub>2060,3</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.71</td><td char="." align="char">0.40</td><td align="left">WF<sub>1578,4</sub>, WF<sub>2181,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ND<sub>2236,2247</sub>, ND<sub>2192,2202</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.31</td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td><td align="left">ND<sub>1716,1727</sub>, ND<sub>1749,1773</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.33</td><td char="." align="char">0.61</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and RMSE values were obtained using a 10-fold cross-validation</p><p>Note the units of RMSE were g/m<sup>2</sup> for LMA and N<sub>area</sub> and % for N<sub>mass</sub></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;11</label><caption><p>The scatter plots of measured and estimated N<sub>mass</sub> derived as the ratio of LMA and N<sub>area</sub> estimated from (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>) wavelet features and (<bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>) ND indices from MR spectra (leaf column) and WR spectra (right column). The LMA and N<sub>area</sub> estimations were generated from the 10-fold cross validation process</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig11_HTML" id="MO23"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par44">In addition to the 10-fold cross validation, the LOO validation accuracies are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. Generally, the estimation accuracy from the LOO process was lower. However, both wavelet features and ND indices derived from the WR spectra still produced higher <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> for LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and the ratio of N<sub>area</sub> to LMA (N<sub>mass</sub> in an indirect way) than those from the MR spectra. As for N<sub>mass</sub> estimation, the indirect way with wavelet features (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.79 and RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.34%) still worked better than the direct way (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.61 and RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.46%).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Assessment of LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> estimations generated with the direct ways and the indirect way</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Dependent variables</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Explanatory variables</th><th align="left" colspan="2">MR spectra</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Explanatory variables</th><th align="left" colspan="2">WR spectra</th></tr><tr><th align="left">
<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</th><th align="left">RMSE</th><th align="left">
<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</th><th align="left">RMSE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">LMA</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2273,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.60</td><td char="." align="char">5.09</td><td align="left">WF<sub>1578,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.63</td><td char="." align="char">4.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ND<sub>2236,2247</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.46</td><td char="." align="char">5.93</td><td align="left">ND<sub>1716,1727</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.50</td><td char="." align="char">5.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">N<sub>area</sub></td><td align="left">WF<sub>2060,3</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.56</td><td char="." align="char">0.25</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2181,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.72</td><td char="." align="char">0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ND<sub>2192,2202</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.25</td><td char="." align="char">0.32</td><td align="left">ND<sub>1749,1773</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.32</td><td char="." align="char">0.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">N<sub>mass</sub>-direct</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2053,3</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.65</td><td char="." align="char">0.44</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2113,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.64</td><td char="." align="char">0.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ND<sub>2283,2286</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.29</td><td char="." align="char">0.63</td><td align="left">ND<sub>2153,2154</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.14</td><td char="." align="char">0.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">N<sub>mass</sub>-indirect</td><td align="left">WF<sub>2273,4</sub>, WF<sub>2060,3</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.61</td><td char="." align="char">0.46</td><td align="left">WF<sub>1578,4</sub>, WF<sub>2181,4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.79</td><td char="." align="char">0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ND<sub>2236,2247</sub>, ND<sub>2192,2202</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.01</td><td char="." align="char">0.74</td><td align="left">ND<sub>1716,1727</sub>, ND<sub>1749,1773</sub></td><td char="." align="char">0.26</td><td char="." align="char">0.64</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and RMSE values were obtained using a leave-one-out validation</p><p>Not the units of RMSE were g/m<sup>2</sup> for LMA and N<sub>area</sub> and % for N<sub>mass</sub></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Difference in sensitive spectral features derived from MR and WR spectra</title><p id="Par45">When comparing the spectral features specifically sensitive to LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub>, we found that the difference in wavelet feature was less significant between MR and WR spectra than that in ND index. The highlighted feature regions for ND indices were generally more dispersed across the scalograms, which complicated the selection of the best ND indices and was also seen in the studies by le Maire et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] and Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Two dispersed index regions with even similar <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> values would lead to substantially different wavelength combinations, not to mention many of them as highlighted in Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>. The sensitive wavelet features were mostly concentrated in no more than two feature regions, from which it would be easier to select the best wavelet features in less than three scales and wavelength ranges. The mismatch of the wavelengths selected by ND indices with the absorption centers suggested the weakness of ND indices and the strength of wavelet features in capturing the changes in nitrogen absorption features. This might be attributed to the different calculation principles for ND indices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] and wavelet features [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The former was determined by the reflectance values at two wavelengths and was sensitive to the amplitude of reflectance spectra, but the latter mainly captured the shape of a spectral segment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Before and after water removal, the amplitude of spectra changed but the shapes of absorption features retained and became even more obvious. Therefore, common sensitive wavelet features can be observed between MR and WR spectra, but not for ND indices.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Necessity of removing the effect of water absorption with CWA</title><p id="Par46">The absorption of leaf water is strong in the SWIR region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], hence the subtle absorption features of such dry matter constituents as protein and nitrogen are masked in the reflectance spectra of fresh leaves (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Many studies have shown that this masking effect reduces the estimation accuracy of these chemical constituents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. This is supported by our findings that the estimations of LMA and N<sub>area</sub> were significantly improved through the wavelet-based method after the effect of water absorption had been removed. Particularly, Kokaly and Clark [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] modeled the estimation accuracy of leaf chemistry under eight levels of water content in percentage of fresh weight and found that the accuracy decreased rapidly when leaf water content exceeded 30%. To date, the effect of water absorption on ND indices and wavelet features is still poorly understood. Here we present an exploration of their performance for N<sub>area</sub> estimation under different water content levels in EWT. To avoid the confounding factors of leaf surface property and internal structure, the WHEAT dataset with a wider range of EWT was selected to generate three subsets with EWT levels of 130&#x02013;140&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup> (W1), 150&#x02013;160&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup> (W2), and 170&#x02013;180&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup> (W3).</p><p id="Par47">The optimal index ND<sub>2192,2202</sub> was well correlated to N<sub>area</sub> only at the lowest EWT level (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>a), but WF<sub>2060,3</sub> bore stronger relationships with N<sub>area</sub> at every EWT level (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>b). In contrast to the close relationships of N<sub>area</sub> and ND<sub>2192,2202</sub> under three EWT levels, the N<sub>area</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;WF<sub>2060,3</sub> relationship was sensitive to EWT level. This is probably because WF<sub>2060,3</sub> made use of the spectral information in the 2020&#x02013;2100&#x000a0;nm range [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], which is the right wing of the water absorption valley centered at 1950&#x000a0;nm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and whose shape changes as a function of water content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In spite of the tight N<sub>area</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;WF<sub>2060,3</sub> relationships, the sensitivity of WF<sub>2060,3</sub> to EWT reduced the model transferability, e.g., from subset W1 to subset W3. Therefore, it was essential to remove water absorption for building a robust model that can be directly applied to datasets with different EWT levels.<fig id="Fig12"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;12</label><caption><p>Relationships of N<sub>area</sub> with <bold>a</bold> ND<sub>2192,2202</sub> and <bold>b</bold> WF<sub>2060,3</sub> derived from the MR spectra at three levels of EWT (W1: 130&#x02013;140&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup>, W2: 150&#x02013;160&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup> and W3: 170&#x02013;180&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup>) in the WHEAT dataset. Red, blue and green lines represent linear fits for the data points from W1, W2 and W3, respectively. All regressions are statistically significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig12_HTML" id="MO24"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>How did the water removal technique improve the estimations of N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub>?</title><p id="Par48">The accuracies of LMA and N<sub>area</sub> estimations using wavelet features were improved when the effect of water absorption was removed with the water removal technique. Some recent studies used WR spectra through spectral indices or partial least squares regression to improve the estimations of LMA and N<sub>mass</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>], but they did not provide explanations as to why those improvements were obtained. This study reported the application of CWA to the WR spectra for estimating foliar traits by removing the effect of water absorption and enhancing the absorption features of foliar traits. The better WF<sub>2181,4</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;N<sub>area</sub> relationships in the WR spectra than in the MR spectra (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a, c) could be explained by the information on EWT in WF<sub>2181,4</sub>, which was derived from the MR spectra (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d) but not from the WR spectra (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>f).</p><p id="Par49">With regard to the water removal technique for N<sub>mass</sub>, the wavelet-based direct way did not improve the estimation accuracy but the indirect way exhibited a significant improvement (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). This could be attributed to the improved estimations of both LMA and N<sub>area</sub>. Kokaly and Clark [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] suggested any remote sensing algorithm for retrieving foliar chemicals from fresh leaf spectra should remove the influence of water absorption. Wang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] used the normalized dry matter index (NDMI) from WR spectra to estimate the LMA but only obtained slight improvement over MR spectra as for the use of ND indices in this study (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>c, d). The wavelet features determined for LMA estimation by Cheng et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] from a wide range of plant species performed better than NDMI, but they might still suffer from the effect of water absorption and be hard to be applied to other datasets with different water content levels. Therefore, the difficulty in LMA estimation hampered the indirect estimation of N<sub>mass</sub> due to the dominant role of LMA as the denominator in Eq.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="">9</xref>). For the first time, this study obtained improved estimations for LMA as well as N<sub>area</sub> by applying CWA to the WR spectra and eventually increased the estimation accuracy for N<sub>mass</sub> in the indirect way.</p><p id="Par50">The close fits of data points to the linear regression and the 1:1 lines in Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref> suggested the best models worked well for the whole ranges of N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub>. Although the rice and wheat plants in this experiment were deliberately treated in the field, the data were collected in natural light conditions and the models should be applicable to plants growing in the same condition and without any N treatment. To take advantage of the proposed strategy of combining CWA and water removal, it is imperative to have a dataset exhibiting weak covariance of EWT with LMA and N<sub>area</sub>. Generally, this applies to leaf level but may not apply to canopy level where the traits are determined as the products of leaf traits and leaf area index and high correlations often exist between EWT<sub>canopy</sub> and other traits. In that case, it is difficult to find a wavelet feature insensitive to EWT<sub>canopy</sub> but sensitive to another canopy trait. Therefore, the water removal procedure would have limited contribution to the improvement of N<sub>mass</sub> or N<sub>area</sub> estimation. To test the suitability of our strategy at canopy level, one would need to avoid crop datasets with high correlations of canopy EWT and nitrogen related traits. Alternatively, the strategy could be applied to natural plant types such as trees [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and grasses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Although this research was conducted at leaf level, it represented a significant advance in the mechanistic understanding of water removal technique for removing water signals and enhancing nitrogen and dry matter signals in fresh leaves. The leaf-level analysis concentrated on chemical signals and laid the foundation of water removal application for scaling up to the canopy level. To better understand the mechanism at canopy level, the strategy should be examined in detail by considering other external factors such as canopy structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], soil background [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], solar zenith angle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], view zenith angle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], and diffuse/direct light condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Finally, the signal to noise ratio should also be accounted for in case the nitrogen-related second overtones are suppressed by the spectral noise from instruments and atmospheric interference [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Physical interpretations of determined wavelet features</title><p id="Par51">Low-scale wavelet features are able to capture the local shape of absorption features associated with biochemical parameters while high-scale ones characterize the broad continuum in leaf reflectance spectra [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The matching wavelet features could be found for N<sub>area</sub> and LMA but not for N<sub>mass</sub>, which might suggest that the area-based expressions (N<sub>area</sub> and LMA) were better representations of the interaction between matter and light per unit surface area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p><p id="Par52">The absorption feature at 2270&#x000a0;nm caused by bending and stretching of chemical bonds in cellulose, sugar and starch does not obviously appear in the reflectance spectra (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>a), but it is well represented in the wavelet power spectra of MR-derived WF<sub>2273,4</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>c). Since LMA is equivalent to the dry matter content by definition, we could relate spectral variation to dry matter absorption from the perspective of spectroscopy of foliar chemistry as done in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The amplitude of reflectance in the 2200&#x02013;2350&#x000a0;nm range increases with LMA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>a), which contradicts the common sense that the reflectance should decrease with dry matter absorption. This might be attributed to the leaf internal scattering as well as the confounding effect of water absorption on leaf reflectance, which makes it difficult to derive the LMA with traditional techniques, such as ND index [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. In contrast, the depth of absorption center at 2270&#x000a0;nm in the wavelet power spectra follows the trend of LMA variation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>c). Moreover, the absorption feature at 1580&#x000a0;nm by starch and cellulose are invisible in the MR spectra (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), but it appears clearly in the WR spectra after water removal (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>b). The change in the amplitude at WR spectra-derived WF<sub>2273,4</sub> in the wavelet power spectra matches with the variation in LMA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>d).<fig id="Fig13"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;13</label><caption><p>Effect of LMA on spectral variation between 2200 and 2350&#x000a0;nm (leaf panel) and 1500&#x02013;1650&#x000a0;nm (right panel). <bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Represent the MR spectra and the corresponding wavelet power spectra at scale 4. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>d</bold> Represent the WR spectra and the corresponding wavelet power at scale 4. The location and width of the Gaussian-shaped wavelets for the best LMA-sensitive wavelet features WF<sub>2273,3</sub> and WF<sub>1578,4</sub> from MR and WR spectra are presented in (<bold>a</bold>) and (<bold>b</bold>), respectively. The black arrows in (<bold>c</bold>) and (<bold>d</bold>) point to the wavelength locations of WF<sub>2273,3</sub> and WF<sub>1578,4</sub>, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig13_HTML" id="MO25"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par53">Similar to dry matter, the absorption of nitrogen at 2060&#x000a0;nm and 2180&#x000a0;nm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] could be well characterized by the optimal N<sub>area</sub> sensitive wavelet features WF<sub>2060,3</sub> (MR spectra) and WF<sub>2180,4</sub> (WR spectra) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>). The close matches in wavelength between the determined wavelet features and the documented absorption centers documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] convince us of the physical interpretations underlying the empirical WF-N<sub>area</sub> relationships.<fig id="Fig14"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;14</label><caption><p>Effect of N<sub>area</sub> on spectral variation between 2000 and 2120&#x000a0;nm (leaf panel) and 2100&#x02013;2250&#x000a0;nm (right panel). <bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Represent the MR spectra and the corresponding wavelet power spectra at scale 3. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>d</bold> Represent the WR spectra and the corresponding wavelet power at scale 4. The location and width of the Gaussian-shaped wavelets for the best N<sub>area</sub>-sensitive wavelet features WF<sub>2060,3</sub> and WF<sub>2181,4</sub> from MR and WR spectra are presented in (<bold>a)</bold> and (<bold>b</bold>), respectively. The black arrows in (<bold>c</bold>) and (<bold>d</bold>) point to the wavelength location of the WF<sub>2060,3</sub> and WF<sub>2181,4</sub>, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13007_2018_344_Fig14_HTML" id="MO26"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par54">The enhancement of absorption features of nitrogen in the SWIR region would help improve the spectroscopic estimation of leaf nitrogen content from the SWIR reflectance spectra of fresh leaves. This study evaluated the applicability of the water-removal technique for increasing the estimation accuracies of LMA, N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> with CWA and spectral index methods. After removing water absorption, the estimation accuracies for LMA and N<sub>area</sub> were significantly improved with the use of individual wavelet features but not with ND indices. The two wavelet features WF<sub>1578,4</sub> and WF<sub>2181,4</sub> derived from the WR spectra produced the best estimations for LMA (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.70, RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.38&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup>) and N<sub>area</sub> (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77, RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.18&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup>), respectively. Compared to that from the MR spectra, the estimation of N<sub>mass</sub> from the WR spectra only changed marginally with individual wavelet features (MR spectra: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71, RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40%; WR spectra: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.68, RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.42%). However, a notable improvement was obtained when indirectly deriving N<sub>mass</sub> as a ratio of N<sub>area</sub> to LMA (MR spectra: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71, RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40%; WR spectra: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.82, RMSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32%). Generally, the determined wavelet features performed remarkably better than the optimized ND indices for the estimations of all the three traits.</p><p id="Par55">The results demonstrated the feasibility of improving the estimation of N<sub>area</sub> and N<sub>mass</sub> from the SWIR reflectance spectra by applying CWA to WR spectra. This procedure could suppress the effect of water absorption and enhance the absorption features of foliar chemicals. The characterization of nitrogen absorption variation in the SWIR region with wavelet features offers physical interpretations for the direct detection of leaf nitrogen content and complements the indirect detection of nitrogen content via the use of chlorophyll absorption bands in the red edge region. The integration of CWA and water removal provides a new insight for better understanding spectral responses to the variation in LMA and leaf nitrogen content and has the potential for applications to other crops and different vegetation types. The technique developed in this study could be useful for high throughput phenotyping of leaf nitrogen related traits and the non-destructive detection of nitrogen stress in crops.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>N<sub>area</sub></term><def><p id="Par4">area-based leaf nitrogen content</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>N<sub>mass</sub></term><def><p id="Par5">mass-based leaf nitrogen content</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LMA</term><def><p id="Par6">leaf mass per area</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WR</term><def><p id="Par7">water-removed</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CWA</term><def><p id="Par8">continuous wavelet analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WF</term><def><p id="Par9">wavelet feature</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ND</term><def><p id="Par10">normalized difference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VNIR</term><def><p id="Par11">visible and near infrared</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SWIR</term><def><p id="Par12">shortwave infrared</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></term><def><p id="Par13">coefficient of determination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RMSE</term><def><p id="Par14">root mean square error</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>DL and TC designed the experiment. DL, XW, HZ, and KZ performed the experiment. DL, XY, YT, YZ, WC, and TC performed the overall data analysis. DL and TC drafted the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par56">We would like to thank Min Jia, Ning Lu, Xiao Zhang, Chen Zhou, Yong Liu, Ni Wang, Xue Ma, Xiaoqing Xu and Chaojie Niu for their help in the data collection. The authors also thank two anonymous reviewers for their detailed suggestions for improving the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par57">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par58">The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par59">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par60">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par61">This work was supported by the National Key R&#x00026;D Program (2016YFD0300601), the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (KYLH201603), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31470084, 31725020, 31671582), Jiangsu Distinguished Professor Program, and the Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions (PAPD).</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par62">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seck</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Diagne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wopereis</surname><given-names>MCS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crops that feed the world 7: rice</article-title><source>Food Secur</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiferaw</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Smale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Duveiller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Muricho</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crops that feed the world 10. Past successes and future challenges to the role played by wheat in global food security</article-title><source>Food Secur</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>317</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photosynthesis and nitrogen relationships in leaves of C<sub>3</sub> plants</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1989</year><volume>78</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28311896?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28311896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladha</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupnik</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Six</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessel</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficiency of fertilizer nitrogen in cereal production: retrospects and prospects</article-title><source>Adv Agron</source><year>2005</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>156</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gamon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Surfus</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing leaf pigment content and activity with a reflectometer</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2010</year><volume>143</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>117</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haboudane</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarco-Tejada</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dextraze</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrated narrow-band vegetation indices for prediction of crop chlorophyll content for application to precision agriculture</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2002</year><volume>81</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>426</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>B-B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T-C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved remote sensing of leaf nitrogen concentration in winter wheat using multi-angular hyperspectral data</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2016</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>133</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Skidmore</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new technique for extracting the red edge position from hyperspectral data: the linear extrapolation method</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2006</year><volume>101</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>193</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dury</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating foliage nitrogen concentration from HYMAP data using continuum removal analysis</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2004</year><volume>93</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remote sensing of foliar chemistry</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>1989</year><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>278</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kokaly</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectroscopic determination of leaf biochemistry using band-depth analysis of absorption features and stepwise multiple linear regression</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>1999</year><volume>67</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>287</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kokaly</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating a physical basis for spectroscopic estimates of leaf nitrogen concentration</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2001</year><volume>75</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>161</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pacheco-Labrador</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Cascon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilar Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Riano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the optical responses of leaf nitrogen in Mediterranean Holm oak (Quercus ilex) using field spectroscopy</article-title><source>Int J Appl Earth Observ Geoinf</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettigrew-Crosby</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting nitrogen and chlorophyll content and concentrations from reflectance spectra (400&#x02013;2500&#x000a0;nm) at leaf and canopy scales</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>1995</year><volume>53</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>211</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlerf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Atzberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Buddenbaum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000fc;ler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retrieval of chlorophyll and nitrogen in Norway spruce (Picea abies L. Karst.) using imaging spectroscopy</article-title><source>Int J Appl Earth Observ Geoinf</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ustin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Khosla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Active canopy sensing of winter wheat nitrogen status: an evaluation of two sensor systems</article-title><source>Comput Electron Agric</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Omasa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating rice chlorophyll content and leaf nitrogen concentration with a digital still color camera under natural light</article-title><source>Plant Methods</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>36</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25411579?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25411579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlemmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gitelson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schepers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanahan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rundquist</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remote estimation of nitrogen and chlorophyll contents in maize at leaf and canopy levels</article-title><source>Int J Appl Earth Observ Geoinf</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>54</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacquemoud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baret</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PROSPECT: a model of leaf optical properties spectra</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>1990</year><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>91</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>le Maire</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ois</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufr&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards universal broad leaf chlorophyll indices using PROSPECT simulated database and hyperspectral reflectance measurements</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2004</year><volume>89</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Steyn-Ross</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaare</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvester</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Steyn-Ross</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating leaf nitrogen concentration in ryegrass (<italic>Lolium</italic> spp.) pasture using the chlorophyll red-edge: theoretical modelling and experimental observations</article-title><source>Int J Remote Sens</source><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>3619</fpage><lpage>3648</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schjoerring</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reflectance measurement of canopy biomass and nitrogen status in wheat crops using normalized difference vegetation indices and partial least squares regression</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2003</year><volume>86</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>553</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring leaf nitrogen status with hyperspectral reflectance in wheat</article-title><source>Eur J Agron</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>404</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lepine</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ollinger</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouimette</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining spectral reflectance features related to foliar nitrogen in forests: implications for broad-scale nitrogen mapping</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2016</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecarnot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Compan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Roumet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing leaf nitrogen content and leaf mass per unit area of wheat in the field throughout plant cycle with a portable spectrometer</article-title><source>Field Crops Research</source><year>2013</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hikosaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Terashima</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen partitioning among photosynthetic components and its consequence in sun and shade plants</article-title><source>Funct Ecol</source><year>1996</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>343</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>AFH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extraction of dry leaf spectral features from reflectance spectra of green vegetation</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>1994</year><volume>47</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>374</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramoelo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skidmore</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlerf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitkonig</surname><given-names>IMA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water-removed spectra increase the retrieval accuracy when estimating savanna grass nitrogen and phosphorus concentrations</article-title><source>ISPRS J Photogramm Remote Sens</source><year>2011</year><volume>66</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>417</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramoelo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skidmore</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlerf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitkonig</surname><given-names>IMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Savanna grass nitrogen to phosphorous ratio estimation using field spectroscopy and the potential for estimation with imaging spectroscopy</article-title><source>Int J Appl Earth Observ Geoinf</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>343</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferwerda</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retrieval of chlorophyll concentration from leaf reflectance spectra using wavelet analysis</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2008</year><volume>112</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1614</fpage><lpage>1632</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WREP: a wavelet-based technique for extracting the red edge position from reflectance spectra for estimating leaf and canopy chlorophyll contents of cereal crops</article-title><source>ISPRS J Photogramm Remote Sens</source><year>2017</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>117</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating leaf SPAD values of freeze-damaged winter wheat using continuous wavelet analysis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source><year>2016</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26610092?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26610092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Azofeifa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectroscopic determination of leaf water content using continuous wavelet analysis</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2011</year><volume>115</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>670</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ria&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ustin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting diurnal and seasonal variation in canopy water content of nut tree orchards from airborne imaging spectroscopy data using continuous wavelet analysis</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2014</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Azofeifa</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000e9;ret</surname><given-names>J-B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquemoud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ustin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deriving leaf mass per area (LMA) from foliar reflectance across a variety of plant species using continuous wavelet analysis</article-title><source>ISPRS J Photogramm Remote Sens</source><year>2014</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating canopy leaf area index in the late stages of wheat growth using continuous wavelet transform</article-title><source>J Appl Remote Sens</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>083517</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rivard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Azofeifa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Continuous wavelets for the improved use of spectral libraries and hyperspectral data</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2008</year><volume>112</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2850</fpage><lpage>2862</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houl&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu&#x000e9;rif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mary</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elaboration of a nitrogen nutrition indicator for winter wheat based on leaf area index and chlorophyll content for making nitrogen recommendations</article-title><source>Eur J Agron</source><year>2007</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Filella</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Penuelas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating wheat nitrogen status with canopy reflectance indices and discriminant analysis</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>1995</year><volume>35</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1400</fpage><lpage>1405</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating leaf nitrogen concentration in heterogeneous crop plants from hyperspectral reflectance</article-title><source>Int J Remote Sens</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>4652</fpage><lpage>4667</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Datt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remote sensing of chlorophyll a, chlorophyll b, chlorophyll a&#x02009;+&#x02009;b, and total carotenoid content in Eucalyptus leaves</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>1998</year><volume>66</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>121</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>F&#x000e9;ret</surname><given-names>J-B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ois</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Asner</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gitelson</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bidel</surname><given-names>LPR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ustin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>le Maire</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquemoud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PROSPECT-4 and 5: advances in the leaf optical properties model separating photosynthetic pigments</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2008</year><volume>112</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3030</fpage><lpage>3043</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maupas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendoula</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorretta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retrieving LAI, chlorophyll and nitrogen contents in sugar beet crops from multi-angular optical remote sensing: comparison of vegetation indices and PROSAIL inversion for field phenotyping</article-title><source>Field Crops Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danson</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating live fuel moisture content from remotely sensed reflectance</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2004</year><volume>92</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>321</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Limited effects of water absorption on reducing the accuracy of leaf nitrogen estimation</article-title><source>Remote Sens</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>291</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Westoby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackerly</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Baruch</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavender-Bares</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornelissen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Diemer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The worldwide leaf economics spectrum</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>428</volume><issue>6985</issue><fpage>821</fpage><?supplied-pmid 15103368?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15103368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PROCWT: coupling PROSPECT with continuous wavelet transform to improve the retrieval of foliar chemistry from leaf bidirectional reflectance spectra</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2018</year><volume>206</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ceccato</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gobron</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Flasse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarantola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Designing a spectral index to estimate vegetation water content from remote sensing data: part 1. Theoretical approach</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2002</year><volume>82</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Philpot</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Derivative analysis of hyperspectral data</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>1998</year><volume>66</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baret</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Skidmore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gitelson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlerf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Darvishzadeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Olioso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simple and robust methods for remote sensing of canopy chlorophyll content: a comparative analysis of hyperspectral data for different types of vegetation</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ</source><year>2016</year><volume>39</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2609</fpage><lpage>2623</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27650474?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27650474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>le Maire</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ois</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Soudani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Berveiller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontailler</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000e9;da</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Genet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Davi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufr&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calibration and validation of hyperspectral indices for the estimation of broadleaved forest leaf chlorophyll content, leaf mass per area, leaf area index and leaf canopy biomass</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2008</year><volume>112</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3846</fpage><lpage>3864</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlemmer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanahan</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schepers</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remotely measuring chlorophyll content in corn leaves with differing nitrogen levels and relative water content</article-title><source>Agron J</source><year>2005</year><volume>97</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>ER</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating dry matter content from spectral reflectance for green leaves of different species</article-title><source>Int J Remote Sens</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>7097</fpage><lpage>7109</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouse</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Deering</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring vegetation systems in the great plains with Erts</article-title><source>NASA Spec Publ</source><year>1974</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>317</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dungan</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the foliar biochemical concentration of leaves with reflectance spectrometry: testing the Kokaly and Clark methodologies</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>2001</year><volume>76</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>359</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>ER</surname><given-names>H</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Daughtry</surname><given-names>CST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating dry matter content of fresh leaves from the residuals between leaf and water reflectance</article-title><source>Remote Sens Lett</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>145</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knyazikhin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schull</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mottus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rautiainen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Latorre Carmona</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperspectral remote sensing of foliar nitrogen content</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>E185</fpage><lpage>E192</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23213258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23213258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niemann</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodenough</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Visintini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Loos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addressing the effects of canopy structure on the remote sensing of foliar chemistry of a 3-dimensional, radiometrically porous surface</article-title><source>IEEE J Sel Top Appl Earth Observ Remote Sens</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>593</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darvishzadeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Skidmore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Atzberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wieren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of vegetation LAI from hyperspectral reflectance data: effects of soil type and plant architecture</article-title><source>Int J Appl Earth Observ Geoinf</source><year>2008</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>373</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenz-Wiedemann</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bareth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating leaf chlorophyll of barley at different growth stages using spectral indices to reduce soil background and canopy structure effects</article-title><source>ISPRS J Photogramm Remote Sens</source><year>2014</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Middleton</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solar zenith angle effects on vegetation indices in tallgrass prairie</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>1991</year><volume>38</volume><issue>91</issue><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brede</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Suomalainen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartholomeus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Herold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of solar zenith angle on the enhanced vegetation index of a Guyanese rainforest</article-title><source>Remote Sens Lett</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>972</fpage><lpage>981</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of sunlight conditions on the consistency of vegetation indices in croplands-effective usage of vegetation indices from continuous ground-based spectral measurements</article-title><source>Remote Sens</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>14079</fpage><lpage>14098</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ustin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquemoud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmuck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdebout</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critique of stepwise multiple linear regression for the extraction of leaf biochemistry information from leaf reflectance data</article-title><source>Remote Sens Environ</source><year>1996</year><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>193</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>