<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Malar J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Malar. J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Malaria Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2875</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6106899</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2452</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12936-018-2452-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Blood feeding behaviour comparison and contribution of <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> and <italic>Anopheles gambiae,</italic> two sibling species living in sympatry, to malaria transmission in Alibori and Donga region, northern Benin, West Africa</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>Martin C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Salako</surname><given-names>Albert Sourou</given-names></name><address><email>albertsourousalako@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dagnon</surname><given-names>Fortun&#x000e9;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>A&#x000ef;kpon</surname><given-names>Rock</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kouletio</surname><given-names>Michelle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sovi</surname><given-names>Arthur</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sezonlin</surname><given-names>Michel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.473220.0</institution-id><institution>Centre de Recherche entomologique de Cotonou (CREC), </institution></institution-wrap>Cotonou, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0382 0205</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412037.3</institution-id><institution>Facult&#x000e9; des Sciences et Techniques de l&#x02019;Universit&#x000e9; d&#x02019;Abomey-Calavi, </institution></institution-wrap>Abomey-Calavi, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>US President&#x02019;s Malaria Initiative, US Agency for International Development, Cotonou, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Universit&#x000e9; Nationale des Sciences, Technologies, Ing&#x000e9;nierie et Math&#x000e9;matiques, Abomey, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>PMI VectorLink Project, Abt associates, Bamako, Mali </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>307</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The main goal of this study was to assess the blood feeding behaviour and the contribution <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> and <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>, 2 sibling species of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> sensu stricto. present and living in sympatry in 2 regions of northern Benin targeted for indoor residual spraying (IRS).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The study was carried out in 6 districts of 2 regions of Benin (Alibori and Donga). Human landing catches (HLC) performed inside and outside of the households and pyrethrum spray captures (PSC) carried out in bedrooms were used to sample vector populations (<italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>). Collected mosquitoes were analysed to estimate the human biting rate indoors and outdoors, the circumsporozoite antigen positivity, and the anthropophagic index using ELISA methodology. Polymerase chain reaction was used to estimate the frequency of the knockdown resistance (<italic>kdr</italic>) L1014F and the <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> mutations, 2 markers associated respectively with pyrethroids and carbamate/organophosphate insecticide resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A higher blood feeding rate was observed in <italic>An. gambiae</italic> compared to <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> as well as, a non-pronounced outdoor biting behavior in both species. The latter showed similar anthropophagic and sporozoite rates. However the analysis indicates a seasonal difference in the contribution of each species to malaria transmission associated with shifts in resting behaviour. <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> females accounted for most of the detected infections: 86% in Alibori and 79% in Donga, during the dry season <italic>versus</italic> 14.4% and 21.2%, respectively for <italic>An. gambiae</italic> during the same period. This relationship was reversed in Donga during the rainy season (66% for <italic>An. gambiae</italic> against 34% for <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>). Results also indicated lower frequencies of <italic>kdr</italic> L1014F and <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> in <italic>An. coluzzii versus An. gambiae.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Despite similarity in some parameters related to malaria transmission in both surveyed species, <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> is potentially a more important malaria vector because of high density in the region. It is also characterized by lower frequencies of the <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> mutation than is <italic>An. gambiae</italic>. The ongoing use of pirimiphos methyl (organophosphate) for IRS should continue to show a good impact in Alibori and Donga because of the very low level of the <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> mutation in both species.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></kwd><kwd>Sporozoite index</kwd><kwd>Entomological Inoculation Rate</kwd><kwd>Alibori</kwd><kwd>Donga</kwd><kwd>Benin</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5"><italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> sensu lato (s.l.) is a complex of 8 species, which contribute differently to malaria transmission. Within the complex, <italic>An. gambiae</italic> sensu stricto (s.s.), the nominotypical member, is comprised of 2 species based on molecular evidence: <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> (the <italic>An. gambiae</italic> molecular &#x02018;M form&#x02019;) and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (the &#x02018;S form&#x02019;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Heterogeneity in the vector capacity of each species is due to a highly diverse bio-ecology: feeding on humans or cattle, resting indoors or outdoors. According to Akogb&#x000e9;to [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and Awolola et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], what makes <italic>An. gambiae</italic> an efficient vector is that it is highly anthropomorphic and endophilic, thereby frequently coming into contact with humans. In addition to its possibility of adaptation to various environments due to its genetic variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.s. is a very efficient vector of malaria, especially in tropical Africa. Nonetheless, other sibling species of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> complex play a role, albeit a lesser role, in malaria transmission, for example, <italic>Anopheles melas</italic> in West Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Studies on bio-ecology of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.l. have shown statistical differences of sporozoite index between different populations sibling species of the complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]). Moreover, the main factor of vector competence of a mosquito to a parasite is its ability to offer a suitable physicochemical environment for the development of the parasite during the sporogonic cycle.</p><p id="Par7">The objective of this study was to assess the blood feeding behaviour and the contribution in malaria transmission of each of the 2 sibling species (<italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic>) present and living in sympatry in 2 regions of Benin, targeted for indoor residual spraying (IRS) on malaria transmission prior to the implementation of IRS. Given that the density of each of the 2 sibling species varies from one season to another, the more abundant species during the 3&#x02013;6&#x000a0;months period following spraying when IRS residual efficacy operates, should be more influenced by this intervention.</p><p id="Par8">The study is also evaluating, before spraying, the frequency of mutations associated with organophosphates resistance in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae,</italic> two sibling vector species living in sympatry in the study area and which were likely exposed to the same selection pressure for resistance. Indeed, if low frequencies of resistance mechanisms are observed in a given species, this may be sign that IRS with an organophosphate product could have a positive impact on the control of this species as previously observed by Aikpon et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">Detailed information on bio-ecology of vectors and their role in disease transmission are important for implementation of good vector control strategies or for their evaluation. In the study area (Alibori and Donga region, in the northern Benin) targeted for IRS campaign, where the 2 species are sympatric, the recorded data will be used as the comparison basis of the impact of IRS on each of the 2 <italic>Anopheles</italic> populations.</p><sec id="Sec2"><title>Study area</title><p id="Par10">The study was conducted in 6 districts of the northern Benin: Kandi, Gogounou and Segbana in Alibori region, and Djougou, Copargo and Ouake in Donga region (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The 2 regions are characterized by one dry season (December to May) and one rainy season (June to November). The annual mean rainfall is 1300&#x000a0;mm and the mean monthly temperature varies between 23 and 40&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The Alibori region has more rivers than the Donga region. In Alibori, the soil is sandy type while in Donga, it is clayey type. In both regions the major economic activity is agriculture, including the production of cotton, maize and millet, where various classes of pesticides are used for pest control.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Map of Benin showing the Alibori and Donga regions and the sites of mosquito collections</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2018_2452_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Mosquito sampling and laboratory analysis</title><p id="Par11">HLC carried out indoors and outdoors from 21.00 to 06.00&#x000a0;h and PSC performed inside houses from 06.00 to 09.00 were used to sample vector populations during the rainy (June&#x02013;October 2016) and dry (November&#x02013;May 2016) seasons in the 6 districts targeted for IRS implementation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Human landing catches (HLC) and mosquito analysis</title><p id="Par12">In each district, mosquito sampling was performed in 2 villages: one village in the central part of the district and one village at the periphery. In each village, mosquitoes were collected by adult volunteers in 2 houses for 2 consecutive nights, every month for 5&#x000a0;months per season, with one adult volunteer placed indoors and another placed outdoors. All <italic>Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes caught during the night were identified to species using the method described by Gilles and de Meillon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. To assess the infection status of each species, the head-thoraxes were tested using enzyme-linked immunosorbent analysis (ELISA) according to Wirtz et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] to estimate circumsporozoite (CS) antigen of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>, the major malaria parasite occurring in the study area. Abdomens from females of the vector species were used for PCR analyses, to identify the sibling species of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.s. (<italic>An. gambiae, An. coluzzii</italic>). The indoor and outdoor human biting rate (HBR: also named <italic>ma</italic>) of each species was calculated to estimate the feeding behaviour of the 2 species.</p><p id="Par13">In the study, malaria transmission in both the Alibori and Donga regions is expressed in terms of entomological inoculation rate (EIR&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>ma</italic>&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>s</italic>) due to both of the 2 species. The contribution of each species is the EIR calculated for the species divided by those of the 2 species&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Indoor pyrethrum spray catches and mosquito analysis</title><p id="Par14">In each village, 20 houses were selected for mosquito collection using indoor pyrethrum spray catches (PSC). Selected houses were sprayed with pyrethrum (mixed with water) and a white canvas was placed on the floor to collect the mosquitoes that were killed. After 10&#x000a0;min, all of the fallen mosquitoes were collected from the floor and placed in petri dishes. Fed, unfed, gravid, and half-gravid females of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> were counted to estimate the endophagy behaviour, defined as the proportion of each species resting in houses after blood feeding. Fed mosquitoes were also used to estimate the anthropophagic index in terms of the human blood meal rate using ELISA-blood-meal method. The anthropophagic index represents the proportion of blood meals derived from humans by mosquito vectors used to estimate human biting habit.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>PCR detection of <italic>kdr</italic> L1014F and <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> mutations</title><p id="Par15">The abdomens of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> females were used to identify the presence of L1014F (<italic>kdr</italic>) and G119S (<italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic>) mutations. This was performed using PCR&#x02013;RFLP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] to estimate the frequency of <italic>kdr</italic> L1014F mutation in the sodium channel, which is associated with resistance to pyrethroid insecticides, and that of the <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> mutation, which is associated with carbamate and organophosphate insecticide resistance.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par16">The human biting index (<italic>ma</italic>) (number of <italic>Anopheles</italic> per person and per night), room density (number of <italic>Anopheles</italic> collected in a room) and the circumsporozoite protein (CSP) positive rate were calculated for each species. The human blood-feeding rate was calculated using mosquitoes collected by PSC by dividing the number of fed and half-fed mosquitoes collected by the number of the total of mosquitoes collected. The CSP positive rate (% CS+) was calculated as the proportion of mosquitoes found to be positive for CSP. The EIR was defined as <italic>Anopheles</italic> density by the CSP and estimated as the number of infectious bites per human per night or per month. A Chi square test with the MINITAB statistical software (Version 12.2) was used to compare the proportions. The genotypic differentiation of <italic>kdr</italic> and <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> loci was tested using the Fischer exact test implemented in GenePop software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], and the Fisher test was used to compare these frequencies. An analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed to compare the entomological estimates (<italic>ma</italic>, EIR, CSP) among the 2 species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Ethical consideration</title><p id="Par17">Permission was sought from households to perform collections in their rooms. In addition, community consent had been obtained beforehand in all the villages. The volunteer mosquito collectors gave their consent before participating in the study. They were also subjected to regular medical check-ups with preventive malaria treatment. They were all vaccinated against yellow fever. This study received the approval of the Ethical Institutional Committee of the Centre for Entomological Research of Cotonou (CREC), Ministry of Health.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Distribution of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> complex in the two regions</title><p id="Par18">All samples of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.l. collected by HLC and PSC were used for species identification. In total, 4182 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.l. were analysed by PCR for species identification. Two species of the <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.s. were identified: <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). After 1&#x000a0;year of mosquito collection throughout both dry and rainy seasons, <italic>An. gambiae</italic> represented 54.0% (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;2260) of the overall <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.s. population compared to 46.0% (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;1922) for <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>. However, the predominant species differed from one region to another. In Alibori, <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> represented 62.2% (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;1033) of the overall <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.s. population compared to 37.8% (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;625) for <italic>An. gambiae</italic>. In Donga, <italic>An. gambiae</italic> was the most abundant at 64.7% (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;1631).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Seasonal distribution of <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> and <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> in Alibori and Donga, two regions of northern Benin</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2018_2452_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par19">Both of the sibling species were present throughout the dry and rainy seasons in both regions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). During the dry season (January to June), <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> predominated in both the Alibori and Donga regions. However, during the rainy season, there were regional differences in the predominant species: during the rainy season in Donga, there was a high frequency (79.0%) of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> whereas during the rainy season in Alibori there was a relatively high frequency (53.0%) of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Comparison of (CS) antigen index for <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> during the dry and rainy seasons</title><p id="Par20">More than 4000 head-thoraxes of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> were tested using ELISA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] for the presence of CS of <italic>P. falciparum.</italic> Various samples of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (from HLC and PSC collection) were analysed in order to obtain enough mosquitoes (4182 head-thoraxes) for comparison.</p><p id="Par21">During the dry season, rates of <italic>P. falciparum</italic> CS&#x02009;+&#x02009;were similar for <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (9.3%: 5 out of 54 thoraxes were CS+) and <italic>An. coluzzii (</italic>5.5%: 21 out of 384) (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.426) in Alibori. Results were statistically different in Donga during the dry season with a higher rate of <italic>P. falciparum</italic> CS&#x02009;+&#x02009;for <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (9.6%: 50 out of 520) compared to <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (4.9%: 12 out of 247) (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Percentage of <italic>P. falciparum</italic> circumsporozoite antigen in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> during the dry and the rainy seasons</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Regions</th><th align="left">Species</th><th align="left"/><th align="left">Dry season (May&#x02013;Jun&#x02013;Jan&#x02013;Feb)</th><th align="left">p-value</th><th align="left">Rainy season (Jul&#x02013;Aug&#x02013;Oct)</th><th align="left">p-value</th><th align="left">Total</th><th align="left">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="8">Alibori</td><td align="left" rowspan="4">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">54</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="8">0.426</td><td align="left">575</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="8">0.096</td><td align="left">629</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="8">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">42</td><td align="left">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">9.26</td><td align="left">7.30</td><td align="left">7.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC-95% [IS %]</td><td align="left">[3.07&#x02013;20.30]</td><td align="left">[5.31&#x02013;9.75]</td><td align="left">[5.54&#x02013;9.81]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">384</td><td align="left">649</td><td align="left">1033</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">66</td><td align="left">87</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">5.47</td><td align="left">10.17</td><td align="left">8.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC-95% [IS %]</td><td align="left">[3.41&#x02013;8.24]</td><td align="left">[7.95&#x02013;12.76]</td><td align="left">[6.80&#x02013;10.28]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="8">Donga</td><td align="left" rowspan="4">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">247</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="8">0.002</td><td align="left">1384</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="8">1</td><td align="left">1631</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="8">0.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">132</td><td align="left">144</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">4.86</td><td align="left">9.54</td><td align="left">8.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC-95% [IS %]</td><td align="left">[2.53&#x02013;8.33]</td><td align="left">[8.04&#x02013;11.21]</td><td align="left">[7.49&#x02013;10.31]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">520</td><td align="left">369</td><td align="left">889</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">85</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">9.62</td><td align="left">9.49</td><td align="left">9.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC-95% [IS %]</td><td align="left">[7.22&#x02013;12.48]</td><td align="left">[6.69&#x02013;12.94]</td><td align="left">[7.7&#x02013;11.69]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="8">Alibori-Donga</td><td align="left" rowspan="4">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">301</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="8">0.252</td><td align="left">1959</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="8">0.389</td><td align="left">2260</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="8">0.607</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">174</td><td align="left">191</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">5.65</td><td align="left">8.88</td><td align="left">8.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC-95% [IS %]</td><td align="left">[3.32&#x02013;8.89]</td><td align="left">[7.65&#x02013;10.23]</td><td align="left">[7.33&#x02013;9.67]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">904</td><td align="left">1018</td><td align="left">1922</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left">101</td><td align="left">172</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">7.85</td><td align="left">9.92</td><td align="left">8.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC-95% [IS %]</td><td align="left">[6.18&#x02013;9.80]</td><td align="left">[8.15&#x02013;11.92]</td><td align="left">[7.71&#x02013;10.31]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>p&#x02009;=&#x02009;p-value of comparison of <italic>CircumSporozoite</italic> (CS) <italic>antigen index for Plasmodium falciparum</italic> of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic></p><p><italic>Jun</italic> June, <italic>Jul</italic> July, <italic>Aug</italic> August, <italic>Oct</italic> October, <italic>Jan</italic> January, <italic>Feb</italic> February</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par22">During the rainy season, rates of <italic>P. falciparum</italic> CS&#x02009;+&#x02009;were similar for both species in Alibori (<italic>An. gambiae</italic>: 7.3%: 42 out of 575) thoraxes were CS&#x02009;+&#x02009;; <italic>An. coluzzi</italic>: 10.2%, 66 out of 649) (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.096) and in Donga (<italic>An. gambiae</italic>: 9.5%, 132 out of 1384; <italic>An. coluzzi:</italic> 9.5%, 35 out of 369) (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par23">No differences in CS&#x02009;+&#x02009;between species were observed in either region when data were cumulated over both seasons: 7.5%: 47 out of 629 thoraxes were CS&#x02009;+&#x02009;for <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and 8.4%: 87 out of 1033 for <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> in Alibori (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.55). In Donga, CS&#x02009;+&#x02009;for <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> were 8.8% (144 out of 1631) and 9.6% (85 out of 889), respectively (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.59) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par24">In total, 191 (8.5%) of 2260 thoraces of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> analysed in the two regions by ELISA-CSP were positive for <italic>P. falciparum</italic> CS antigen (Is&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.5%). For <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>, 172 (8.9%) of 1922 thoraces were positive for <italic>P. falciparum</italic> CS antigen (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Contribution of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> to malaria transmission expressed in terms of the EIR</title><p id="Par25">The intensity of the malaria transmission due to each species is expressed in terms of EIR, which is equal to <italic>ma</italic> times the sporozoite rate. As the <italic>ma</italic> parameter depends on the season, the EIR due to each species was assessed for the dry season when <italic>ma</italic> is expected to be low and for the rainy season when <italic>ma</italic> is expected to be high.</p><p id="Par26">In both the Alibori and Donga regions, <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> accounts for most malaria transmission during the dry season. In Alibori, <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> accounts for 85.6% of malaria transmission during the dry season (EIR&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.61 infected bite per man per month) compared to 14.3% (EIR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.27/month). In Donga, <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> account for 78.8% (EIR&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.20/month) and 20.2% (EIR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.81/month) of malaria transmission in the dry season, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Contribution of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> expressed in the proportion of Entomological Inoculation Rate due to each species in Alibori and Donga during the dry season</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2018_2452_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par27">During the rainy season, <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> continues to account for most malaria transmission in the Alibori region as occurred during the dry season: <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> accounts for 64.8% (14.37 infected bites) of malaria transmission compared to 35.2% (7.81 infected bites) for <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). However, in the Donga region, inverted results were observed showing a higher EIR due to <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (77.7%: EIR&#x02009;=&#x02009;26.25 infected bites/month) as compared to <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). When cumulated data, which were registered during the 7&#x000a0;months of the study, the observed EIR trend during the dry season was confirmed due to the high <italic>ma</italic> of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> during this period: the EIR of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>&#x000a0;was 2 times higher than <italic>An. gambiae</italic> in Alibori (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0043) and 2 times lower in Donga (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.000084) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Malaria transmission expressed in terms of Entomological Inoculation Rate (EIR) in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> in Alibori and Donga</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Regions</th><th align="left">Species</th><th align="left"/><th align="left">Dry season (May&#x02013;Jun&#x02013;Jan&#x02013;Feb)</th><th align="left">p-value</th><th align="left">Rainy season (Jul&#x02013;Aug&#x02013;Oct)</th><th align="left">p-value</th><th align="left">Total</th><th align="left">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="10">Alibori</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">12</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="10">0.125</td><td align="left">362</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="10">
<italic>0.016</italic>
</td><td align="left">374</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="10">
<italic>0.0043</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">8.33</td><td align="left">6.91</td><td align="left">6.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ma/month</td><td align="left">3.21</td><td align="left">113.12</td><td align="left">53.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EIR/month</td><td align="left">0.27</td><td align="left">7.81</td><td align="left">3.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">135</td><td align="left">446</td><td align="left">581</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">52</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">4.44</td><td align="left">10.31</td><td align="left">8.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ma/month</td><td align="left">36.16</td><td align="left">139.37</td><td align="left">83.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EIR/month</td><td align="left">1.61</td><td align="left">14.37</td><td align="left">7.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="10">Donga</td><td align="left" rowspan="5">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">147</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="10">
<italic>0.03</italic>
</td><td align="left">846</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="10">
<italic>0.000054</italic>
</td><td align="left">993</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="10">
<italic>0.000084</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">84</td><td align="left">87</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">2.04</td><td align="left">9.93</td><td align="left">8.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ma/month</td><td align="left">1.31</td><td align="left">264.37</td><td align="left">143.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EIR/month</td><td align="left">0.810</td><td align="left">26.25</td><td align="left">12.54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</td><td align="left">Thorax</td><td align="left">214</td><td align="left">257</td><td align="left">471</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thorax+</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Is (%)</td><td align="left">5.607</td><td align="left">9.339</td><td align="left">7.643</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ma/month</td><td align="left">57.32</td><td align="left">80.31</td><td align="left">67.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EIR/month</td><td align="left">3.20</td><td align="left">7.50</td><td align="left">5.19</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Italic values indicate significance of p value (p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05)</p><p>p&#x02009;=&#x02009;p-value of comparison of <italic>CircumSporozoite</italic> (CS) antigen index for <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic></p><p><italic>Jun</italic> June, <italic>Jul</italic> July, <italic>Aug</italic> August, <italic>Oct</italic> October, <italic>Jan</italic> January, <italic>Feb</italic> February</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Contribution of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> expressed in the proportion of Entomological Inoculation Rate due to each species in Alibori and Donga during the rainy season</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2018_2452_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Contribution of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> expressed in the proportion of Entomological Inoculation Rate due to each species in Alibori and Donga during the two seasons</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2018_2452_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Indoor and outdoor biting behaviour of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic></title><p id="Par28">More than 2400 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> collected by HLC and analysed by PCR showed that, the biting behaviour of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> was variable according to the location (indoors or outdoors). Out of 1302 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> collected by HLC in Alibori and Donga, 57.7% (752/1302) were collected indoors compared to 42.3% (550/1302) outdoors (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">3</xref>). As for <italic>An. coluzzii,</italic> a similar biting behaviour was observed indoors and outdoors with respectively: 51.6% (575/1114) and 48.4% (539/1114) of specimens (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.13), after cumulating data of both regions (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). During the dry season, the biting behaviour of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> was higher indoors with 56.4% (216/383) of specimens as compared to outdoors (43.6%) (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0004). In the same season, the biting behavior was similar indoors and outdoors (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.25) for <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Number of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> collected indoors and outdoors by HLC</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Seasons</th><th align="left">Species</th><th align="left">Indoors</th><th align="left">Outdoors</th><th align="left">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Alibori</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Dry season</td><td align="left"><italic>An. gambiae</italic> (N)</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (N)</td><td align="left">59</td><td align="left">74</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Rainy season</td><td align="left"><italic>An. gambiae</italic> (N)</td><td align="left">212</td><td align="left">164</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (N)</td><td align="left">256</td><td align="left">176</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Donga</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Dry season</td><td align="left"><italic>An. gambiae</italic> (N)</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left">51</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (N)</td><td align="left">157</td><td align="left">93</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Rainy season</td><td align="left"><italic>An. gambiae</italic> (N)</td><td align="left">472</td><td align="left">329</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (N)</td><td align="left">103</td><td align="left">196</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Both regions</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Dry season</td><td align="left"><italic>An. gambiae</italic> [% (N/T)]</td><td align="left">53.6% (67/125)</td><td align="left">46.4% (58/125)</td><td align="left">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>An. coluzzii</italic> [% (N/T)]</td><td align="left">56.4% (216/383)</td><td align="left">43.60% (167/383)</td><td align="left">
<italic>0.0004</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Rainy season</td><td align="left"><italic>An. gambiae</italic> [% (N/T)]</td><td align="left">58.11% (684/1177)</td><td align="left">41.88% (493/1177)</td><td align="left">
<italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>An. coluzzii</italic> [% (N/T)]</td><td align="left">49.11% (359/731)</td><td align="left">50.88% (372/731)</td><td align="left">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Both regions</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Both seasons</td><td align="left"><italic>An. gambiae</italic> [% (N/T)]</td><td align="left">57.7% (751/1302)</td><td align="left">42.3% (551/1302)</td><td align="left">
<italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>An. coluzzii</italic> [% (N/T)]</td><td align="left">51.6% (575/1114)</td><td align="left">48.4% (539/1114)</td><td align="left">0.13</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Italic values indicate significance of p value (p&#x0003c;0.05)</p><p><italic>N</italic> number of species collected in one location (indoors or outdoors), <italic>T</italic> total number of species collected in both locations (indoors&#x02009;+&#x02009;outdoors)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par29">During the rainy season, the trend was reversed with a similar biting behaviour indoors and outdoors (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.5) for <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and, a higher indoor biting behaviour for <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Blood feeding rate and anthropophagic index</title><p id="Par30">With PSC performed in bedrooms, a significant higher blood feeding rate [96.68% (846 of fed and half-gravid females out of 875 total females)] was observed in <italic>An. gambiae</italic> as compared to <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> [90.20% (792/878)] (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). A high and similar anthropophagic index (0.97) was observed for both species with 34/35 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> specimens and 33/34 <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> having fed on humans (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.98).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Blood feeding rate of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> collected by PSC method in Alibori and Donga</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Regions</th><th align="left" colspan="6">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="6">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">p-value</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Total collected</th><th align="left">Unfed</th><th align="left">Fed</th><th align="left">Gravid</th><th align="left">Half-gravid</th><th align="left">Blood feeding rate (%)</th><th align="left">Total collected</th><th align="left">Unfed</th><th align="left">Fed</th><th align="left">Gravid</th><th align="left">Half-gravid</th><th align="left">Blood feeding rate (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Alibori</td><td char="." align="char">235</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">216</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td char="." align="char">96.6</td><td char="." align="char">460</td><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="." align="char">358</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td char="." align="char">47</td><td char="." align="char">88.04</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0.0003</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Donga</td><td char="." align="char">640</td><td char="." align="char">13</td><td char="." align="char">604</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">15</td><td char="." align="char">96.72</td><td char="." align="char">418</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td char="." align="char">347</td><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="." align="char">40</td><td char="." align="char">92.58</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0.003</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Both regions</td><td char="." align="char">875</td><td char="." align="char">18</td><td char="." align="char">820</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td char="." align="char">26</td><td char="." align="char">96.68</td><td char="." align="char">878</td><td char="." align="char">31</td><td char="." align="char">705</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">87</td><td char="." align="char">90.20</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&#x0003c;</italic>&#x02009;<italic>0.0001</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Italic values indicate significance of p value (p&#x0003c;0.05)</p><p>p-value: p-value of comparison of the feeding rate of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> to that of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> by region</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Frequency of <italic>kdr</italic> mutation in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> populations</title><p id="Par31">A total of 557 females of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and 423 <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> were analysed for L1014F <italic>kdr</italic> mutation and G119S mutation (<italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> gene) using PCR&#x02013;RFLP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The frequency of the 2 mutations is higher in <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (0.82 for <italic>kdr</italic> and 0.03 for <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic>) than in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (0.73 for <italic>kdr</italic> and 0.01 for <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic>) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Distribution of Knock-down resistance (<italic>Kdr</italic>) and <italic>Ace</italic>-<italic>1R</italic> frequencies in <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> in Alibori and Donga</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Regions</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Species</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Number tested</th><th align="left" colspan="5">
<italic>Mutation KdrL1014F</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="5">
<italic>Mutation Ace 1R</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left">RR</th><th align="left">RS</th><th align="left">SS</th><th align="left">F (Kdr)</th><th align="left">p-value</th><th align="left">RR</th><th align="left">RS</th><th align="left">SS</th><th align="left">F (Ace 1)</th><th align="left">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Alibori</td><td align="left">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">170</td><td char="." align="char">123</td><td char="." align="char">34</td><td char="." align="char">13</td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">
<italic>0.0024</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td char="." align="char">160</td><td char="." align="char">0.03</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">0.1381</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">271</td><td char="." align="char">143</td><td char="." align="char">90</td><td char="." align="char">38</td><td char="." align="char">0.69</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">264</td><td char="." align="char">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Donga</td><td align="left">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">387</td><td char="." align="char">272</td><td char="." align="char">93</td><td char="." align="char">22</td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">0.153</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="." align="char">367</td><td char="." align="char">0.03</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">0.2981</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">152</td><td char="." align="char">102</td><td char="." align="char">34</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td char="." align="char">0.78</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">148</td><td char="." align="char">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Total</td><td align="left">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">557</td><td char="." align="char">395</td><td char="." align="char">127</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">
<italic>0.0032</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">30</td><td char="." align="char">527</td><td char="." align="char">0.03</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">
<italic>0.0483</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">423</td><td char="." align="char">245</td><td char="." align="char">124</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="." align="char">0.73</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td char="." align="char">412</td><td char="." align="char">0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Italic values indicate significance of p value (p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05)</p><p>p&#x02009;=&#x02009;p-value of comparison of the frequencies <italic>Kdr</italic> and <italic>Ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> between <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par32">In Africa, vector surveillance is an integral component to the planning, implementation, monitoring, and the evaluation of vector control interventions. To assist with this goal, the current study was initiated in an area of Benin targeted for an IRS campaign to provide baseline data that could be used to help evaluate the impact and efficacy of IRS in the future.</p><p id="Par33"><italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> complex is the most important malaria vector in sub-Saharan Africa and has 4 species that occur in West Africa: <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>, <italic>An. gambiae</italic>, <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> and <italic>An. melas</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In the area investigated by the current study only 2 species maintain malaria transmission: <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>. Both species are present year-round with a strong predominance of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> in dry season. Despite the 2 study areas having a similar climate, there was a disparity in the distribution of the 2 species during the rainy season with a strong occurrence of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> in the Alibori region compared with the Donga region. The low proportions of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> in the dry season may be due to temporary breeding sites that dry up, in addition to the presence of permanent and semi-permanent breeding sites more favourable to the development of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> larvae.</p><p id="Par34">Despite the large number of <italic>An. gambiae s.s</italic>. specimens (more than 4000) collected by HLC and PSC that were analysed by PCR, no <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> was found. Only one specimen of <italic>Anopheles nili</italic> was morphologically identified in Alibori and Donga. The absence of <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> in the study area could be due to the exophilic and zoophilic behaviour of this species and to its gradual disappearance in some environments in West Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], particularly in northern Benin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Indeed, in 1992, Akogbeto [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] reported its presence in sympatry with <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.s. in northern Benin, but in 2010, A&#x000ef;kpon et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] reported its disappearance in the same region.</p><p id="Par35">The overall biting rate of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> was not higher outdoors than indoors in both the rainy and dry seasons, which suggests an important role for ITNs in the effort to prevent malaria. However, despite the presence of ITNs in houses in the study area, <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.s. maintained a high index of human-vector contact as indicated by high human biting rates, which could be a result of its resistance to the pyrethroid insecticides used to treat bed nets.</p><p id="Par36">The significant higher blood feeding rate observed in <italic>An. gambiae</italic> as compared to <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> indoors (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001) would be likely due to a higher ability of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> to bite and feed on humans inside houses. Indeed, the collected HLC data show an overall more pronounced indoor man-vector contact in <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (56.6%: 751/1326) as compared to <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (43.4%: 575/1326) (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). This result is similar to that obtained in Ghana by Tuno et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] who showed that <italic>An. gambiae</italic> bit people inside dwellings more than did <italic>An. melas</italic>.</p><p id="Par37">The fact that, the majority (&#x02265;&#x02009;90%) of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> collected indoors were blood-fed with a high and similar anthropophagic index (0.97), mirrors results from similar studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. As a result of both species having similar attractions to humans, <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> had similar sporozoitic indexes at 8.5 and 8.9%, respectively (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60). This result is reminiscent of that of Carnevale et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] who showed the same infection rate in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> in Lobito, Angola. Given the similar affinity for humans and the large number of specimens (more than 4000) examined through ELISA-CSP, it is likely that <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> have the same ability to offer a physicochemical environment suitable for the development of the parasite during the sporogonic cycle.</p><p id="Par38">By taking into account the fact that vector capacity of a population of <italic>Anopheles</italic> depends on several factors, in particular, the ability to foster the development of the sporogonic cycle, the contribution of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> to malaria transmission was expressed in terms of the sporozoitic index (<italic>s</italic>) and the frequency of human-vector contacts (<italic>ma</italic>). Based on the calculated EIRs, <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> is involved in 85.6% of malaria transmission in Alibori and 78.8% of transmission in the Donga during the dry season, compared to only 14.4 and 21.2% for <italic>An. gambiae</italic> in Alibori and Donga, respectively. Further, during the rainy season <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> continues to account for most malaria transmission in Alibori (64.8% compared to 35.2% for <italic>An. gambiae</italic>), but the role is reversed in Donga during the rainy season with a higher contribution toward malaria transmission from <italic>An. gambiae</italic> (65.7% compared to 34.3% for <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>). The variation in abundance of each vector species from one season to another could explain this. Indeed, Alibori and Donga regions are crossed by several rivers and water dams that create throughout the year (rainy and dry seasons), permanent and semi-permanent breeding sites suitable for the development of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> larvae. In addition, the Donga region is characterized by a clayey type soil, which retains water, allowing then the formation of numerous temporary breeding sites favourable to the emergence of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> as leading vector of malaria transmission in the rainy season. By against, in Alibori, the sandy type soil causes the quick infiltration of water and as a result, fewer temporary larval habitats are formed, which justifies that <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> coming from permanent and semi-permanent breeding sites continues to play the major role in malaria transmission during the rainy season in this region. As observed in Donga from dry to rainy season, the switch of the mosquito species that leads malaria transmission has also been reported in Lobito, Angola from 2005 to 2006 and, the suspected causes were environmental anthropic modifications (installation of water cisterns that disrepair over time and are used as dumps, reduction of some artificial larval habitats types favourable to <italic>An. gambiae</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par39">There have been numerous reports of resistance to pyrethroid throughout Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In Benin, the resistance of malaria vectors to pyrethroids observed first in Cotonou spread not only to central and southern regions of the country, but also to the northern parts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The lower frequency of <italic>kdr</italic> L1014F mutation in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> in Alibori could favour the impact of ITNs and result in better control of malaria in Alibori compared to Donga. However, if pirimiphos methyl (organophosphate) is used again for IRS in the study area as it was in previous years, a positive impact could be expected because of the very low level (0.01&#x02013;0.03) of the <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> mutation in both species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par40"><italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic> have been observed to have the same anthropophagic and sporozoite rates in the 2 regions. However, <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> is highly involved in malaria transmission in Alibori and Donga during the dry season as compared to <italic>An. gambiae</italic>. During the rainy season <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> was still playing the leading role in Alibori whereas, in Donga, this role is reversed with a stronger participation of <italic>An. gambiae</italic>. Overall, the blood feeding rate was higher in <italic>An. gambiae</italic> than in <italic>An. coluzzii.</italic> Moreover, data collected reveal <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> is characterized by lower frequencies of the <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> mutation than is <italic>An. gambiae</italic>. But, a good impact on malaria control in Alibori and Donga is expected if pirimiphos methyl (organophosphate) is used again for IRS in Benin as in previous years, because of the very low level of the <italic>ace</italic>-<italic>1</italic> mutation in both species.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>MCA, ASS, FD and RA designed the study. AS, ASS and RA carried out the experiments. MCA drafted the manuscript. FD, MS, MK and AS critically revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par41">The research leading to these results was financially supported by The President&#x02019;s Malaria Initiative of the US Government. We acknowledge The President&#x02019;s Malaria Initiative through USAID Cotonou, Benin. We also thank Monica Patton, Peter Thomas and Raymond Beach of the US Centers of Disease Control and Prevention for providing technical support and proofreading the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par42">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par43">The data used and/or analysed in this study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par44">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par45">The protocol of this study was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Ethics Committee of CREC (IECC). Before mosquito collectors were involved in this study, they gave their consent to participate. They were vaccinated against yellow fever, regularly checked up by a medical doctor and taken care in case of confirmed malaria case.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par46">This study was financially supported by the US President&#x02019;s Malaria Initiative (PMI) thru the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) Africa Indoor Residual Spraying Project (AIRS) Project.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par47">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coetzee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkerson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Della Tore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulibali</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Besansky</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> and <italic>Anopheles amharicus</italic>, new members of the <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> complex</article-title><source>Zootaxa.</source><year>2013</year><volume>3619</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.3619.3.2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26131476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26131476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Akogb&#x000e9;to M. Etude des aspects &#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miologiques sur la transmission du paludisme c&#x000f4;tier lagunaire au B&#x000e9;nin, Afrique de l&#x02019;Ouest. Th&#x000e8;se de doctorat &#x000e8;s-sciences, Universit&#x000e9; de Paris XI, Centre d&#x02019;Orsay; 1992.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awolola</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyewole</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Koekemoer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Coetzee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of three members of the <italic>Anopheles funestus</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) group and their role in malaria transmission</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2005</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trstmh.2004.12.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15869772?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15869772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coluzzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrarca</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Deco</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal differentiation and adaptations to human environments in the <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> complex</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><year>1979</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0035-9203(79)90036-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 394408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">394408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coluzzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrarca</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Deco</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal inversion intergradation and incipient speciation in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>Bollettino di Zoologia.</source><year>1985</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/11250008509440343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Deco</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>R&#x000e9;partition des membres du complexe <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> et leurs variants chromosomiques au B&#x000e9;nin et au Togo, Afrique occidentale</article-title><source>J Afr Zool.</source><year>1995</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>454</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laug&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Deco</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observation sur la bio&#x000e9;cologie de <italic>Anopheles melas</italic> dans un milieu c&#x000f4;tier lagunaire, B&#x000e9;nin, Afrique occidentale</article-title><source>J Afr Zool.</source><year>1995</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>406</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fontenille D, Traor&#x000e9;-Lamizana M, Cornet JP, Adam F, Lochouarn L. Activit&#x000e9;s du laboratoire ORSTOM de Zoologie M&#x000e9;dicale. Rapport sur le fonctionnement technique de l&#x02019;Institut Pasteur de Dakar; 1993.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaye</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontenille</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Konat&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bebrard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparaison de la transmission du paludisme dans deux faci&#x000e8;s &#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miologiques au S&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;gal: la zone c&#x000f4;ti&#x000e8;re sah&#x000e9;lienne et la zone m&#x000e9;ridionale soudanienne</article-title><source>Dakar M&#x000e9;dical.</source><year>1995</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9827082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9827082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salako</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>A&#x000ef;kpon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Surveillance entomologique en pr&#x000e9;lude &#x000e0; la mise en &#x00153;uvre de la pulv&#x000e9;risation intradomiciliaire dans l&#x02019;Alibori et la Donga</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>USAID/CREC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Rapport Final</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>A&#x000ef;kpon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e8;zonlin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokponon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ok&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oussou</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ok&#x000e9;-Agbo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Good performances but short lasting efficacy of Actellic 50 EC Indoor Residual Spraying (IRS) on malaria transmission in Benin, West Africa</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>256</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-7-256</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24886499?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24886499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gillies MT, de Meillon B. The anophelinae of Africa, south of the Sahara. Johannesburg: The South African Institute for Medical Research; 1968. p. 343.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wirtz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zavala</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Charoenvit</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkot</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative testing of monoclonal antibodies against <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> sporozoites for ELISA development</article-title><source>Bull World Health Organ</source><year>1967</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Favia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanfrancotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Spanos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Siden-Kiamos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of ribosomal DNA polymorphisms discriminating among chromosomal forms of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.s</article-title><source>Insect Mol Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2583.2001.00236.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11240633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11240633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rousset</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GENEPOP (version 1.2): population genetics software&#x000a0;for&#x000a0;exact tests and&#x000a0;ecumenicism</article-title><source>J Heredity.</source><year>1995</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a111573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tour&#x000e9; TY. G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique &#x000e9;cologique et capacit&#x000e9; vectorielle des membres du complexe <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> au Mali. Th&#x000e8;se de doctorat d&#x02019;Etat &#x000e8;s-science, Universit&#x000e9; Ex-Marseille, France; 1985.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>A&#x000ef;kpon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oss&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Govo&#x000e9;tchan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sovi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ok&#x000e9;-Agbo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Entomological baseline data on malaria transmission and susceptibility of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> to insecticides in preparation for Indoor Residual Spraying (IRS) in Atacora, (Benin)</article-title><source>J Parasitol Vector Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>111</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjaerandsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Badu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruppa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blood-Feeding Behavior of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and <italic>Anopheles melas</italic> in Ghana, Western Africa</article-title><source>J Med Entomol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jmedent/47.1.28</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20180305?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20180305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padonou</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gbedjissi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadouleton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Azondekon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Razack</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Oussou</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decreased proportions of indoor feeding and endophily in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.l. populations following the indoor residual spraying and insecticide-treated net interventions in Benin (West Africa)</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>262</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-5-262</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23151270?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23151270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ototo</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbigi</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanjala</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Githeko</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surveillance of malaria vector population density and biting behavior in Western Kenya</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>244</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12936-015-0763-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26082138?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26082138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padonou</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sezonlin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gbedjissi</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Azondekon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Djenontin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biology of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and insecticide resistance: entomological study for a large scale of indoor residual spraying in south east Benin</article-title><source>J Parasitol Vector Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>A&#x000ef;kpon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Agossa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Oss&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oussou</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>A&#x000ef;zoun</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ok&#x000e9;-Agbo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bendiocarb resistance in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.l. populations from Atacora department in Benin, West Africa: a threat for malaria vector control</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>192</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-6-192</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23803527?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23803527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gnanguenon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Govoetchan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Agossa</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Oss&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oke-Agbo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Azondekon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transmission patterns of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> by <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> in Benin</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>444</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-13-444</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25412948?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25412948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carnevale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Toto</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Besnard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatio-temporal variations of <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An gambiae</italic> and their <italic>Plasmodium</italic> infectivity rates in Lobito</article-title><source>Angola. J Vect Ecol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvec.12147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nwane</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Etang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chouaibou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Toto</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerah-hinzoumbe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mimpfoundi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trends in DDT and pyrethroid resistance in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.s. populations from urban and agro-industrial settings in southern Cameroon</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>163</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-9-163</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19793389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19793389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koffi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahoua Alou</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Koffi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabran</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kon&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping insecticide resistance in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.l. from C&#x000f4;te d&#x02019;Ivoire. Mapping insecticide resistance in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.l. from C&#x000f4;te d&#x02019;Ivoire</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>19</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-017-2546-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29310704?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29310704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathias</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochomo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Atieli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ombok</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabie Bayoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Olang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial and temporal variation in the <italic>kdr</italic> allele L1014S in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.s. and phenotypic variability in susceptibility to insecticides in western Kenya</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-10-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21235783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21235783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hien</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soma</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hema</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayili</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Namountougou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnankin&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evidence that agricultural use of pesticides selects pyrethroid resistance within <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.l. populations from cotton growing areas in Burkina Faso, West Africa</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0173098</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0173098</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28253316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28253316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ol&#x000e9; Sangba</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Govoetchan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dide-Agossou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Oss&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evidence of multiple insecticide resistance mechanisms in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> populations in Bangui, Central African Republic</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>23</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-016-1965-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dj&#x000e8;gb&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Akoton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchigossou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahadji-Dabla</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Atoyebi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ad&#x000e9;oti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First report of the presence of L1014S Knockdown-resistance mutation in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.s. and <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> from Togo</article-title><source>West Africa. Wellcome Open Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/wellcomeopenres.13888.1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29707654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29707654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sovi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Govo&#x000e9;tchan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokponnon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hounkonnou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>A&#x000ef;kpon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Agossa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of land-use on malaria transmission in the Plateau region, southeastern Benin</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>352</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-6-352</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24330734?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24330734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gnanguenon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Agossa</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Badirou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Govoetchan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Anagonou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oke-Agbo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Malaria vectors resistance to insecticides in Benin: current trends and mechanisms involved</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>223</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-015-0833-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25886599?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25886599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yahou&#x000e9;do</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornelie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dj&#x000e8;gb&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlonsou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aboubakar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of pyrethroid resistance in malaria vectors in southern Benin following a large scale implementation of vector control interventions</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>385</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-016-1661-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27378358?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27378358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Aikpon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Azondekon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Padonou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Osse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Agossa</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Six years of experience in entomological surveillance of indoor residual spraying against malaria transmission in Benin: lessons learned, challenges and outlooks</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>242</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12936-015-0757-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26063497?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26063497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakoubou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>R&#x000e9;sistance des vecteurs du paludisme vis-&#x000e0;-vis des pyr&#x000e9;thrino&#x000ef;des utilis&#x000e9;s pour l&#x02019;impr&#x000e9;gnation des moustiquaires au B&#x000e9;nin, Afrique de l&#x02019;Ouest</article-title><source>Bull Soc Path Exot.</source><year>1999</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10399604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Manguin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brengues</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>DossouYovo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Darriet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Diabate</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Current distribution of a pyrethroid resistance gene (<italic>kdr</italic>) in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> complex from West Africa and further evidence for reproductive isolation of the Mopti form</article-title><source>Parassitologia.</source><year>1999</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10697876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10697876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x02019;guessan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brengues</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Djogbenou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiple insecticide resistance mechanisms in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> from Benin, West Africa</article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><year>2007</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2007.01.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17359927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17359927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadouleton</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Asidi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Djouaka</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bra&#x000ef;ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Agossou</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of vegetable farming: a cause of the emergence of insecticide resistance in populations of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> in urban areas of Benin</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>103</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-8-103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19442297?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19442297</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>