<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art550.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.5.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_CHOM1911 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEgr6 jpg ?><?FILEgr7 jpg ?><?FILEfx1 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 pdf ?><?FILEmmc2 xlsx ?><?FILEmmc3 xlsx ?><?FILEmmc4 xlsx ?><?FILEmmc5 xlsx ?><?FILEmmc6 xlsx ?><?FILEmmc7 xlsx ?><?FILEmmc8 pdf ?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cell Host Microbe</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cell Host Microbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cell Host &#x00026; Microbe</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1931-3128</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1934-6069</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cell Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6053594</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1931-3128(18)30318-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2018.06.006</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Modular Traits of the Rhizobiales Root Microbiota and Their Evolutionary Relationship with Symbiotic Rhizobia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garrido-Oter</surname><given-names>Ruben</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>Ryohei Thomas</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dombrowski</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Ka-Wai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>The AgBiome Team</collab><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McHardy</surname><given-names>Alice C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schulze-Lefert</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><email>schlef@mpipz.mpg.de</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="fn">7</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Plant Microbe Interactions, Max Planck Institute for Plant Breeding Research, Cologne 50829, Germany</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Cluster of Excellence on Plant Sciences, Dusseldorf 40225, Germany</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>University of Texas Austin, Marine Science Institute, Port Aransas, TX 78373, USA</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>AgBiome, 104 T.W. Alexander Drive, Building 1, Research Triangle Park, NC 27709, USA</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Computational Biology of Infection Research, Helmholtz Center for Infection Research, Braunschweig 38124, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author <email>schlef@mpipz.mpg.de</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>6</label><p id="ntpara0010">These authors contributed equally</p></fn><fn id="aff6"><label>7</label><p id="ntpara0015">Lead Contact</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="ppub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>167.e5</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><title>Summary</title><p>Rhizobia are a paraphyletic group of soil-borne bacteria that induce nodule organogenesis in legume roots and fix atmospheric nitrogen for plant growth. In non-leguminous plants, species from the Rhizobiales order define a core lineage of the plant microbiota, suggesting additional functional interactions with plant hosts. In this work, genome analyses of 1,314 Rhizobiales isolates along with amplicon studies of the root microbiota reveal the evolutionary history of nitrogen-fixing symbiosis in this bacterial order. Key symbiosis genes were acquired multiple times, and the most recent common ancestor could colonize roots of a broad host range. In addition, root growth promotion is a characteristic trait of Rhizobiales in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, whereas interference with plant immunity constitutes a separate, strain-specific phenotype of root commensal Alphaproteobacteria. Additional studies with a tripartite gnotobiotic plant system reveal that these traits operate in a modular fashion and thus might be relevant to microbial homeostasis in healthy roots.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="fx1"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0010">Comparative genomics of &#x0003e;1,300 Rhizobiales isolated from diverse plant hosts</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">Commensalism predates nitrogen-fixing nodule symbiosis in rhizobia</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0020">Root growth promotion is a conserved trait of commensal Rhizobiales</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0025">Microbiota members exhibit strain-specific interference of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> immune responses</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025"><p>Garrido-Oter, Nakano, Dombrowski, et&#x000a0;al. employ comparative genomics of &#x0223c;1,000 Rhizobiales strains that were isolated from diverse plant species to reconstruct the evolutionary history of nitrogen-fixing symbiosis. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> re-colonization experiments reveal that root growth promotion and interference with host immune responses are modular traits of the root microbiota.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>microbiota</kwd><kwd>rhizobiales</kwd><kwd>symbiosis</kwd><kwd>commensalism</kwd><kwd>plant immunity</kwd><kwd>phylogenomics</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><p id="misc0010">Published: July 11, 2018</p></notes></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0030">Extracellular non-self perception in plants is typically mediated by plasma membrane-bound pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) that detect conserved microbial epitopes, termed microbe-associated molecular patterns (MAMPs) (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Boller and Felix, 2009</xref>). Activation of a PRR by a cognate MAMP induces plant defense responses, collectively termed MAMP-triggered immunity (MTI), which limit pathogen growth (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Jones and Dangl, 2006</xref>). While early MTI responses (&#x0003c;1&#x000a0;hr), such as reactive oxygen species burst and extensive transcriptional and metabolic reprogramming, are necessary to limit bacterial growth (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>), chronic exposure of seedlings to the bacterial flagellin peptide flg22 results in MTI-mediated inhibition of shoot and root growth (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000f3;mez-G&#x000f3;mez et&#x000a0;al., 1999</xref>), which is thought to be an indirect consequence of immune signaling and to reflect growth-defense tradeoffs due to limited resources (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Huot et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Genes encoding MAMP epitopes, such as flg22, are evolutionarily conserved in bacteria with different lifestyles, but whether non-pathogenic bacteria can also elicit MTI responses and influence growth-defense tradeoffs is unclear.</p><p id="p0035">In nature, healthy plants live in intimate association with diverse bacteria, called the plant microbiota, which form taxonomically structured communities on above- and below-ground organs. Despite extensive variation at lower taxonomic ranks, a subset of bacterial lineages, designated the &#x0201c;core root microbiota,&#x0201d; are ubiquitous across a wide range of environments and host species. One of the most abundant groups is the bacterial order Rhizobiales (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Hacquard et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Yeoh et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>), which includes species known as rhizobia that engage in beneficial interactions with legumes, and are able to induce nodule organogenesis in legume roots and fix atmospheric nitrogen for plant growth. These symbiotic relationships require dedicated signaling molecules (e.g., bacterial Nod factors and root-secreted isoflavonoids; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Fisher and Long, 1992</xref>, <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Oldroyd, 2013</xref>) that mediate recognition of compatible symbionts to initiate nodule organogenesis, bacterial accommodation, and subsequent transcriptional and metabolic reprogramming in both partners (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Colebatch et&#x000a0;al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Oldroyd et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Udvardi and Poole, 2013</xref>). Interestingly, rhizobia are also able to suppress legume immunity during establishment of symbiosis (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Kawaharada et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Liang et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Okazaki et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). This raises the questions of whether Rhizobiales that associate with the roots of non-legumes&#x000a0;also possess the genetic toolkit required for symbiosis and if they are capable of interfering with root development and immune responses.</p><p id="p0040">To date, isolation and whole-genome sequencing efforts targeting the Rhizobiales order have largely focused on strains derived from legume nodules, which are almost exclusively colonized by nitrogen-fixing symbionts. Based on these datasets, a common origin and repeated subsequent losses of symbiotic capabilities have been proposed (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Raymond et&#x000a0;al., 2004</xref>). Whether this model holds true for Rhizobiales species enriched in niches other than legume nodules is unknown. We describe here a collection of Rhizobiales isolates from plant- and soil-associated environments of unprecedented size and taxonomic diversity. We compared their whole-genome sequences with those belonging to legume symbionts and reconstructed the evolutionary history of nitrogen-fixing symbiosis in this bacterial order. In addition, large-scale binary and ternary co-inoculation experiments of germ-free <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> plants and representative native root commensals from Rhizobiales and its sister lineages reveals modular traits and emergent properties of the root microbiota.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Conserved Microbiota Membership of the Bacterial Order Rhizobiales</title><p id="p0045">Large-scale bacterial isolation and DNA sequencing allowed us to assemble high-quality whole-genome sequences of 944 bacterial representatives of the Rhizobiales order. These strains originated from a panel of taxonomically distant plant hosts, including non-legumes,&#x000a0;as well as associated environmental sources such as soil, insects, and nematodes (<xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>). These genomes cover known Rhizobiales lineages as well as several lineages previously not present in public databases. We compared these sequences with 370&#x000a0;high-quality genome assemblies of rhizobia, mostly from legume nodule symbionts, retrieved from public databases (<xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>).</p><p id="p0050">We cross-referenced 16S rRNA gene sequences from these genomes with five previous culture-independent amplicon studies of the plant microbiota from five associated micro-habitats (soil, root, rhizosphere, leaf, and legume nodule) of a taxonomically broad set of plant hosts grown in six different soil types (<xref rid="mmc3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2)</xref> (<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Schlaeppi et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bulgarelli et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bai et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">Zgadzaj et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). This high-resolution analysis (99% sequence identity) confirmed that Rhizobiales are consistently found in high relative abundances and enriched in the root and leaf communities of phylogenetically diverse plant hosts, and are therefore part of the core plant microbiota (5%&#x02013;17% mean relative abundance; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>A). Beta-diversity analyses within the order Rhizobiales showed no clear differences between samples obtained from the root, rhizosphere, or unplanted soil (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>B), indicating a conserved adaptation of soil-borne Rhizobiales to the root environment. In contrast, we observed separation between samples from root compartments and those from leaves and legume nodules, explained by the predominance of <italic>Methylobacterium</italic> in the phyllosphere and the compatible symbiont <italic>Mesorhizobium loti</italic> in <italic>L.&#x000a0;japonicus</italic> nodules, respectively (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S1</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Conserved Microbiota Membership of the Bacterial Order Rhizobiales</p><p>Analysis of Rhizobiales community diversity using data from five previous 16S rRNA gene amplicon surveys covering root, rhizosphere, and nodule samples of a taxonomically diverse panel of plant hosts grown in a variety of natural and agricultural soils.</p><p>(A) Aggregated relative abundances of Rhizobiales in each host and compartment (n&#x000a0;= 453). Percentages show the average contribution of Rhizobiales to each subset of samples.</p><p>(B) Analysis of beta-diversity of Rhizobiales between samples across hosts and compartments (indicated by different colors and shapes, respectively). Dashed lines correspond to a Gaussian distribution fitted to each cluster (95% confidence interval). See also <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S1</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> and <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Tables S1</xref> and <xref rid="mmc3" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Evolutionarily Conserved Adaptation of Rhizobiales Sublineages to the Plant Niche</title><p id="p0055">To study the functional diversity of Rhizobiales, we performed a comparative analysis of the 1,314 whole genomes present in the dataset. Rhizobial genomes are typically mosaic and multipartite in structure due to the presence of large extra-chromosomal replicons, which result in large pan-genomes consisting of a stable and conserved core and a variable accessory gene repertoire (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Galibert et&#x000a0;al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Young et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>). Permutation-based analysis of annotated and <italic>de novo</italic> predicted gene families revealed a small core (27.30% of genes per isolate; 802 gene families on average) and a vast and largely uncharacterized pan-genome (&#x0003e;100,000 orthologous genes; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S2</xref>C and S2D). Principal coordinates analysis of genome-wide functional distances based on a calculation of presence and absence profiles of Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes-annotated genes showed a clear differentiation by taxonomic lineage but no separation between nodulating and non-nodulating strains or between root- and soil-derived isolates (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S2</xref>A). This indicates that the acquisition of symbiosis genes required for interactions with legumes was not accompanied by&#x000a0;whole-genome level signatures of adaptation. Furthermore, we found no segregation between root commensal genomes according to host species (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S2</xref>B), suggesting a broad host range of Rhizobiales microbiota members. Interestingly, a subset of strains isolated from insects showed high whole-genome level similarity to other members of the Rhizobiaceae family (black dots; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S2</xref>B and <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>), indicating that insects might act as transmission vectors for rhizobia.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Convergent Evolution of Nitrogen-Fixing Symbiosis in Rhizobiales</title><p id="p0060">To explore the evolutionary history of nitrogen-fixing symbiosis in rhizobia, we performed a phylogenomic reconstruction of ancestral characters for all sequenced genomes. First, a rooted species tree was generated from a multiple sequence alignment of conserved, single-copy, and vertically inherited genes. Next, we reconstructed the presence or absence of key symbiotic genes, the nitrogenase-encoding <italic>nif</italic> and nodulation factor <italic>nod</italic> genes, in each of the ancestral genomes along the branches of the species tree using a maximum likelihood approach (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>). We identified a high correlation of gain and loss patterns of the corresponding gene families required for legume symbiosis (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S2</xref>E), indicating concerted acquisition of these genes, likely via horizontal gene transfer. Given this pattern of evolutionarily concurrent gain and loss, we then employed the conserved <italic>nifH</italic> marker as a proxy for symbiotic capability. This revealed that the most recent common ancestor of all rhizobia likely lacked the symbiosis genetic toolkit and that the capacity to form nodules and fix atmospheric nitrogen was acquired multiple independent times after the speciation events that led to the formation of the major rhizobial taxonomic groups (green branches in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>). Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>nifH</italic> sequences found in the current dataset (n&#x000a0;= 296; <xref rid="mmc4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S3</xref>) and in non-Rhizobiales genomes (n&#x000a0;= 585) confirmed that the <italic>nifH</italic> genes found in rhizobial strains belonging to the Bradyrhizobiaceae and Rhizobiaceae families constitute two separate but closely related clades (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S2</xref>F), suggesting that one or two primordial acquisitions from unknown non-Rhizobiales donor(s) was followed by multiple horizontal gene transfers within this bacterial order.<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Convergent Evolution of Nitrogen-Fixing Symbiosis in Rhizobiales</p><p>Phylogenetic tree of rhizobia and maximum likelihood reconstruction of ancestral symbiotic genotypes. Phylogenetic tree of sequenced isolates (n&#x000a0;= 1,314) inferred from aligned single-copy marker genes using a Bayesian approach. Different taxonomic groups are indicated by the various colors in the first ring. The second ring depicts newly sequenced isolates in gray (n&#x000a0;= 944). Green branches correspond to likely gains of symbiosis genes whereas those in red correspond to probable losses. See also <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S2</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref> and <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Conserved Rhizobiales Root Growth Promotion Activity in <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic></title><p id="p0065">The enrichment of all major Rhizobiales taxonomic groups in samples from plants grown in natural soils (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>) and the lack of nodulation and nitrogen fixation capability in the majority of isolates from roots (99.74% of strains; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>) predict an ancestral mechanism of interaction with both non-leguminous and leguminous hosts that enables successful root colonization. We tested whether this association influenced host physiology by performing binary interaction experiments with a panel of Rhizobiales isolates and germ-free <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> plants co-cultivated under laboratory conditions. Guided by the phylogenomic reconstruction, we selected a subset of taxonomically and functionally diverse strains belonging to all major Rhizobiales clades of the <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> root microbiota, as well as characterized isolates for nitrogen-fixing nodule symbiosis (rhizobia) or for transfer DNA delivery into&#x000a0;plant cells (<italic>Agrobacterium</italic>) (arrowheads in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>). We grew wild-type <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> plants for 3&#x000a0;weeks on agarose media containing individual bacterial strains and measured primary root length and shoot fresh weight. The majority of the tested strains elicited robust root growth promotion (RGP) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>; <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table&#x000a0;S4</xref>). Importantly, this phenotype was detected in isolates belonging to the five major taxonomic groups that contain nitrogen-fixing nodule symbionts and <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> root-derived commensals, suggesting that this trait is characteristic of the Rhizobiales order. All isolates that do not affect root growth were undetectable in roots except for NGR234 (isolates 157, 635, and 685; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S4</xref>A), indicating that the lack of the RGP phenotype is mostly due to their inability to colonize the plant host in our experimental setup. Of note, representative <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> root-derived commensals from sister core root microbiota lineages within the Alphaproteobacteria (Caulobacterales and Sphingomonadales orders) showed no RGP phenotype despite efficient root colonization (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>A). Experiments with four <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> accessions and multiple exemplars of the most abundant Rhizobiales species found in the <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> root microbiota (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Bulgarelli et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>) indicated that RGP is a conserved trait in host and microbial populations (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S5</xref>A and S5B). Furthermore, binary interaction experiments with <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> grown under nutrient-limiting conditions revealed that Rhizobiales isolates consistently rescued phosphate starvation-induced root growth inhibition (RGI) and retained RGP under nitrogen starvation (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S5</xref>C&#x02013;S5E). This suggests that, unlike nodule symbiosis (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Carroll and Gresshoff, 1983</xref>), commensal RGP in <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> operates both under nitrogen-replete and -deficient conditions.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Conserved Rhizobiales Root Growth Promotion Activity in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></p><p>Binary interaction experiments between isolates from Rhizobiales or sister lineages and germ-free <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> wild-type plants (Col-0) grown on agarose media. Macroscopic plant phenotypes after co-cultivation on agarose media containing individual isolates were recorded after 3&#x000a0;weeks.</p><p>(A) Primary root length relative to mock control for each treatment as well as an additional heat-killed bacteria control (n&#x000a0;= 1,487).</p><p>(B) Shoot fresh weight relative to mock control for each treatment and a heat-killed bacteria control (n&#x000a0;= 247). Different shapes depict data points from seven separate full-factorial replicates. Asterisks indicate statistical significance corresponding to&#x000a0;a&#x000a0;Dunnett's test with false discovery rate correction (&#x003b1;&#x000a0;= 0.05). See also <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S4</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref> and <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Interference with Root Meristem Homeostasis and MAMP-Triggered Responses</title><p id="p0070">To gain deeper insights into how Rhizobiales commensals influence root development, we performed time-resolved developmental and transcriptomic analyses with <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E that lacks <italic>nif</italic> and <italic>nod</italic> genes (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>) and belongs to one of the most abundant operational taxonomic units enriched in the <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> root microbiota (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Bulgarelli et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). Binary interaction experiments with wild-type <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> Col-0 plants revealed an enlargement of the root meristematic zone at 14&#x000a0;days post inoculation (dpi) (approximately 2-fold; <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>), whereas cell growth in root elongation and differentiation zones remained indistinguishable from germ-free control plants (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S6</xref>A&#x02013;S6D). While antagonism between the phytohormones cytokinin and auxin is critical for root meristem homeostasis (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Dello Ioio et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>), RGP was retained in <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> mutants lacking a cytokinin receptor (<italic>ahk3-3</italic>) or cytokinin signaling components (<italic>arr1arr12</italic>; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S6</xref>E and S6F), as well as in mutants lacking either an auxin receptor (<italic>tir1-1</italic>), auxin transporters (<italic>aux1-7</italic> and <italic>axr4</italic>), or auxin signaling components (<italic>arf7arf19</italic>; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S6</xref>G).<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Interference with Root Meristem Homeostasis by <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E</p><p>(A) Confocal micrographs in the meristematic zone (MZ) (indicated by dotted lines) of the roots of transgenic <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> (Wave_131Y) expressing a plasma membrane-targeted yellow fluorescent protein inoculated with 129E or with a mock control. Arrowheads indicate the place of transition from cell division to cell elongation. Bars correspond to 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m.</p><p>(B) Number of cells within the MZ was recorded with primary root length at 5, 10, 14, 19, and 27&#x000a0;days post inoculation (n&#x000a0;= 65). Shaded areas indicate means&#x000a0;&#x000b1;SD. Letters indicate statistical significance corresponding to Tukey's HSD test (&#x003b1;&#x000a0;= 0.05) and asterisks highlight significant difference between mock and <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E-treated roots within each time point. See also <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S6</xref> and <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p><p id="p0075">To further investigate the mechanism(s) by which <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E interferes with host physiology, we performed RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) of <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> roots after inoculation with <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E. To identify plant genes responding to bacterial colonization independently of nutrient status, we collected samples at four time points (4, 8, 12, and 16 dpi) under P<sub>i</sub>-sufficient and P<sub>i</sub>-deficient conditions, both of which resulted in commensal-mediated RGP (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>A). Bacterial root colonization under both nutrient conditions was comparable and reached a plateau at 12 dpi after&#x000a0;multiplication by three log<sub>10</sub> units (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S4</xref>B). We found 1,771 genes to be differentially expressed in inoculated roots with respect to mock controls for at least one time point, demonstrating that the interaction with <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E results in dynamic host transcriptional reprogramming (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>B; <xref rid="mmc6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S5</xref>). Strikingly, four gene clusters (Clusters 1, 15, 13, and 6; 433 genes) were significantly enriched in functional categories related to immune responses and mostly downregulated by colonization of <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>C). This finding prompted us to compare our sequencing data with&#x000a0;a published dataset of transcriptional changes in roots in&#x000a0;response to flg22 treatment (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Castrillo et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). We observed a significant anti-correlation between the transcriptional response to root&#x000a0;colonization by <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E and treatment with bacterial&#x000a0;pathogen-derived flg22 (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>D), implying that this commensal can partially suppress MAMP-triggered transcriptional reprogramming.<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Transcriptional Interference with MAMP-Triggered Responses</p><p>(A) Time course measurement of primary root growth under high P<sub>i</sub> (625&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) and low P<sub>i</sub> (50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) conditions (n&#x000a0;= 2,323). Letters indicate statistical significance corresponding to Tukey's HSD test corrected for multiple comparisons (&#x003b1;&#x000a0;= 0.05).</p><p>(B) Heatmaps showing expression level (log<sub>2</sub> counts per million; log2cpm), expression pattern (gene-wise median-centered <italic>Z</italic> scores), response to <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E (log<sub>2</sub> fold changes; logFC; green and magenta colors indicate up- and downregulation, respectively) and significance (false discovery rate-corrected p&#x000a0;values &#x0003c;0.05). Co-expressed gene clusters (cluster) are defined by <italic>k-</italic>means clustering (<italic>k</italic>&#x000a0;= 21).</p><p>(C) Enrichment analysis of the clusters 1, 15, 13, and 6 identified defense-related gene ontology categories. Gene numbers used for the analysis are shown in parentheses.</p><p>(D) Comparison of plant responses to <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E at 16&#x000a0;days post inoculation and to chronic 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M flg22 treatment for 12&#x000a0;days (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Castrillo et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). DEG, differentially expressed genes. Asterisks indicate statistical significance corresponding to one sample t test (&#x003bc;&#x000a0;= 0) with Bonferroni's correction for multiple comparisons (&#x003b1;&#x000a0;= 0.05). See also <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S4</xref> and <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Tables S4</xref> and <xref rid="mmc6" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="p0080">A long-known output of MTI is RGI (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000f3;mez-G&#x000f3;mez et&#x000a0;al., 1999</xref>), which is believed to reflect a tradeoff between growth and defense in plants (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Huot et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Lozano-Dur&#x000e1;n and Zipfel, 2015</xref>). We examined whether <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E can attenuate RGI upon chronic exposure of roots to flg22 and found that the&#x000a0;commensal can fully override RGI (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>A), further supporting its capacity to suppress MAMP-induced responses. We explored the prevalence of this trait among microbiota strains belonging to Alphaproteobacteria (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>B). None out&#x000a0;of four&#x000a0;further tested Rhizobiales strains (isolates 491, 13A, 142, and 423) overcame flg22-stimulated RGI, demonstrating strain-specificity of this trait and that the RGP character and&#x000a0;MAMP response suppression are separable traits among root&#x000a0;commensal Rhizobiales. Sphingomonadales 1497 fully suppressed flg22-induced RGI despite a lack of RGP activity, revealing that suppression of MAMP-induced responses also evolved in another taxonomic lineage of the core root microbiota. The RGP activity of all non-suppressive Rhizobiales isolates was maintained in the mutant lacking the flg22 receptor FLAGELLIN SENSITIVE2 (FLS2; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000f3;mez-G&#x000f3;mez et&#x000a0;al., 1999</xref>) in the presence of this MAMP epitope, indicating that loss of bacterial RGP activity upon flg22 treatment is caused by MAMP-stimulated plant responses. Collectively, these data suggest that <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E and Sphingomonadales 1497 commensals can influence the outcome of defense-growth tradeoffs in the presence of MAMPs. To test the potential relevance of MAMP response suppression in a microbiota context, we analyzed the genome sequences of the taxonomically representative <italic>At</italic>-SPHERE culture collection of the root microbiota derived from <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> roots (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bai et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). This revealed widespread presence of protein sequences containing potential MAMP epitopes (flg22, flgII-28, elf18, csp22, and nlp20; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000f6;hm et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Cai et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Felix and Boller, 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Felix et&#x000a0;al., 1999</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Kunze et&#x000a0;al., 2004</xref>) in bacteria isolated from healthy plants (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S7</xref>A). Consistently, three out of four tested root-derived Pseudomonadales from the <italic>At</italic>-SPHERE collection activated MTI reporter gene expression in the roots of transgenic <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana CYP71A12</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:GUS</italic> seedlings (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S7</xref>B) (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Millet et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>).<fig id="fig6"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Root Commensals Interfere with MAMP-Triggered Growth Outputs</p><p>(A) FLAGELLIN SENSITIVE2 (FLS2)-dependent root growth inhibition induced by chronic exposure to 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M flg22 for 14&#x000a0;days was repressed by inoculation with <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E (n&#x000a0;= 302).</p><p>(B) The ability to interfere with flg22-induced root growth inhibition is specific to <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E and Sphingomonadales 1497 (n&#x000a0;= 1,424). Root growth promotion activity of the other Rhizobiales isolates was abolished in wild-type plants but not in the mutant lacking the flg22 receptor protein FLS2. Open (left boxplots) and closed shapes (right boxplots) within each condition indicate mock and flg22 treatment (1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M), respectively. Letters indicate statistical significance corresponding to Tukey's HSD test corrected for multiple comparisons (&#x003b1;&#x000a0;= 0.05). Different shapes depict data points from full-factorial biological replicates. See also <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S7</xref> and <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>Modularity of Commensal RGP and Interference with MAMP Responses</title><p id="p0085">The phenotypic variation observed in mono-associations with root commensals isolated from <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> grown in the same soil raised the question of whether RGP and suppression of MAMP-induced outputs operate independently in a microbial community context. We tested for potential functional modularity of these bacterial traits by selecting commensals with distinct combinations of these traits from the Rhizobiales order (isolates 129E and 142) as well as from sister clades of Alphaproteobacteria (isolates 1497 and 700) for tripartite co-inoculation experiments (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>). We measured primary root growth of <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> after co-inoculation with all single and pairwise combinations of bacterial isolates in the presence or absence of exogenous flg22. This revealed that RGP and MAMP response suppression are largely dominant traits, expressed whenever one of the bacterial partners has the respective function (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>). For example, co-inoculation of the root growth-promoting and MAMP response-suppressive isolate <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E with Caulobacterales 700, which lacks either character, resulted in&#x000a0;retention of both phenotypes. Importantly, co-inoculation of <italic>Sinorhizobium</italic> 142, which promotes root growth only in the absence of flg22, with the MAMP response-suppressive strain Sphingomonadales 1497, which lacks RGP activity, conferred a full RGP phenotype under both mock and flg22 treatments (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>). In this combination, RGP in the presence of flg22 cannot be explained by the sum of phenotypes seen in the&#x000a0;corresponding mono-associations because none of the strains&#x000a0;showed RGP under this condition, suggesting that these modular traits operate synergistically and are an emergent property of this tripartite interaction.<fig id="fig7"><label>Figure&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Modularity of Commensal Root Growth Promotion and Interference with MAMP Responses</p><p>Primary root growth under binary and tripartite inoculations was measured in the presence and absence of 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M flg22 (n&#x000a0;= 1,219). Functional profiles of tested isolates are summarized on the left. Individual isolates or combinations of isolates were mono- or co-inoculated with germ-free <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic>. Inoculated isolates are depicted in the bottom table with colors. Left and right boxplots within each condition with open and closed shapes indicate mock and flg22 treatments, respectively. Different shapes depict data points from full-factorial biological replicates. Letters indicate statistical significance corresponding to Tukey's HSD test corrected for multiple comparisons (&#x003b1;&#x000a0;= 0.05). See also <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S7</xref> and <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Adaptation to the Root Environment Predates Acquisition of Symbiosis Genes</title><p id="p0090">The majority of bacterial species within the Rhizobiales bacterial order are consistently enriched in the roots and leaves of legume and non-legume plant species and are therefore core members of the plant microbiota (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>A). The high similarity between the Rhizobiales communities in soil, root, and rhizosphere samples collected from diverse plant species grown in six different soil types suggests that the majority of soil-borne Rhizobiales are also adapted to the root environment. The prevalence of root-competent Rhizobiales in the soil biome could be explained by a positive plant-soil feedback sustained over evolutionary timescales (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Bever et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>), a process whereby plants alter the biotic qualities of the soil in which they grow. Large-scale plant growth assays revealed a consistent RGP phenotype present in isolates from all five major Rhizobiales lineages capable of colonizing <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> roots (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>A) without a negative impact on shoot fresh weight (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>B), which is indicative of a commensal lifestyle. Thus, most Rhizobiales are capable of actively interacting with the non-leguminous plant and altering their host niche rather than merely colonizing the root. Further experimentation is needed to elucidate whether the genetic basis and the mechanism of action of this prevalent commensal lifestyle is conserved across Rhizobiales species.</p><p id="p0095">Our dataset, which includes genomes from Rhizobiales strains isolated from root- and soil-associated environmental sources, complements current databases that are highly biased toward genomes of legume nodule symbionts, enabling us to perform a comprehensive analysis of the evolutionary history of the Rhizobiales order and nodule symbiosis. This revealed that the most recent common ancestor of Rhizobiales did not have key symbiosis genes, which were acquired jointly rather than sequentially (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>E). Thus, robust microbiota membership across flowering plants and a commensal lifestyle clearly predates and possibly predisposed ancestral Rhizobiales to the subsequent acquisition of genes required for nodule symbiosis. A recent study described a symbiont switch from the actinomycete <italic>Frankia</italic> to rhizobia in the non-leguminous <italic>Parasponia</italic> lineage (<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">van Velzen et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>), suggesting that extant rhizobia might have acquired the <italic>nod</italic> and <italic>nif</italic> genes from an outside donor that was already capable of nitrogen-fixing nodule symbiosis such as actinorhizal symbionts. Interestingly, members of the Burkholderiales order, belonging to the class Betaproteobacteria, and representing another core lineage of the root microbiota, have strong plant growth-promoting activity or engage in nodulation and nitrogen-fixing symbiosis with basal legumes (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Chen et&#x000a0;al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Masson-Boivin et&#x000a0;al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Moulin et&#x000a0;al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Poupin et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). This suggests that convergent evolution toward nitrogen-fixing symbiosis from a state of rhizosphere competence and microbiota membership might have relevance beyond Rhizobiales.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Lifestyle Transition from Root Commensalism to Nodule Symbiosis</title><p id="p0100">The capacity of nitrogen-fixing rhizobia to suppress immune responses in legumes has been interpreted as evidence that nodule symbiosis emerged from a pathogenic lifestyle (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Cao et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Experimental evolution studies that introduced the&#x000a0;symbiotic plasmid of the nitrogen-fixing legume symbiont <italic>Cupriavidus taiwanensis</italic> into the root pathogen <italic>Ralstonia solanacearum</italic>, both belonging to the order Burkholderiales, demonstrated a change of lifestyle from saprophytism toward mutualism, accompanied by genome remodeling that enabled efficient engagement with the symbiotic hosts (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Capela et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Remigi et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). Our combined phylogenomic (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;2</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>) and phenotypic analyses (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref>, <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), however, suggest another scenario in which an ancestral state of adaptation to the root environment and microbiota membership allowed a shift from commensalism to mutualism. This model predicts that nodulating rhizobia and Rhizobiales root commensals share conserved components for root colonization. A recent genome-wide mutagenesis screen in the alfalfa symbiont <italic>Ensifer meliloti</italic> (formerly <italic>Sinorhizobium meliloti</italic>) revealed that nearly 2% of genes, &#x0223c;80% of which were chromosomally located, were relevant for rhizosphere colonization (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Salas et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). We tested whether these rhizosphere competence genes are present in other Rhizobiales lineages and non-leguminous root commensals lacking the key symbiotic toolkit and found that, on average, 86% are conserved in each of the 1,314 genomes (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S2</xref>G). This strongly supports our hypothesis that the most recent ancestor of the Rhizobiales was already fully adapted to the root environment. Moreover, the observation that six extant members of nitrogen-fixing sublineages of rhizobia that were&#x000a0;isolated from <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> roots (<italic>Sinorhizobium</italic>/<italic>Ensifer</italic>, <italic>Mesorhizobium</italic>, and <italic>Bradyrhizobium</italic> spp.) lost key symbiotic genes suggests that a lifestyle transition from mutualism back&#x000a0;to commensalism can also occur. In addition, a recent genome-wide comparative analysis of 37 plant species identified multiple independent loss-of-function events of the crucial symbiotic regulator NODULE INCEPTION (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Griesmann et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>), further indicating that selective pressures against nitrogen-fixing nodule symbiosis can act on both the host and the symbiont.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>Diversification of Bacterial Interference with Root Development</title><p id="p0105">Our finding that commensal Rhizobiales are able to manipulate root development is consistent with recent studies showing altered <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> root architecture in association with nitrogen-fixing <italic>Mesorhizobium loti</italic> MAFF303099 or <italic>Rhizobium</italic> IRBG74 (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Poitout et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). However, whereas in those studies RGI was reported, similarly to <italic>Bradyrhizobium elkanii</italic> USDA61 in our survey, we observed an increase in primary root length with all other root-colonizing isolates (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>). We favor the view that these differences indicate <italic>bona fide</italic> mechanistic diversity in the manipulation of root development. First, while interference with root development by <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E is independent of the auxin receptor TIR1 and transporter AUX1, these proteins play a major role in the RGI activity of nodule symbionts <italic>M.&#x000a0;loti</italic> MAFF303099 and <italic>Rhizobium</italic> IRBG74 in <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic>. Second, the activation of cytokinin signaling pathways is essential for nodule organogenesis in legumes (via&#x000a0;<italic>Lj</italic>LHK1 or <italic>Mt</italic>CRE1 receptors; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Oldroyd et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>), but reduces root meristem size in <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Dello Ioio et&#x000a0;al., 2007</xref>). Finally, a well-characterized plant growth-promoting rhizobacterium (PGPR), <italic>Pseudomonas simiae</italic> WCS417, also increases root meristem size, although this bacterium confers RGI by suppressing cell elongation (<xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Zamioudis et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). Overall, these findings suggest diverse machineries underlying the alterations of host root architecture mediated by symbiotic rhizobia, PGPR <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>, and commensal Rhizobiales.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>Commensal Rhizobiales Interfere with MAMP-Induced Responses in <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> Independently of Nod Factor Production</title><p id="p0110">Comparison of our time-resolved transcriptomic data with published datasets of flg22-treated <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> roots showed that the majority of genes induced by MAMP perception were downregulated in response to <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E colonization (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>D), suggesting the ability to interfere with MAMP-induced host transcriptional responses in the absence of external MAMPs. <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E, however, lacks the bacterial type III secretion system components and Nod factor biosynthesis genes, which are necessary for MTI suppression by phytopathogenic bacteria (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Alfano and Collmer, 2004</xref>) or legume nodule symbionts (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Liang et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>), respectively. This implies that this commensal strain interferes with host MAMP-induced transcriptional responses independently from previously described MTI suppression pathways. <italic>In planta</italic> proliferation of <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E reached a plateau at 12 dpi after exponential growth by &#x0223c;3 log<sub>10</sub> units without recognizable detrimental effects on the host (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref>A and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>B), suggesting that the plant can still control bacterial proliferation despite the suppressed MAMP-induced transcriptional response in the host roots.</p><p id="p0115">Unlike RGP, representative Rhizobiales showed population-level diversity and strain-specific ability to override RGI in <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> in the presence of flg22 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>). This indicates that Rhizobiales RGP and interference with flg22-induced RGI are separable traits, excluding the possibility that RGP is merely an indirect consequence of suppressing MAMP-stimulated RGI. This also demonstrates that interference with host MAMP responses by <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref> and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) is due to a direct interaction rather than representing a general plant response to the presence of bacterial cells. In addition, an isolate from a sister lineage within the Alphaproteobacteria suppressed MAMP-activated RGI without RGP activity (isolate 1497; <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>B), showing that other members of the core root microbiota share the ability to interfere with host MAMP responses. This is further supported by previous reports showing that PGPR strains from&#x000a0;Gammaproteobacteria (<italic>P.&#x000a0;simiae</italic> WCS471; <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Stringlis et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>) and Firmicutes (<italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> FB17; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Lakshmanan et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>) can suppress <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> defense responses. Taken together with our findings, this points to a sparse but taxonomically wide distribution of suppression of MAMP-induced responses in bacterial populations isolated from the roots of healthy plants and suggests that this trait may have been frequently gained and/or lost by microbiota members. Further, this implies that the plant innate immune system can exert selective pressure on root microbiota members to acquire and maintain trait(s) involved in suppressing MAMP-induced responses. The widespread presence of sequences encoding peptides of high similarity to canonical MAMPs in the genomes of the <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> root microbiota (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S7</xref>), and the observed dominant character of the MAMP response interference trait (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>B), indicate that microbial homeostasis in healthy roots may depend on the co-occurrence of commensal community members with MTI-activating and MTI-suppressing activities.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title>Modular Traits and Emergent Properties of the Plant Microbiota</title><p id="p0120">Co-inoculation experiments of wild-type <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> plants with combinations of commensal Alphaproteobacteria isolates with varying capacities for RGP and suppression of flg22-triggered RGI reveal that these traits can act synergistically, resulting in an emergent property of the tripartite system and plant physiological outputs that cannot be predicted by the behavior of the individual strains (RGP of flg22-treated plants; <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>). This can be explained by interactions between these two traits, where host MAMP responses disable RGP either by directly interfering with bacterial activity or by reducing host sensitivity. This complex behavior might also explain the phenotypic diversity of RGP and MAMP response suppression among members of the root microbiota and suggests that these bacterial traits impact the fitness of the entire community and the host. We speculate that variation in the efficacy of field applications of PGPR results from similar complex interactions with resident microbiota members on crops (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Ansari et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). Furthermore, despite the reductionism of our experimental setup we observed complex interactions between microbial traits acting in a modular and synergistic manner. Our findings illustrate the necessity of bottom-up experimental approaches, in which populations of microbiota members are first systematically sampled in an unbiased manner, followed by characterization of representative isolates in mono-associations, and finally in a community context under controlled conditions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>STAR&#x02605;Methods</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>Key Resources Table</title><p id="p0125"><table-wrap id="undtbl1" position="float"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>REAGENT or RESOURCE</th><th>SOURCE</th><th>IDENTIFIER</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3"><bold>Bacterial and Virus Strains</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Plant-associated bacterial strains</td><td>See <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref></td><td>See <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><bold>Chemicals, Peptides, and Recombinant Proteins</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>flg22 (Flagelin 22)</td><td>EZBiolab</td><td>Cat# cp7201</td></tr><tr><td>Streptomycin sulfate salt,powder</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat# S6501</td></tr><tr><td>Tryptone/Peptone ex casein</td><td>Carl Roth</td><td>Cat# 8952</td></tr><tr><td>Yeast extract</td><td>BD Biosciences</td><td>Cat# 212750</td></tr><tr><td>Agar, granulated</td><td>BD Biosciences</td><td>Cat# 214530</td></tr><tr><td>Tryptic Soy Broth</td><td>Sigma-Aldrich</td><td>Cat# T8907</td></tr><tr><td>X-Gluc (5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl-beta-D-glucuronic acid, cyclohexylammonium salt)</td><td>Thermo Scientific</td><td>Cat# R0852</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><bold>Deposited Data</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Bacterial genome sequences</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/" id="intref0010">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/</ext-link></td><td>PRJEB26998</td></tr><tr><td>Raw RNA-seq data</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/" id="intref0015">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/</ext-link></td><td>PRJEB27007</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><bold>Experimental Models: Organisms/Strains</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> wild-type, Columbia (Col-0)</td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS60000</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> wild-type Bayreuth (Bay-0)</td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS6608</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> wild-type St. Maria d. Feiria (Fei-0)</td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS22645</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> wild-type Drahonin (Dra-2)</td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS1120</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> Wave_131Y</td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS781665</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana ahk3-3</italic></td><td><xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Higuchi et&#x000a0;al., 2004</xref></td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana arr1-3 arr12-1</italic></td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS6981</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana tir1-1</italic></td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS3798</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana aux1-7</italic></td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS3074</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana axr4-2</italic></td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS8019</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana arf7-1 arf19-1</italic></td><td><xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Okushima et&#x000a0;al., 2005</xref></td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana fls2</italic></td><td>TAIR</td><td>CS875982</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> proCYP71A12::GUS</td><td><xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Millet et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref></td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><bold>Oligonucleotides</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Primers used in this study</td><td>See <xref rid="mmc7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S6</xref></td><td>See <xref rid="mmc7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S6</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><bold>Software and Algorithms</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Trimmomatic</td><td><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bolger et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.usadellab.org/cms/?page=trimmomatic" id="intref0020">http://www.usadellab.org/cms/?page=trimmomatic</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>A5</td><td><xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Tritt et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/p/ngopt/wiki/A5PipelineREADME/" id="intref0025">https://sourceforge.net/p/ngopt/wiki/A5PipelineREADME/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>SOAPdenovo</td><td><xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://soap.genomics.org.cn/soapdenovo.html" id="intref0030">http://soap.genomics.org.cn/soapdenovo.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>HGAP</td><td><xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Chin et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/PacificBiosciences/Bioinformatics-Training/wiki/HGAP" id="intref0035">https://github.com/PacificBiosciences/Bioinformatics-Training/wiki/HGAP</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>HMMER</td><td><xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Eddy, 2011</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hmmer.org" id="intref0040">http://hmmer.org</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>OrthoFinder</td><td><xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Emms and Kelly, 2015</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/davidemms/OrthoFinder" id="intref0045">https://github.com/davidemms/OrthoFinder</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>USEARCH</td><td><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Edgar, 2013</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.drive5.com/usearch/" id="intref0050">https://www.drive5.com/usearch/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>QIIME</td><td><xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Caporaso et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://qiime.com" id="intref0055">http://qiime.com</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>UCHIME</td><td><xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.drive5.com/uchime/" id="intref0060">https://www.drive5.com/uchime/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>CLUSTALO</td><td><xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Sievers et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/" id="intref0065">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>MrBayes</td><td><xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Ronquist and Huelsenbeck, 2003</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mrbayes.sourceforge.net/" id="intref0070">http://mrbayes.sourceforge.net/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>FastTree</td><td><xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Price et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.microbesonline.org/fasttree/" id="intref0075">http://www.microbesonline.org/fasttree/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>FASTX-Toolkit</td><td>N/A</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/" id="intref0080">http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>TopHat2</td><td><xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Kim et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ccb.jhu.edu/software/tophat/index.shtml" id="intref0085">http://ccb.jhu.edu/software/tophat/index.shtml</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>Bowtie2</td><td><xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Langmead and Salzberg, 2012</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/bowtie2/index.shtml" id="intref0090">http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/bowtie2/index.shtml</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>BEDtools</td><td><xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Quinlan and Hall, 2010</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bedtools.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html" id="intref0095">http://bedtools.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>ImageJ</td><td><xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Schneider et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref></td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imagej.nih.gov/ij/" id="intref0100">https://imagej.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>R</td><td>N/A</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/" id="intref0105">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td>Plotting and statistical analyses (custom scripts)</td><td>N/A</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mpipz.mpg.de/R_scripts" id="intref0110">http://www.mpipz.mpg.de/R_scripts</ext-link></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>Contact for Reagent and Resource Sharing</title><p id="p0130">Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Paul Schulze-Lefert (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="mailto:schlef@mpipz.mpg.de" id="intref0115">schlef@mpipz.mpg.de</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title>Experimental Model and Subject Details</title><sec id="sec4.3.1"><title>Bacterial Strains</title><p id="p0135">The bacterial strains used in this study are summarized in <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Tables S1</xref> and <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>. NGR234 and R7A, CIAT899, and USDA61 were kindly provided by S. Radutoiu (Aarhus University, Denmark), R. Geurts (Wageningen University, Netherlands), and S. Okazaki (Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, Japan), respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3.2"><title>Plant Model</title><p id="p0140"><italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> Col-0 wild-type (N60000) and transgenic line Wave_131Y (N781665) were obtained from the Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Centre (NASC). Natural accessions of <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> (Bay-0, Fei-0, and Dra-2), cytokinin receptor (<italic>ahk3-3</italic>) and signaling mutants (<italic>arr1-3arr12-1</italic>), auxin receptor (<italic>tir1-1</italic>) and transporter (<italic>aux1-7</italic> and <italic>axr4-2</italic>) mutants, auxin signaling mutant (<italic>arf7-1arf19-1</italic>), <italic>fls2</italic> mutant&#x000a0;(SAIL_691C4), and a transgenic line expressing a proCYP71A12::GUS construct were kindly provided by K. Schlaeppi (Agroscope, Switzerland), S. Sabatini (Sapienza University of Rome, Italy), E. Kombrink (MPIPZ, Germany), M. Bennett (University of Nottingham,&#x000a0;UK), K. Tsuda (MPIPZ, Germany), and F. Ausubel (The Massachusetts General Hospital, USA), respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3.3"><title>Growing Conditions for Plant Models</title><p id="p0145">Seeds were surface-sterilized in 70% ethanol for 10&#x000a0;min followed by a brief wash with 100% ethanol. Plants were grown on agar plates prepared with half-strength Murashige and Skoog (MS) medium (750&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 625&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 10.3&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub>, 9.4&#x000a0;mM KNO<sub>3</sub>, 1.5&#x000a0;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 55&#x000a0;nM CoCl<sub>2</sub>, 53&#x000a0;nM CuCl<sub>2</sub>, 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 2.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M KI, 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 520&#x000a0;nM Na<sub>2</sub>MoO<sub>4</sub>, 15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M ZnCl<sub>2</sub>, 75&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Fe-EDTA, 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M MES-KOH pH 5.5) supplemented with 1% Difco Agar Granulated (BD Biosciences, USA), an agar which contains limited amounts of bioavailable nutrients (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Gruber et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). Phosphate- and nitrogen-depleted media were prepared according to a previous study (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Gruber et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). Plants were grown under short-day conditions at 21&#x000b0;C under light (10&#x000a0;hr) and at 19&#x000b0;C under dark (14&#x000a0;hr).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3.4"><title>Culture Conditions for <italic>In&#x000a0;Vitro</italic> Systems</title><p id="p0150">Bacterial strains were routinely cultured in TY (5 g/L tryptone, 3 g/L yeast extract, 10&#x000a0;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>) or 50% TSB media (Sigma-Aldrich, USA) and stored in 16% glycerol at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><title>Method Details</title><sec id="sec4.4.1"><title>Isolation and Sequencing of Bacterial Strains</title><p id="p0155">Surface-sterilized <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> seeds were sown at a density of four plants per pot (7&#x000d7;7&#x000d7;9&#x000a0;cm) and stratified for 3-4&#x000a0;days. Plants were grown in the greenhouse for 6&#x000a0;weeks under short day conditions (8/16&#x000a0;hr day/night with temperatures of 22&#x000b0;C/18&#x000b0;C and relative humidity of 70%). After harvest, roots were mechanically separated from the adhering soil particles and a defined root segment of 3&#x000a0;cm, beginning 0.5&#x000a0;cm distal from the hypocotyl, was sampled. Soil particles still attached to the roots were removed by gentle tapping. Roots were collected in 15-mL conical tubes containing 5&#x000a0;mL phosphate-buffered saline (PBS)-S buffer (130&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 7&#x000a0;mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 3&#x000a0;mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.0, 0.02% Silwet L-77) and washed for 15&#x000a0;min at 180&#x000a0;rpm on a shaker. Roots were transferred to a&#x000a0;new 15-mL conical tube and the remaining soil particles were centrifuged for 20&#x000a0;min at 15,000&#x000a0;&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>. After washing for a second time, roots were transferred to a new 15-mL conical tube and sonicated with ten cycles of a 30&#x000a0;s pulse at 160&#x000a0;W followed by a 30&#x000a0;s interval (Bioruptor Next Gen UCD-300; Diagenode, Belgium). Roots were transferred to a 1.5-mL tube containing 10&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and mechanically disrupted using sterile 3-mm metal beads and a Precellys24 tissue homogenizer (Bertin, France) by three cycles of 5,000&#x000a0;rpm for 30 s. The supernatant was collected by centrifugation at 1,000&#x000a0;&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 5&#x000a0;min and serial dilutions were plated onto flour and TWYE media (flour: 6 g/L flour, 0.3 g/L yeast extract, 0.3 g/L sucrose, 0.3 g/L CaCO<sub>3</sub>, 1.8% agar; TWYE: 0.25 g/L yeast extract, 0.5 g/L K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 1.8% agar), including 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL benzimidazole to inhibit fungal growth. Plates were incubated for 3-4&#x000a0;days at 28&#x000b0;C. Emerged single colonies were transferred with a sterile pipette tip to 400&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L liquid media in a 96-well format and incubated for up to 7&#x000a0;days at 28&#x000b0;C at 200&#x000a0;rpm. For taxonomic identification, 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of the culture was transferred to a 96-well PCR plate, bacterial cells were heat-disrupted for ten min at 100&#x000b0;C, and cell debris was removed by centrifugation at 3,000&#x000a0;rpm for 10&#x000a0;min. The supernatant was used for PCR amplification of 16S rRNA V5-V8 regions using the primers 799F (5&#x02032;-AACMGGATTAGATACCCKG-3&#x02032;) and 1392R (5&#x02032;-ACGGGCGGTGTGTRC-3&#x02032;). PCR reactions were performed under sterile conditions using 3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of the supernatant in a total volume of 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L that contained 1.25&#x000a0;U DFS-Taq DNA Polymerase (Bioron, Germany), 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7; complete reaction buffer, 0.3% BSA, 200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M of each dNTP, and 400&#x000a0;nM of each primer, using the following PCR program: 94&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min, 35 cycles of 94&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 50&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s and 72&#x000b0;C for 30 s, followed by 72&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min. PCR quality was assessed by visualizing 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of the amplicon on a 1% TAE-agarose gel with ethidium bromide. PCR products were purified using the QIAquick PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen, Germany), DNA concentrations were measured using a Nanodrop spectrophotometer (PeqLab, Germany) and adjusted to 20&#x000a0;ng/&#x003bc;L, and the purified products were subjected to Sanger sequencing. Genomic DNA of each strain was extracted and purified as described previously (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bai et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>) and sequenced using a combination of the Illumina HiSeq 2500 (Illumina, USA) and PacBio RS II (Pacific Biosciences, USA) platforms (see below). All sequencing was performed at the Max Planck Genome Center (Cologne, Germany) or at AgBiome (Research Triangle Park, USA).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4.2"><title>Bacterial Inoculation and Image Analysis</title><p id="p0160">Bacteria strains were cultured for 2-3&#x000a0;days until strains reached the stationary phase in their respective liquid media (see <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>) at 28&#x000b0;C (180-200&#x000a0;rpm). Bacterial cultures in the stationary phase were diluted 5-fold in sterile liquid media and pre-cultured for another 2-4&#x000a0;hr in order to metabolically activate bacterial cells. Bacterial cells were collected and resuspended in 10&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and adjusted to an optical density of 0.5 at 600&#x000a0;nm (OD<sub>600nm</sub>). The bacterial resuspension mixture was added to plant MS media cooled to 40&#x000b0;C&#x000a0;-45&#x000b0;C to obtain a final OD<sub>600nm</sub> of 0.00005, which corresponds to approximately 5&#x000d7;10<sup>4</sup> cells/mL. For the root growth assay of a panel of Alphaproteobacteria (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>) and the developmental analysis with <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6</xref>), surface sterilized seeds were directly planted onto the bacteria-containing medium and grown for 5-27&#x000a0;days. For the analyses using three <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> accessions (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S5</xref>A and S5B) and phosphorus- and nitrogen-deficient conditions (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S5</xref>C&#x02013;S5E), as well as for the RNA-seq experiment (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S12</xref>), plants were precultured on half-strength MS medium supplemented with 1% sucrose for 6&#x000a0;days before seedlings were transferred onto bacteria-containing media under sterile conditions and grown for 18&#x000a0;days. For flg22 treatment (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref> and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), the mock or bacteria-containing medium was supplemented with 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M flg22 peptide (EZBiolab, USA). Wild-type Col-0 or the <italic>fls2</italic> mutant were pre-grown on half-strength MS medium supplemented with 1% sucrose and 1% agar for 5-7&#x000a0;days and transferred to bacteria-containing medium with sterile toothpicks. Plants were grown for 14-15&#x000a0;days after transfer. For co-inoculation assays, each bacterial strain was added in an equal volume (1/10,000 volume at OD<sub>600</sub>=0.5), resulting in a doubled amount of total bacterial titer compared to the mono-association assays.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4.3"><title>DNA Extraction and Quantitative PCR</title><p id="p0165">Roots inoculated with bacteria were collected from plates and briefly washed two times in sterile water. After removal of excess water with a glass fiber filter paper (Whatman, UK), roots were frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at -80&#x000b0;C until further processing. DNA was extracted using Lysing Matrix E (MP Biomedicals, USA) and the DNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen, Germany) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Quantitative PCR was performed in a 15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L reaction mixture containing 7.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L iQ SYBR Green Supermix (BIO-RAD, USA), 0.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M forward primer, 0.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M reverse primer, and 2-4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L DNA template. PCR was performed using a CFX Connect (Bio-Rad, USA) using the following cycles: 95&#x000b0;C for 3&#x000a0;min, followed by 40 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 10 s, 60&#x000b0;C for 30 s, and 72&#x000b0;C for 30 s. The delta-Ct method was used to estimate the relative abundance of bacteria to the abundance of plant DNA. Primers used in this study are shown in <xref rid="mmc7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4.4"><title>Confocal Microscopy and Image Analysis</title><p id="p0170">Transgenic <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> line Wave_131Y, expressing NPSN12 fused with the enhanced yellow fluorescent protein (EYFP), was observed under a CLSM780 confocal microscope (Zeiss, Germany) equipped with a water-immersion 20&#x000d7; objective using the 514-nm line of a 25 mW argon ion laser. All image analysis was performed using ImageJ (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Schneider et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). Plates were scanned and marked prior to the microscopy, allowing correlations between the parameters of individual plants.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4.5"><title>RNA Extraction and RNA-seq</title><p id="p0175">For transcriptomic analysis, 6-day-old <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> seedlings were inoculated with <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E or mock control under phosphate-sufficient or phosphate-depleted conditions and incubated for 4, 8, 12, and 16&#x000a0;days under short-day conditions, as described above. Roots from three plates were combined for one replicate and a total of three replicates were sampled for each condition. Roots were homogenized with Lysing Matrix E and TissueLyser II (20 beats per second for 30 s; Qiagen, Netherlands) and RNA was extracted with the miRNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. RNA quality was determined using a 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, USA). Preparation of Illumina sequencing libraries was conducted by the Max Planck Genome Center) using an input of 1.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of total RNA. Sequences were generated using the Illumina HiSeq2500 platform. Approximately 20M reads per sample with a length of 100&#x000a0;bp were generated and further analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4.6"><title>GUS Histochemical Assay</title><p id="p0180">GUS staining was performed as described previously (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Millet et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>) with slight modifications. Briefly, approximately 15 <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> seeds were germinated in a six-well culture plate in half-strength MS liquid medium (0.5% sucrose) and incubated for 7&#x000a0;days under short-day conditions at 21&#x000b0;C under light (10&#x000a0;hr) and at 19&#x000b0;C under dark (14&#x000a0;hr). Afterwards, the growth medium was&#x000a0;replaced by fresh liquid MS medium without sucrose. Bacterial cells actively growing in 50% TSA medium were collected, washed once, and then resuspended with 10&#x000a0;mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>. OD<sub>600nm</sub> was measured by a spectrometer. Bacterial suspensions (final OD<sub>600nm</sub>=0.1), flg22 (final concentration of 100&#x000a0;nM), or an equal volume of 10&#x000a0;mM MgSO<sub>4</sub> was added to the liquid medium in the six-well plates and incubated for 24&#x000a0;hr under the same conditions. Treated seedlings were washed with 50&#x000a0;mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) and incubated with GUS substrate solution (50&#x000a0;mM sodium phosphate buffer [pH 7.0], 10&#x000a0;mM EDTA, 0.5&#x000a0;mM K<sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>], 0.5&#x000a0;mM K<sub>3</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>], 0.5&#x000a0;mM X-Gluc, and 0.01% Silwet L-77) at 37&#x000b0;C for 2-3&#x000a0;hr after 5&#x000a0;min of vacuum infiltration. Tissues&#x000a0;were fixed twice with a 3:1 ethanol:acetic acid solution and cleared in lactic acid. Images were taken using an Axio Imager A2 microscope (Zeiss).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4.5"><title>Quantification and Statistical Analysis</title><sec id="sec4.5.1"><title>Genome Assembly</title><p id="p0185">Genomes sequenced using the Illumina platform with an insert size of 350&#x000a0;bp and an approximate depth of 5M reads per strain were&#x000a0;quality-filtered by passing short reads through a quality and length-trimming filter using Trimmomatic (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bolger et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>) with the default parameters and subsequently assembling them using an ensemble of two approaches: A5 (<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Tritt et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>) and SOAPdenovo (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). In each case, the assembly with the smaller number of scaffolds was selected. Contigs smaller than 1,000 bases were removed from the assemblies. Additionally, a subset of genomes were sequenced using the Pacific Biosciences platform and these long reads were assembled into complete genomes using the Hierarchical Genome Assembly Process (HGAP) assembler (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Chin et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). Detailed statistics concerning the assemblies of all genomes analyzed in this study can be found in <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>. Accession numbers corresponding to the raw reads of all genomes, including those of previously published organisms, can likewise be found in <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5.2"><title>Genome Annotation and Orthology Inference</title><p id="p0190">To determine homology relationships between gene sequences, we first predicted putative protein-coding sequences using Prodigal (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Hyatt et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). Annotation of candidate Open Reading Frames (ORFs) was then conducted using the KEGG Orthology (KO) database (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Kanehisa et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>) as previously described (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bai et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). Briefly, sequences from each KO were aligned using Clustal Omega (<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Sievers et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>) and hidden Markov models (HMMs) generated based on each multiple sequence alignment using the HMMER suite (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Eddy, 2011</xref>). Subsequently, the HMMs were employed to search all putative protein-coding sequences. Sequences matching a given KO group with an E value lower than 10&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> with a coverage of at least 70% of the total length were assigned to that KO group. All sequences assigned to the same KO were considered homologous and classified as belonging to the same Cluster of Orthologous Groups (COG). For the pangenome analysis and permutation-based analysis of saturation curves we also conducted a more comprehensive prediction of COGs using OrthoFinder (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Emms and Kelly, 2015</xref>), a sequence-based <italic>de novo</italic> method for orthogroup inference. Subsequently, for each COG we generated a phyletic pattern consisting of a binary vector of presence/absence for each KO group or COG in each genome of the dataset.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5.3"><title>Natural Community Amplicon Sequencing Meta-Analysis</title><p id="p0195">First, we retrieved from the public databases all raw, unprocessed sequences corresponding to the analyzed 16S rRNA gene surveys (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bai et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bulgarelli et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Schlaeppi et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">Zgadzaj et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>) and compiled a master meta-data table containing information of all samples across studies (<xref rid="mmc3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>). Next, a database of high-quality reference sequences was built by extracting 16S rRNA gene sequences from the Rhizobiales genome assemblies using RNAmmer (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Lagesen et&#x000a0;al., 2007</xref>). Identical reference sequences were dereplicated prior to downstream analyses using usearch. Subsequently, 16S rRNA gene sequences were processed using a combination of custom scripts as well as tools from the QIIME (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Caporaso et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>) and USEARCH (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Edgar, 2013</xref>) pipelines. First, reads were truncated to an even length (290&#x000a0;bp) using the truncate <italic>fasta_qual_files.py</italic> QIIME script. Libraries were demultiplexed (<italic>split_libraries.py</italic>) and only reads with a quality score above 25 were retained for subsequent analysis. After dereplication and removal of singletons we conducted a reference-based clustering of sequences into operational taxonomic units (OTUs) using the UPARSE algorithm (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Edgar, 2013</xref>) at 99% identity using high-quality 16S dereplicated sequences extracted from the whole-genome assemblies. In parallel, we conducted <italic>de novo</italic> clustering of all sequences into OTUs using the standard UPARSE algorithm at 97% identity. After chimeric sequences were filtered using UCHIME (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>), we used all non-artifactual OTUs per sample to normalize Rhizobiales abundances as a percentage of the total sample size (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>A). The resulting OTU table was used in all subsequent statistical analyses of differentially abundant taxa as well analyses of diversity (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>B).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5.4"><title>Comparative Genomics and Ancestral Character Reconstruction</title><p id="p0200">Inference of an accurate species tree was conducted as follows: first, from each genome, we extracted a set of up to 32 single-copy phylogenetic marker genes that are present in the majority of sequenced bacterial genomes called AMPHORA genes (<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Wu and Eisen, 2008</xref>) using custom-built HMMs and the hmmsearch tool (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Eddy, 2011</xref>). The resulting sequences were concatenated independently for each genome and then aligned using Clustal Omega (<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Sievers et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>). For each dataset, rooted species trees were generated from the AMPHORA multiple sequence alignments using MrBayes (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Huelsenbeck and Ronquist, 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Ronquist and Huelsenbeck, 2003</xref>) with a strict molecular clock and a general time reversible model (GTR+G+I; 10,800,000 iterations, parameters <italic>nst=6, rates=invgamma</italic> and <italic>brlenspr=clock:uniform</italic>). Similar results as reported above were obtained by reconstructing the species tree using an alternative maximum likelihood approach that is implemented in FastTree (<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Price et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>) with a general time reversible model of DNA evolution and without a molecular clock constraint (data not shown). Polytomies in the trees were resolved by inserting branches of zero length to avoid conflicts in the inference of ancestral characters. Given the matrix of phyletic patterns and the estimated species tree, we used a maximum likelihood approach (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Pagel, 1994</xref>) for the estimation of ancestral states using the implementation provided with the ape package (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Paradis et&#x000a0;al., 2004</xref>) for R software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/" id="intref0120">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>), which employs a &#x02018;two-pass&#x02019; algorithm for the joint estimation of the likelihood of the ancestral states (<xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Yang, 2006</xref>). This approach gives similar results as stochastic mapping (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Paradis et&#x000a0;al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Pupko et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>) while being much faster, thus enabling the estimation of ancestral characters for very large datasets (several thousands of genomes or more).</p><p id="p0205">Analyses of functional diversity between sequenced isolates were conducted as previously described (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bai et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). First, we&#x000a0;generated a presence/absence profile of each KO group (or phyletic pattern) for each genome in the data set. Subsequently, a distance measure based on the Pearson correlation of each pair of phyletic patterns was calculated which allowed us to embed each genome as a data point in a metric space.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5.5"><title>Image Analysis for Root Growth Quantification</title><p id="p0210">Plate images were taken and root length was measured using ImageJ (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Schneider et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). Shoot fresh weights were measured after removal of excess water by a paper towel. Each biological replicate contained at least three technical replicates. Primary root&#x000a0;lengths and shoot fresh weights were normalized to the mock control within each replicate. Statistical tests were performed using R software according to Dunnett&#x02019;s or Tukey&#x02019;s HSD tests depending on the dataset (see figure legends).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5.6"><title>Image Analysis for Root Developmental Analysis</title><p id="p0215">Transitions from the meristematic zone (MZ) to the elongation zone (EZ) was determined as described previously (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Perilli and Sabatini, 2010</xref>). The number of cortex cells within the MZ was counted until the area where cells began to elongate after transition (see arrowheads in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>A). Transition from the EZ to the differentiation zone (DZ) was determined by the first appearance of a root hair in the epidermal cell layer, and the longitudinal length of the cortex cell underneath was measured accordingly (see dotted lines in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S6</xref>A and S6B). For each root, two Z stack images were randomly taken from the DZ and the longitudinal length of all cortex cells was measured (n&#x000a0;= 638, average of 23.6 cells/root), of which mean values were used as the cell length in the DZ.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5.7"><title>RNA-seq Data Analysis</title><p id="p0220">Obtained sequences were quality filtered by trimming the Illumina adaptor and discarding every sequence with a quality score below 25 using the FASTX toolkit. High quality sequences were mapped to the <italic>A.&#x000a0;thaliana</italic> genome (TAIR10 annotation file) TopHat2 (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Kim et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>) and Bowtie2 (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Langmead and Salzberg, 2012</xref>). A count table for each gene and sample was then generated using the BEDtools suite (function coverageBED) (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Quinlan and Hall, 2010</xref>).</p><p id="p0225">All statistical analyses were performed using R. Read count data from <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Castrillo et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> were retrieved from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSE87336" id="intref0125">GSE87336</ext-link>). Genes were removed from the analysis unless at least 100 counts over all samples and more than ten counts at least in two samples were detected. Normalization using the library size-dependent trimmed mean of M-values (TMM) method, calculation of log<sub>2</sub> counts per million and fold changes, and statistical analyses of differentially expressed genes were completed using the edgeR R package (<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). Median-centered Z scores based on log<sub>2</sub> counts per million were used for <italic>k</italic>-means clustering, for which <italic>k</italic> was objectively determined by computing Bayesian information criterion. Differentially expressed genes were identified by fitting a negative binomial generalized linear model to the genes using the <italic>glmFit</italic> function with the following formula: &#x0223c; 0&#x000a0;+ treatment<sup>&#x02217;</sup>nutrient<sup>&#x02217;</sup>timepoint&#x000a0;+ replicate. P values were calculated using the <italic>glmLRT</italic> function and corrected for multiple tests controlling for the false discovery rate (FDR) with &#x003b1;&#x000a0;= 0.05 using the <italic>decideTestsDGE</italic> function. Cluster-wise gene ontology enrichment analysis was performed with the clusterProfiler R package using <italic>compareCluster</italic> and <italic>enrichGO</italic> functions (<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Yu et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4.6"><title>Data and Software Availability</title><p id="p0230">Whole-genome assemblies and transcriptome sequencing reads have been deposited in the European Nucleotide Archive (ENA) under the accession numbers ENA: PRJEB26998, PRJEB27007, respectively. To ensure reproducibility, the scripts used for computational analyses and the corresponding raw and intermediate data will be made available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mpipz.mpg.de/R_scripts" id="intref0130">http://www.mpipz.mpg.de/R_scripts</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Consortia</title><p id="p0260">The AgBiome Team: Elka Armstrong, Stacey Badders, Vadim Beilinson, Brooke Bissinger, Courtney Bogard, Mauricio Borgen, Kelly Craig, Larry Daquioag, Billie Espejo, Andrew Graham, Philip E. Hammer, James R. Henriksen, Janice C. Jones, Karen Juan, Rebekah Kelly, Dylan Kraus, Mary Kroner, Larry Nea, Narendra Palekar, Jessica Parks, Jacob Pearce, Vinh D. Pham, Tracy Raines, Kira Bulazel Roberts, Mark Roberts, Steve J. Ronyak, Maureen Schirtzinger, Amy Shekita, Amber Smith, Murray Spruill, Kelly S. Smith, Rebecca Thayer, Dan Tomso, Jake Trimble, Mathias Twizeyimana, Katharine Tyson, Scott Uknes, Sandy Volrath, Eric Ward, Christy Wiggins, Kelly Williamson.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alfano</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collmer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Type III secretion system effector proteins: double agents in bacterial disease and plant defense</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Phytopathol.</source><volume>42</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15283671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tipre</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dave</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficiency evaluation of commercial liquid biofertilizers for growth of <italic>Cicer aeritinum</italic> (chickpea) in pot and field study</article-title><source>Biocatal. Agric. Biotechnol.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido-Oter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Potthoff</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rott</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dombrowski</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nch</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spaepen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Remus-Emsermann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional overlap of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaf and root microbiota</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>528</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26633631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bever</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial population and community dynamics on plant roots and their feedbacks on plant communities</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol.</source><volume>66</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22726216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;hm</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oome</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raaymakers</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Ackerveken</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurnberger</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A conserved peptide pattern from a widespread microbial virulence factor triggers pattern-induced immunity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>e1004491</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25375108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>30</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>2114</fpage><lpage>2120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A renaissance of elicitors: perception of microbe-associated molecular patterns and danger signals by pattern-recognition receptors</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><volume>60</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19400727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulgarelli</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido-Oter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nch</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dr&#x000f6;ge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>McHardy</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze-Lefert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and function of the bacterial root microbiota in wild and domesticated barley</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><volume>17</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25732064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulgarelli</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rott</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaeppi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ver Loren van Themaat</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadinejad</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Assenza</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauf</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huettel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhardt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmelzer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revealing structure and assembly cues for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root-inhabiting bacterial microbiota</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>488</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22859207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campanile</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Studholme</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindeberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plant pathogen <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. tomato is genetically monomorphic and under strong selection to evade tomato immunity</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>e1002130</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21901088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halane</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gassmann</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stacey</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of plant innate immunity in the legume-rhizobium symbiosis</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><volume>68</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28142283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capela</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clerissi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guetta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gris</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valls</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jauneau</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruveiller</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>E.P.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recruitment of a lineage-specific virulence regulatory pathway promotes intracellular infection by a plant pathogen experimentally evolved into a legume symbiont</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><volume>34</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2503</fpage><lpage>2521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28535261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuczynski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stombaugh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bittinger</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bushman</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fierer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing data</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><volume>7</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gresshoff</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrate inhibition of nodulation and nitrogen-fixation in white clover</article-title><source>Z.&#x000a0;Pflanzenphysiol.</source><volume>110</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castrillo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paredes</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lorenzo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feltcher</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkel</surname><given-names>O.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Breakfield</surname><given-names>N.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mieczkowski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Root microbiota drive direct integration of phosphate stress and immunity</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>543</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28297714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bontemps</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bena</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boivin-Masson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Legume symbiotic nitrogen fixation by beta-proteobacteria is widespread in nature</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Bacteriol.</source><volume>185</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>7266</fpage><lpage>7272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14645288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>C.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klammer</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heiner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clum</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huddleston</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichler</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonhybrid, finished microbial genome assemblies from long-read SMRT sequencing data</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><volume>10</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23644548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colebatch</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desbrosses</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krusell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montanari</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloska</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global changes in transcription orchestrate metabolic differentiation during symbiotic nitrogen fixation in <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15272870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dello Ioio</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linhares</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scacchi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casamitjana-Martinez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heidstra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytokinins determine <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root-meristem size by controlling cell differentiation</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><volume>17</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>678</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17363254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dello Ioio</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moubayidin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perilli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genetic framework for the control of cell division and differentiation in the root meristem</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>322</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1380</fpage><lpage>1384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19039136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accelerated profile HMM searches</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>e1002195</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22039361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UPARSE: highly accurate OTU sequences from microbial amplicon reads</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><volume>10</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>996</fpage><lpage>998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23955772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quince</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UCHIME improves sensitivity and speed of chimera detection</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>27</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>2194</fpage><lpage>2200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emms</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OrthoFinder: solving fundamental biases in&#x000a0;whole genome comparisons dramatically improves orthogroup inference accuracy</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26243257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular sensing of bacteria in plants. The highly conserved RNA-binding motif RNP-1 of bacterial cold shock proteins is recognized as an elicitor signal in tobacco</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Biol. Chem.</source><volume>278</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>6201</fpage><lpage>6208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Volko</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants have a sensitive perception system for the most conserved domain of bacterial flagellin</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><volume>18</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Rhizobium</italic>&#x02013;plant signal exchange</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>357</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1614514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galibert</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Finan</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puhler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abola</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ampe</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barloy-Hubler</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boistard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The composite genome of the legume symbiont <italic>Sinorhizobium meliloti</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><volume>293</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11474104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single locus determines sensitivity to bacterial flagellin in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><volume>18</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griesmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haberer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Billault-Penneteau</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauressergues</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imanishi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenomics reveals multiple losses of nitrogen-fixing root nodule symbiosis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giehl</surname><given-names>R.F.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>von Wir&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasticity of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root system under nutrient deficiencies</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><volume>163</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23852440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hacquard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido-Oter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spaepen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackermann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebeis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>McHardy</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangl</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiota and host nutrition across plant and animal kingdoms</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><volume>17</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25974302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pischke</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahonen</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyawaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In planta functions of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cytokinin receptor family</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>101</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>8821</fpage><lpage>8826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15166290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>17</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>754</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11524383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huot</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth-defense tradeoffs in plants: a balancing act to optimize fitness</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><volume>7</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1267</fpage><lpage>1287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24777989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Locascio</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Land</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larimer</surname><given-names>F.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prodigal: prokaryotic gene recognition and translation initiation site identification</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>11</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>119</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20211023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangl</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plant immune system</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>444</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17108957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Furumichi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KEGG as a reference resource for gene and protein annotation</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>44</volume><issue>D1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>D457</fpage><lpage>D462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26476454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawaharada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hjuler</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gysel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muszy&#x00144;ski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thygesen</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asmussen</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Receptor-mediated exopolysaccharide perception controls bacterial infection</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>523</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26153863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusions</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>R36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunze</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robatzek</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niehaus</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The N terminus of bacterial elongation factor Tu elicits innate immunity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>16</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>3496</fpage><lpage>3507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15548740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagesen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f8;dland</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staerfeldt</surname><given-names>H.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rognes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ussery</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNAmmer: consistent and rapid annotation of ribosomal RNA genes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>3100</fpage><lpage>3108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lakshmanan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castaneda</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudrappa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bais</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Root transcriptome analysis of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> exposed to beneficial <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> FB17 rhizobacteria revealed genes for bacterial recruitment and plant defense independent of malate efflux</article-title><source>Planta</source><volume>238</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23794026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><volume>9</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The FLS2-associated kinase BIK1 directly phosphorylates the NADPH oxidase RbohD to control plant immunity</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><volume>15</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24629339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristiansen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>De novo assembly of human genomes with massively parallel short read sequencing</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><volume>20</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20019144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thibivilliers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>C.h.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stacey</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonlegumes respond to rhizobial Nod factors by suppressing the innate immune response</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>341</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1384</fpage><lpage>1387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24009356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lozano-Dur&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trade-off between growth and immunity: role of brassinosteroids</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><volume>20</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25278266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masson-Boivin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraud</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perret</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batut</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishing nitrogen-fixing symbiosis with legumes: how many rhizobium recipes?</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol.</source><volume>17</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19766492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danna</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Songnuan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Werck-Reichhart</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innate immune responses activated in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> roots by microbe-associated molecular patterns</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>22</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20348432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moulin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munive</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreyfus</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boivin-Masson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nodulation of legumes by members of the beta-subclass of Proteobacteria</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>411</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>948</fpage><lpage>950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11418858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hijacking of leguminous nodulation signaling by the rhizobial type III secretion system</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>110</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>17131</fpage><lpage>17136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24082124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okushima</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Overvoorde</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional genomic analysis of the auxin response factor gene family members in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: unique and overlapping functions of ARF7 and ARF19</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>17</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oldroyd</surname><given-names>G.E.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Speak, friend, and enter: signalling systems that promote beneficial symbiotic associations in plants</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23493145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oldroyd</surname><given-names>G.E.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Downie</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rules&#x000a0;of engagement in the legume-rhizobial symbiosis</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Genet.</source><volume>45</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21838550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting correlated evolution on phylogenies: a general method for the comparative analysis of discrete characters</article-title><source>Proc. Biol. Sci.</source><volume>255</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Claude</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strimmer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>APE: analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R language</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>20</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14734327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perilli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of root meristem size development</article-title><source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source><volume>655</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20734261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poitout</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martiniere</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kucharczyk</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Queruel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva-Andia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mashkoor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamet</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varoquaux</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paris</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sentenac</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local signalling pathways regulate the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root developmental response to <italic>Mesorhizobium loti</italic> inoculation</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Exp. Bot.</source><volume>68</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1199</fpage><lpage>1211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28199673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poupin</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmona</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinedo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A complex molecular interplay of auxin and ethylene signaling pathways is involved in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> growth promotion by <italic>Burkholderia phytofirmans</italic> PsJN</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>492</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27148317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehal</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkin</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FastTree 2 &#x02013; approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignments</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>5</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>e9490</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20224823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pupko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe'er</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamir</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graur</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A fast algorithm for joint reconstruction of ancestral amino acid sequences</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><volume>17</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10833195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siefert</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blankenship</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The natural history of nitrogen fixation</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><volume>21</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14694078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Remigi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J.P.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masson-Boivin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Symbiosis within symbiosis: evolving nitrogen-fixing legume symbionts</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26612499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>19</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1572</fpage><lpage>1574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12912839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Draghi</surname><given-names>W.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrania</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres Tejerizo</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albicoro</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistorio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Papa</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specificity traits consistent with legume-rhizobia coevolution displayed by <italic>Ensifer meliloti</italic> rhizosphere colonization</article-title><source>Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>3423</fpage><lpage>3438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28618121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref69"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlaeppi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dombrowski</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido-Oter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ver Loren van Themaat</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze-Lefert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative divergence of the bacterial root microbiota in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> relatives</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>111</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24379374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasband</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliceiri</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><volume>9</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref71"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilm</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dineen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McWilliam</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Remmert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000f6;ding</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast, scalable generation of high-quality protein multiple sequence alignments using Clustal Omega</article-title><source>Mol. Syst. Biol.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>539</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21988835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref72"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stringlis</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Proietti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Verk</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamioudis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>C.M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Root transcriptional dynamics induced by beneficial rhizobacteria and microbial immune elicitors reveal signatures of adaptation to mutualists</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><volume>93</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29024173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref73"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tritt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Facciotti</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrated pipeline for de novo assembly of microbial genomes</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>e42304</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23028432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref74"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transport and metabolism in legume-rhizobia symbioses</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><volume>64</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23451778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref75"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Velzen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutten</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zeijl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santuari</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of the nonlegume <italic>Parasponia</italic> reveals insights into evolution of nitrogen-fixing rhizobium symbioses</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>115</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>E4700</fpage><lpage>E4709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29717040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref76"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple, fast, and accurate method of phylogenomic inference</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>R151</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18851752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref77"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Computational Molecular Evolution</chapter-title><year>2006</year><publisher-name>Oxford University Press Oxford</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref78"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeoh</surname><given-names>Y.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paungfoo-Lonhienne</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brackin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hugenholtz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary conservation of a core root microbiome across plant phyla along a tropical soil chronosequence</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>215</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28790312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref79"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J.P.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossman</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>A.W.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghazoui</surname><given-names>Z.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hull</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wexler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curson</surname><given-names>A.R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genome of <italic>Rhizobium leguminosarum</italic> has recognizable core and accessory components</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>R34</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16640791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref80"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>clusterProfiler: an R package for comparing biological themes among gene clusters</article-title><source>OMICS</source><volume>16</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref81"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zamioudis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastranesti</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhonukshe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blilou</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>C.M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unraveling root developmental programs initiated by beneficial <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> bacteria</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><volume>162</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23542149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref82"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zgadzaj</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido-Oter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koprivova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze-Lefert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Radutoiu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Root nodule symbiosis in <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic> drives the&#x000a0;establishment of distinctive rhizosphere, root, and nodule bacterial communities</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>113</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>E7996</fpage><lpage>E8005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27864511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref83"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gyaneshwar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rhizobium sp. IRBG74 alters <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root development by affecting auxin signaling</article-title><source>Front. Microbiol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2556</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29354099</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="app2" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplemental Information</title><p id="p0255"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Document S1. Figures S1&#x02013;S7</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2"><caption><title>Table S1. Metadata of Sequenced Isolates, Related to Figures 1, 2, S1, S2, and S3 and STAR Methods</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc2.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3"><caption><title>Table S2. Metadata of 16S RNA Gene Meta-Analysis, Related to Figures 1 and S1 and STAR Methods</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc3.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4"><caption><title>Table S3. Metadata of nifH Phylogenetic Analysis, Related to Figures 2 and S2</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc4.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc5"><caption><title>Table S4. Data of Growth Promotion Assays, Related to Figures 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, S5, and S6</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc5.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc6"><caption><title>Table S5. A List of Differentially Expressed Genes upon <italic>Rhizobium</italic> 129E Colonization, Related to Figure&#x000a0;5</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc6.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc7"><caption><title>Table S6. Primers Used in this Study, Related to Figure&#x000a0;S4 and STAR Methods</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc7.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc8"><caption><title>Document S2. Article plus Supplemental Information</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc8.pdf"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to thank Paloma Duran, Dr. Rafal Zgadzaj, Dr. Kenichi Tsuda, Dr. Jane Parker, and Dr. Simona Radutoiu for their useful comments on this manuscript. We also thank Neysan Donnelly and Jack Roach for their comments and help editing the manuscript. This work was supported by funds from the <funding-source id="gs1">Max Planck Society</funding-source>, a <funding-source id="gs2">European Research Council</funding-source> advanced grant (ROOTMICROBIOTA), and the &#x0201c;Cluster of Excellence on Plant Sciences&#x0201d; (CEPLAS) program funded by the <funding-source id="gs3">Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funding-source>.</p><sec id="sec5"><title>Author Contributions</title><p id="p0240">R.G.-O., R.T.N., N.D., A.C.M., and P.S.-L. designed the research. The AgBiome Team collected samples, isolated strains, and assembled genomes for 826 bacteria. R.T.N. and N.D. performed and analyzed plant phenotypic experiments. N.D. performed RNA-seq experiments and R.T.N. analyzed those data. R.G.-O. conducted the amplicon data meta-analysis, genome assembly, and annotation and performed comparative genomic analyses and statistical tests. K.-W.M. performed the MTI activation assay. R.G.-O., R.T.N., N.D., K.-W.M., and P.S.-L. interpreted the data, and R.G.-O., R.T.N., and P.S.-L. wrote the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Declaration of Interests</title><p id="p0245">Paul Schulze-Lefert is a co-founder of AgBiome and a member of its scientific advisory board.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn id="app1" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="p0250">Supplemental Information includes seven figures and six tables and can be found with this article online at <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.chom.2018.06.006" id="intref0135">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2018.06.006</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>