<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6135824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">31518</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-31518-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Draft genome sequence of first monocot-halophytic species <italic>Oryza coarctata</italic> reveals stress-specific genes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>Tapan Kumar</given-names></name><address><email>mondaltk@rediffmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Rawal</surname><given-names>Hukam Chand</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chowrasia</surname><given-names>Soni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Varshney</surname><given-names>Deepti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>Alok Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>Abhishek</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>Harmeet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gaikwad</surname><given-names>Kishor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Tilak Raj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Nagendra Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0499 4444</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.466936.8</institution-id><institution>ICAR-National Research Centre on Plant Biotechnology, </institution></institution-wrap>Pusa, New Delhi 110012 India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>13698</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><italic>Oryza coarctata</italic> (KKLL; 2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4x&#x02009;=&#x02009;48, 665&#x02009;Mb) also&#x000a0;known as <italic>Porteresia coarctata</italic> is an extreme halophyte species of genus <italic>Oryza</italic>. Using Illumina and Nanopore reads, we achieved the assembled genome size of 569.9&#x02009;Mb, accounting 85.69% of the estimated genome size with N50 of 1.85&#x02009;Mb and 19.89% repetitive region. We also found 230,968 simple sequence repeats (SSRs) and 5,512 non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs). The functional annotation of predicted 33,627 protein-coding genes and 4,916 transcription factors revealed that high salinity adaptation of this species is due to the exclusive or excessive presence of stress-specific genes as compared to rice. We have identified 8 homologs to salt-tolerant <italic>SOS1</italic> genes, one of the three main components of salt overly sensitive (<italic>SOS</italic>) signal pathway. On the other hand, the phylogenetic analysis of the assembled chloroplast (134.75&#x02009;kb) and mitochondrial genome (491.06&#x02009;kb) favours the conservative nature of these organelle genomes within <italic>Oryza</italic> taxon.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Soil salinity is a major abiotic stress reducing the yield of rice cultivated globally and is increasing gradually due to surface irrigation, high cropping intensity and cultivation of high yielding variety<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. In general, rice is a glycophyte species except few tolerant landraces which can grow up to a maximum limit of 12 E.Ce (electrical conductivity) dS/m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Those landraces have been extensively used by the plant breeders to identify salt tolerant QTLs for introgression to popular salt sensitive genotypes of rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Thus genetic potential for salt tolerance among the existing population has been fully exploited. Therefore, alternative effectual alleles from wild species may aid in amending the salinity tolerance to an advanced level. Wild species are a potential alternative source of many useful alleles that may not be present in the primary gene pool of the domesticated species.</p><p id="Par3"><italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic>, an allo-tetraploid species (chromosome number of 2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4X&#x02009;=&#x02009;48, KKLL genome)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> is popularly known as Asian wild rice, grows naturally in the coastal region of South-East Asian countries, where this plant experiences the lunar tide and is exposed to submerge saline sea water in every alternative 12&#x02009;h. It set flowers and seeds under high saline conditions of upto 40 E.CedS m<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> saline soil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. It is the only halophytic species in the genus <italic>Oryza</italic> and represents the evolutionary transition of aquatic plant to land plant because of the presence of ancient as well as advanced characteristics of terrestrial habitat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Although several pinitol biosynthesis pathway genes individually have been cloned for functional genomics study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> but there is lack of large scale genomics resources for this species except one study each on transcriptome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> and on microRNA (miRNAs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Apart from these, some BAC end sequences and repeat libraries for <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> were also reported as part of The Oryza Map Alignment Project (OMAP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> but no efforts seems to be reported to decode the genome assembly of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic>, which is the pre-requisite to harness its genetic potential for salinity tolerance. There are 24 morphologically distinct species in the genus <italic>Oryza</italic>, yet 11 of them have been sequenced till today though none of them are halophyte in nature. Genome sequence has several advantages such as i) generation of large number of markers which in turn help in marker assistant breeding, ii) revealed several genomic resources both for coding and non-coding region and hence can be used for evolutionary study by comparative genomics, iii) helps to identify the conserved and novel genes along with paralogs, hence providing better opportunity to select the gene of interest.</p><p id="Par4">Most of the work done so far on the salinity genes have been employed on model but glycophytic species i.e. rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> which have very less or no significance to endure high salinity. Recently, few halophytes have been sequenced such as <italic>Thellungiella parvula</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>salsuginea</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, <italic>Eutrema salsugineum</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, but none of them are monocot in nature. Being a close wild relative of one of the most important cultivated crop world-wide i.e. rice, and monocot in nature, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> may aid to generate an important and large reservoir of salinity tolerant genes which, either through conventional breeding or through genetic engineering approaches, will help research community for improving salinity tolerance in rice plants.</p><p id="Par5">In the present study, we have decoded the whole genome of a halophytic monocot species <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> using Illumina and Nanopore reads to generate a high-quality (HQ) draft genome assembly of 569.9&#x02009;Mb with a scaffold N50 of 1.85&#x02009;Mb. We also assembled and reported the complete sequence of chloroplast and mitochondrial genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic>. We discovered many stress-specific or salinity responsive genes, including <italic>SOS1</italic> (salt overly sensitive 1) genes, in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> which are either missing or present in low copy number in the rice. Evolutionary and syntenic studies have been performed at genome level, organelle level and gene level to unravel not only the conserved features of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> within <italic>Oryza</italic> genus but also to uncover its similarity with other halophytic species and differences from AA, BB and FF genome types of the genus <italic>Oryza</italic>. The genomic resources developed in this sequencing effort should contribute in advancing molecular breeding programmes against salinity and to investigate the <italic>Oryza</italic> genome evolution.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Genome size estimation</title><p id="Par6">The plant, after collecting from the coastal region of Sundarban delta of West Bengal, India (21&#x000b0;36&#x02032;N and 88&#x000b0; 15&#x02032;E) was established at Net house through clonal propagation. To estimate the genome size, we used 20&#x02009;mg leaf extract from a 10&#x02009;cm long plant grown in pot. DNA content was estimated as fluorescence of propidium iodide (PI)-stained<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> nuclei of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome using <italic>Pisum sativum</italic> (pea) (1&#x02009;C&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.09&#x02009;pg) as an external standard<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Experiment was conducted with FACS cell sorter by BD-LSR II(BD-JH FACS Academy, Jamia Hamdard (Hamdard University) Hamdard Nagar, New Delhi, India)and data were analyzed by BD FACS Diva v.8.0.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bdbiosciences.com/in/instruments/software/facsdiva/features/overview.jsp">http://www.bdbiosciences.com/in/instruments/software/facsdiva/features/overview.jsp</ext-link>). The whole experiment was repeated 3 times with 8 samples in each time.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Library preparation and sequencing</title><p id="Par7">Genomic DNA (gDNA) was isolated by CTAB method as per our previous protocol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> from young leaf of the same plant used to estimate the genome size. The quality of the isolated DNA was checked by a NanoDrop D-1000 spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, DE) and Qubit Fluorometer. This DNA was used to make one Illumina short Paired-end (PE) library of 151&#x02009;bp long reads and four Mate-pair (MP)library such as 2&#x02009;kb, 4&#x02009;kb, 6&#x02009;kb and 8&#x02009;kb in size following the standard Illumina protocols (Illumina, San Diego, CA) and sequenced with HiSeq4000 platform (Illumina, San Diego, CA). In addition, we also used Nanopore long reads for better assembly which was sequenced on MinION Mk1b (Oxford Nanopore Technologies, Oxford, UK) using SpotON flow cell (R9.4) in a 48&#x02009;h sequencing protocol on MinKNOW 1.4.32. Base calling was performed using Albacore and base called reads were processed using Poretools version 0.6.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. All the sequencing works were carried out at M/S Genotypic Technology Private Limited, Bengaluru, India.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><italic>De-novo</italic> assembly of nuclear genome</title><p id="Par8">First, the raw reads were quality checked using FastQC_v.0.11.5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/">https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link>) and were further processed by PLATANUStrimmer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> for trimming the adaptors and low quality regions towards 3&#x02032;-end at PHRED quality score cut-off of Q30. The processed paired-end (PE) reads were used for contig assembly using PLATANUS <italic>de novo</italic> assembler v1.2.4<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> at default parameters. Scaffolding of the assembled contigs was performed using PLATANUS v1.2.4 and SSPACE (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.baseclear.com/genomics/bioinformatics/basetools/SSPACE">https://www.baseclear.com/genomics/bioinformatics/basetools/SSPACE</ext-link>, V3.0) with MP and Nanopore libraries followed by gap closing with GapCloser program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://soap.genomics.org.cn/about.html">http://soap.genomics.org.cn/about.html</ext-link>) to fill the gaps within scaffolds.</p><p id="Par9">Completeness of the assembled genome was evaluated by Core Eukaryotic Genes Mapping Approach (CEGMA) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://korflab.ucdavis.edu/datasets/cegma/">http://korflab.ucdavis.edu/datasets/cegma/</ext-link>) and Benchmarking Universal Single-Copy Orthologs (BUSCO) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://busco.ezlab.org/">http://busco.ezlab.org/</ext-link>) with <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> as the reference genome.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Genome annotation of nuclear genome</title><p id="Par10">Putative protein-coding genes were predicted using a combined strategy that integrates <italic>ab intio</italic> gene predictor AUGUSTUS 3.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinf.uni-greifswald.de/augustus/">http://bioinf.uni-greifswald.de/augustus/</ext-link>) and sequence evidence based annotation pipeline, MAKER-P v2.31.8 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.yandell-lab.org/software/maker-p.html">http://www.yandell-lab.org/software/maker-p.html</ext-link>) with <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> as reference gene model. In addition, 5 transcriptome SRA [SRX248542 (Salt450 along with Submerged); SRX248538 (Control); SRX248541 (Submerged); SRX248540 (Salt700); SRX248539 (Salt450)] were used as expression evidence for this prediction (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Resulting gene models were filtered for valid start codon. The final set of predicted protein-coding genes was annotated with Blast2GO (version 4.01)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> by using BLAST<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> based approach against a database containing functional plant genes downloaded from NCBI with an E-value cut-off of &#x02264;1e<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>. Genes with significant hits were assigned with GO (Gene Ontology) terms and EC (Enzyme Commission) numbers. InterProScan search and pathway analyses with KEGG database were also performed by using Blast2GO.</p><p id="Par11">In order to predict the conserved and unique gene families among the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome and 11 other <italic>Oryza</italic> species, an HMMScan of HMMER 3.1 package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hmmer.org/">http://hmmer.org/</ext-link>) was run against the protein sequences of all these 12 species (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>), based on the profiles compiled in Pfam release 31.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pfam.xfam.org/">http://pfam.xfam.org/</ext-link>) of the Pfam database at default parameters.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Prediction and analysis of F-box and SOS pathway genes</title><p id="Par12">A combined approach of HMMER search and BLAST search was used to retrieve the putative F-box genes. F-box HMM domain (PF00646) was downloaded from Pfam site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pfam.xfam.org/">http://pfam.xfam.org/</ext-link>). HMMER search and BLAST search was done against 33,627 protein sequences of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> with the E-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1e<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>. Both results were merged for non-redundant significant hits and were checked for the presence of F-box domain (PF00646) by CD search tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/bwrpsb/bwrpsb.cgi">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/bwrpsb/bwrpsb.cgi</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par13">A keyword based search was done for available <italic>SOS1</italic> genes at NCBI with keyword &#x0201c;plasma membrane Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;<italic>SOS1</italic>&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;salt overly sensitive 1&#x0201d;. A non-redundant set of 149 <italic>SOS1</italic> genes was found in different plant species, ranging from a minimum length of 65 amino-acid to maximum 1213 amino-acid. Out of total 149 genes, 123 genes were found to have the &#x0201c;Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter or exchanger family&#x0201d; domain as predicted by CD-batch search tool. To predict the <italic>SOS1</italic> genes in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome, the 33627 genes of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> were BLAST searched against these 123 <italic>SOS1</italic> genes. The significant hits, with 60% identity, were checked for the presence of &#x0201c;Sodium/hydrogen exchanger family&#x0201d; domain (PF00999) at threshold of e-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1e-<sup>10</sup> by CD search tool. MEGA 7.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> was used to perform alignment and phylogenetic analyses between the newly predicted <italic>SOS1</italic> genes in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> and known <italic>SOS1</italic> genes from other plant species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Identification of transcription factors</title><p id="Par14">To identify the transcription factors (TFs) in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genes, plant transcription factors sequences were downloaded from Plant Transcription Factor Database v4.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://planttfdb.cbi.pku.edu.cn/">http://planttfdb.cbi.pku.edu.cn/</ext-link>) and a BLAST search based approach was used with cut-off values for E-value, identity and query-coverage as &#x02264;1e<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>, &#x02265;40% and &#x02265;50%, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Identification of repetitive elements and SSR markers</title><p id="Par15">Repetitive elements, retrotransposons and DNA transposons were identified and masked in the assembled <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome by using RepeatMasker Tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.repeatmasker.org/">http://www.repeatmasker.org/</ext-link>) against the RepBase v.20170127 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.girinst.org/repbase/">http://www.girinst.org/repbase/</ext-link>) using the reference genomic repeats of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> for hard masking. LTR_FINDER v1.05 was used to identify full-length LTR (long terminal repeat) retrotransposon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. The SSRs were identified by MIcroSAtellite identification tool (MISA) perl script (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pgrc.ipk-gatersleben.de/misa/">http://pgrc.ipk-gatersleben.de/misa/</ext-link>). The minimum number of nucleotide repeats searched during the SSR analysis was set as ten for mono-, six for di-, four for tri- and three for tetra-, penta- and hexa-nucleotide repeats with maximal number of bases interrupting 2 SSRs in a compound microsatellite as 100.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Identification of non-coding RNAs (ncRNA)</title><p id="Par16">The ribosomal RNA (rRNA) and small nuclear RNA (snRNA) were identified by INFERNAL<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> with default parameters against Rfam database (release 9.1) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rfam.xfam.org">http://rfam.xfam.org</ext-link>). To predict the miRNAs, we used two steps procedure: first, homology search against Rfam database with a cut-off of 90% identity and query coverage, secondly the presence of hairpin structure in the surrounding sequence of predicted miRNA. The tRNAscan-SE algorithms (Version 1.23)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> were used to identify and annotate transfer RNA (tRNA) genes with default parameters. For the prediction and annotation of small nucleolar RNA (snoRNA) genes in the assembled genome, snoScan was used with the yeast rRNA methylation sites and yeast rRNA sequences provided by the snoScan distribution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Phylogenetic analysis with single-copy genes among <italic>Oryza</italic> species</title><p id="Par17">All protein sequences of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome and 11 other sequenced <italic>Oryza</italic> species (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>) were subjected to CD-HIT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> for clustering at cut-off of 90% coverage and similarity to form unique clusters. Clusters with a single copy gene from all 12 genomes, termed as Single-Copy-gene Clusters, were used for molecular phylogenetic analysis by using the steps as described by Kawano <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Synteny analysis for conserved regions with other species</title><p id="Par18">Conserved synteny is used as a measurement for evolutionary divergence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> or as calculation of conserved coding or non-coding region across different genomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. To identify the conserved regions across genomes of interest, we performed the synteny analysis of the assembled genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> with the reference genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> and the model dicot species <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic>, along with its wild halophytic relatives <italic>Schrenkiella parvula</italic> and <italic>E</italic>. <italic>salsugineum</italic>. The genome sequences of these 4 species were downloaded from NCBI (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>) and BLAST search was used to find out the conserved regions between <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> assembled genome and these 4 reference genomes with an e-value cut-off of&#x02009;&#x02264;1e<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>. Homologous blocks of alignment length of &#x02265;500&#x02009;bp between the references and the assembled genome were rendered in the synteny plot generated using CIRCOS tool v0.67-7<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Reference-based assembly of chloroplast genome</title><p id="Par19">We used the Nanopore long reads to assemble the chloroplast genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic>. The Nanopore reads were BLAST searched against chloroplast genomes of 11 <italic>Oryza</italic> species of interest (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Out of 1,717,607 Nanopore reads, 28,218 reads (95.26&#x02009;Mb) were showing significant hits (E-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1e<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>) against <italic>Oryza</italic> species and were used for 2-round assembly by CLC Genomics Workbench 9.5.1 (CLC Bio, Arhus, Denmark) with chloroplast sequence of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa&#x000a0;</italic>ssp. <italic>indica</italic> and <italic>japonica</italic> as reference. Circular orientation was checked and chloroplast annotation was done by CpGAVAS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The four junctions between 2 inverted repeat&#x000a0;regions and 2 single copy regions were validated by PCR amplification using 4 pairs of primers (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). GenBank file was prepared with sequin and subjected to OGDraw v1.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> to generate chloroplast gene map. We also performed the phylogenetic analysis of this assembled chloroplast genome along with chloroplast sequence of 11 other sequenced <italic>Oryza</italic> species. All 12 sequences were aligned by ClustalW and evolutionary analyses were conducted using the Maximum Likelihood method based on the Tamura-Nei model in MEGA7<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Reference based assembly of mitochondrial genome</title><p id="Par20">The processed and quality filtered PE and MP reads were aligned against the mitochondrion genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> (NC_011033.1, 490,520&#x02009;bp) using bowtie2-2.2.5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/index.shtml">http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/index.shtml</ext-link>) and aligned reads were <italic>de novo</italic> assembled by Spades-3.9.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. The scaffolding and gap closing were done with SSPACE and GapCloser, respectively. The assembled genome was annotated for genes and tRNAs by MITOS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> and MiTFi<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>, respectively. Phylogenetic analysis was done with 4 other available mitochondrial genomes of <italic>Oryza</italic> species (<italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica, O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>indica, O</italic>. <italic>rufipogon</italic> and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>minuta</italic>), 2 monocot species (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> and <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>) and 2 dicot species (<italic>Glycine max</italic> and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic>) by MEGA7<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Accession Numbers</title><p id="Par21">Project Information: NCBI BioProject ID: PRJNA396417. Chloroplast Genome Assembly: GenBank Accession no. MG383937. Mitochondrial genome Assembly: GenBank Accession no. MG429050.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Genome sequencing, assembly and quality assessment</title><p id="Par22">The genome size calculation for <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome from young leaf tissue of pot-grown single plant using <italic>P</italic>. <italic>sativum</italic> as an external standard with flow cytometric method resulted in the estimated genome size of 665&#x02009;Mb (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1a,b</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. We have generated a total of 166.69&#x02009;Gb of HQraw data comprising of short Illumina PEreads (123.78&#x02009;Gb), MP libraries of 2 Kb (11.12&#x02009;Gb), 4&#x02009;Kb (3.06&#x02009;Gb), 6&#x02009;Kb (11.23&#x02009;Gb) and 8&#x02009;Kb (11.13&#x02009;Gb) insert size, and Nanopore reads (6.35&#x02009;Gb) to yield the genome-sequencing depth (x) of 250.66 (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). The average read length for Illumina reads were 151&#x02009;bp, and that for long reads from Nanopore was 3,697&#x02009;bp with GC% in the range of 42&#x02013;44% for the sequencing reads generated from each of these technology. The nanopore technology, which was used to generate long reads, was quite successful as more than 60% of the reads having length above 1&#x02009;Kb, including ~10% above 10&#x02009;Kb length with maximum read length of 677.71&#x02009;Kb (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2a,b</xref>). The HQ Illumina PE reads were assembled into 101,992 contigs (555.66&#x02009;Mb; N50&#x02009;=&#x02009;15.13&#x02009;Kb) using PLATANUS followed by scaffolding with MP and Nanopore reads using SSPACE. The final assembly of 569.99&#x02009;Mb covering 85.71% of the estimated genome size was obtained after filling the gaps within the scaffolds (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This final assembly contains 58,362 scaffolds with N50 and L50 values were 1,858,627&#x02009;bp and 84, respectively. The long reads performed significantly well by reducing 101,992 contigs into 58,362 scaffolds and increased the N50 to ~122 times higher (15.13&#x02009;Kb to 1.85&#x02009;Mb). In this final assembly of 569.99&#x02009;Mb, we achieved the longest contig size of 7.85&#x02009;Mb with an average scaffold length of 9,766&#x02009;bp.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of genome assembly, predicted genes and repeats statistics.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2">Assembly</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Genome-sequencing depth (X)</td><td>250.66</td></tr><tr><td>Estimated genome size (Mb)</td><td>665</td></tr><tr><td>Estimated coverage (%)</td><td>85.71</td></tr><tr><td>Number of Scaffolds</td><td>58,362</td></tr><tr><td>Total Length of Scaffolds (bp)</td><td>569,994,164</td></tr><tr><td>Longest Scaffold (bp)</td><td>7,855,609</td></tr><tr><td>Average Scaffold Length (bp)</td><td>9766.5</td></tr><tr><td>GC %</td><td>41.5</td></tr><tr><td>Total Number of Non-ATGC Characters</td><td>3,579,650</td></tr><tr><td>Percentage of Non-ATGC Characters</td><td>0.63</td></tr><tr><td>Scaffolds&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 Kbp</td><td>13840 (551.47&#x02009;Mb)</td></tr><tr><td>Scaffolds&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;100 Kbp</td><td>411 (526.46&#x02009;Mb)</td></tr><tr><td>Scaffolds&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 Mbp</td><td>181 (417.36&#x02009;Mb)</td></tr><tr><td>Scaffolds&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 Mbp</td><td>12 (76.96&#x02009;Mb)</td></tr><tr><td>N50 of Scaffolds (bp)</td><td>1,858,627</td></tr><tr><td>L50 of Scaffolds (bp)</td><td>84</td></tr><tr><td>Number of contigs</td><td>101,992</td></tr><tr><td>Total Length of Contigs (bp)</td><td>555,666,118</td></tr><tr><td>N50 of Contigs (bp)</td><td>15,132</td></tr><tr><td>Longest Contig (bp)</td><td>157,100</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">
<bold>Gene Annotation</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>Number of Gene Models</td><td>33,627</td></tr><tr><td>Total Span of Genes (bp)</td><td>38,572,471</td></tr><tr><td>Gene Length in the Genome (%)</td><td>6.77%</td></tr><tr><td>Average Gene Length (bp)</td><td>1,147</td></tr><tr><td>Largest Gene Length (bp)</td><td>14,926</td></tr><tr><td>Number of Genes annotated</td><td>26,569 (79.01%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">
<bold>Repeats</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>Masked Repeat Sequence Length (bp)</td><td>113,352,647</td></tr><tr><td>Repeat Sequences in the genome (%)</td><td>19.89</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">Both CEGMA and BUSCO were used to check the completeness of the assembled genome for the presence of core genes. Results from CEGMA, registered for 92.34% (97.18%, partial) completeness of the assembled genome with 229 of 248 ultra-conserved core eukaryotic genes (CEGs) were present in the genome (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). The genome completeness raised upto 98.70% when normalized with respect to reference genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> spp. <italic>japonica</italic> Nipponbare-IRGSP-1.0. Similar results were found for the analysis with BUSCO that registered 97.08% completeness with normalized value of 99.43% (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Gene prediction and annotation</title><p id="Par24">With high level of completeness for the presence of core genes in the assembled genome, as predicted with CEGMA and BUSCO, we proceed with gene prediction and annotation in the assembled 58,362 scaffolds by integrating AUGUSTUS and MAKER-P annotation pipeline. A 3.32% (1,938) of the total scaffolds were found containing a total of 33,627 predicted protein-coding genes with length ranging from 180&#x02009;bp to 1926 bp and an average length of 1,147&#x02009;bp. These numbers are quite comparable with the predicted genes among the 11 other <italic>Oryza</italic> species sequenced so far (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">Of 33,627 predicted genes, a total number of 26,569 (79.01%) were assigned functions based on their significant best BLASTP hits to Plant Genes DB by using Blast2GO. Species distribution showed that majority (i.e. 59.28%) of these 26,569 genes had top BLAST hits against <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>, followed by <italic>O</italic>. <italic>brachyantha, Aegilops tauschii, Setaria italica</italic> and <italic>Zea mays</italic> with 28.13%, 2.15%, 2.27% and 2.01%, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). In total, a good amount of 87.41% genes showed homology against rice and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>brachyantha</italic>, in spite of less number of genes from these genomes in the plant gene database used for annotation (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>), suggesting its existence somewhere between AA and FF genome type or between domesticated and wild relatives. In order to identify the genes associated with biological processes, molecular functions and cellular process, we carried out the functional annotation in terms of Gene Ontology (GO) using BLASTP results. A total of 35,690 GO terms were assigned to 16,357 genes associated with biological processes, cellular components and molecular functions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). Among the biological processes, the most prevalent were metabolic process (6,564), cellular process (5,661) and single-organism process (3,169) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). Apart from these three generally high-scoring categories, there are 19 more groups with at least 1 or more genes with assigned GO terms but noticeable ones are &#x0201c;response to stimulus&#x0201d; (827 genes), &#x0201c;signalling&#x0201d; (251 genes) and &#x0201c;developmental process&#x0201d; (130 genes). The 827 genes under GO category &#x0201c;response to stimulus&#x0201d; were assigned with 207 GO terms or sub-categories like &#x0201c;response to stress&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;salt-stress&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;oxidative stress&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;water deprivation&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;auxin&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;abscisic acid&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;biotic-&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;abiotic-stimulus&#x0201d; pointing towards the significant presence of stress-related genes in the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome, which are either absent or present in very less number in rice (IRGSP 1.0) (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). For cellular processes associated genes, ~40% of genes were assigned GO terms for cell or cell-part category and ~29% genes to that for membrane or membrane-part category (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). With 51.59% (8,732 genes), the largest category among genes associated with GO terms for molecular functions was binding activity followed by catalytic activity (35.33%; 5,980 genes) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). A total of 2,844 genes were annotated with enzyme code distribution in which high abundance of genes were assigned hydrolases enzyme (1336) and transferases (707) followed by oxidoreductase (404), lyases (155), isomerases (127) and ligases (115). Additionally, 4,640 of the predicted genes were functionally annotated with Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database. The observed different types in abundance of protein function classes may be important to support different life-styles of the plant species. Finally, there were 7,058 genes in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> without any significant BLAST hits (E-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1e<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>) against plant genes database and 2,216 of these genes were found neither any significant GO hits nor any InterProScan match which accounts for 22.33% and 6.60% of total genes, respectively indicating that these could act as a gene-pool for <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> specific and unique genes (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>BLAST based annotation of predicted genes in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic>. (<bold>a</bold>) Species distribution of 26,569 genes with BLAST hits showed that majority of them (i.e. 59.28%) had top BLAST hits against <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic>ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>, followed by <italic>O</italic>. <italic>brachyantha, Aegilop stauschii, Setaria italica</italic> and <italic>Zea mays</italic> with28.13%, 2.15%, 2.27% and 2.01%, respectively, (<bold>b</bold>) GO terms distribution of 26,569 genes in level 2 GO categroization in biological Process, cellular component, and molecular function.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_31518_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1394"/></fig></p><p id="Par26">Transcription factors (TF), as key regulator for gene expression, are best suited for understanding the molecular mechanism and incorporating the abiotic stress tolerance in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. The BLAST based homology search of genes of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> against available plant TFs sequences in PlantTFDB 4.0 identified 4,916 genes (14.62% of total genes) in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> distributed in 56 different TF classes across 133 plant species (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>). These 4,916 TFs have a high abundance of the stress-response influencing TFs like MYB or MYB_related (519), NAC (322), bZIP (231), WRKY (177), HB (118), HSF (40), and AP (33). The identified 4,916 TF genes showed homology primarily against <italic>O</italic>. <italic>punctata, O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica, O</italic>. <italic>meridionalis, O</italic>. <italic>brachyantha, Malus domestica, O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>indica, Leersia perrieri, O</italic>. <italic>glumaepatula, O</italic>. <italic>nivara, O</italic>. <italic>longistaminata, Sisymbriumirio, Actinidia chinensis</italic> and <italic>Fragaria vesca</italic> with over 100 genes against each of these plant species (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>). About 40.30% (1,981) of the identified 8,135 TF genes were showing homology against 11 <italic>Oryza</italic> species.</p><p id="Par27">We compared the conserved and unique gene families between <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome and 11 other sequenced <italic>Oryza</italic> species with representatives from <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica, O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>indica, O</italic>. <italic>rufipogon, O</italic>. <italic>punctata, O</italic>. <italic>nivara, O</italic>. <italic>meridionalis, O</italic>. <italic>longistaminata, O</italic>. <italic>glumaepatula, O</italic>. <italic>glaberrima, O</italic>. <italic>brachyantha</italic> and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>barthii</italic>. This comparison resulted in a core set of 652,000 genes representing 3,215 clusters shared among all 12 <italic>Oryza</italic> species, encoding ancestral gene families (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). We found a total of 20 gene clusters comprising 22 genes unique to the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome followed by <italic>O</italic>. <italic>rufipogon</italic> (21 unique gene families: 28 genes), <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> (18 unique gene families: 20 genes), <italic>O</italic>. <italic>glumaepatula</italic> (16 unique gene families: 26 genes) and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>glaberrima</italic> (11 unique gene families: 29 genes). Interestingly, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp.<italic>indica</italic> had 468 unique gene families that contain 1,011 genes. The number of unique gene families clusters and gene in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>longistaminata</italic> (54 unique gene families: 59 genes)and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>punctate</italic> (51 unique gene families: 64 genes) genome were very similar followed by <italic>O</italic>. <italic>meridionalis</italic> (43 unique gene families: 59 genes).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Number of shared and unique gene families among 12 <italic>Oryza</italic> species including <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome with number of genes within families in parentheses showing a high number of shared genes (652,000) and families (3,215) among these <italic>Oryza</italic> species.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_31518_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1615"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">F-box domain proteins are important for our analysis not only as one of the largest gene family controlling many biological functions but because of its important role in the regulation of various stress-response pathways and developmental processes in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. We identified 421 F-box genes in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome using HMMER and BLAST search based approach against F-box domain (PF00646). These F-box genes are about 1.25% of total genes in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> comparable to those with <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> (2.53%), <italic>V</italic>. <italic>vinifera</italic> (0.51%), <italic>P</italic>. <italic>trichocarpa</italic> (0.81%), <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> (1.91%), <italic>S</italic>. <italic>bicolor</italic> (1.59%), <italic>S</italic>. <italic>moellendorffii</italic> (1.11%), and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>patens</italic> (0.42%), plant genomes representing different levels of plant kingdoms including a bryophyte, a lycophyte, monocots, and eudicots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par29">There are 3 main genes in the SOS (salt overly sensitive) signal pathway, i.e. <italic>SOS1</italic>, <italic>SOS2</italic> and <italic>SOS3</italic> but as <italic>SOS2</italic> gets activated by <italic>SOS3</italic> after interaction, and their complex is required to fully activate <italic>SOS1</italic>, we focused on the identification of <italic>SOS1</italic> gene, a set of genes with most important role in plant salt-tolerance, to get an overlay of the abundance of <italic>SOS</italic> pathway related genes in the assembled genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Moreover <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> is halophytic in nature and <italic>SOS1</italic> was found to have the activity needed for halophytic characteristic as reported in halophytic dicot <italic>T</italic>. <italic>salsuginea</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. <italic>SOS1</italic> is one among the very few genes that required for plant salt tolerance which encodes for &#x0201c;plasma membrane Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter&#x0201d;, which not only plays an important role in germination but more importantly aid in the growth of plants in saline conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. So we focused on &#x0201c;Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter&#x0201d; domain or keyword based strategy to identify <italic>SOS1</italic> genes, as described in methodology. We identified a total of 8&#x000a0;<italic>SOS1</italic> genes in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome either by homology search against known <italic>SOS1</italic> genes or BLAST based function annotation of predicted genes and with the presence of &#x0201c;Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter or exchanger family&#x0201d; domain. To classify these eight&#x000a0;<italic>SOS1</italic> genes in to plasma membrane Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> or vacuolar Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter gene, we have chosen 18 <italic>SOS1</italic> genes as used by Chen <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> and are available at NCBI with Accession numbers as: AF256224, AF510074, AB439132, GU188850, KC410809, KJ577576, EU780458, AY785147, AB021878, DQ517530, FJ866610, DQ071264, EU879059, AY131235, AB198179, KF914414, EF207775, EU333827, representing 11 plasma membrane and 7 vacuolar Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter genes from different plant species including <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana, Chrysanthemum crassum, Halostachys caspica, Helianthus tuberosus, Kosteletzkya virginica, Limonium gmelinii, O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica, Populus euphratica, Pennisetum glaucum, Salicornia brachiata, Salicornia europaea, Suaeda japonica, S. salsa, T</italic>. <italic>halophile</italic> and <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic>. A multiple sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis was performed between these sequences and the close analysis of so obtained Neighbour Joining (NJ) tree suggested that only 1 of the 8 <italic>SOS1</italic> genes (<italic>OcSOS1-1</italic>) clustered with plasma-membrane Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporters of other plant species while rest of the 7<italic>SOS1</italic> genes (<italic>OcSOS1-2,3,4,5,6,7,8</italic>) were part of the cluster having vacuolar Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporters from other plant species (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). But in both clusters, these genes were closely related with <italic>SOS1</italic> homologs of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>. Three of these identified <italic>SOS1</italic> genes i.e. <italic>OcSOS1-6, OcSOS1-7</italic> and <italic>OcSOS1-8</italic> could be the newly evolving ones as they showed a very low or no homology against known SOS1 genes and were present in a separate cluster in the obtained tree.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The phylogenetic analysis of <italic>OcSOS1</italic> genes with some other representative plant species to classify the identified 8&#x000a0;<italic>SOS1</italic> genes in to plasma membrane or vacuolar Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter genes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_31518_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1904"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Analysis of repetitive elements, SSRs and ncRNAs</title><p id="Par30">A total of 113,352,647&#x02009;bp (19.89%) of the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome was estimated to consist of repeated sequences (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). We were able to identify 129,734 (14.95%) retrotransposons (class I), 79,468 (3.53%) DNA transposons (class II) and 3,092 (0.16%) unclassified elements in the genome (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>).Among retroelements, 14.48% (82.53&#x02009;Mb) of genome accounts for LTR retrotransposons and just 0.47% for Non-LTRs (SINEs and LINEs). The copia and gypsy are the two main components of LTR retrotransposons accounting 8.24% (46.94&#x02009;Mb) and 6.04% (34.42&#x02009;Mb) of the assembled genome, respectively. With LTR_FINDER, we have identified 218 full length LTR retrotransposons in 142 scaffolds (out of total 58362 scaffolds) comprising of a total of 1.30&#x02009;Mb which accounts just 0.23% of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>).</p><p id="Par31">A total of 230,968 SSRs were obtained across genome with an average frequency of one SSR per 2.46&#x02009;kb. Out of total 58,362 scaffolds, 12,926 (22.15%) were found to contain SSR and 5,171 of these had more than one SSR (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S11</xref>). Among these identified SSRs, tetranucleotides (27.64%) were highest followed by trinucleotides (26.66%), mono- (19.99%), di- (16.79%), penta- (5.92%) and hexa-nucleotides (3.00%) (Fig&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5a</xref>). For mono-, di- and tri- types of SSRs A/T, AT/TA, and CCG/CGG, were the motifs with highest percentages of 16.86%, 10.28% and 7.54%, respectively (Fig&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5b</xref>).</p><p id="Par32">Non-coding RNA genes have important regulatory roles in a number of plant phenomenons like chromosomal silencing, regulating the transcription process, developmental control, and various stress-responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Different types of ncRNAs were identified in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome included miRNA, rRNA, snRNA, tRNA and snoRNA (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S12</xref>). The <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome was found to have 200 miRNA genes, 118 snRNA genes and 3,110 rRNA (LSU, SSU, 5_8S_rRNA and 5S_rRNA) genes encoded by &#x0201c;cmsearch&#x0201d; module of the INFERNAL package using the relevant covariance model from Rfam. The tRNAScan-SE algorithms, as applied with default parameters to the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome assembly, resulted in the identification of 900 putative tRNAs in the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> assembly. The snoRNA is a small RNA molecule that leads the chemical modifications of other RNAs, including rRNAs, tRNAs and snRNAs. In total 1,184 snoRNA were identified in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Single copy genes: Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> along with other 11 <italic>Oryza</italic> species</title><p id="Par33">In order to perform the genome level phylogenetic analysis of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> along with other 11 <italic>Oryza</italic> species, a total of 194,069 unique clusters were formed with a cut-off of 90% for coverage and similarity from their protein sequences. The cluster analysis resulted in total of 170 putative single copy gene clusters. These single copy proteins from the 12 genomes were considered for phylogenetic analysis. The tree generated with these single-copy orthologous genes placed <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> as an individual clade and was found consistent with the species-tree obtained from the TimeTree database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>, which generally used to retrieved the divergence times among species. A consensus analysis based on both the tree depict that FF genome (<italic>O</italic>. <italic>brachyantha</italic>) diverged about 15 million years ago (MYA) followed by <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> around 10 MYA and the BB genome (<italic>O</italic>. <italic>punctata</italic>) about 6 MYA from the AA genome types. Among AA type genomes, it seems that Australian species, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>meridionlais</italic> was first to diverge from other AA genome species (South-American, Asian and African) and that happened somewhere around 2&#x02013;3 MYA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Tree topology of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> along with 11 other Oryza species based on the 170 clusters derived from 1:1 single-copy orthologous genes to depict the phylogeny at genome level to have an estimate of evolution of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> along with AA, BB and FF genome types.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_31518_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2066"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Synteny analysis</title><p id="Par34">For representation of homologous blocks in synteny plots, unplaced scaffolds from each reference were concatenated and represented as single contig (&#x0201c;Un&#x0201d;) and the contigs with less than 1MB size in our assembled genome were concatenated and are represented as a single scaffold (&#x0201c;Unplaced&#x0201d;) (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). In the synteny analysis of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> with three of the dicot species including <italic>A</italic>.<italic>thaliana</italic>, <italic>E</italic>. <italic>salsugineum</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parvula</italic>,high numbers of syntenic blocks were found with just 1 scaffold (S128; 1,335,219&#x02009;bp) of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> having no collinear or syntenic block with any of these three species (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6a&#x02013;c</xref>). On the other hand, in spite of large genome size and more number of chromosomes in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>, there were 8 scaffolds of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> showing no collinearity or synteny with <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6d</xref>) indicating that these scaffolds, which account for 12.52&#x02009;Mb i.e. 2.19% of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome, might have some possible roles in halophytic adaptation of this species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Analysis of chloroplast genome</title><p id="Par35">The chloroplast genome exists as circular molecule in angiosperms with size ranging from 120 to 160&#x02009;kb in length<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. We used 11 chloroplast sequences of <italic>Oryza</italic> species with size ranging from 134,558&#x02009;bp to 135,525&#x02009;bp as reference (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Chloroplast reads were extracted from Nanopore data by BLAST search and assembled by guidance-based assembly into a circular contig of 134,750&#x02009;bp length. It has a typical and standard quadripartite plant chloroplast structure with comparable regions of ~20.8&#x02009;kb, ~80.8&#x02009;kb and ~12.3&#x02009;kb inverted repeats (IR), large single copy (LSC) and small single copy (SSC) regions, respectively with that of other <italic>Oryza</italic> species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. These four junctions were further confirmed and validated by PCR amplification (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). While the IRa and IRb spanned for 20,800&#x02009;bp region of assembled chloroplast, the LSC and SSC regions covered 80,816&#x02009;bp and 12,334&#x02009;bp, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref> and Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S13</xref>). There were 82 protein coding genes, 33 tRNA genes and 8 rRNA genes, making a total of 123 genes with 18 genes as one copy in each of the 2 IR regions (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S13</xref>). In total, it has 43 genes involved in photosynthesis and divided in 6 different classes (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S14</xref>). No <italic>ycf1</italic> gene was found in this newly assembled chloroplast which supports the early loss of this gene in <italic>Poaceae</italic> family<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. The phylogenetic analysis with chloroplast genomes of 11 other <italic>Oryza</italic> species infer that this newly assembled chloroplast genome is close to <italic>japonica</italic> subgroup of <italic>Oryza</italic> and is a part of the clade consisting of AA genome type while the BB and FF genome type, i.e. <italic>punctata</italic> and <italic>brachyantha</italic>, respectively were representing single different clades each (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Genome organization and phylogeny of chloroplast genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic>. (<bold>a</bold>) the chloroplast genome organization showing the genes transcribed clockwise (drawn inside the circle) and counter clockwise (drawn outside) with different gene functional groups are colour coded. (<bold>b</bold>) phylogenetic relationship of 12 <italic>Oryza</italic> species based upon whole choloroplast genome.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_31518_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2241"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Analysis of mitochondrial genome</title><p id="Par36">The assembled mitochondrial genome is 491,065&#x02009;bp long (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>) with 43.07% of GC content comprising of 46 protein coding genes, 37 tRNA genes and 4 rRNA genes (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S15</xref>). The annotation also confirm the presence of 4 genes related to functional category &#x02018;Origins of replication&#x02019;, making a total of 91 genes in the mitochondrial genome with a total of 48,960&#x02009;bp (i.e.9.97% of assembled mitochondrial genome). The genome organization is comparable with available mitochondrial genomes of 4 other <italic>Oryza</italic> species with almost similar GC content and same range of protein coding genes, tRNA genes and rRNAgenes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. The annotated 46 protein coding genes here, included 25 genes related to the production of ATP synthase and the electron transport chain with 9, 1, 3 and 5 subunits of complex I (<italic>nad1-9</italic>), III (<italic>cob</italic>), IV (<italic>cox1-3</italic>) and V (<italic>atp1,4,6,8,9</italic>), respectively (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S16</xref>). Besides, there were 11 ribosomal proteins and only a single maturase (<italic>mat-r</italic>) gene.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Assembly and phylogeny of mitochondrial genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic>. (<bold>a</bold>) Circular representation of the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> mitochondrial genome showing GC content and identity with reference mitochondrial genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> at each base level. (<bold>b</bold>) Phylogenetic relationship of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> along with other species from Poaceae family and some other monocot and dicot species at mitochondrial genome level.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_31518_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2321"/></fig></p><p id="Par37">To understand the evolutionary relationship of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic>, at mitochondrial level, with other <italic>Oryza</italic> species, the mitochondrial genome sequences of 4 members of <italic>Poaceae</italic> family (<italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica, O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>indica, O</italic>. <italic>rufipogon</italic> and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>minuta</italic>), 2 other monocot species (<italic>T</italic>. <italic>aestivum</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>bicolor</italic>) and 2 dicot species (<italic>G</italic>. <italic>max</italic> and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic>) were aligned to the newly assembled mitochondria genome of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> to construct a NJ tree (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). On one hand, this phylogenetic analysis with NJ tree clearly separates <italic>Poaceae</italic> family members from other 4 species included in the analysis and on the other hand, it placed <italic>O</italic>. <italic>rufipogon</italic> and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>minuta</italic> in one clade while <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>indica</italic> in other clade as reported earlier by researchers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. But most importantly, we found <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> in a group of <italic>Poaceae</italic> family, but in a different clade and closely related to the reference genome i.e. <italic>O</italic>. <italic>sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec24" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par38">We report first time the draft genome sequence of a monocot halophyte, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> which provides an excellent platform for exploring the genetic potential of this wild species of rice. Our flow cytometry based results indicated the genome size be of 665&#x02009;Mb, which is much closer to the previously reported estimated size of 771 Mb<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. The results demonstrate several other interesting biological aspects and features of the genome. The Nanopore long reads significantly improved almost all the metrics related to quality of assembly, including reduced number of scaffolds, large size of the scaffolds (upto 7.85&#x02009;Mb), a significant N50 (1.85&#x02009;Mb) or L50 value, a good range of mean and median lengths (9.76&#x02009;kb) along with a high percentage of genome completeness measure (upto 97.08%) based on the presence of core orthologous genes and hence contributed in the best representation of genome. It also helped us to retrieve the complete set of chloroplast genome sequence. To date, this is the only largest sequenced genome of any halophyte with the deepest sequencing coverage of 250.66-fold, considering the available sequenced halophytic genome such as <italic>T</italic>. <italic>parvula</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>salsuginea</italic> and/or <italic>E</italic>. <italic>salsugineum</italic> (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S17</xref>). A total of 33,627 predicted protein-coding genes that we discovered here, are the highest among sequenced halophytes and are comparable with other <italic>Oryza</italic> species. A 22.33% of these genes were found specific and unique to <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> but rest were showing a good homology with rice (domesticated and AA type) and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>brachyantha</italic> (wild and FF type). The small genomes of chloroplast and mitochondria aid well in understanding the evolutionary background of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> in <italic>Oryza</italic> genus and among with AA, BB and FF genome type and supports the conservative nature of chloroplast and mitochondrial genomes within the taxon. Further, a phylogenetic analysis based on the single copy genes among <italic>Oryza</italic> species pointing towards the existence of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> genome somewhere between the divergence of FF and BB genome form AA genome. It could be true as assumed by researchers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> but needs to be validated with further study.</p><p id="Par39">Further, when compared with rice, there were found 123 GO terms including &#x0201c;response to salt-stress&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;abscisic acid&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;biotic stress&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;desiccation&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;defence response to fungus&#x0201d;, etc., under GO category &#x0201c;response to stimulus&#x0201d;, exclusively present in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> but completely absent or present in low number in rice favouring the high salinity adaptation of this species. Moreover the presence of 8 <italic>SOS1</italic> gene copies in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> mayfavours and ads up to its salinity tolerance mechanism as <italic>SOS1</italic>contribute to salt tolerance by pumping the sodium ions out of the cells once activated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Even the total identified (4,916) and stress-responsive TFs (1,440) were much larger in number than those found in rice (2,478 and 1,408, respectively) in earlier reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. <italic>Oryza coarctata</italic>, even being a tetraploid, is found to have low repetitive content which is an exception and similar results were found reported by earlier researchers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Although 82.53&#x02009;Mb (14.48%) of genome consists of LTR retrotransposons but only 1.30&#x02009;Mb (i.e. 0.23% of genome) of them were found as full-length LTRs, suggesting the probably high occurrences of recombination or deletion events post retrotransposition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. Comparatively a little higher synteny was found for <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> with <italic>E</italic>. <italic>salsugineum</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parvula</italic> as compared to rice, which could be due to the halophytic nature of these species indicating that, this genome sequence offers advantages as an ideal system for functional genomics to understand the salinity tolerance mechanisms of monocots as rest halophyte sequenced genome are dicot species. More importantly, our genome information will complement the I-OMAP project along with already existing genomic resources of different wild and cultivated <italic>Oryza</italic> species and will aid in both the genome level and the salinity based comparative genomics, evolutionary studies and extension of gene pool for improvement in cultivated rice.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec25"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_31518_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary files</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Tapan Kumar Mondal and Hukam Chand Rawal contributed equally.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-31518-y.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The work was done with the financial support from Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR), New Delhi, India through in-house project. TKM is grateful to Mr Sukhdev Nath, Swami Vivekananda Youth Cultural Society, Sagar, Sundarban, South 24-Parganas, West Bengal, India for supplying the <italic>O</italic>. <italic>coarctata</italic> plants. The authors are thankful to M/S Genotypic Technology Private Limited, Bengaluru, India for sequencing work and M/S BD-JH FACS Academy, BD Biosciences India for flow cytometer work.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>T.K.M. conceptualized, initiated the project, designed the study, wrote and revised the manuscript. H.C.R. curated data, performed bioinformatics analysis, wrote the manuscript. S.C. performed wet lab analysis such as flow cytometry and validation of chloroplast genome. D.V. analyzed the data, wrote the manuscript. A.K.P., A.M., H.K. performed the research, K.G. helped in data curation and analysis, T.R.S. performed the formal analysis and supervision, N.K.S. conceptualized, administrated the project.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molla</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Debnath</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganie</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and analysis of novel salt responsive candidate gene based SSRs (cgSSRs) from rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>122</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-015-0498-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25982586?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25982586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganie</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of genetic diversity of Saltol QTL among the rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) genotypes</article-title><source>Physiol. Mol. Biol. Plants</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12298-016-0342-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27186024?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27186024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the saltol quantitative trait locus for salinity tolerance in rice</article-title><source>Rice</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12284-010-9053-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative sequence analysis of MONOCULM1-orthologous regions in 14 Oryza genomes</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>2071</fpage><lpage>2076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0812798106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19164767?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19164767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sanchez, P. L., Wing, R. A. &#x00026; Brar, D. S. The wild relative of Rice: Genomes and genomics. In: <italic>Genetics and Genomics of Rice</italic> 9&#x02013;25, 10.1007/978-1-4614-7903-1_2 (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bal</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutt</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of salt tolerance in wild rice (<italic>Oryza coarctata</italic> Roxb)</article-title><source>Plant and Soil</source><year>1986</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02372487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frew</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Memoirs: Nucleolar behaviour in the mitosis of plant cells</article-title><source>Quarterly J. Microscopical Sci.</source><year>1929</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>212</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Majumder</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insight into the salt tolerance factors of a wild halophytic rice, <italic>Porteresia coarctata</italic>: A physiological and proteomic approach</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2009</year><volume>229</volume><fpage>911</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-008-0878-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19130079?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19130079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deep transcriptome sequencing of wild halophyte rice, <italic>Porteresia coarctata</italic>, provides novel insights into the salinity and submergence tolerance factors</article-title><source>DNA Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dst042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24104396?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24104396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mondal, T. K., Ganie, S. A. &#x00026; Debnath, A. B. Identification of novel and conserved miRNAs from extreme halophyte, <italic>Oryza coarctata</italic>, a wild relative of rice. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic><bold>10</bold>, 10.1371/journal.pone.0140675 (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ammiraju</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Oryza</italic> bacterial artificial chromosome library resource: construction and analysis of 12 deep-coverage large-insert BAC libraries that represent the 10 genome types of the genus</article-title><source>Oryza. Genome Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.3766306</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16344555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16344555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zuccolo, A. <italic>et al</italic>. Transposable element distribution, abundance and role in genome size variation in the genus <italic>Oryza</italic>. <italic>BMC Evol</italic>. <italic>Biol</italic>. <bold>7</bold>, 10.1186/1471-2148-7-152 (2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ammiraju</surname><given-names>JSSD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Oryza BAC resource: A genus-wide and genome scale tool for exploring rice genome evolution and leveraging useful genetic diversity from wild relatives</article-title><source>Breeding Sci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1270/jsbbs.60.536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dassanayake</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genome of the extremophile crucifer <italic>Thellungiella parvula</italic></article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2011</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.889</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21822265?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21822265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insights into salt tolerance from the genome of <italic>Thellungiella salsuginea</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>12219</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1209954109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22778405?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22778405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The reference genome of the halophytic plant <italic>Eutremasalsugineum</italic></article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>46</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23518688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23518688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolezel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Greilhuber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of nuclear DNA content in plants using flow cytometry</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2233</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2007.310</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17853881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17853881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baranyi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Greilhuber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flow cytometric analysis of genome size variation in cultivated and wild <italic>Pisum sativum</italic> (Fabaceae)</article-title><source>Plant Syst. Evol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00982857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loman</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poretools: A toolkit for analyzing nanopore sequence data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>3399</fpage><lpage>3401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu555</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25143291?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25143291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kajitani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficient <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of highly heterozygous genomes from whole-genome shotgun short reads</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1384</fpage><lpage>1395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.170720.113</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24755901?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24755901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Conesa, A. &#x00026; G&#x000f6;tz, S. Blast2GO: A comprehensive suite for functional analysis in plant genomics. <italic>Int</italic>. <italic>J</italic>. <italic>Plant Genomics</italic><bold>2008</bold>, 10.1155/2008/619832 (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1990</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2231712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA7: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis Version 7.0 for Bigger Datasets</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1870</fpage><lpage>1874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw054</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27004904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27004904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hittalmani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome and transcriptome sequence of Finger millet (<italic>Eleusine coracana</italic> (L.) Gaertn.) provides insights into drought tolerance and nutraceutical properties</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>465</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-017-3850-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28619070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28619070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LTR_FINDER: an efficient tool for the prediction of full-length LTR retrotransposons</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>W265</fpage><lpage>W268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm286</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17485477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawrocki</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolbe</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infernal 1.0: Inference of RNA alignments</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1335</fpage><lpage>1337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp157</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19307242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19307242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TRNAscan-SE: A program for improved detection of transfer RNA genes in genomic sequence</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1996</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.5.0955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A computational screen for methylation guide snoRNAs in Yeast</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>1168</fpage><lpage>1171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.283.5405.1168</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10024243?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10024243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Godzik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cd-hit: A fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of protein or nucleotide sequences</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1658</fpage><lpage>1659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl158</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16731699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kawano, T. <italic>et al</italic>. Genetic diversity of Entamoeba: Novel ribosomal lineages from cockroaches. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic><bold>12</bold>, 10.1371/journal.pone.0185233 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synteny and collinearity in plant genomes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1153917</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18436778?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18436778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haudry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An atlas of over 90,000 conserved noncoding sequences provides insight into crucifer regulatory regions</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2684</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23817568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23817568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krzywinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circos: An information aesthetic for comparative genomics</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>1645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.092759.109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19541911?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19541911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CpGAVAS, an integrated web server for the annotation, visualization, analysis, and GenBank submission of completely sequenced chloroplast genome sequences</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>715</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-13-715</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23256920?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23256920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Drechsel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OrganellarGenomeDRAW (OGDRAW): A tool for the easy generation of high-quality custom graphical maps of plastid and mitochondrial genomes</article-title><source>Current Genet.</source><year>2007</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00294-007-0161-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nurk, S. <italic>et al</italic>. Assembling genomes and mini-metagenomes from highly chimeric reads. In Lecture Notes in Computer Science (including subseries Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence and Lecture Notes in Bioinformatics). <bold>7821</bold>, 158&#x02013;170, 10.1007/978-3-642-37195-0_13 (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MITOS: Improved <italic>de novo</italic> metazoan mitochondrial genome annotation</article-title><source>Mol. Phylogenetics Evol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2012.08.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000fc;hling</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improved systematic tRNA gene annotation allows new insights into the evolution of mitochondrial tRNA structures and into the mechanisms of mitochondrial genome rearrangements</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>2833</fpage><lpage>2845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr1131</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22139921?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22139921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawal</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaikwad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First <italic>de novo</italic> draft genome sequence of <italic>Oryzacoarctata</italic>, the only halophytic species in the genus <italic>Oryza</italic></article-title><source>F1000 Research</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1750</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.12414.2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29123646?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29123646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulatory networks in response to abiotic stresses in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and grasses</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.129791</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19126699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19126699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Omics&#x0201d; analyses of regulatory networks in plant abiotic stress responses</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2009.12.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20080055?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gagne</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Downes</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Durski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The F-box subunit of the SCF E3 complex is encoded by a diverse superfamily of genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>11519</fpage><lpage>11524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.162339999</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12169662?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vansiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Potuschak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Genschik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>F-box proteins everywhere</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2006.09.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17005440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17005440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of F-box genes in plants: Different modes of sequence divergence and their relationships with functional diversification</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>835</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0812043106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19126682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19126682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of an F-box protein gene reduces abiotic stress tolerance and promotes root growth in rice</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssq066</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21059694?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21059694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schumann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro-Quezada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullrich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Quint</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular evolution and selection patterns of plant F-Box proteins with C-terminal kelch repeats</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>155</volume><issue>2011</issue><fpage>835</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.166579</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21119043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21119043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishitani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> salt tolerance gene SOS1 encodes a putative Na+/H+ antiporter</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>6896</fpage><lpage>6901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.120170197</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10823923?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10823923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumaker</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of SOS1, a plasma membrane Na+/H+ exchanger in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, by SOS2 and SOS3</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>8436</fpage><lpage>8441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.122224699</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12034882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halfter</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishitani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SOS2 protein kinase physically interacts with and is activated by the calcium-binding protein SOS3</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>3735</fpage><lpage>3740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.7.3735</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10725350?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10725350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of SOS (salt overly sensitive) genes increases salt tolerance in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssn058</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19529826?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19529826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of halophytism by interference with SOS1 expression</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.137802</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19571313?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19571313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahrizi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of SOS1 gene in different species based on coding sequences</article-title><source>Middle-East J. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1226</fpage><lpage>1229</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GhSOS1, a plasma membrane Na+/H+ antiporter gene from upland cotton, enhances salt tolerance in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0181450</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0181450</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28723926?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28723926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacIntosh</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkerson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and analysis of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> expressed sequence tags characteristic of non-coding RNAs</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.010501</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11706161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11706161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suleski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paymer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tree of life reveals clock-like speciation and diversification</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>835</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msv037</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25739733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25739733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Learn</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rates and patterns of chloroplast DNA evolution</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>6795</fpage><lpage>67801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.15.6795</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8041699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8041699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wicke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneeweiss</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>dePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Quandt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolution of the plastid chromosome in land plants: Gene content, gene order, gene function</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-011-9762-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21424877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21424877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asaf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The complete chloroplast genome of wild rice (<italic>Oryzaminuta</italic>) and its comparison to related species</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>304</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00304</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28326093?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28326093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>YCF1: A Green TIC: Response to the de Vries <italic>et al</italic>. Commentary: Fig. 1</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1834</fpage><lpage>1838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00363</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26071422?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26071422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Asaf, S. <italic>et al</italic>. Mitochondrial genome analysis of wild rice (<italic>Oryzaminuta</italic>) and its comparison with other related species. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic><bold>11</bold>, 10.1371/journal.pone.0152937 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Construction, alignment and analysis of twelve framework physical maps that represent the ten genome types of the genus Oryza</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>R45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2008-9-2-r45</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18304353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18304353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny of rice genomes with emphasis on origins of allotetraploid species</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>14400</fpage><lpage>14405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.25.14400</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10588717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10588717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ammiraju</surname><given-names>JSS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatio-temporal patterns of genome evolution in allotetraploid species of the genus <italic>Oryza</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04251.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20487382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20487382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Priya, P. &#x00026; Jain, M. RiceSRTFDB: A database of rice transcription factors containing comprehensive expression, cis-regulatory element and mutant information to facilitate gene function analysis. <italic>Database</italic><bold>2013</bold>, 10.1093/database/bat027 (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic <italic>Oryza</italic> genomes: repetitive DNA sequences as genome modeling agents</article-title><source>Rice</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12284-010-9054-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-Wide Survey and Comparative Analysis of LTR Retrotransposons and Their Captured Genes in Rice and Sorghum</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e71118</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0071118</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23923055?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23923055</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>