<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur. J. Med. Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Journal of Medical Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0949-2321</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2047-783X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6306001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">358</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40001-018-0358-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between bisphenol A diglycidyl ether-specific IgG in serum and food sensitization in young children</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>Mayumi</given-names></name><address><phone>+81-93-691-7429</phone><email>tsuji@med.uoeh-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koriyama</surname><given-names>Chihaya</given-names></name><address><email>fiy@m.kufm.kagoshima-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>Yasuhiro</given-names></name><address><email>ishiyasu@hiroshima-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>Christoph F. A.</given-names></name><address><email>cfvogel@ucdavis.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>Toshihiro</given-names></name><address><email>kawamott@med.uoeh-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0374 5913</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.271052.3</institution-id><institution>Department of Environmental Health, </institution><institution>University of Occupational and Environmental Health, </institution></institution-wrap>1-1 Iseigaoka, Yahatanishi-ku, Kitakyusyu, Fukuoka Prefecture 807-8555 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1167 1801</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.258333.c</institution-id><institution>Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine, </institution><institution>Kagoshima University Graduate School of Medical and Dental Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>8-35-1 Sakuragaoka, Kagoshima, 890-8520 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8711 3200</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.257022.0</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Molecular Brain Science, Graduate School of Integrated Arts and Sciences, </institution><institution>Hiroshima University, </institution></institution-wrap>1-7-1 Kagamiyama, Higashi-Hiroshima, 739-8521 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9684</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27860.3b</institution-id><institution>Department of Environmental Toxicology, </institution><institution>University of California, Davis, </institution></institution-wrap>Davis, CA USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><elocation-id>61</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Recent studies have reported that endocrine-disrupting compound (EDC) exposure is related to food sensitization. Bisphenol A diglycidyl ether (BADGE) is one of the most widespread EDCs and its biological effects are considered to be greater on children than on adults. This study investigated the relationship between serum BADGE-specific immunoglobulin G (IgG) concentrations and food sensitization in young children by measuring food-specific IgE levels.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">In total, 98 young children (59 boys and 39 girls; median age: 7&#x000a0;months; 25th and 75th percentile ages: 6 and 8&#x000a0;months, respectively) were enrolled. Blood samples were collected twice from all children (median sampling interval: 6&#x000a0;months; 25th and 75th percentile: 5 and 7&#x000a0;months). Food sensitization was evaluated based on food-specific IgE titers (egg white, milk, and wheat), which were determined using the capsulated hydrophilic carrier polymer-radioallergosorbent test. Furthermore, a dot-blotting assay for BADGE-specific IgG and quantitative reverse-transcriptase PCR for <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>6</italic>, <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>8</italic>, <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>10</italic>, and <italic>COX</italic>-<italic>2</italic> mRNA expression were conducted.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">BADGE-specific IgG was detected in 20% of study subjects. A significant association was observed between the presence of BADGE-specific IgG and elevated wheat-specific IgE levels (OR&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.56; 95% CI 1.13&#x02013;11.2; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.031). This relationship was particularly strong in girls (OR&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.46; 95% CI 1.01&#x02013;89.0; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.049). A slight but non-significant association was noted between the presence of BADGE-specific IgG and elevated milk-specific IgE levels (OR&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.77; 95% CI 0.93&#x02013;8.22; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.067). The expression of <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>6</italic> mRNA among children with BADGE-specific IgG tended to increase, along with wheat-specific IgE levels.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">BADGE exposure might enhance food sensitization in early childhood. Therefore, this should be strictly regulated, especially in younger children.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s40001-018-0358-1) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Bisphenol A diglycidyl ether</kwd><kwd>Children</kwd><kwd>Food sensitization</kwd><kwd>IgE</kwd><kwd>Inflammatory cytokines</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) KAKENHI Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research </institution></funding-source><award-id>22790546</award-id><award-id>25860472</award-id><award-id>17K09174</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>Mayumi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Medical Research Encouragement Prize of The Japan Medical Association</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Bisphenol A (BPA) is produced in large quantities for use primarily in the synthesis of polycarbonate plastics and epoxy resins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Its content in products has been regulated in many countries because of its estrogenic activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Bisphenol A diglycidyl ether (BADGE) is a reactive prepolymer of BPA and one of the most widely used epoxy resins in the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In contrast to BPA, the safety of BADGE has not been well evaluated and its toxicity is not well understood. Importantly, however, it has also been reported to have estrogenic activity, albeit weaker than that of BPA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In our previous study, BADGE-specific IgG was identified in sera obtained from workers with contact dermatitis who had used this material in their working space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. This result suggested that serum BADGE-specific IgG could reflect exposure to BADGE and that exposure is related to allergic diseases.</p><p id="Par6">Recent studies have reported that exposure to endocrine-disrupting compounds (EDCs) including BPA and BADGE might increase the risk of allergic diseases such as respiratory allergies, contact dermatitis, food sensitization, and food tolerance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. BPA was suggested to induce a T helper 2 (Th2)-dominated immune response through its estrogenic activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Furthermore, it was shown to have adjuvant effects on increases in ovalbumin (OVA)-specific IgE levels by promoting Th-2-immune responses, macrophage activation, and the production of inflammatory cytokines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], suggesting that exposure to EDCs can induce the onset and/or progression of food sensitization.</p><p id="Par7">BADGE is used in infant clothing, textiles, and flooring materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Because infants exhibit immature behaviors such as crawling on the floor and putting random items into their mouths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], the risk of BADGE exposure in childhood might be greater than that in adulthood. In fact, the estimated daily intake of BADGE from indoor dust is increased in children compared to that in adults, especially in Japan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, little is known about the relationship between BADGE exposure and childhood allergic diseases. For young children, transient and persistent IgE sensitization to food allergens is closely related to late childhood allergy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Therefore, it is important to mitigate food sensitization in early childhood to prevent subsequent childhood allergies. In young Japanese children, egg white, milk, and wheat are the most common allergens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In this study, we investigated the relationship between serum BADGE-specific IgG levels and egg white, milk, and wheat sensitization in young children.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Subjects and questionnaires</title><p id="Par8">Children aged 6&#x000a0;months&#x02013;1&#x000a0;year and their parents were recruited at a single clinic between January 2009 and February 2010. In total, 115 mothers of 140 children provided informed consent to participate in the study (consent rate: 82%). Nine mothers could not recall their children&#x02019;s birth weight and blood samples could not be obtained from one child because of exceptionally thin blood vessels. Seven children were older than 1&#x000a0;year of age. Thus, the final number of subjects for analysis was 98 children [59 boys (median age: 7&#x000a0;months) and 39 girls (median age: 7&#x000a0;months]. The questionnaire administered at the maternal interview included questions concerning birth weight, feeding, number of siblings, allergy history, parental smoking habits, and parental allergy history. The survey was conducted at the time of first blood sample collection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Blood collection</title><p id="Par9">Blood samples were collected from children without fever, allergic symptoms, infectious diseases, and skin eczema, at least 1&#x000a0;month prior to sampling. Blood sampling for children with these symptoms was postponed until 1&#x000a0;month following the disappearance of symptoms. Blood samples were collected twice from all children, and the median blood sampling interval was 6&#x000a0;months (25th and 75th percentile: 5 and 7&#x000a0;months). The first blood sampling was conducted approximately 6&#x000a0;months after birth because children in Japan typically begin eating solids at that age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In addition, antibody-specific IgE tests for children under 6&#x000a0;months of age often present inaccurate results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. According to the food allergy guidelines for children, the standard interval for IgE measurements is every 6&#x000a0;months for children under 3&#x000a0;years of age and every 6&#x02013;12&#x000a0;months for oral food-challenge tests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Therefore, we conducted the second sampling between 6 and 12&#x000a0;months after the first blood sampling. Approximately 3&#x02013;5&#x000a0;mL of blood was collected at each sampling.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Allergen-specific IgE assays</title><p id="Par10">Egg white-, milk-, and wheat-specific IgE levels were determined using the capsulated hydrophilic carrier polymer-radioallergosorbent test (CAP-RAST; FALCO Biosystems Ltd., Kyoto, Japan). Both the first and second blood samples were subjected to CAP-RAST to examine changes in response levels to these antigens. For this, 0.3&#x000a0;mL of serum was used to evaluate each allergen. The detection of IgE levels greater than 0.35 UA/mL was considered as a sign of sensitization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Therefore, subjects presenting with values&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.35 UA/mL were placed in the food-specific IgE-positive group and those with values of&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.35 UA/mL were assigned to the food-specific IgE-negative group.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Detection of BADGE-specific IgG by dot blotting</title><p id="Par11">BADGE-specific IgG concentrations were measured using only the first-collected blood sample in accordance with our previously reported protocol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Briefly, BADGE (Sigma-Aldrich., St. Louis, MO, USA) and human serum albumin (HSA; Sigma-Aldrich) were mixed at a 1:100 ratio at pH 10.8 to form an HSA-BADGE adduct, which was used as an antigen. The antigens and human IgG (positive control; Zymed Laboratories, Inc., San Francisco, CA, USA) were electroblotted onto nitrocellulose membranes (Amersham, GE Healthcare, Japan) and blocked. The membranes were probed with serum (1:200 dilution) and subsequently treated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-human IgG (Millipore, Japan; 1:4000 dilution), which was followed by visualization.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR)</title><p id="Par12">IL-6, IL-8, and IL-10 are involved in IgE production and immunological tolerance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. COX-2 has been reported to suppress IgE production during Th2 responses in allergic children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Using the first-collected blood samples, mRNA levels of genes encoding these cytokines were measured by qRT-PCR as reported in our previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Whole blood was collected in a heparin-coated tube under a vacuum and maintained at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Total RNA was isolated using a QIAamp RNA Blood Mini kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). RNA was reverse-transcribed into cDNA using a Quanti Tect Reverse Transcription kit (Qiagen) and quantitative detection was performed using a Step One Plus Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Inc., Foster City, CA, USA) with Fast SYBR Green Master Mix (Applied Biosystems Inc.). The sequences of primers used in this study are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p id="Par13">The study subjects were divided into two groups based on food-specific IgE levels, specifically negative (&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.35 UA/mL) and positive (&#x02265;&#x02009;0.35 UA/mL), to examine the association between this classification and the presence of BADGE-specific IgG. Individual changes in food sensitization were also examined by determining the difference of IgE titers between the first and second collections [2nd sample IgE value (UA/mL)&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1st sample IgE value (UA/mL)]. Based on the calculation of this difference, the subjects were then further divided into two groups as decrease/no change (&#x02264;&#x02009;0 UA/mL) and increase (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0 UA/mL).</p><p id="Par14">Two-group comparisons were performed using Mann&#x02013;Whitney U tests and multivariable logistic regression analysis. Adjusted <italic>P</italic> values were obtained by multivariable logistic regression models using age at first CAP-RAST, feeding, and allergic diseases (wheezing, allergic rhinitis, and atopic dermatitis) as covariates. Because a significant sex-specific difference in the effects of EDCs on the immune response was previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], boys and girls were also separately analyzed.</p><p id="Par15">All analyses were performed using STATA version 14 (Stata Corporation, Inc., College Station, TX, USA), and statistical significance was assumed when <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 (two sided).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><p id="Par16">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the characteristics of the study subjects. The median age (25th and 75th percentile) at first blood collection was 7 (6, 8) months for both boys and girls. There was no significant difference in the distribution of the evaluated variables between boys and girls. When BADGE-specific IgG (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL) was detected, the subject was assigned to the &#x0201c;detected&#x0201d; group. The BADGE-IgG detection rate in subjects was 20%. The median (range) BADGE-specific IgG concentrations in boys and girls of the detected groups were 0.57 (0.03&#x02013;12.4) and 0.35 (0.04&#x02013;3.85) &#x000b5;g/mL, respectively. There was no significant association between the detection of BADGE-specific IgG in children and the allergic history of parents (none vs either or both parents) by Fisher&#x02019;s exact test (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.000).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of study subjects</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="3">Number (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value<sup>&#x02021;</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left">All</th><th align="left">Boys</th><th align="left">Girls</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Number</td><td char="(" align="char">98 (100)</td><td char="(" align="char">59 (100)</td><td char="(" align="char">39 (100)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Birth weight (g)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2500</td><td char="(" align="char">9 (9)</td><td char="(" align="char">4 (7)</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (13)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x02009;2500</td><td char="(" align="char">89 (91)</td><td char="(" align="char">55 (93)</td><td char="(" align="char">34 (87)</td><td char="." align="char">0.477</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Feeding</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Breast milk</td><td char="(" align="char">52 (53)</td><td char="(" align="char">29 (49)</td><td char="(" align="char">23 (59)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Breast milk/formula</td><td char="(" align="char">46 (47)</td><td char="(" align="char">30 (51)</td><td char="(" align="char">16 (41)</td><td char="." align="char">0.410</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Number of siblings</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;0</td><td char="(" align="char">56 (57)</td><td char="(" align="char">33 (56)</td><td char="(" align="char">23 (59)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1</td><td char="(" align="char">32 (33)</td><td char="(" align="char">20 (34)</td><td char="(" align="char">12 (31)</td><td char="." align="char">0.823</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x02009;2</td><td char="(" align="char">10 (10)</td><td char="(" align="char">6 (10)</td><td char="(" align="char">4 (10)</td><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Wheezing</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td char="(" align="char">78 (79)</td><td char="(" align="char">48 (81)</td><td char="(" align="char">30 (77)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td char="(" align="char">20 (20)</td><td char="(" align="char">11 (19)</td><td char="(" align="char">9 (23)</td><td char="." align="char">0.617</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Atopic dermatitis</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td char="(" align="char">89 (91)</td><td char="(" align="char">52 (88)</td><td char="(" align="char">37 (95)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td char="(" align="char">9 (9)</td><td char="(" align="char">7 (12)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (5)</td><td char="." align="char">0.310</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Allergic rhinitis</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td char="(" align="char">89 (91)</td><td char="(" align="char">52 (88)</td><td char="(" align="char">37 (95)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td char="(" align="char">9 (9)</td><td char="(" align="char">7 (12)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (5)</td><td char="." align="char">0.310</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Smoking habits of parents</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;No</td><td char="(" align="char">42 (43)</td><td char="(" align="char">27 (46)</td><td char="(" align="char">15 (38)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes</td><td char="(" align="char">56 (57)</td><td char="(" align="char">32 (54)</td><td char="(" align="char">24 (62)</td><td char="." align="char">0.535</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Allergic history of parents</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;None</td><td char="(" align="char">11 (11)</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (8)</td><td char="(" align="char">6 (15)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Either</td><td char="(" align="char">57 (58)</td><td char="(" align="char">35 (59)</td><td char="(" align="char">22 (56)</td><td char="." align="char">0.341</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Both</td><td char="(" align="char">30 (31)</td><td char="(" align="char">19 (32)</td><td char="(" align="char">11 (28)</td><td char="." align="char">0.476</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">BADGE-specific IgG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Not detected</td><td char="(" align="char">78 (80)</td><td char="(" align="char">47 (80)</td><td char="(" align="char">31 (79)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Detected<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td char="(" align="char">20 (20)</td><td char="(" align="char">12 (20)</td><td char="(" align="char">8 (21)</td><td char="." align="char">0.269</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Detected:&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL</p><p><sup>&#x02021;</sup><italic>P</italic> values were obtained by performing a Fisher&#x02019;s exact test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par17">The number of subjects positive for food-specific IgE and the change in serum IgE levels between the first and second tests are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. For 93% (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;91) of the subjects, the second blood sampling was performed between 6 and 12&#x000a0;months after the first blood collection, and the remaining 7% (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) of samples were collected between 1 and 2&#x000a0;years after the first sampling. The frequencies of positive subjects based on the first CAP-RAST were 74%, 32%, and 19% for egg white-, milk-, and wheat-specific IgE, respectively.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Distribution of food-specific IgE levels and change in IgE levels between first and second blood collections</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="3">Number (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value<sup>&#x000a7;</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left">All</th><th align="left">Boys</th><th align="left">Girls</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">First CAP-RAST<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">&#x000a0;Egg-specific IgE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Positive</td><td char="(" align="char">73 (74)</td><td char="(" align="char">44 (75)</td><td char="(" align="char">29 (74)</td><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">&#x000a0;Milk-specific IgE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Positive</td><td char="(" align="char">31 (32)</td><td char="(" align="char">17 (29)</td><td char="(" align="char">14 (36)</td><td char="." align="char">0.510</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">&#x000a0;Wheat-specific IgE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Positive</td><td char="(" align="char">19 (19)</td><td char="(" align="char">15 (25)</td><td char="(" align="char">4 (10)</td><td char="." align="char">0.073</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Second CAP-RAST<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">&#x000a0;Egg-specific IgE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Positive</td><td char="(" align="char">82 (84)</td><td char="(" align="char">49 (83)</td><td char="(" align="char">33 (85)</td><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">&#x000a0;Milk-specific IgE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Positive</td><td char="(" align="char">37 (38)</td><td char="(" align="char">22 (37)</td><td char="(" align="char">15 (38)</td><td char="." align="char">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">&#x000a0;Wheat-specific IgE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Positive</td><td char="(" align="char">31 (32)</td><td char="(" align="char">21 (36)</td><td char="(" align="char">10 (26)</td><td char="." align="char">0.377</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Change in CAP-RAST values<sup>&#x02021;</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">&#x000a0;Egg-specific IgE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Decrease or no change</td><td char="(" align="char">62 (63)</td><td char="(" align="char">40 (68)</td><td char="(" align="char">22 (56)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Increase</td><td char="(" align="char">36 (37)</td><td char="(" align="char">19 (32)</td><td char="(" align="char">17 (44)</td><td char="." align="char">0.289</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">&#x000a0;Milk-specific IgE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Decrease or no change</td><td char="(" align="char">75 (77)</td><td char="(" align="char">47 (80)</td><td char="(" align="char">28 (72)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Increase</td><td char="(" align="char">23 (23)</td><td char="(" align="char">12 (20)</td><td char="(" align="char">11 (28)</td><td char="." align="char">0.466</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">&#x000a0;Wheat-specific IgE</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Decrease or no change</td><td char="(" align="char">78 (80)</td><td char="(" align="char">45 (76)</td><td char="(" align="char">33 (85)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Increase</td><td char="(" align="char">20 (20)</td><td char="(" align="char">14 (24)</td><td char="(" align="char">6 (15)</td><td char="." align="char">0.443</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>CAP-RAST</italic> carrier polymer-radioallergosorbent test</p><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Negative:&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.35; positive:&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.35 UA/mL</p><p><sup>&#x02021;</sup>Decrease/no change: [2nd IgE value (UA/mL)&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1st IgE value (UA/mL)]&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0, Increase: [2nd IgE value (UA/mL)&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1st IgE value (UA/mL)]&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0</p><p><sup>&#x000a7;</sup><italic>P</italic> values were obtained by performing a Fisher&#x02019;s exact test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par18">The relationship between the presence of BADGE-specific IgG and food-specific IgE titers at the first CAP-RAST was also examined, but no food-specific IgE was related to the presence of BADGE-specific IgG (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Relationship between BADGE-specific IgG detection and food-specific IgE levels at first carrier polymer-radioallergosorbent test (CAP-RAST)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">BADGE-specific IgG</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Egg white-specific IgE</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value<sup>&#x02021;</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="3">Milk-specific IgE</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value<sup>&#x02021;</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="3">Wheat-specific IgE</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value<sup>&#x02021;</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Negative<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">Positive<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">OR<break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left">Negative<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">Positive<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">OR<break/>(95% CI)</th><th align="left">Negative<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">Positive<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">OR<break/>(95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">All</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Not detected</td><td char="." align="char">21</td><td char="." align="char">57</td><td align="left">1.00<break/>(reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">53</td><td char="." align="char">25</td><td align="left">1.00<break/>(reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">62</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td align="left">1.00<break/>(reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Detected</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td align="left">1.42<break/>(0.41&#x02013;4.89)</td><td char="." align="char">0.580</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td align="left">0.85<break/>(0.28&#x02013;2.53)</td><td char="." align="char">0.764</td><td char="." align="char">17</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">0.60<break/>(0.15&#x02013;2.40)</td><td char="." align="char">0.470</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Boys</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Not detected</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td align="left">1.00<break/>(reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">33</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td align="left">1.00<break/>(reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">35</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td align="left">1.00<break/>(reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Detected</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left">1.02<break/>(0.21&#x02013;4.98)</td><td char="." align="char">0.977</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">0.59<break/>(0.12&#x02013;2.89)</td><td char="." align="char">0.518</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">0.82<break/>(0.18&#x02013;3.76)</td><td char="." align="char">0.793</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Girls</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Not detected</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td char="." align="char">22</td><td align="left">1.00<break/>(reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td align="left">1.00<break/>(reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">27</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left">1.00<break/>(reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Detected</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td align="left">2.69<break/>(0.27&#x02013;26.8)</td><td char="." align="char">0.400</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">1.22<break/>(0.23&#x02013;6.49)</td><td char="." align="char">0.819</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Negative:&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.35, positive:&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.35 (UA/mL)</p><p><sup>&#x02021;</sup><italic>P</italic> values were obtained using multivariable logistic regression analysis adjusted for age at first CAP-RAST, feeding, and allergic diseases (wheezing, allergic rhinitis, atopic dermatitis)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par19">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> shows the relationship between BADGE-specific IgG detection and the change in IgE titers between the first and second tests. All subjects with BADGE-specific IgG showed a significant increase in wheat-specific IgE (OR&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.56; 95% CI, 1.13&#x02013;11.2; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.031). This relationship was also significant when the subjects were limited to those from whom the second blood sample was collected within one year of first sampling (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;91, OR&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.97; 95% CI, 1.23&#x02013;12.9; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.021). Furthermore, this association was more significant in girls (OR&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.46; 95% CI, 1.01&#x02013;89.0; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.049); however, the interaction with sex was not statistically significant (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>=&#x02009;0.535). All subjects with BADGE-specific IgG tended to show an increase in milk-specific IgE levels (OR&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.77; 95% CI, 0.93&#x02013;8.22; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.067), although this association was not statistically significant.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Relationship between BADGE-specific IgG detection and change in food-specific IgE values</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">BADGE-specific IgG</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Egg white-specific IgE</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value<sup>&#x02021;</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="3">Milk-specific IgE</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value<sup>&#x02021;</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="3">Wheat-specific IgE</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value<sup>&#x02021;</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Decrease/no change<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">Increase<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="left">Decrease/no change<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">Increase<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="left">Decrease/no change<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">Increase<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">All</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Not detected</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="." align="char">28</td><td align="left">1.00 (reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">63</td><td char="." align="char">15</td><td align="left">1.00 (reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">66</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td align="left">1.00 (reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Detected</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td align="left">1.22<break/>(0.41&#x02013;3.59)</td><td char="." align="char">0.722</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td align="left">2.77<break/>(0.93&#x02013;8.22)</td><td char="." align="char">0.067</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td align="left">3.56<break/>(1.13&#x02013;11.2)</td><td char="." align="char">0.031</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Boys</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Not detected</td><td char="." align="char">33</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td align="left">1.00 (reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">40</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td align="left">1.00 (reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">38</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left">1.00 (reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Detected</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left">2.16<break/>(0.50&#x02013;9.44)</td><td char="." align="char">0.304</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left">4.93<break/>(0.89&#x02013;27.2)</td><td char="." align="char">0.067</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left">2.77<break/>(0.65&#x02013;11.8)</td><td char="." align="char">0.167</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="13">Girls</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Not detected</td><td char="." align="char">17</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td align="left">1.00 (reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">23</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td align="left">1.00 (reference)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">28</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">1.00 (reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Detected</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">0.44<break/>(0.07&#x02013;2.86)</td><td char="." align="char">0.391</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">2.14<break/>(0.35&#x02013;13.2)</td><td char="." align="char">0.412</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">9.46<break/>(1.01&#x02013;89.0)</td><td char="." align="char">0.049</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Decrease/no change: [IgE value at 2nd (UA/mL)&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;IgE value at 1st (UA/mL)]&#x02009;&#x02264;0; increase: [IgE value at 2nd (UA/mL)&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;IgE value at 1st (UA/mL)]&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0</p><p><sup>&#x02021;</sup><italic>P</italic> values were obtained using multivariable logistic regression analysis adjusted for age at first carrier polymer-radioallergosorbent test (CAP-RAST), feeding, and allergic diseases (wheezing, allergic rhinitis, atopic dermatitis)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par20">To examine the immunological responses related to IgE production, <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>6</italic>, <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>8</italic>, <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>10</italic>, and <italic>COX2</italic> expression was examined. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the comparison of mRNA expression levels between the group with increased wheat-specific IgE and others according to the presence of BADGE-specific IgG. Three subjects were not examined due to insufficient blood samples. No significant relationships were identified between the expression of cytokines and COX-2 based on a Mann&#x02013;Whitney <italic>U</italic> test, but the subjects with both BADGE-specific IgG and increased wheat-specific IgE levels presented an approximate two- to threefold increase in median <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>6</italic> mRNA expression, compared to the other groups.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Relationship between mRNA expression and changes in wheat-specific IgE values between the first and second blood samples in groups with or without detected BADGE-specific IgG. Shown is a box plot bordered at the 25th and 75th percentiles of the variable on the <italic>y</italic>-axis with a median line at the 50th percentile for the expression of each mRNA</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40001_2018_358_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par21">In the present study, the BADGE-IgG detection rate was 20%. A significant increase in risk for elevated wheat-specific IgE levels was observed among children with BADGE-specific IgG, and this association was more significant in girls than in boys, although the interaction with sex was not statistically significant. There was no significant difference between BADGE-specific IgG status in children and the allergic history of parents. There are no previous studies describing the relationship between BADGE-specific IgG and the allergic history of parents. Therefore, this study is the first to indicate that the allergic history of parents does not influence BADGE-specific IgG in children. In future studies, the allergic history of parents should be included when measuring childhood BADGE-specific IgG.</p><p id="Par22">The subjects with both BADGE-specific IgG and increased wheat-specific IgE levels presented with increased <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>6</italic> mRNA expression compared to the other groups. Serum BADGE-specific IgGs probably reflect BADGE exposure even though the association with dose&#x02013;response is unclear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], 90% (9 of 10) of workers who had used epoxy resin and developed contact dermatitis had BADGE-specific IgG. In contrast, 13% (8 of 104) of adults without occupational BADGE exposure harbored BADGE-specific IgG, which was also detected by the same dot blot analysis (unpublished data). Thus, the results of the present study suggest that food sensitization among young children might be enhanced by BADGE exposure in their daily lives.</p><p id="Par23">As stated, up-regulation of IL-6, a Th2-related cytokine, was detected in the group presenting both elevated wheat-specific IgE levels and detectable BADGE-specific IgG. Considering that BADGE has estrogenic activity, although not to the same extent as BPA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], and that BPA has been suggested to induce a Th2 immune response through its estrogenic activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], BADGE exposure might elicit a Th2 immune response via IL-6 upregulation through its estrogenic activity. In addition, exposure to BADGE induces Toll-like receptor (TLR) 4 expression in rat macrophages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and this receptor might drive a Th2 immune response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Therefore, the expression of TLR4 in response to BADGE exposure might be one cause of the observed increase in food-specific IgE levels. Further experiments are needed to verify this.</p><p id="Par24">The association between the presence of BADGE-specific IgG and the increase in wheat specific-IgE levels was stronger among girls than among boys, although this interaction was not statistically significant. The effect of BPA exposure was previously shown to vary based on sex, wherein female mice showed a consistently enhanced Th2 response upon BPA exposure, compared to that in male mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Similarly, in the present study, girls in the BADGE-IgG-detected group showed slightly higher mRNA expression levels of <italic>IL</italic>-<italic>6</italic>, which encodes a Th2-related cytokine (median: 2.54; 25th and 75th percentile: 0.63 and 4.64, respectively), compared to the boys (median: 1.58; 25th and 75th percentile: 1.00 and 5.41, respectively). However, BADGE-specific IgG levels in girls were lower than those in boys; the median (range) BADGE-specific IgG levels in boys and girls of the BADGE-detected groups were 0.57 (0.03&#x02013;12.4) and 0.35 (0.04&#x02013;3.85) &#x000b5;g/mL, respectively. These results suggest that the reaction to BADGE exposure is stronger in girls than in boys.</p><p id="Par25">The present study has some limitations that merit discussion and further research. First, in this study, a significantly increased risk of elevation in wheat-specific IgE levels was observed among children with detected BADGE-specific IgG. For the other two food-specific IgEs, namely egg white and milk, a similar tendency was also observed, although these associations were not statistically significant (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). There is currently no explanation for why a significant association was observed only for wheat-specific IgE. Individuals in our cohort were not subjected to food limitation, and we did not obtain information regarding their nutrition intake. Further studies employing a food-frequency questionnaire are required to reveal whether BADGE exposure is involved in food-specific IgE increases and subsequently enhanced sensitization to specific foods. Second, to comprehensively measure cytokines, we detected mRNA expression levels using qRT-PCR. Enzyme-link immunosorbent assay (ELISA) is another method to detect cytokines. Trends for cytokine profiles based on measuring mRNA expression by qRT-PCR are generally the same as those determined by ELISA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. However, unlike ELISA, cytokine mRNA expression levels do not always correspond to actual protein levels. Future studies will also incorporate the quantification of proteins by ELISA into these protocols and more quantitative studies will be performed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par26">This is the first study investigating the relationship between BADGE-specific IgG and food-specific IgE sensitization in early childhood. Our study suggests that exposure to this material might affect food sensitization in early childhood. Therefore, BADGE exposure should be strictly regulated, especially in younger children.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional file</title><sec id="Sec12"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="40001_2018_358_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Table S1.</bold> List of real-time PCR primers used in this study.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>MT, YI, CK, CV, and TK designed the study and wrote the manuscript. MT, CK, and YI contributed to data collection. MT and CK performed the statistical analysis and interpreted the results. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par27">We would also like to thank Editage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.editage.jp">http://www.editage.jp</ext-link>) for English language editing.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par28">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par29">Data sharing is not applicable to this article as no datasets were generated or analyzed during the current study.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par30">This study, including the manner in which parental written informed consent was obtained, was approved by the review boards of Kumamoto University (Genome No. 118) and the University of Occupational and Environmental Health (H23-03).</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par31">This study was funded by the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) KAKENHI Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research (Grant Numbers 22790546, 25860472, and 17K09174 to M.T.) and the Medical Research Encouragement Prize of The Japan Medical Association.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par32">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shelby MD. NTP-CERHR monograph on the potential human reproductive and developmental effects of bisphenol A. <italic>Ntp cerhr mon</italic> 2008:v, vii-ix, 1-64 passim.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chamorro-Garcia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Janesick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bisphenol A diglycidyl ether induces adipogenic differentiation of multipotent stromal stem cells through a peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma-independent mechanism</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2012</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>984</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.1205063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22763116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyoung</surname><given-names>UJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Myoung</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental toxicity by exposure to bisphenol A diglycidyl ether during gestation and lactation period in Sprague&#x02013;Dawley male rats</article-title><source>J Prev Med Public Health</source><year>2007</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3961/jpmph.2007.40.2.155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17426428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Isse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of IgG against plastic resin in workers with and without chemical dermatitis</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>930</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-015-2302-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26390923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimber</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bisphenol A and immunotoxic potential: a commentary</article-title><source>Regul Toxicol Pharmacol</source><year>2017</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yrtph.2017.08.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28870489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keet</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urinary levels of triclosan and parabens are associated with aeroallergen and food sensitization</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2012</year><volume>130</volume><issue>453&#x02013;460</issue><fpage>e457</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipperheide</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipke</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zapf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Treudler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Molin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahler</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfohler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Loffler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Contact allergy induced by bisphenol A diglycidyl ether leachables from aluminium tubes for pharmaceutical use</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2015</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/all.12538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25582652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Narita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirosawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bisphenol A in combination with TNF-alpha selectively induces Th2 cell-promoting dendritic cells in vitro with an estrogen-like activity</article-title><source>Cell Mol Immunol</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cmi.2010.14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichinose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to bisphenol A enhanced lung eosinophilia in adult male mice</article-title><source>Allergy Asthma Clin Immunol</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13223-016-0122-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27087817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hannu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Frilander</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauppi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuuliala</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Alanko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IgE-mediated occupational asthma from epoxy resin</article-title><source>Int Arch Allergy Immunol</source><year>2009</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000151504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18716402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bisphenols, benzophenones, and bisphenol A diglycidyl ethers in textiles and infant clothing</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><year>2017</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>5279</fpage><lpage>5286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.7b00701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28368574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Occurrence and human exposure of p-hydroxybenzoic acid esters (parabens), bisphenol A diglycidyl ether (BADGE), and their hydrolysis products in indoor dust from the United States and three East Asian countries</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><year>2012</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>11584</fpage><lpage>11593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es303516u</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23025715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjaer</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Eller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bindslev-Jensen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Host</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortz</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Halken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early-life sensitization to hen&#x02019;s egg predicts asthma and rhinoconjunctivitis at 14&#x000a0;years of age</article-title><source>Pediatr Allergy Immunol</source><year>2017</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>776</fpage><lpage>783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pai.12815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28981985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebisawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Japanese guidelines for food allergy 2017</article-title><source>Allergol Int</source><year>2017</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.alit.2017.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28285847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Food Allergy Medical Manual 2014. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.foodallergy.jp/wp-content/themes/foodallergy/pdf/manual2014.pdf#search%3d%2527%25E9%25A3%259F%25E7%2589%25A9%25E3%2582%25A2%25E3%2583%25AC%25E3%2583%25AB%25E3%2582%25AE%25E3%2583%25BC%25E8%25A8%25BA%25E7%2599%2582%25E3%2581%25AE%25E6%2589%258B%25E5%25BC%2595%25E3%2581%258D2014%2527">https://www.foodallergy.jp/wp-content/themes/foodallergy/pdf/manual2014.pdf#search=%27%E9%A3%9F%E7%89%A9%E3%82%A2%E3%83%AC%E3%83%AB%E3%82%AE%E3%83%BC%E8%A8%BA%E7%99%82%E3%81%AE%E6%89%8B%E5%BC%95%E3%81%8D2014%27</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto-Hanada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishitsuka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mezawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allergic profiles of mothers and fathers in the Japan Environment and Children&#x02019;s Study (JECS): a nationwide birth cohort study</article-title><source>World Allergy Organ J</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>24</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40413-017-0157-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28811862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kawamoto T, Yoshida Y, Isse T. Method for detecting exposure to synthetic resin raw material monomer or synthetic resin precursor. Japan patent. JP5757519B2 (2015.7.29). 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Isse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda-Ishihara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuchiya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method for detection of multiple chemical-specific IgGs in serum based on dot blotting</article-title><source>Health</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1645</fpage><lpage>1653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/health.2016.815160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranganath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Asnagli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Afkarian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling and transcription in T helper development</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.18.1.451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10837066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The lineage decisions of helper T cells</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>933</fpage><lpage>944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12461566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differentiation of effector CD4 T cell populations (*)</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-030409-101212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merlo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fais</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Battini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciccone</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossi</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Saverino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory receptors CD85j, LAIR-1, and CD152 down-regulate immunoglobulin and cytokine production by human B lymphocytes</article-title><source>Clin Diagn Lab Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15939744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15939744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yalcin</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisgin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorczynski</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IL-8, IL-10, TGF-beta, and GCSF levels were increased in severe persistent allergic asthma patients with the anti-IgE treatment</article-title><source>Mediators Inflamm</source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>720976</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/720976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23316107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laouini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkhal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yalcindag</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oettgen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Geha</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COX-2 inhibition enhances the TH2 immune response to epicutaneous sensitization</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2005.03.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16083795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Koriyama</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of serum levels of polychlorinated biphenyls with IL-8 mRNA expression in blood samples from asthmatic and non-asthmatic Japanese children</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2012</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1228</fpage><lpage>1234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2012.01.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22326254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sciullo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzmicky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kado</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of proinflammatory cytokines and C-reactive protein in human macrophage cell line U937 exposed to air pollution particulates</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2005</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>1536</fpage><lpage>1541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.8094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16263508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of bisphenol A and phthalates on allergy, asthma, and immune function: a review of latest findings</article-title><source>Curr Environ Health Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40572-015-0066-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26337065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda-Ishihara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Koriyama</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakiuchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>CFA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of chemical-specific IgGs in serum by an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay with partial peptides of human serum albumin</article-title><source>J Toxicol Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2131/jts.43.25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29415949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PPARgamma agonists regulate tobacco smoke-induced Toll like receptor 4 expression in alveolar macrophages</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>28</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1465-9921-15-28</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24612634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of TLR2 and TLR4 and Th1/Th2 shift in inflammatory responses induced by fine ambient particulate matter in mice</article-title><source>Inhal Toxicol</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>918</fpage><lpage>927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/08958378.2012.731093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23121301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Emo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Georas</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of maternal exposure to bisphenol A on allergic lung inflammation into adulthood</article-title><source>Toxicol Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/toxsci/kfs227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22821851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melgert</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuipers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Geerlings</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luinge</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Strate</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerstjens</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Timens</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hylkema</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Female mice are more susceptible to the development of allergic airway inflammation than male mice</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>2005</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1496</fpage><lpage>1503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2222.2005.02362.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16297148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonini</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdely</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeidler-Erdely</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Performance evaluation of cytometric bead assays for the measurement of lung cytokines in two rodent models</article-title><source>J Immunol Methods</source><year>2008</year><volume>331</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jim.2007.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18089291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nicotine could augment adhesion molecule expression in human endothelial cells through macrophages secreting TNF-alpha, IL-1beta</article-title><source>Int Immunopharmacol</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1675</fpage><lpage>1686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2004.07.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15454119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Karisola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindholm</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Luukkonen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sallinen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Porkka-Heiskanen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Alenius</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep restriction increases the risk of developing cardiovascular diseases by augmenting proinflammatory responses through IL-17 and CRP</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e4589</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19240794</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>