<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Materials (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Materials (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">materials</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Materials</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1996-1944</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6073333</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma11071088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">materials-11-01088</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Combined Effects of Texture and Grain Size Distribution on the Tensile Behavior of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Titanium</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9475-8554</contrib-id><name><surname>Richeton</surname><given-names>Thiebaud</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-materials-11-01088">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-materials-11-01088">2</xref><xref rid="c1-materials-11-01088" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>Francis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-materials-11-01088">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-materials-11-01088">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Cai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-materials-11-01088">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-materials-11-01088">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7598-9026</contrib-id><name><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>Laszlo S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-materials-11-01088">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-materials-11-01088">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-materials-11-01088"><label>1</label>Universit&#x000e9; de Lorraine, CNRS, Arts et M&#x000e9;tiers ParisTech, LEM3, F-57000 Metz, France; <email>francis.wagner@univ-lorraine.fr</email> (F.W.); <email>laszlo.toth@univ-lorraine.fr</email> (L.S.T.)</aff><aff id="af2-materials-11-01088"><label>2</label>Laboratory of Excellence on Design of Alloy Metals for Low-Mass Structures (DAMAS), Universit&#x000e9; de Lorraine, 57073 Metz, France; <email>cai.chen@njust.edu.cn</email></aff><aff id="af3-materials-11-01088"><label>3</label>Nanjing University of Science and Technology, 210094 Nanjing, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-materials-11-01088"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>thiebaud.richeton@univ-lorraine.fr</email>; Tel.: +33-3-72-74-78-02</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>1088</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>This work analyzes the role of both the grain size distribution and the crystallographic texture on the tensile behavior of commercially pure titanium. Specimens with different microstructures, especially with several mean grain sizes, were specifically prepared for that purpose. It is observed that the yield stress depends on the grain size following a Hall&#x02013;Petch relationship, that the stress&#x02013;strain curves have a tendency to form a plateau that becomes more and more pronounced with decreasing mean grain size and that the hardening capacity increases with the grain size. All these observations are well reproduced by an elasto-visco-plastic self-consistent model that incorporates grain size effects within a crystal plasticity framework where dislocations&#x02019; densities are the state variables. First, the critical resolved shear stresses are made dependent on the individual grain size through the addition of a Hall&#x02013;Petch type term. Then, the main originality of the model comes from the fact that the multiplication of mobile dislocation densities is also made grain size dependent. The underlying assumption is that grain boundaries act mainly as barriers or sinks for dislocations. Hence, the smaller the grain size, the smaller the expansion of dislocation loops and thus the smaller the increase rate of mobile dislocation density is. As a consequence of this hypothesis, both mobile and forest dislocation densities increase with the grain size and provide an explanation for the grain size dependence of the transient low work hardening rate and hardening capacity.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>grain size</kwd><kwd>texture</kwd><kwd>crystal plasticity</kwd><kwd>elasto-visco-plastic self-consistent (EVPSC) scheme</kwd><kwd>hardening</kwd><kwd>dislocation density</kwd><kwd>titanium</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1-materials-11-01088"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Both crystallographic texture and grain size distribution are recognized to be of prime importance to understand the mechanical behavior of polycrystals [<xref rid="B1-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In particular, since the works of Hall [<xref rid="B5-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and Petch [<xref rid="B6-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], the grain size is known to strongly influence the yield stress of polycrystals. For grain sizes larger than 1 &#x000b5;m, the work hardening behavior is, however, generally reported to become almost insensitive to the grain size after a few percent of strain, particularly in face centered cubic metals [<xref rid="B7-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Texture effects arise because of elastic and plastic anisotropies at the crystal level and are well captured by homogenization schemes like self-consistent approaches which can handle an extensive number of crystallographic orientations within reasonable CPU time simulations. However, only a few approaches do account explicitly for grain size distribution in addition to crystallographic texture [<xref rid="B2-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B4-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B10-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In these mean-field approaches, the individual grain sizes get into the constitutive laws of the model as ad hoc parameters. Otherwise, no grain size effect could be predicted since these classical homogenization schemes do not include any internal length scale. Predicting direct grain size effects is, however, possible from strain gradient theories or generalized continuum plasticity models (e.g., [<xref rid="B14-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]). Though not the grain size, these models consider nevertheless an internal length scale parameter whose value is generally also defined in an ad hoc way. Since the equivalent grain diameter, similarly to the grain orientation Euler angles, can now be readily determined by EBSD analyses, considering the individual grain size in self-consistent models still remains an attractive approach due to its potential good compromise between relative model simplicity, low CPU time and reliability of the predictions. The question is, however, to know how to modify the constitutive laws to include relevant effects of the individual grain size.</p><p>The present work focuses on the tensile behavior of commercially pure (cp) <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm50"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-titanium which exhibits a hexagonal close-packed (hcp) crystallographic structure. In particular, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm124"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-Ti is characterized by a high anisotropy of glide resistance [<xref rid="B15-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and also by non-negligible anisotropy of slip family rate dependence [<xref rid="B16-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B21-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Tensile tests were performed on Ti specimens which were specifically prepared to exhibit various microstructures in order to study the combined role of the texture and the grain size distribution. On the other hand, the constitutive setting of an elasto-visco-plastic self-consistent (EVPSC) scheme [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B23-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] is modified in order to include grain size effects. The constitutive framework is based on crystal plasticity and considers dislocations&#x02019; densities as state variables. The first goal of the present paper is to present an original way to account for the grain size effect in the dislocation evolution laws. Then, by comparison of the experimental and simulated results, its other purpose is to clarify the respective role of the texture and the grain size distribution and to contribute to a better understanding of the tensile hardening behavior of cp Ti.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot1-materials-11-01088">Section 2.1</xref> presents experimental details. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot2-materials-11-01088">Section 2.2</xref> describes the micromechanical model and the way grain size effects are considered. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3-materials-11-01088">Section 3</xref> shows and discusses the simulations results in comparison with the experimental characterizations. Concluding remarks follow.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-materials-11-01088"><title>2. Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2dot1-materials-11-01088"><title>2.1. Preparation, Microstructural and Mechanical Characterization of the Specimens</title><p>The as-received material was a 2 mm-thick plate of commercially pure titanium (Ti grade 2) in a fully recrystallized state with a mean grain size <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm125"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of about 10 &#x000b5;m. Specimens cut off from this plate were cold rolled, either along the previous rolling direction or along the previous transverse direction. After rolling, the specimens were annealed under various conditions in a furnace working under secondary vacuum. The samples were small dog-bone-shaped specimens with total length <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm127"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>43</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> mm, gauge length <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm128"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>11.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> mm, width <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm129"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> mm, thickness <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm130"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> mm and could be put entirely in an FEG-SEM. Tensile tests were performed at ambient temperature on a Deben Microtest MT10331-1kN tensile machine (Woolpit, UK) at a constant displacement speed of 0.5 mm&#x000b7;mn<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, which corresponds to an initial strain rate of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm123"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The extension direction was parallel either to the last rolling direction or to the last transverse direction. Throughout the paper, the nomenclature to name the specimens is the following: the first letter corresponds to the last rolling direction (R means rolling along the previous rolling direction and T along the previous transverse direction) whereas the second letter refers to the direction of tension (R means tension along the last rolling direction and T along the last transverse direction) and the number to the mean grain size in microns. The names of the seven selected specimens used in this study and their conditions of preparation are reported in <xref rid="materials-11-01088-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f001">Figure 1</xref> exhibits examples of experimental tensile curves obtained for three specimens of RR type (i.e., rolling and tension along the previous rolling direction) with different mean grain sizes.</p><p>The microstructural characterization was made by EBSD in an FEG-SEM. From each EBSD map, the equivalent diameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm134"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the mean orientation of each grain were collected using a post-processing software (Channel 5 (v5.11, Oxford Instrument, High Wycombe, UK) or ATEX [<xref rid="B25-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]). In all the cases, the specimens were fully recrystallized. The specimens with the smallest mean grain size were close to the end of the primary recrystallization. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f002">Figure 2</xref> shows examples of obtained grain size distributions for the two samples with the minimum and maximum mean grain size. In the top part of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f002">Figure 2</xref>, the scales and the bin sizes used to plot the distributions were exactly the same in order to highlight the differences between the obtained microstructures. When normalized by the mean grain size, all the distributions look, however, pretty similar and follow approximately log-normal probability density functions (see the bottom part of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f002">Figure 2</xref>).</p><p>For each specimen, the data set of the grains (volume fractions and orientations) was used to plot the texture. An example is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f003">Figure 3</xref> in terms of pole figures. The pole figures correspond to well known textures for this material [<xref rid="B17-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B26-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] where basal planes are tilted <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm135"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>30</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02218;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02218;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> from the normal toward the transverse direction. When the grains are small, which means that the annealing was stopped close to the end of the primary recrystallization, the texture resembles the deformation one whereas the grain growth texture is obtained after heat treatments made at higher temperatures (see [<xref rid="B31-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] for further information). The data set of the grains (grain diameters in addition to volume fractions and orientations) are the microstructural information used further in the simulations.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-materials-11-01088"><title>2.2. Micromechanical Modeling Including Grain Size Effects</title><p>The model used to simulate the tensile behavior is a modified version of the one that was developed in [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] to study hardening mechanisms in cp Ti. The purpose of the modification is to account for grain size effects. The model is still based on an advanced elasto-viscoplastic self-consistent (EVPSC) homogenization scheme which considers a small strain setting and an affine linearization of the viscoplastic flow rule. The 1-site self-consistent approximation is formulated thanks to the translated field method [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B23-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Compared to hereditary approaches [<xref rid="B32-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], the numerical implementation of such internal variable approach is much easier as no use of Laplace&#x02013;Carson transform is needed. In the present model, each grain is represented by a sphere to which is associated a mean crystallographic orientation, a volume fraction and a diameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm136"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> which hence allows for considering grain size distribution effects. The EVPSC model has been described in detail in several references [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B23-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and therefore only the main equations are recalled here.</p><sec id="sec2dot2dot1-materials-11-01088"><title>2.2.1. Micro-Macro Scale Transition</title><p>In homogenization theory, the macroscopic stress rate and strain rate tensors, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm137"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm138"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, of a representative volume element <italic>V</italic> are obtained by volume averaging the local stress rate and strain rate tensors, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm139"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm140"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (scale of the grains), as follows:<disp-formula id="FD1-materials-11-01088"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="mm188"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Within the small strain framework, the local total strain rate relative to an elasto-viscoplastic behavior splits into an elastic part and a viscoplastic one:<disp-formula id="FD2-materials-11-01088"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="mm189"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">e</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">p</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The linear Hooke&#x02019;s law relates <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm141"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">e</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to the local Cauchy stress rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm142"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="FD3-materials-11-01088"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="mm190"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">e</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where the colon : denotes the contracted product of two tensors, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm121"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the local elastic compliance tensor. The viscoplastic strain rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm110"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">p</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a nonlinear tensorial function of the Cauchy stress <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm120"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Using a first order affine linearization, it can be written:<disp-formula id="FD4-materials-11-01088"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="mm191"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">p</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">m</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b7;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm100"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the tangent viscoplastic compliance tensor defined by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm101"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">p</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02202;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm102"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b7;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> corresponds to a back-extrapolated strain rate. In the absence of volume forces, static equilibrium conditions impose:<disp-formula id="FD5-materials-11-01088"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="mm192"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>div</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>div</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
whereas kinematic compatibility gives:<disp-formula id="FD6-materials-11-01088"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="mm193"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x025bd;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x025bd;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm103"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">u</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the material velocity field. For uniaxial tensile tests along the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm104"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-axis, mixed boundary conditions are prescribed as follows: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm105"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> experimental applied strain rate and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm106"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>33</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>23</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>31</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>As a result of the translated field method and self-consistent approximations, the explicit expressions of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm107"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm108"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be obtained in each grain as a function of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm99"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm109"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, crystallographic orientation and stress history <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm111"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the grain [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B23-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. These expressions account for coupled elastic and viscoplastic inter-granular accommodations.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2dot2-materials-11-01088"><title>2.2.2. Single Crystal Constitutive Laws</title><p>Crystal elasticity and plasticity were considered at the single crystal level. Plastic strain and plastic rotation <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm112"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">p</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can occur by dislocation-based crystallographic slip only:<disp-formula id="FD7-materials-11-01088"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="mm194"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm113"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the slip rates on systems <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm114"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> while <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm115"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm116"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are, respectively, the symmetric and the skew-symmetric Schmid orientation tensors associated to system <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm117"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Glide on prismatic, basal, pyramidal &#x0003c;a&#x0003e;, 1st order pyramidal &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e; and 2nd order pyramidal &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e; slip systems were taken into account. Twinning was not considered since the twin volume fraction in cp Ti was observed to be very small during tensile tests, especially along the rolling direction [<xref rid="B17-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The slip rates result from the Orowan relation:<disp-formula id="FD8-materials-11-01088"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="mm195"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm118"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the Burgers vector magnitude. From relation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD8-materials-11-01088">8</xref>, it is seen that the evolution of mobile dislocation densities <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm144"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and dislocation velocities <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm143"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are treated separately on each slip system. This allows for accounting for an initial fast multiplication of mobile dislocations, as suggested by Conrad [<xref rid="B33-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and Naka [<xref rid="B34-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] to explain the presence of a yield plateau in Ti. When dislocations multiply rapidly, the actual strain rate may overcome the imposed strain rate. As a consequence, the average dislocation velocity has to be adjusted so as to retrieve the imposed strain rate, which can cause a significant slow-down of the flow stress increase. The average dislocation velocity on system <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm122"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was assumed to follow a classic power law relationship:<disp-formula id="FD9-materials-11-01088"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="mm196"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mfenced separators="" open="|" close="|"><mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:msup><mml:mi>sgn</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm145"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a reference velocity, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm185"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the inverse of the strain rate sensitivity and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm179"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the resolved shear stress. It is noteworthy that the components of the tangent viscoplastic compliance tensor <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and of the back-extrapolated strain rate tensor <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm187"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003b7;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4-materials-11-01088">4</xref>)) are deduced from the combination of Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7-materials-11-01088">7</xref>)&#x02013;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD9-materials-11-01088">9</xref>) [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Although in elasto-viscoplasticity all non-zero shear stress levels produce some slip, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm171"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be described as the critical resolved shear stress (CRSS) given the values considered for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm172"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see further <xref rid="materials-11-01088-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). It writes as the sum of the lattice friction stress <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm173"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and a generalized dislocation strengthening relation that accounts for dislocation interactions between systems [<xref rid="B35-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="B36-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Moreover, following references [<xref rid="B2-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B4-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B10-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm174"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is also assumed to depend on the individual grain size <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm175"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in a Hall&#x02013;Petch type relationship:<disp-formula id="FD10-materials-11-01088"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="mm197"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm176"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the interaction coefficient which is related to the strength of the interaction between system <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm177"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm178"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm180"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the directional shear modulus of system <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm181"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm182"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> depicts forest (or sessile) dislocation density on system <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm183"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm184"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a Hall&#x02013;Petch type slope resolved on slip system <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm186"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. It is noteworthy that, with this supplementary term, the CRSSs are different from grain to grain according to both their orientation and their size. For the same orientation, the smallest grains are harder than the largest ones, which is in agreement with recent experimental characterizations of CRSSs in grade 1 cp Ti by high energy X-ray diffraction microscopy [<xref rid="B37-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Moreover, it must be underlined that, through Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-materials-11-01088">10</xref>), &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e; systems will display stronger hardening by virtue of the values of Burgers vector magnitude and directional shear modulus (see <xref rid="materials-11-01088-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), which is in accordance with experimental observations [<xref rid="B38-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B39-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Finally, both mobile and sessile dislocation densities evolve with plastic deformation [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B40-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]:<disp-formula id="FD11-materials-11-01088"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="mm198"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced separators="" open="[" close="]"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced separators="" open="|" close="|"><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="FD12-materials-11-01088"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="mm199"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced separators="" open="[" close="]"><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced separators="" open="|" close="|"><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The negative terms in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-materials-11-01088">11</xref>), which correspond to mobile dislocation immobilization, appear as positive terms in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12-materials-11-01088">12</xref>) and stand for storage of forest dislocations. The mean free path of mobile dislocations <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm156"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is assumed to depend on reactions with other mobile dislocations, which are considered through the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm168"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and interactions with forest dislocations, which are taken into account through the interaction coefficients <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm167"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the constant <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm147"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="FD13-materials-11-01088"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="mm200"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:msup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm148"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the annihilation distance between dislocations and the term associated to it thus accounts for dynamic recovery.</p><p>In Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-materials-11-01088">11</xref>), the mobile dislocation density production is related to the term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm149"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and thus is set proportional to the grain diameter. The idea underlying this formalism is that the expansion of dislocation loops (e.g., from a Frank&#x02013;Read source) is less constrained in larger grains. In smaller grains, dislocation loops will pile-up (as observed in cp Ti [<xref rid="B41-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]) or will be absorbed [<xref rid="B42-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="B43-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="B44-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] at the grain boundary sooner, i.e., for a smaller increase of dislocation length (= smaller increase of dislocation density). The mechanism of loops expansion should be preserved in cp Ti down to grains of 1 &#x000b5;m or lower (the obstacles spacing <italic>d</italic> for line tension strengthening may be estimated as <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm151"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which gives <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm152"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> 0.3 &#x000b5;m for prismatic systems with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm154"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>150</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> MPa). Furthermore, with decreasing grain size, the ratio of grain boundary area over grain volume increases. Hence, the probability of dislocation absorption by grain boundaries should increase when the grain size decreases. Through Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-materials-11-01088">11</xref>)&#x02013;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13-materials-11-01088">13</xref>), it is observed that the grain size, by influencing the increase rate of mobile dislocation densities, will also affect the evolution of forest dislocation densities and hence the hardening behavior. Finally, one may argue that the mean free path of dislocations (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13-materials-11-01088">13</xref>)), in addition to being dependent on dislocation density, should also depend on the grain size. Accordingly, a term that scales as <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm146"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> could have been added in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13-materials-11-01088">13</xref>) as well, as was done for instance in [<xref rid="B4-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, by doing so, one would get higher forest dislocation densities, and thus stronger work hardening in small grain samples, which is the opposite of what is observed (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f001">Figure 1</xref> and further). Hence, our modelling assumption is that the main effect of grain boundaries in cp Ti is to act as barriers or sinks for dislocations [<xref rid="B41-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="B42-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="B43-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="B44-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] which, as a consequence, restricts the expansion of dislocation length, rather than having a significant contribution to the creation of forest dislocations, which is mainly accounted for by dislocations&#x02019; interactions.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2dot3-materials-11-01088"><title>2.2.3. Model Parameters</title><p>The model is coded in Fortran and solved in an explicit way using very small time steps. It was checked that convergences of the solutions were indeed reached. The values of the model&#x02019;s parameters are given in <xref rid="materials-11-01088-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> (parameters specific to slip families) and <xref rid="materials-11-01088-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> (parameters not specific to slip families). Except for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm155"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm157"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm158"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm159"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, these values are identical as in [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. It was shown in [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] that the above described constitutive setting (without the incorporation of grain size effects) was able to explain the opposite effect of strain rate with regard to the orientation of the tensile axis on the three-stage hardening behavior of cp Ti thanks to the consideration of lower strain-rate sensitivity for prismatic systems. Because of the presence of the Hall&#x02013;Petch type term in the expression of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm160"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-materials-11-01088">10</xref>), the values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm161"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm162"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> had to be modified to retrieve CRSSs with about the same level as in [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The value of the resolved Hall&#x02013;Petch type slope <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm163"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> corresponds approximately to the macroscopic Hall&#x02013;Petch slope determined in [<xref rid="B31-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] divided by the Taylor factor. The value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm164"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was adjusted so that the product <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm165"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is about the former value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm166"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] for a mean grain size of 10 &#x000b5;m.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec3-materials-11-01088"><title>3. Results and Discussion</title><p>The tensile curves of the seven specimens were simulated using the same set of model parameters. The specific set of grain orientations, volume fractions and equivalent diameters was used for each specimen. The numbers of grains considered in the simulations were the numbers of grains of the EBSD maps indicated in <xref rid="materials-11-01088-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f004">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f005">Figure 5</xref> show the simulated curves and their equivalent experimental counterparts. In order to characterize further the mechanical behavior, several quantities were collected from the tensile curves:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>the 0.2% yield stress: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm97"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item><list-item><p>the maximal engineering stress: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm96"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item><list-item><p>the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm27"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> corresponding engineering strain: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm28"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item><list-item><p>the hardening amplitude: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm29"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list></p><p>Both the experimental and simulated values of these quantities are reported in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f006">Figure 6</xref> for the seven specimen.</p><sec id="sec3dot1-materials-11-01088"><title>3.1. Yield Stress</title><p>The experimental yield stress increases with decreasing mean grain size <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm30"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and follows rather well a Hall&#x02013;Petch relationship (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f007">Figure 7</xref>), i.e., a scaling <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm31"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, as it was already shown on a larger data set of cp Ti specimens that also included partially recrystallized microstructures [<xref rid="B31-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The calculated yield stresses follow a pretty correct trend considering the unlikely ranking of measured yield stresses between samples RR 4.8 and RR 9.8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f006">Figure 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f007">Figure 7</xref>). The assumption made for the dependence of the CRSS on the grain size (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-materials-11-01088">10</xref>)) thus appears relevant. As also found in earlier works [<xref rid="B2-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B4-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B10-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], it is confirmed that the consideration of a Hall&#x02013;Petch type dependence at the scale of slip systems enables for retrieving a Hall&#x02013;Petch law at the macroscopic scale (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f007">Figure 7</xref>). This transition may, however, not be as direct as it seems since the macroscopic Hall&#x02013;Petch law deals with the mean grain size, whereas the individual grain size is considered at the scale of slip systems. Hence, the smallest grains of the distribution might act as limiting factors for the complete diffusion of plasticity in the sample.</p><p>As already observed [<xref rid="B17-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B45-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], for the same mean grain size, the yield stress is higher when the tensile axis is parallel to the transverse direction (comparisons of samples RT 9.8 and RR 9.8) due to less-well oriented easy prismatic systems.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot2-materials-11-01088"><title>3.2. Local Mechanical Fields</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f008">Figure 8</xref> shows the evolution of the tensile component of local stresses and local strains in the grains for specimens with different average grain sizes. Each dot represents the local stress and local strain values in a given grain. As can be seen, the clouds formed by these dots become larger and larger with increasing macroscopic strain, while their shapes evolve from vertically elongated towards more and more horizontally spread. This result is radically different from the predictions of a simple Taylor model, which would give dots aligned along vertical lines at any strain (uniform strain). The results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f008">Figure 8</xref> are in agreement with strain measurements obtained locally in polycrystalline materials [<xref rid="B46-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="B47-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="B48-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], especially for hexagonal structure [<xref rid="B49-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The stress and strain fluctuations arise in the present modeling because of the consideration of non-uniform distributions of grain orientations and sizes coupled with elastic and plastic anisotropies at the single crystal level, as well as grain size dependent CRSSs (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-materials-11-01088">10</xref>)) and grain size dependent dislocation density evolution laws (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-materials-11-01088">11</xref>)). At 1% macroscopic strain, the fluctuations are mostly due to elastic incompatibilities. With increasing deformation, plastic strains become rapidly larger than elastic strains and plastic incompatibilities become predominant. Moreover, as noticed in [<xref rid="B2-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B4-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], the grain size dispersion strongly influences the local mechanical fields. Actually, for a same grain size dispersion, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm33"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the relative dispersion of the Hall&#x02013;Petch type term, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm34"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-materials-11-01088">10</xref>), is invariant whatever the mean grain size is. Since the contribution of the Hall&#x02013;Petch type term increases with decreasing grain size, the absolute dispersion of the CRSSs becomes larger and larger in samples having smaller and smaller mean grain sizes (considering that the normalized grain size distributions of our samples are quite similar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f002">Figure 2</xref>)). It was checked that this effect alone cannot explain totally the impressive increase in the scattering of the local strains and stresses when decreasing the mean grain size in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f008">Figure 8</xref>. Indeed, there is an additional effect that is related to the grain size dependence of the mobile dislocation density evolution (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-materials-11-01088">11</xref>)). The latter impedes significantly the multiplication of mobile dislocations in the smallest grains (see further Figure 11) and thus restricts the value of the slip rates in those grains (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD8-materials-11-01088">8</xref>)). For instance, the smallest grain diameter considered in our simulations, 0.45 &#x000b5;m in sample RR 2.8, is relatively close to the value of 0.14 &#x000b5;m below which <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm37"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is initially negative in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-materials-11-01088">11</xref>). As a result, local stresses almost as high as 1200 MPa are reached in some grains of sample RR 2.8 at a macroscopic strain of 15% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f008">Figure 8</xref>). These grains are very small and act like hard particles as they exhibit very little deformation (the corresponding local strains are barely greater than 1%). They represent, however, a very small volume fraction of the whole sample.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot3-materials-11-01088"><title>3.3. Slip Activity</title><p>From the simulations, it is possible to estimate the relative activity <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm41"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of a slip family as:<disp-formula id="FD14-materials-11-01088"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="mm201"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where the slip system numbers of a specific family goes from <italic>p</italic> to <italic>q</italic>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm42"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total number of slip systems, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm43"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the total number of grains and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm44"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the grain volume fraction. The distribution of the slip activity is mainly influenced by the texture, the initial values of the CRSSs and the intergranular stresses that arise from strain incompatibilities. For tensile tests along the rolling direction, it is known that, as a result of the texture, a vast majority of the grains have large macroscopic Schmid factors for prismatic, pyramidal &#x0003c;a&#x0003e; and 1st order pyramidal &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e; glide and low ones for basal slip [<xref rid="B17-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B31-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. On the contrary, along the transverse direction, there is no big difference of Schmid factors among the four main slip families, 1st order pyramidal &#x0003c;a&#x0003e; and &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e; being nevertheless the most favorably oriented ones [<xref rid="B17-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B31-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. As a consequence, for deformation simulation along the last rolling direction, prismatic slip strongly dominates at the very beginning of deformation because of its low CRSS value. Then, it decreases to reach a quasi steady-state of about 50% of the total slip activity whatever the mean grain size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f009">Figure 9</xref>). The second most important contribution to plastic deformation arises from 1st order pyramidal &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e; systems, which exhibit a maximum around 0.5% plastic strain with a rapid initial increase before and a very slight steadily decrease after. This decrease is probably due to the stronger hardening of &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e; systems. Pyramidal &#x0003c;a&#x0003e; and basal systems have also non negligible contributions, while the one of 2nd order pyramidal systems is completely unimportant due to the much higher value of its CRSS. During the simulations, dislocations of 2nd order pyramidal systems act thus only as a static forest. For deformation along the transverse direction, the fall of the prismatic activity is much stronger and occurs sooner. In steady-state, the contribution of the four main slip families are between 20% and 35%.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot4-materials-11-01088"><title>3.4. Hardening Behavior</title><p>It can be noticed from the tensile experimental curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f004">Figure 4</xref>) that the tendency to form an initial plateau becomes more and more pronounced with decreasing mean grain size. This general trend is in agreement with other experiments in titanium [<xref rid="B50-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and was also characterized as such in copper [<xref rid="B9-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] for instance. The model reproduces very well this trend (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f004">Figure 4</xref>). Moreover, the evolution of the work hardening rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm24"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for all the simulations of RR type is plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f010">Figure 10</xref>. In agreement with the present experiments and previous tensile tests on cp Ti [<xref rid="B17-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B29-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], a three-stage work hardening behavior is obtained, where an initial fall of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm14"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is followed by an increase and a final progressive decrease. More importantly, the model predicts a growing well depth with decreasing grain size, or, in other words, a transient low work hardening rate with smaller and smaller value as the grain size decreases. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f010">Figure 10</xref>, it is also noteworthy that the predicted work hardening rates of all the specimens converge at high strains, meaning that the model correctly predicts an insensitivity to grain size at high strains [<xref rid="B9-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The reason is that the mobile dislocation density reaches a saturation value (see further <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f011">Figure 11</xref>).</p><p>The low point of the work hardening rate precisely corresponds to the moment when the activity of the 1st order pyramidal &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e; systems approaches its maximum value, around 0.5% of plastic strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f009">Figure 9</xref>). Hence, the appearance of a low point in the work hardening rate evolution seems to be related to the start of multiple slip within grains, or to a kind of balance between &#x0003c;a&#x0003e; and &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e; slip activities. Under such conditions, plastic strain incompatibilities and the induced intergranular stresses are strongly decreased. Along with the fast multiplication of mobile dislocations (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-materials-11-01088">11</xref>)), this gives rise to an initial state with very weak hardening. In agreement with previous experiments, when the tensile axis is parallel to the transverse direction (comparisons of samples RT 9.8 and RR 9.8), the plateau effect is even more pronounced due to an even more balanced slip activity distribution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f009">Figure 9</xref>). This texture effect is very well reproduced by the model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f005">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>The grain size effect on the work hardening rate can be understood by analyzing the predicted evolutions of dislocation densities in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f011">Figure 11</xref>. As expected from Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-materials-11-01088">11</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12-materials-11-01088">12</xref>), the assumption of a mobile dislocation density production that grows with grain size makes both mobile and forest dislocation densities increase with the grain size. This implies that the rate of CRSS increase is more important in large grains since <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm3"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the Hall&#x02013;Petch type term do not evolve with deformation (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-materials-11-01088">10</xref>)). The increase of CRSSs counterbalances the previously mentioned effects, which lead to a low point in the work hardening rate evolution. As a result, the model indeed predicts a less and less pronounced transient low work hardening rate as the grain size increases.</p><p>The same explanation holds to interpret the effect of the grain size on the hardening capacity. Both the observations and the model predictions indicate a hardening amplitude <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm4"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> that tends to increase with the grain size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f006">Figure 6</xref>). The CRSSs of the small grains are initially higher than those of the large grains while the latter can display larger increases. By consequence, large grains exhibit a higher hardening capacity.</p><p>In addition, the correct prediction of a smaller hardening amplitude obtained for sample RT 9.8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f005">Figure 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f006">Figure 6</xref>) results from the choice of a greater <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> value for prismatic systems compared to other slip families (<xref rid="materials-11-01088-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Indeed, since the contribution of prismatic slip is less important for deformation along the transverse direction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f009">Figure 9</xref>), this assumption leads to much lower dislocation densities in sample RT 9.8 compared to RR 9.8 and thus to much weaker work hardening (see [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] for further information).</p><p>Finally, it can be observed that the model reproduces the Considere point (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm7"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), i.e., a limit for the homogeneous deformation, which matches satisfactorily the experimental results. The maximal engineering stress, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm8"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, compares rather well with experiments, whereas the corresponding engineering strain, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm9"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is slightly underestimated except for the case RT 9.8 (extension along the transverse direction) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-11-01088-f006">Figure 6</xref>). The model, with its assumptions and with the used parameters, is thus able to account for the balance of appearing and disappearing dislocations. The value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm10"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is mainly controlled by the dynamic recovery parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm11"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12-materials-11-01088">12</xref>)). <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm12"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is set to one unique value all along the deformation, which obviously does not allow for capturing totally the complexity of the dynamics of the recovery process (e.g., effect of thermally-activated cross-slip).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4-materials-11-01088"><title>4. Conclusions</title><p>This study considers tensile curves of a set of cp Ti specimens with different microstructures, especially with several mean grain sizes. It is observed that the yield stress depends on the grain size following a Hall&#x02013;Petch relationship. The hardening behavior shows also some dependence with the grain size. The tendency of stress&#x02013;strain curves to form a plateau becomes more and more pronounced with decreasing mean grain size while the hardening amplitude <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm2"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> increases with the grain size. All these observations are well reproduced by an EVPSC model that incorporates grain size effects in a crystal plasticity framework where dislocation densities are the state variables. While the CRSSs are made dependent on the individual grain size through the addition of a Hall&#x02013;Petch type term (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-materials-11-01088">10</xref>)), the originality of the model comes from the fact that the multiplication of mobile dislocation densities is also made grain size dependent (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-materials-11-01088">11</xref>)). Our assumption is that, due to grain boundaries acting mainly as barriers or sinks for dislocations, the smaller the grain size, the smaller the expansion of dislocation loops and thus the smaller the increase rate of mobile dislocation density. As a consequence of this assumption, both mobile and forest dislocation densities increase with the grain size, which provides an explanation for the grain size dependence of the transient low work hardening rate and hardening amplitude. It is noteworthy, however, that, in agreement with observations, the predicted work hardening rates of different mean grain size samples eventually converge at high strains because the mobile dislocation density reaches a saturation value. The fact that the model provides correct estimates of the homogeneous deformations is also quite positive and shows that the formalism, as well as the choice of the parameters, reflects rather well the complex reality.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank Yvon Millet from the company Timet for providing cp Ti sheets and Laurent Peltier for performing various heat treatments. This work was supported by the French State through the program &#x0201c;Investment in the Future&#x0201d; operated by the National Research Agency (ANR) and referenced by ANR-11-LABX-0008-01 (LabEx DAMAS).</p></ack><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>F.W. and C.C conceived and designed the experiments; C.C. performed the experiments; T.R. and F.W. conceived the model and performed the simulations; T.R., F.W., C.C. and L.S.T. analyzed the data; T.R. and F.W. wrote the paper. All the authors participated in the discussion and reviewed the paper.</p></notes><notes><title>Funding</title><p>This research was funded by by the French State through the program &#x0201c;Investment in the Future&#x0201d; operated by the National Research Agency (ANR) and referenced by grant number [ANR-11-LABX-0008-01] (LabEx DAMAS).</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. The founding sponsors had no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analyses, or interpretation of data; in the writing of the manuscript, and in the decision to publish the results.</p></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><p>The following abbreviations are used in this manuscript:
<array orientation="portrait"><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ti</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">titanium</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cp</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">commercially pure</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rolling direction</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TD</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transverse direction</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBSD</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">electron backscatter diffraction</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">scanning electron microscopy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEG</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">field emission gun</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EVPSC</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">elasto-visco-plastic self-consistent</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRSS</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">critical resolved shear stress</td></tr></tbody></array></p></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-materials-11-01088"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kocks</surname><given-names>U.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tom&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenk</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Texture and Anisotropy</source><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc><year>1998</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-materials-11-01088"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berbenni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Favier</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berveiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of the grain size distribution on the behaviour of heterogeneous materials</article-title><source>Int. J. Plast.</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijplas.2006.03.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-materials-11-01088"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roters</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenlohr</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hantcherli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjahjanto</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieler</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raabe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overview of constitutive laws, kinematics, homogenization and multiscale methods in crystal plasticity finite-element modeling: Theory, experiments, applications</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2010</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1152</fpage><lpage>1211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actamat.2009.10.058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-materials-11-01088"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicaise</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berbenni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berveiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coupled effects of grain size distributions and crystallographic textures on the plastic behaviour of IF steels</article-title><source>Int. J. Plast.</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijplas.2010.05.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-materials-11-01088"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The deformation and aging of mild steel. Part III: discussion and results</article-title><source>Proc. Phys. Soc. Lond.</source><year>1951</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0370-1301/64/9/303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-materials-11-01088"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petch</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cleavage strength of polycrystals</article-title><source>J. Iron Steel Inst.</source><year>1953</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-materials-11-01088"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The strain and grain size dependence of the flow stress of copper</article-title><source>Acta Metall.</source><year>1982</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0001-6160(82)90221-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-materials-11-01088"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polycrystalline strengthening</article-title><source>Metall. Trans. A</source><year>1985</year><volume>16A</volume><fpage>2167</fpage><lpage>2190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02670417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-materials-11-01088"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000e9;chet</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model for the grain size dependent work hardening of copper</article-title><source>Scr. Mater.</source><year>2006</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>732</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scriptamat.2006.05.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-materials-11-01088"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bunge</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houtte</surname><given-names>P.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new way to include the grain shape in texture simulations with the Taylor model</article-title><source>J. Phys. Lett.</source><year>1985</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>L1109</fpage><lpage>L1113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/jphyslet:0198500460230110900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-materials-11-01088"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raeisinia</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tome</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the impact of grain size distribution on the plastic behaviour of polycrystalline metals</article-title><source>Model. Simul. Mater. Sci. Eng.</source><year>2008</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>025001</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0965-0393/16/2/025001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-materials-11-01088"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duygulu</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tom&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnew</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grain size effects on the tensile properties and deformation mechanisms of a magnesium alloy, AZ31B, sheet</article-title><source>Mater. Sci. Eng. A</source><year>2008</year><volume>486</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msea.2007.09.069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-materials-11-01088"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fromm</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knezevic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grain size and orientation distributions: Application to yielding of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-titanium</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2009</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>2339</fpage><lpage>2348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actamat.2008.12.037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-materials-11-01088"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cordero</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forest</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busso</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berbenni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherkaoui</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grain size effects on plastic strain and dislocation density tensor fields in metal polycrystals</article-title><source>Comput. Mater. Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.commatsci.2011.02.043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15-materials-11-01088"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Churchman</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The slip modes of titanium and the effect of purity on their occurence during tensile deformation of single crystals</article-title><source>Proc. R. Soc. A</source><year>1954</year><volume>226</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspa.1954.0250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16-materials-11-01088"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deformation mechanisms in Titanium at low temperatures</article-title><source>Trans. Metall. Soc. AIME</source><year>1966</year><volume>236</volume><fpage>1558</fpage><lpage>1565</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17-materials-11-01088"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebyodkin</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebedkina</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecomte</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richeton</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amouzou</surname><given-names>K.E.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of anisotropy of mechanical properties of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-titanium in tension conditions</article-title><source>Mater. Sci. Eng. A</source><year>2014</year><volume>596</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msea.2013.12.061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18-materials-11-01088"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doquet</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barkia</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A micromechanical model of the viscoplastic behaviour of titanium accounting for its anisotropic and strain-rate dependent viscosity</article-title><source>Mech. Time-Depend. Mater.</source><year>2015</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11043-015-9257-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19-materials-11-01088"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amouzou</surname><given-names>K.E.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richeton</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebyodkin</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebedkina</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micromechanical modeling of hardening mechanisms in commercially pure <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-titanium in tensile condition</article-title><source>Int. J. Plast.</source><year>2016</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijplas.2015.09.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20-materials-11-01088"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>F.P.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of Ti-6242 <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> slip properties using micro-pillar test and computational crystal plasticity</article-title><source>J. Mech. Phys. Solids</source><year>2016</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmps.2016.06.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21-materials-11-01088"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>F.P.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrinsic anisotropy of strain rate sensitivity in single crystal alpha titanium</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2016</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actamat.2016.07.044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22-materials-11-01088"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>F.P.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microstructure, Slip Accumulation and Load Shedding in Multiphase Alloys</article-title><source>Int. J. Fatigue</source><year>2018</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>324</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfatigue.2018.03.030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23-materials-11-01088"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mareau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berbenni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An affine formulation for the self-consistent modeling of elasto-viscoplastic heterogeneous materials based on the translated fields method</article-title><source>Int. J. Plast.</source><year>2015</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijplas.2014.08.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24-materials-11-01088"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lhadi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berbenni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gey</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richeton</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micromechanical modeling of the effect of elastic and plastic anisotropies on the mechanical behavior of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-Ti alloys</article-title><source>Int. J. Plast.</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijplas.2018.05.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25-materials-11-01088"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beausir</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fundenberger</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ATEX-Software, Analysis Tools for Electron and X-ray Diffraction, Universit&#x000e9; de Lorraine</article-title><year>2018</year><comment>Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://atex-software.eu/">http://atex-software.eu/</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2018-05-17">(accessed on 17 May 2018)</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26-materials-11-01088"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozzolo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landuyt</surname><given-names>O.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosdidier</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of recrystallisation texture and microstructure in low alloyed titanium sheets</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1359-6454(01)00427-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27-materials-11-01088"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Texture analysis in hexagonal materials</article-title><source>Mater. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2003</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0254-0584(03)00168-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28-materials-11-01088"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzer</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of texture during thermomechanical processing of titanium and its alloys</article-title><source>Trans. Indian Inst. Met.</source><year>2008</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12666-008-0069-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29-materials-11-01088"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantleon</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Work-hardening stages and deformation mechanism maps during tensile deformation of commercially pure titanium</article-title><source>Comput. Mater. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.commatsci.2013.03.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30-materials-11-01088"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barkia</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doquet</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Couzini&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillot</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e9;ripr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In situ</italic> monitoring of the deformation mechanisms in titanium with different oxygen contents</article-title><source>Mater. Sci. Eng. A</source><year>2015</year><volume>636</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msea.2015.03.044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31-materials-11-01088"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouarem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richeton</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving Mechanical Properties of cp Titanium by Heat Treatment Optimization</article-title><source>Adv. Eng. Mater.</source><year>2018</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1700237</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adem.201700237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32-materials-11-01088"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaoui</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-consistent estimates for the rate-dependentelastoplastic behaviour of polycrystalline materials</article-title><source>J. Mech. Phys. Solids</source><year>1999</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1543</fpage><lpage>1568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5096(98)00106-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33-materials-11-01088"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of interstitial solutes on the strength and ductility of titanium</article-title><source>Prog. Mater. Sci.</source><year>1981</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0079-6425(81)90001-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34-materials-11-01088"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etude des M&#x000e9;canismes de D&#x000e9;formation Plastique &#x000e0; Basse Temp&#x000e9;rature de Monocristaux de Titane &#x003b1;</article-title><source>Ph.D. Thesis</source><publisher-name>Universit&#x000e9; de Paris Sud (Orsay)</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Orsay, France</publisher-loc><year>1983</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35-materials-11-01088"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franciosi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berveiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaoui</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Latent hardening in copper and aluminium single crystals</article-title><source>Acta Metall.</source><year>1980</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0001-6160(80)90162-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36-materials-11-01088"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messner</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arsenlis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A crystal plasticity model for slip in hexagonal close packed metals based on discrete dislocation simulations</article-title><source>Model. Simul. Mater. Sci. Eng.</source><year>2017</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>044001</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1361-651X/aa687a</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37-materials-11-01088"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phuka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenesei</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suter</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieler</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct measurement of critical resolved shear stress of prismatic and basal slip in polycrystalline Ti using high energy X-ray diffraction microscopy</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2017</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actamat.2017.05.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38-materials-11-01088"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagan</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shade</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenesei</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menasche</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling slip system strength evolution in Ti-7Al informed by in-situ grain stress measurements</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2017</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actamat.2017.02.042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39-materials-11-01088"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagan</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>J.Y.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blank</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shade</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measuring Ti-7Al slip system strengths at elevated temperature using high-energy X-ray diffraction</article-title><source>Scr. Mater.</source><year>2018</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scriptamat.2017.08.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40-materials-11-01088"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Estrin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubin</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local strain hardening and nonuniformity of plastic deformation</article-title><source>Acta Metall.</source><year>1986</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2455</fpage><lpage>2466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0001-6160(86)90148-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41-materials-11-01088"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress fields and geometrically necessarry dislocation density distributions near the head of a blocked slip band</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2012</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>5773</fpage><lpage>5782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actamat.2012.07.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42-materials-11-01088"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabski</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grain boundaries as sinks for dislocations</article-title><source>Philos. Mag.</source><year>1970</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786437008220941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43-materials-11-01088"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the absorption of dislocations by grain boundaries</article-title><source>Philos. Mag.</source><year>1977</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786437708244939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44-materials-11-01088"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of dislocations with grain boundaries</article-title><source>J. Phys. Colloq.</source><year>1982</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>C6225</fpage><lpage>C6237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/jphyscol:1982621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45-materials-11-01088"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Won</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anisotropic yielding behavior of rolling textured High purity titanium</article-title><source>Mater. Sci. Eng. A</source><year>2015</year><volume>637</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msea.2015.03.096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46-materials-11-01088"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raabe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachtleber</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roters</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaefferer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micromechanical and macromechanical effects in grain scale polycrystal plasticity experimentation and simulation</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2001</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>3433</fpage><lpage>3441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1359-6454(01)00242-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47-materials-11-01088"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allain-Bonasso</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berbenni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study of plastic heterogeneity in IF steel by EBSD</article-title><source>Mater. Sci. Eng. A</source><year>2012</year><volume>548</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msea.2012.03.068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48-materials-11-01088"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouarem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allain-Bonasso</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new method to determine plastic deformation at the grain scale</article-title><source>Mater. Charact.</source><year>2014</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matchar.2014.03.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49-materials-11-01088"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grennerat</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montagnat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castelnau</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vacher</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulinec</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suquet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental characterization of the intragranular strain field in columnar ice during transient creep</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2012</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>3655</fpage><lpage>3666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actamat.2012.03.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50-materials-11-01088"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghaderi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensitivity of deformation twinning to grain size in titanium and magnesium</article-title><source>Acta Mater.</source><year>2011</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>7824</fpage><lpage>7839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actamat.2011.09.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="materials-11-01088-f001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Engineering stress versus engineering plastic strain for three specimens of RR type with different mean grain sizes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g001"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Probability distributions of grain sizes for specimens RR 2.8 and RR 21.3. In the bottom part, the distributions are normalized by the mean grain size <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm13"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the maximum likelihood estimate for a log-normal distribution computed thanks to the MATLAB software (R2015a, MathWorks, Natick, Massachusetts, US) being superimposed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g002"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Pole figures for the specimens RR 2.8 (<bold>a</bold>,<bold>b</bold>) and RR 11.7 (<bold>c</bold>,<bold>d</bold>) plotted thanks to the ATEX software [<xref rid="B25-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. <italic>x</italic> represents the last rolling direction and <italic>y</italic> the transverse direction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g003"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Tensile curves (engineering stress and strain) for model predictions and experimental measurements for the six specimens deformed along the last rolling direction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g004"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Tensile curves (engineering stress and strain) for model predictions and experimental measurements for the specimen deformed along the last transverse direction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g005"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Comparisons between experimental and calculated values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm15"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm16"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm17"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm18"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see text for definitions).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g006"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Comparisons of experimental and calculated values of the yield stress <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm19"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with respect to the mean grain size <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm20"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the specimens of RR type. Linear fit estimates obtained by MATLAB between <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm22"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are shown in green (Model) and black (Exp.) dotted lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g007"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Distribution of predicted tensile stress&#x02013;strain relationships for each grain at 1% (magenta), 5% (red), 10% (blue) and 15% (green) of macroscopic strain for specimens RR 2.8, RR 4.8, RR 9.8 and RR 21.3. The corresponding model tensile curve is superimposed on each plot (black thick line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g008"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Relative activities of slip families (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm77"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) predicted by the model for specimen RR 9.8 (<bold>left</bold>) and RT 9.8 (<bold>right</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g009"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f010" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Model predictions for the work hardening rate evolution for the specimens of RR type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g010"/></fig><fig id="materials-11-01088-f011" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Model predictions for the evolution of the total forest (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm78"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and mobile (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm79"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) dislocation densities for the specimens of RR type. Densities are cumulated over the 30 slip systems and averaged over the grains&#x02019; population.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="materials-11-01088-g011"/></fig><table-wrap id="materials-11-01088-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">materials-11-01088-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Preparation conditions and some metallurgical data of the seven specimens.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimen</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cold Rolling Reduction</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annealing Conditions</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Grains in the Data Set</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR 2.8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500 &#x000b0;C - 40 mn</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6254</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TR 2.8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500 &#x000b0;C - 40 mn</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7328</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR 4.8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">650 &#x000b0;C - 1 h</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8793</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR 9.8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">730 &#x000b0;C - 2 h</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3262</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT 9.8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">730 &#x000b0;C - 2 h</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3262</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR 11.7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">740 &#x000b0;C - 2 h</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4075</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR 21.3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">840 &#x000b0;C - 4 h</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1273</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="materials-11-01088-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">materials-11-01088-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Model parameters that are specific to slip families (Prismatic: <italic>P</italic>, Basal: <italic>B</italic>, Pyramidal &#x0003c;a&#x0003e;: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm88"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x003a0;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, 1st order Pyramidal &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e;: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm89"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x003a0;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, 2nd order Pyramidal &#x0003c;c+a&#x0003e;: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm90"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x003a0;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm91"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-sans-serif">&#x003a0;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm92"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-sans-serif">&#x003a0;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm93"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-sans-serif">&#x003a0;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>b</italic> (&#x000c5;)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.53</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.53</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm94"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (GPa)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm95"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (MPa)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm87"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm75"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="materials-11-01088-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">materials-11-01088-t003_Table 3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Model parameters that are not specific to slip families. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm74"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the stiffness constants. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm52"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the interaction coefficient related to collinear interactions, i.e., reactions between dislocations with parallel Burgers vectors gliding in different planes, whereas <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm53"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> refers to non-collinear interactions (see details in [<xref rid="B19-materials-11-01088" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm54"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">c</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm55"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">C</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">11</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (GPa)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm56"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">C</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">33</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (GPa)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm57"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">C</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">44</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (GPa)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm58"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">C</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">12</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (GPa)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm59"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">C</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">13</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (GPa)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm60"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (MPa.m<sup>0.5</sup>)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.587</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm51"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">v</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (ms<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm63"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">m</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm65"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">f</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm67"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">C</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm68"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm69"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">coli</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm70"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02260;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">coli</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm71"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm72"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm73"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm169"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>