<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharmacogn Mag</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharmacogn Mag</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pharmacognosy Magazine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0973-1296</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0976-4062</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5307909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PM-13-21</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0973-1296.197645</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> Root Extract Modulates the Growth of IMR-32 and SK-N-MC Neuroblastoma Cell Lines Through <italic>MYCN</italic> Mediated Regulation of MDM2 and p53</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suryavanshi</surname><given-names>Snehal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>Prerna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>Rashmi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaul-Ghanekar</surname><given-names>Ruchika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Interactive Research School for Health Affairs (IRSHA), Bharati Vidyapeeth University, Katraj-Dhankawadi, Pune, Maharashtra, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Dr. Ruchika Kaul-Ghanekar, Interactive Research School for Health Affairs (IRSHA), Bharati Vidyapeeth Deemed University, IRSHA, Pune-Satara Road, Katraj-Dhankawadi, Pune, Maharashtra, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="ruchika.kaulghanekar@gmail.com">ruchika.kaulghanekar@gmail.com</email>; <email xlink:href="kaul_r@yahoo.com">kaul_r@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Mar</season><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>49</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2017 Pharmacognosy Magazine</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Aim:</title><p>The present study evaluated the effect of ethanolic extract of <italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> roots (NJ<sub>et</sub>) on MYCN mediated regulation of expression of MDM2 and p53 proteins in neuroblastoma cell lines, IMR-32 and SK-N-MC.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>The effect of NJ<sub>et</sub> on cell viability was determined by MTT; and on growth kinetics was evaluated by trypan blue dye exclusion method and soft agar assay. The expression of p53, MDM2 and MYCN proteins in response to NJ<sub>et</sub> treatment was evaluated by immunoblotting.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>NJ<sub>et</sub> decreased the viability of neuroblastoma cells without affecting the viability of non-cancerous, HEK-293 cells. It altered the growth kinetics of the cancer cells in a dose-dependent manner. NJ<sub>et</sub> down regulated the expression of MYCN and MDM2 proteins with a simultaneous increase in the expression of tumor suppressor protein p53.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>The present data demonstrated that NJ<sub>et</sub> regulated the growth of IMR-32 and SK-N-MC through reduction in MYCN expression that lead to down regulation of MDM2 protein and increase in p53 expression. These preliminary results warrant further in depth studies to explore the therapeutic potential of <italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> in the management of neuroblastoma.</p></sec><sec id="st5"><title>SUMMARY</title><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>NJ<sub>et</sub> reduced the viability of human neuroblastoma cell lines without affecting the viability of non-cancerous, HEK-293 cells.</p></list-item><list-item><p>NJ<sub>et</sub> regulated the growth kinetics of the cancer cells.</p></list-item><list-item><p>NJ<sub>et</sub> decreased the expression of MYCN and MDM2 proteins and simultaneously increased the expression of tumor suppressor protein p53.</p></list-item></list>
</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="PM-13-21-g001"/></fig><p><bold>Abbreviation used:</bold> NJ<sub>et</sub>: Ethanolic extract of <italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> MTT: 3-(4, 5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide HPTLC: High performance thin layer chromatography</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Neuroblastoma</kwd><kwd><italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic></kwd><kwd>MYCN</kwd><kwd>p53</kwd><kwd>MDM2</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p><italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> (Valerianaceae), commonly known as muskroot, is indigenous to the Himalayan regions of India.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] In Ayurveda, <italic>N. jatamansi</italic> has been used traditionally since centuries for treating various neurological disorders. It has been used as a sedative, an antispasmodic, for mind rejuvenation, promotion of sleep, alleviating mental diseases and as a brain tonic.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] It has also been used for treating headache, insomnia, epilepsy; disorders of cardiovascular system; flatulence and intestinal colic as well as menopausal symptoms.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] <italic>N. jatamansi</italic> has been shown to possess anti-inflammatory,[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] anti-oxidant,[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] anti-bacterial,[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] anticonvulsant[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and hepatoprotective activities.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] It has been shown to exhibit anti-tumour activity in lung, liver, ovary, breast and prostate cancers.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Recently, the higher doses of alcoholic and n-hexane extract of <italic>N. jatamansi</italic> were shown to significantly inhibit the growth of neurobalstoma cell lines, IMR 32 and SK-N-SH.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</p><p>In the present study, we have shown that ethanolic extract of <italic>N. jatamansi</italic> roots (NJ<sub>et</sub>) significantly altered the growth kinetics of IMR-32 and SK-N-MC neuroblastoma cells at lower doses through down regulation of <italic>MYCN</italic> and MDM2 proteins and upregulation of p53.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Drugs and chemicals</title><p>Tissue culture plasticware was purchased from BD Biosciences (CA, USA). DMEM powder, penicillin and streptomycin were obtained from Invitrogen (Grand Island, NY, USA). Fetal bovine serum (FBS), 3-(4, 5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2, 5-diphenylthiazolium bromide (MTT), Valerinic acid and primary antibody against <italic>MYCN</italic> were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). Primary antibody against p53 (DO-1), MDM2, tubulin (B-7) and donkey anti-mouse IgG antibody were purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc. (Santa Cruz, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Plant material, extract preparation and preliminary phytochemical analysis</title><p><italic>N. jatamansi</italic> roots were purchased from Green Pharmacy (Pune, Maharashtra, India). The sample was authenticated and validated macroscopically and microscopically at the Department of Botany, Agharkar Research Institute (ARI), Pune (Maharashtra, India) (ref no.1045). Voucher specimen sample (Number R-154) has been deposited at the Department.</p><p><italic>N. jatamansi</italic> roots were weighed, powdered and extracted in ethanol using soxhlet apparatus. The resulting extract was centrifuged at 13000 rpm for 15 min to remove the particulate matter. The supernatant was filter-sterilized using swiney filter (pore size, 0.45 &#x000b5;m) and the resultant filtrate was stored in aliquots at -80&#x000b0;C until use.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Cell culture</title><p>The cell lines (IMR-32, SK-N-MC and HEK-293) used in the present study were obtained from National Centre for Cell Science (NCCS), Pune, India. The cells were grown in DMEM containing 2 mM L-glutamine supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum and 20 U/ml of penicillin-streptomycin and incubated in a humidified 5% CO<sub>2</sub> incubator at 37&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Cell viability</title><p>IMR-32, SK-N-MC and HEK-293 were seeded at a density of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ ml in a 96-well plate. The cells were treated with different concentrations of NJ<sub>et</sub> (0-160 &#x000b5;g/ml) in triplicates for 24 h. Cell viability was determined by MTT assay as described previously.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Cell growth analysis</title><p>IMR-32 and SK-N-MC were seeded at a density of 5 &#x000d7; 104 cells/well in 24-well plate. The cells were treated with different concentrations of NJ<sub>et</sub> (0-20 &#x000b5;g/ml) in triplicates for 24, 48 and 72 h. The effect of NJ<sub>et</sub> on cell growth was determined by trypan blue dye exclusion method as described previously.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Soft agar assay</title><p>IMR-32 and SK-N-MC cells (5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml) treated with different concentrations of NJ<sub>et</sub> (0-20 &#x003bc;g/ ml) were mixed with culture medium containing 0.35% agarose and plated over a previously gelled layer of 0.5% agarose as described previously.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] The colonies were manually counted and photographed directly using an Axiovert 200 M microscope (Carl Zeiss, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Western blotting</title><p>IMR-32 and SK-N-MC cells were plated at a seeding density of 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/well in a 6-well plate and incubated for 24 h at 37&#x000b0;C in CO<sub>2</sub> incubator. Next day, the cells were treated with different concentrations of NJ<sub>et</sub> (0-20 &#x003bc;g/ml) for 24 h. The cells were lysed as previously described.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] The protein was estimated using Bradford reagent (Biorad Laboratories Inc, CA, USA). Equal amount of protein was loaded on a 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gel and transferred electrophoretically to Amersham Hybond-P PVDF membrane (GE Healthcare, UK) in sodium phosphate buffer (pH 6.8). The membrane was blocked in 5% BSA in TBST and incubated at room temperature for 3 h with mouse monoclonal primary antibodies against p53, MDM2 and tubulin (Santacruz, CA, USA) at 1:2000 and <italic>MYCN</italic> (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) at 1:500 dilutions respectively. The blots were washed in TBST and incubated with donkey anti mouse IgG HRP conjugate at 1:4000 (for p53, MDM2, tubulin) and 1:2000 (for <italic>MYCN</italic>) dilutions. Proteins were visualized using a chemiluminescence kit (Amersham ECL Advance western blotting detection kit, GE Healthcare, UK) and densitometric analysis of X-ray films was performed using the Image J gel analysis tool.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Measurement of apoptosis</title><p>The cells were plated at a seeding density of 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/well in a 6-well plate and treated with different concentrations of NJ<sub>et</sub> (0-20 &#x003bc;g/ml). After 24 h of treatment, the cells were harvested and washed with PBS twice. Cells were stained with Annexin V-FITC following the manufacturer's instructions (Annexin V-FITC apoptosis kit #3, Invitrogen) and analyzed for apoptosis by FACS using Cell Quest Software.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All the results were obtained from three independent experiments, each performed in triplicates and the values have been presented as mean &#x000b1; SD. Differences among means were tested for statistical significance using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). The analyses were carried out using Graph-pad prism 5 software (San Diego, CA, USA). *p &#x0003c; 0.05; **p &#x0003c; 0.01; ***p &#x0003c; 0.001 were considered to be statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Chromatographic analysis of NJ<sub>et</sub></title><p>HPTLC chromatographic examination of NJ<sub>et</sub> was carried out to authenticate <italic>N. jatamansi</italic> root extract based on its marker compound, valerinic acid [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 1</xref>]. The finger print profile was developed in toluene: ethylacetate: formic acid (8:2:0.5) solvent system and the peaks corresponding to valerinic acid were recorded at Rf 0.75. Similar peaks were found in chromatographic profile of NJ<sub>et</sub> at the same Rf value of 0.75. The calibration curves were linear in the range of 200-1200 ng of valerinic acid. The amount of valerinic acid in NJ<sub>et</sub> was found to be 41.58 mg/g.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>HPTLC images and standardization of NJ<sub>et</sub>. HPTLC densitogram of (A) marker compound valerinic acid and (B) NJ<sub>et</sub>. (C) Calibration curves in linear range of 200, 400, 800, 1000, 1200 ng of standard valerinic acid. (D) UV spectra of standard valerinic acid and samples of NJ<sub>et</sub> obtained by HPTLC spot scanning from 200 to 400 nm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PM-13-21-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>NJ<sub>et</sub> altered growth kinetics of neuroblastoma cell lines</title><p>In IMR-32 and SKNMC, NJ<sub>et</sub> altered growth kinetics of neuroblastoma cell lines exhibited IC<sub>50</sub> values of 61.43 and 63.42 &#x000b5;g/ml, respectively [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 2</xref>]. Contrarily, in non-cancerous HEK-293 cells, IC<sub>50</sub> was not obtained upto 160 &#x000b5;g/ml concentration of NJ<sub>et</sub> [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 2</xref>]. Thus, NJ<sub>et</sub> significantly reduced the viability of neuroblastoma cells at lower doses without affecting the viability of the non-cancerous cells. Further studies were carried out at non-cytotoxic doses (0-20 &#x000b5;g/ml) of NJ<sub>et</sub> to analyze its effect at cellular and molecular level.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of NJ<sub>et</sub> on cell viability. IMR-32, SK-NMC and HEK-293 cells were treated with different concentrations (0-160 &#x003bc;g/ml) of <italic>N. jatamansi</italic> root extract. The cell viability was determined by MTT dye uptake method and the data represents mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments, each performed in triplicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PM-13-21-g003"/></fig><p>In IMR-32, NJ<sub>et</sub> reduced the cell proliferation at 20 &#x000b5;g/ml dose by ~2-fold at 24 h and by ~1.5-folds at 48 and 72 h (p = &#x0003c; 0.001) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 3A</xref>]. On the other hand, in SK-N-MC, the proliferation was reduced by~2- (p = &#x0003c;0.001), 3-(p = &#x0003c; 0.001) and 2- folds (p = &#x0003c; 0.001), respectively at 24, 48 and 72 h compared to the untreated control cells [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 3B</xref>]. The effect of NJ<sub>et</sub> on the cell growth was further evaluated by soft agar assay that showed a dose dependent decrease in the number of soft agar colonies. At 20&#x000b5;g/ml, there was ~2.5- (p &#x02264; 0.001) and 3.5-folds (p &#x02264; 0.001) reduction in the number of colonies in IMR-32 and SK-N-MC, respectively, compared to the untreated control cells [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 3C</xref>]. These data demonstrated that NJ<sub>et</sub> significantly regulated the proliferation and growth kinetics of IMR-32 and SK-N-MC cells.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effect of NJ<sub>et</sub> on growth kinetics of neuroblastoma cells. (A) IMR-32 and (B) SK-N-MC cell lines were treated with NJ<sub>et</sub> (0-20 &#x003bc;g/ml) for 24, 48 and 72 h and the number of viable cells were counted by trypan blue dye exclusion method. Data represent mean&#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments (C) IMR-32 and SK-N-MC cell lines were treated with NJ<sub>et</sub> (0-20 &#x003bc;g/ml) and grown in soft agar for two weeks. Colonies were counted from at least 10 different areas and the average of each has been plotted. The data represents mean &#x000b1; SD of five independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PM-13-21-g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-12"><title>NJ<sub>et</sub> increased the expression of p53 through down regulation of <italic>MYCN</italic> and MDM2</title><p>It was found that NJ<sub>et</sub> up regulated p53 expression in a dose-dependent manner in IMR-32 and SK-N-MC [Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">B</xref>, respectively] cells. At 20&#x000b5;g/ml, there was~1.5-(p &#x0003c; 0.05) and 18.36-folds (p &#x0003c; 0.05) increase in p53 expression in IMR-32 and SK-N-MC cells, respectively, compared to the untreated control cells [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 4C</xref>]. Contrarily, a dose dependant decrease in the expression of MDM2 and <italic>MYCN</italic> proteins was observed in IMR-32 and SK-N-MC cells compared to the untreated control cells [Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">B</xref>, respectively]. In IMR-32 and SK-N-MC cells, at 20 &#x000b5;g/ml dose of NJ<sub>et</sub>, there was ~4- and 9-folds (p &#x0003c; 0.05) decrease in the expression of MDM2 (p &#x0003c; 0.05) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 4D</xref>], respectively, as well as ~1.7- and 4.4-folds decrease in <italic>MYCN</italic> expression, respectively, compared to the untreated control cells [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 4E</xref>].</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Effect of NJ<sub>et</sub> on the expression of tumor regulatory markers. (A-E) IMR-32 and SK-N-MC cells were analyzed for the expression of p53, MDM2 and MYCN proteins by western blotting. Tubulin was used as a loading control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PM-13-21-g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The present study reported the mechanism of anti-cancer potential of <italic>N. jatamansi</italic> root extract (NJ<sub>et</sub>) in the human neuroblastoma cell lines, IMR-32 and SK-N-MC. NJ<sub>et</sub> reduced the viability of neuroblastoma cell lines at lower doses (40 &#x003bc;g/ml onwards) compared to the non-cancerous cells. At 80 &#x000b5;g/ml dose, NJ<sub>et</sub> reduced the cell viability of IMR-32 and SK-N-MC by 70 and 62%, respectively, with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 61.43 and 63.42 &#x000b5;g/ml, respectively. It negatively regulated the growth kinetics of neuroblastoma cells in a significant manner and effectively reduced their proliferation. Previously, Monga and Kumar in 2013 had reported the anti- proliferative potential of alcoholic extract and n-hexane fraction of roots of <italic>N. jatamansi</italic> against neuroblastoma cell lines, IMR-32 and SK-N-SH.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] They had shown that at 100 &#x003bc;g/ml dose, the alcoholic extract reduced the proliferation of IMR-32 and SK-N-SH by 71 and 85%, respectively, whereas at the same dose hexane fraction reduced the proliferation by 91 and 82% respectively. Interestingly, in our study NJ<sub>et</sub> reduced the viability at much lower doses compared to that reported by Monga and Kumar, which is excellent for drug development point of view. The difference in these results could be due to time of collection of the roots, method of preparation of the extract and the method of cell proliferation assay. Various reports have shown anticancer activity of herbal formulations against neuroblastoma cell lines. PienTze Huang, a popular Chinese medicine for liver diseases, has been reported to decrease survival of SH-SY5Y neuroblastoma cell line.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] The leaf extracts of <italic>Holarrhena antidysenterica</italic> have been reported to be cytotoxic to SK-N-MC neuroblastoma cells.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] <italic>Calotropisprocera</italic>, <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> and <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> have been shown to be cytotoxic to IMR-32.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] However, neither of the studies has delineated the molecular mechanisms underlying the anticancer activity of these medicinal plants.</p><p>In the present work, we have shown the preliminary mechanism of action of NJ<sub>et</sub> in neuroblastoma cell lines. We found that NJ<sub>et</sub> significantly down regulated the expression of <italic>MYCN</italic>, the major negative prognostic marker in neuroblastoma with significant role in the pathogenesis and clinical onset of this aggressive malignancy.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] <italic>MYCN</italic> has been reported to activate proliferative cellular pathways and inhibition of p53-mediated apoptosis has been considered as the prerequisite for MYC-driven tumorigenesis.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Interestingly, NJ<sub>et</sub> not only decreased the expression of MYCN but simultaneously upregulated the expression of tumor suppressor protein p53. Moreover, NJ<sub>et</sub> significantly reduced the expression of MDM2, the negative regulator of p53. MDM2 is amplified in a variety of human cancers, including neuroblastoma.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] It has been reported to be a predictor for poor treatment outcome in neuroblastoma patients.[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Thus, NJ<sub>et</sub> regulated the growth of the neuroblastoma cells through disruption of <italic>MYCN</italic> and MDM2 expression and stabilization of p53. These results lead us to study the mechanism of cell death induced by NJ<sub>et</sub>, which was found to induce apoptosis in IMR-32 and G2/M arrest in SK-N-MC cells (data not shown).</p><p>All these data suggested the potential of ethanolic extract of <italic>N. jatamansi</italic> (NJ<sub>et</sub>) in regulating the growth of neuroblastoma cells.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>The present study has evaluated the mechanism of anticancer activity of NJ<sub>et</sub> in IMR-32 and SK-N-MC neuroblastoma cell lines. However, further in-depth studies are warranted against other neurablastoma cell lines as well as <italic>in vivo</italic> studies need to be done to establish the chemopreventive potential of <italic>N. jatamansi</italic>.</p><sec id="sec2-13"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>This work was supported by funding from the Interactive Research School for Health Affairs (IRSHA), Bharati Vidyapeeth University.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-14" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>The authors thank Director of IRSHA for his generous support and encouragement. The authors would like to acknowledge Dr. Anand Zanwar, Department of Food and Nutrition Lab, for helping in HPTLC profiling of the extract.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Negi</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil composition of <italic>Valerianajatamansi</italic> jones from himalayan regions of India</article-title><source>Indian J Pharm Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26009656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monga</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phytopharmacological review on Jatamansi</article-title><source>Pharm Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaishali Panda</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Panigrahi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of anti-inflammatory potential of <italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> rhizome in experimental rodents</article-title><source>Jcoastlife med</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrashekar</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Setty</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Devkar</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of antioxidant and anticancer activity of extract and fractions of <italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> DC in breast carcinoma</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>50</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25886964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bengal Das</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee A</surname><given-names>Anu</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study on <italic>In vitro</italic> antibacterial and antifungal properties of five medicinal plants of west</article-title><source>Asian J Plant Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhagat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandita</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> and <italic>In vivo</italic> Biological Activities of <italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> roots</article-title><source>MAP</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>6</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jafry</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabeer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Diwakar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> protects against liver damage induced by thioacetamide in rats</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2000</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10940571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choudhari</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Suryavanshi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaul-Ghanekar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The aqueous extract of <italic>Ficusreligiosa</italic> induces cell cycle arrest in human cervical cancer cell lines SiHa (HPV-16 Positive) and apoptosis in HeLa (HPV-18 positive)</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e70127</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23922932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koppikar</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhari</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Suryavanshi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaul-Ghanekar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aqueous cinnamon extract (ACE-c) from the bark of <italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic> causes apoptosis in human cervical cancer cell line (SiHa) through loss of mitochondrial membrane potential</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>210</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20482751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wai</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yew</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PienTze Huang, a composite Chinese traditional herbal extract, affects survival of neuroblastoma cells. Int</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2009</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> cytotoxic activity of leaves extracts of <italic>Holarrhena antidysenterica</italic> against some human cancer cell lines</article-title><source>Indian J Biochem Biophys</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> cytotoxic activity of Indian medicinal plants used traditionally to treat cancer</article-title><source>Asian J Pharm Clin Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pule</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pession</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The p53 regulatory gene MDM2 is a direct transcriptional target of MYCN in neuroblastoma</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15644444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbieri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Burlingame</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mdm2 deficiency suppresses MYCN-driven neuroblastoma tumorigenesis <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>Neoplasia</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19649205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J1</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crosstalk between MYCN and MDM2-p53 signal pathways regulates tumor cell growth and apoptosis in neuroblastoma</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2994</fpage><lpage>3002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21862876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carol</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Keir</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorlick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Initial testing of the MDM2 inhibitor RG7112 by the Pediatric Preclinical Testing Program</article-title><source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source><year>2013</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22753001</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>