<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6131628</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.01308</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>SiYGL2 Is Involved in the Regulation of Leaf Senescence and Photosystem II Efficiency in <italic>Setaria italica</italic> (L.) P. Beauv.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Shuo</given-names></name><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/475413/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhi</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/589676/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wen</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Jianguo</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Chanjuan</given-names></name><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/589650/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Guanqing</given-names></name><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/502169/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Sha</given-names></name><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/246004/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>Xianmin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/383613/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Institute of Crop Sciences, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Thomas P. Brutnell, Shandong Agricultural University, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Ru Zhang, Donald Danforth Plant Science Center, United States; Yan Lu, Western Michigan University, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Xianmin Diao, <email>diaoxianmin@caas.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Breeding, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1308</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Zhang, Zhi, Li, Shan, Tang, Jia, Tang and Diao.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhang, Zhi, Li, Shan, Tang, Jia, Tang and Diao</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A yellow-green leaf mutant was isolated from EMS-mutagenized lines of <italic>Setaria italica</italic> variety Yugu1. Map-based cloning revealed the mutant gene is a homolog of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana AtEGY1</italic>. EGY1 (ethylene-dependent gravitropism-deficient and yellow-green 1) is an ATP-independent metalloprotease (MP) that is required for chloroplast development, photosystem protein accumulation, hypocotyl gravitropism, leaf senescence, and ABA signal response in <italic>A. thaliana</italic>. However, the function of EGY1 in monocotyledonous C<sub>4</sub> plants has not yet been described. The <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant is phenotypically characterized by chlorotic organs, premature senescence, and damaged PS II function. Sequence comparisons of the AtEGY1 and SiYGL2 proteins reveals the potential for SiYGL2 to encode a partially functional protein. Phenotypic characterization and gene expression analysis suggested that SiYGL2 participates in the regulation of chlorophyll content, leaf senescence progression, and PS II function. Additionally, our research will contribute to further characterization of the mechanisms regulating leaf senescence and photosynthesis in <italic>S. italica</italic>, and in C<sub>4</sub> plants in general.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>EGY1</kwd><kwd><italic>Setaria italica</italic></kwd><kwd>chlorotic mutant</kwd><kwd>leaf senescence</kwd><kwd>PS II efficiency</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100005196</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">CAAS-XTCX2016002</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Ministry of Agriculture of the People&#x02019;s Republic of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100004573</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">CARS06-13.5-A04</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100005196</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn003">31501324</award-id><award-id rid="cn003">31522040</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="10"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="1"/><ref-count count="49"/><page-count count="15"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>AtEGY1 is an ATP-independent metalloprotease (MP) belonging to the M50 family (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">van der Hoorn, 2008</xref>). Members of the M50 family typically contain four to eight transmembrane helices (TMHs), three adjacent ones of which can form a conserved three-TMH core structure. The conversed motifs HEXXH and NPDG are located in the first TMH and the third TMH of the core structure, respectively (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Kinch et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Koussis et al., 2017</xref>). M50 family members contain three metal ligand-binding sites required for protease activity. Two of the ligand-binding sites reside in the HEXXH motif and the third is coordinated by the Asp residue in NPDG motif (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Yu and Kroos, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al., 2007</xref>). As MPs, M50 family proteins participate in multiple cellular processes by cleaving substrates such as membrane-tethered proteins, transcription factors, and signal peptides (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000f6;lter et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Kinch et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Mukherjee et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Che et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Saito et al., 2011</xref>). AtEGY1 is targeted to chloroplasts and can be upregulated by both light and ethylene treatment in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005</xref>). The function of AtEGY1 has been characterized in a number of different studies. AtEGY1 has three conversed motifs: GNLR, HEXXH, and NPDG. The first is a signature motif unique to EGY family proteins (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005</xref>); the function of this motif has not yet been clarified. The latter two motifs are metal-chelating motifs unique to M50 family members. AtEGY1 was shown to play a role in many biological processes including the regulation of chloroplast development, ethylene-dependent hypocotyl gravitropism, the accumulation of membrane-bound chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>/<italic>b</italic> binding (CAB) proteins, and responding to ammonium and phosphate stress (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2016</xref>). In addition, AtEGY1 was reported to be involved in leaf senescence. The T-DNA insertion mutant of <italic>AtEGY1, Ategy1</italic>, had yellow rosette leaves and reduced chlorophyll content, leaf survival, and Fv/Fm. Mutants also showed decreased soluble protein content and increased ion leakage compared with WT. The expression of senescence-associated genes were increased in <italic>Ategy1</italic>. Under dark treatment, the aging phenotype in <italic>Ategy1</italic> was more obvious than that in WT. These data indicated that the loss of AtEGY1 function accelerated leaf aging and decreased photosystem II (PS II) efficiency. In addition, exogenously applied glucose could rescue these mutant phenotypes (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>Leaf senescence is an important plant developmental process that is associated with a range of unique physiological and biochemical characteristics. During leaf senescence, leaves turn yellow; chlorophyll is degraded; proteins, fatty acids, nucleic acids, and other macromolecules are metabolized; plastids disintegrate rapidly; and nitrogen and nutrients are efficiently transferred into growing tissues and sink organs (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Yang and Ohlrogge, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Sakamoto and Takami, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Diaz-Mendoza et al., 2016</xref>). Concurrently, thousands of senescence-associated genes are upregulated or downregulated at the transcriptional or post-transcriptional level as senescence is a well-controlled process that transfers nutrients from source to sink (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Gupta et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2016</xref>). Crop yield and quality are, therefore, closely related to the timing of senescence. Proteins in old organs are extensively degraded into amino acids, amides, and ammoniums. For cereal crops, leaf senescence provides most of the nitrogen in grains. It has been reported that delayed senescence could lead to high yields (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2017</xref>) because the filling period is prolonged and sugar and nitrogen accumulation is increased (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Egli, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Gregersen et al., 2013</xref>). Conversely, grain quality has negative correlations with senescence progression. Because delayed senescence could cause inefficient nitrogen remobilization. The grain quality parameters such as proteins and micronutrients are diluted by carbohydrates, thereby leading to a low grain quality (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gregersen et al., 2008</xref>). There is a balance between grain yield and quality. Thus, the better understanding of the senescence process could help improve crop production and seed quality (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Diaz-Mendoza et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>Metalloproteases (MPs) are one type of plant proteases, which plays important roles in leaf senescence. There are approximately 100 MPs in plants, belonging to 19 families which are classified by the similarity in amino acid sequence. Although they are involved in many biological processes, the roles of MPs in leaf senescence are poorly understood (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">van der Hoorn, 2008</xref>). The most studied senescence-associated MPs are FtsH (filamentation temperature sensitive H) proteases that belong to the M41 family. FtsH1, 2, 5, and 8 can form a hexameric ring in the chloroplast thylakoid to regulate the thylakoid structure and remove photodamaged D1 protein in PS II under light stress (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Yoshioka-Nishimura et al., 2014</xref>). Changes in the expression of <italic>FtsH1, 2</italic>, and <italic>5</italic> observed in senescing and aging leaves was found to be associated with light stress, dark conditions, or nitrogen stress (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Roberts et al., 2012</xref>). FtsH6 is reportedly involved in detached leaf senescence and dark-induced leaf senescence. Other proteases including members of the M10 and M17 MP families have also been reported associated with leaf senescence. Matrix MPs (MMPs) belong to the M10 family and are reportedly upregulated during senescence (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Roberts et al., 2012</xref>). A mutant of At2-MMP shows a late flowering and early senescence phenotype, suggesting that MMPs are responsible for senescence regulation (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Golldack et al., 2002</xref>). Leucine aminopeptidase 2 (LAP2) is a member of the M17 family. In <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, a mutant of LAP2 displays an early-senescence phenotype, suggesting that LAPs are involved in leaf longevity (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Waditee-Sirisattha et al., 2011</xref>). EGY1 belongs to M50 family. To date, seven M50 family members have been identified in <italic>A. thaliana, Oryza sativa</italic>, and <italic>Zea mays</italic>. These proteases play roles in chloroplast development, hypocotyl elongation and gravitropism, stress response, nuclear plastid signaling pathway, and plant development, respectively (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Nishimura et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p><italic>Setaria italica</italic> is a new model C<sub>4</sub> monocotyledonous species that promises to accelerate functional genomics studies in the grasses (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Doust et al., 2009</xref>). In this study, a pale green mutant <italic>siygl2</italic> was isolated from EMS-mutagenized lines of the <italic>S. italica</italic> Yugu1 cultivar. Map-based cloning indicated that the mutant gene encoded SiYGL2, a homolog of AtEGY1. Phenotypic surveys showed that <italic>siygl2</italic>, such as <italic>Ategy1</italic>, is characterized by chlorotic organs, premature senescence, and damaged PS II function. Unlike <italic>Ategy1</italic>, however, chloroplast development is not impaired in <italic>siygl2</italic>. Our study focused on the function of SiYGL1 in regulating senescence and photosynthesis in <italic>S. italica</italic> to supplement the existing functional gene knowledge available for this C<sub>4</sub> model plant. Additionally, our research provides further insight into the mechanisms underlying the regulation of leaf senescence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Plant Materials and Growth Condition</title><p>The <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant was identified in screens of EMS mutagenized populations of <italic>S. italica</italic> cultivar Yugu1. To determine the chlorophyll content and the photosynthetic rate, plants were planted under natural conditions in the experimental field of institute of Crop Sciences, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, in Beijing (116.6&#x000b0;E, 40.1&#x000b0;N) in summer season. For dark-induced senescence, detached leaves were incubated in water at 28&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Chlorophyll Content, Photosynthetic Rate, and Chlorophyll Fluorescence</title><p>For analysis of photosynthetic pigments, leaves were cut into pieces and soaked in 95% alcohol for approximately 72 h until leaf pieces were completely transparent. The absorbance values of the supernatant were measured at 665 and 649 nm with UV-1800 ultraviolet/visible light. Chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> (Chl <italic>a</italic>) and chlorophyll <italic>b</italic> (Chl <italic>b</italic>) levels were then calculated as described by <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Lichtenthaler (1987)</xref>. Statistics analysis was conducted using Welch&#x02019;s two-sample <italic>t</italic> test. Multiple comparisons were made with LSD by IBM SPSS Statistics 23.0. The photosynthetic rate and chlorophyll fluorescence were measured on sunny days using a Li-6400 portable photosynthesis system (LI-COR, Lincoln, NE, United States) using mature leaves from five individuals. The light source used for measuring the photosynthetic parameters is 6400-02B LED light source, the ParIn parameter was set to 1000 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>-2</sup> s<sup>1</sup>. The equations for the photosynthetic parameters are calculated as follows (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2014</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;&#x003a6;PS&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>II</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>Fm</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>Fs</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo>Fm</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;ETR</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>PAR</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>photosynthetic&#x000a0;active&#x000a0;radiation</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x00394;&#x003a6;PS&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>II</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.84</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></sec><sec><title>Transmission Electron Microscopy</title><p>The second leaf and seventh leaf were obtained from plants that were at the eight-leaf stage. Leaf material was cut into 2 mm &#x000d7; 1 mm pieces and fixed overnight in 0.1 M phosphate buffer with 2.5% glutaraldehyde. The samples were then washed with 0.2 M phosphate buffer three times and post-fixed in 1% osmium tetroxide for 1 h. After staining with uranyl acetate, samples were further dehydrated in a gradient ethanol series and finally embedded into resin. Ultrathin sections were made and examined by JEM 1230 transmission electron microscopy (TEM). The areas of plastoglobulis are calculated by Image-Pro plus 6.0 (Media Cybernetics, Silver Spring, Georgia Avenue, United States). Statistics treatment was made with Welch&#x02019;s two-sample <italic>t</italic> test.</p></sec><sec><title>Map-Based Cloning</title><p>An F2 population generated from a cross between <italic>siygl2</italic> and the SSR41 cultivar was used for mapping of the <italic>SiYGL2</italic> locus. Sixty-five SSR markers based on earlier studies (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>) were adopted for gene cross positioning. Thirteen cleaved amplified polymorphism sequences (CAPS) markers were newly designed for fine mapping based on the single-nucleotide polymorphism information between Yugu1 and SSR41 (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2013</xref>) (<bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S1</xref></bold>). To identify mutant locations, 40 sequencing primers were developed that covered the whole candidate region based on the genome sequence information from the <italic>S. italica</italic> genome project V2.2<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref></sup> database (<bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S2</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Preparation and Transcript Analysis</title><p>RNA was isolated from wild-type (WT) and <italic>siygl2</italic> stems, panicles, and 1st and 10th leaves from the top of the plant at the heading stage from fresh plant tissues using a Pure Link RNA Mini Kit (Cat no. 12183018, Invitrogen, United Kingdom). First-srtand cDNA was synthesized with a PrimerScript 1st Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Cat no. 6210A, TaKaRa, Otsu Shiga, Japan). Quantitative PCR was conducted using a Fast Start Universal SYBR Green Master (ROX) (Cat no. 04913914001, Roche, Mannheim, Germany) using the specific primers listed in <bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S3</xref></bold>. <italic>Cullin</italic> was selected as the reference gene according to a previous study (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Martins et al., 2016</xref>). The data were detected and analyzed using an Applied Biosystems 7300 Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, United States). Statistics treatment was made with Welch&#x02019;s two-sample <italic>t</italic> test.</p></sec><sec><title>Bioinformatics Analysis</title><p>The sequences and structures of the candidate genes were obtained from the <italic>S. italica</italic> genome project V2.2. For phylogenetic analysis, homologs were obtained by NCBI Protein Blast<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn02">2</xref></sup>. Sequence alignments and cladograms were produced using MEGA 5.0 software. Protein TMHs were calculated using TMHMM_v.2<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn03">3</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Subcellular Localization</title><p>The full-length cDNA of <italic>SiYGL2</italic>, excluding the stop code, was amplified from Yugu1 using the following primers: 5&#x02032;<underline>TATCTCTAGAGGATCC</underline>CTATCCTCCTTCGGTCCTTCCCATT 3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032; <underline>TGCTCACCATGGATCC</underline>GAACGAAGTAACAAGCCCTACACCT 3&#x02032; [the underlined sequences are adaptors for In-fusion<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> PCR cloning system (Cat no. 072012, Clontech, United States) and contain <italic>Bam</italic>HI cleavage sites]. The cDNA sequences were cloned into the p16318hGFP vector to form fusion proteins with the C-terminus of GFP. These vectors were then transfected into foxtail millet protoplasts by PEG-mediated transformation and detected by confocal microscopy (LSM700, Carl Zeiss, Germany).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>The Chlorotic Mutant <italic>siygl2</italic> Has Reduced Chlorophyll Accumulation and Poor Agronomic Traits</title><p>The <italic>S. italica</italic> chlorotic mutant <italic>siygl2</italic> was generated from the Yugu1 cultivar by EMS treatment. The <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant showed a relatively normal phenotype in the seedling stage (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref></bold>). Throughout development, however, these plants gradually became chlorotic, and in the late developmental stages, <italic>siygl2</italic> produced chlorotic leaves, stems, and panicles (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">E</xref></bold>). Additionally, the lower leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic> had more abnormal phenotypes than the upper leaves (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1F</xref></bold>). Senescence appeared to be accelerated in <italic>siygl2</italic> as the basal leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic> were tip burned. Several key agronomic traits of <italic>siygl2</italic> and WT plants were analyzed. The results showed that some yield characteristics, such as floret grain number and panicle weight, are significantly reduced compared to WT (<bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Phenotypic characteristics of the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant. <bold>(A)</bold> Five-week-old seedling phenotypes of the wild-type (WT) cultivar Yugu1 and the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant. <bold>(B)</bold> Heading stage phenotypes of Yugu1 and <italic>siygl2.</italic> The red bars point out the significant abnormal phenotypes in panicles, stems, and bottom leaves. <bold>(C&#x02013;E)</bold> Lower leaves, stems, and panicles of heading stage plants. <bold>(F)</bold> Leaf color comparison of the WT (left) and <italic>siygl2</italic> (right) at the heading stage. Leaves from the top of the plant to the bottom are arranged accordingly.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Agronomic traits in wild-type Yugu1 and mutant <italic>siygl2</italic> plants.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait</th><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yugu1</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>siygl2</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant height (cm)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.6 &#x000b1; 7.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.1 &#x000b1; 5.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tiller number</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.212</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Main panicle length (cm)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 &#x000b1; 1.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Main panicle diameter (cm)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8 &#x000b1; 1.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8 &#x000b1; 6.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Floret number</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.2 &#x000b1; 13.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124.6 &#x000b1; 22.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Floret grain number</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.6 &#x000b1; 26.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.6 &#x000b1; 18.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panicle weight per plant (g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2 &#x000b1; 9.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 &#x000b1; 4.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Main panicle weight (g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8 &#x000b1; 1.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0 &#x000b1; 3.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thousand seed weight (g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.309</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>Means and standard deviations were obtained from ten independent leaf samples grown under normal growth conditions. Means and standard deviations are obtained from 10 independent samples. Statistics treatment was made with Welch&#x02019;s two-sample <italic>t</italic> test. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup>Significantly different at <italic>P</italic> = 0.01. <sup>&#x02217;</sup>Significantly different at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Analysis of the Chlorophyll Content and Photosynthetic Rate</title><p>To further characterize the chlorotic phenotype of the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant, we measured the chlorophyll content of leaf, sheath, panicle, and stem at the heading stage (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref></bold>), and found them to have 71, 35, 28, and 28% the chlorophyll content of WT tissues, respectively. Both Chl <italic>a</italic> and Chl <italic>b</italic> levels were reduced in <italic>siygl2</italic>, with the reduction in Chl <italic>b</italic> being more severe in leaves.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Chlorophyll content of leaves, sheaths, panicles, and stems at the heading stage of wild-type cultivar Yugu1 and the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant. Black and gray boxes show the amount of chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> and chlorophyll <italic>b</italic>, respectively. FW, fresh weight; Chl <italic>a</italic>, chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>; Chl <italic>b</italic>, chlorophyll <italic>b</italic>. Means and standard deviations were obtained from five independent leaf samples grown under normal growth conditions. <bold>(B)</bold> Photosynthetic parameters in different developmental stages. Means and standard deviations were obtained from five independent leaf samples grown under normal growth conditions. Photo, photosynthetic rate; Cond, stomatal conductance; Ci, intercellular carbon dioxide concentration; Trmmol, transpiration rate. Means and standard deviations are obtained from five independent samples. <sup>&#x02217;</sup>Significantly different at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup>Significantly different at <italic>P</italic> = 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g002"/></fig><p>As reductions in chlorophyll may be associated with changes of the photosynthetic capacity, the photosynthetic parameters of the newly emerging leaves (from the top of the plant) were measured (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref></bold>). Surprisingly, <italic>siygl2</italic> photosynthetic capacity was not significantly affected at the seedling stage, the elongation stage, or the heading stage. The stomatal conductance of <italic>siygl2</italic> decreased about 22% in the elongation stage concurrent with a decrease in the intercellular carbon dioxide concentration of approximately 40%. Overall, the decrease in chlorophyll accumulation in <italic>siygl2</italic> did not significantly affect photosynthesis in the newly developed leaves. Variations in the intercellular carbon dioxide concentration and stomatal conductance may be caused by other effects of the mutant gene or environmental factors. Further study in investigating the ACi curve of both WT and mutants would help to reveal the effects of EGY1 in photosynthesis.</p></sec><sec><title>SiYGL2 May Be Involved in the Regulation of Leaf Senescence and PS II Efficiency</title><p>As the basal leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic> had a more obvious chlorotic phenotype than the top leaves and showed accelerated senescence (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B,F</xref></bold>), the chlorophyll pigment levels of the 1st, 4th, 7th, and 11th leaves from the top of <italic>siygl2</italic> and WT Yugu1 plants were examined (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref></bold>). Chlorophyll accumulation in the first leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic> declined by approximately 30% compared with Yugu1. However, in basal leaves, <italic>siygl2</italic> only contained one-third of the chlorophyll of the WT leaves at the same position. This suggests that chlorophyll levels decline earlier in the old leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic> than in Yugu1. We also noticed that in the first and fourth leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic>, the Chl <italic>b</italic> levels decreased while Chl <italic>a</italic> levels did not. In the 11th leaves, both Chl <italic>a</italic> and Chl <italic>b</italic> in <italic>siygl2</italic> are sharply decreased compared with Yugu1 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref></bold>). Anyhow, the accelerated leaf senescence of <italic>siygl2</italic> could be associated with changes in the function of SiYGL2.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Chlorophyll accumulation in different leaves at the heading stage (mg/g FW). Black and gray boxes represent Chl <italic>a</italic> and Chl <italic>b</italic>, respectively. <bold>(B)</bold> Chlorophyll accumulations after different durations of dark treatment. <bold>(C)</bold> Leaves of Yugu1 and <italic>siygl2</italic> after different durations of dark treatment. <bold>(D)</bold> Chlorophyll fluorescence in different leaves of Yugu1 and <italic>siygl2</italic>. The <italic>X</italic> axis shows the leaf position from the top of plants. For measuring the chlorophyll content and chlorophyll fluorescence, means and standard deviations are obtained from five independent plants for each genotype. <sup>&#x02217;</sup>Significantly different at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup>Significantly different at <italic>P</italic> = 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g003"/></fig><p>To verify the changes in leaf aging in <italic>siygl2</italic>, we first conducted a detached leaf senescence assay using dark treatments (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B,C</xref></bold>). After 3 days of dark treatment, first leaves of WT and <italic>siygl2</italic> were compared. The leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic> began turning yellow, while the leaves of the WT remained green (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref></bold>). After 6 d of dark treatment, <italic>siygl2</italic> leaves were completely yellow, whereas only the cut ends of the WT leaves showed yellowing (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref></bold>). The chlorophyll content also reflected the changes induced by dark treatment (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref></bold>). These results suggest that SiYGL2 helps to negatively regulate dark-induced leaf senescence, with senescence promoted by the loss of SiYGL2 function. In addition, we noticed that at the beginning of dark treatment, the effect on the reduction of Chl <italic>b</italic> levels are stronger than on the reduction of Chl <italic>a</italic> levels (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref></bold>). This is similar with the phenomenon showed in <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref></bold>.</p><p>The maximum photochemical efficiency (Fv/Fm) is a senescence-associated index. We measured the Fv/Fm values of the 1st, 3rd, 5th, 7th, 11th, 13th, and 15th leaves of WT and <italic>siygl2</italic> plants. The Fv/Fm values of the WT Yugu1 plants decreased gradually from the upper to the lower leaves. The Fv/Fm values of the mutant <italic>siygl2</italic> leaves displayed a similar decreasing tendency, with levels declining more sharply than in the WT in the 13th and 15th leaves (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref></bold>). This suggests that the basal leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic> enter senescence earlier than Yugu1. We further tested effective PSII quantum yield (&#x00394;&#x003a6;PS II) and photosynthetic electron transport rate (&#x00394;ETR) to describe the changes PS II light-use efficiency (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref></bold>). Both &#x00394;&#x003a6;PS II and &#x00394;ETR declined generally in leaves when moving from the top to the bottom of the plant, indicating that PS II photosynthesis capacity decreases with aging. In the whole-plant leaves, both &#x00394;&#x003a6;PS II and &#x00394;ETR of <italic>siygl2</italic> were lower than in Yugu1. From the 11th leaf, the ratio of both &#x00394;&#x003a6;PS II and &#x00394;ETR of Yugu1/<italic>siygl2</italic> significantly increased compared with that in the upper leaves, indicating that these two indices drop more acutely than in <italic>siygl2</italic> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref></bold>). These results verify that PS II photosynthesis capacity is decreased and senescence is premature in <italic>siygl2</italic>.</p><p>Leaf senescence is always accompanied by changes in chloroplast ultrastructure. We obtained entirely expanded young leaves and basal leaves of plants at the elongating stage (eight leaf-stage) and surveyed the mesophyll cell-chloroplasts of these leaves. TEM observations showed that in the young leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic>, the chloroplasts were similar to those of Yugu1 (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A,C</xref></bold>), indicating that thylakoid and chloroplast development were not impaired. However, in the basal leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic>, the chloroplasts were seriously disintegrated. The size of the plastoglobuli increased by 57.4% in <italic>siygl2</italic> (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref></bold>), and irregular grana thylakoid stacks were also be observed in the chloroplasts of the mutant (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref></bold>). In <italic>siygl2</italic> leaves at the same position as in Yugu1, chloroplasts retained their normal state (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref></bold>). This result indicates that chloroplast degradation of <italic>siygl2</italic> is advanced.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Transmission electron microscopic images of chloroplasts in the WT Yugu1 cultivar <bold>(A,B)</bold> and <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant <bold>(C,D)</bold>. <bold>(A,C)</bold> Chloroplasts in tender leaves. <bold>(B,D)</bold> Chloroplasts in tender aging leaves. SG, starch granules; PG, plastoglobuli; GT, grana thylakoid stacks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g004"/></fig><p>Taken together, the above results suggest that the <italic>SiYGL2</italic> gene may play a role in maintaining chlorophyll accumulation and chloroplast structure in aging leaves, and may delay the onset of leaf senescence. Suppression of SiYGL2 function could, therefore, lead to early senescence of basal leaves.</p></sec><sec><title>Map-Based Cloning of the <italic>SiYGL2</italic> Locus and Bioinformatic Analysis</title><p>For genetic analysis of the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant, we constructed an F<sub>2</sub> population by hybridizing <italic>siygl2</italic> with the Yugu1 cultivar. The F<sub>2</sub> progeny showed a segregation ratio of 3:1 (266:80, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 0.56 &#x0003c; &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>0.05</sub> = 3.84), suggesting that this chlorotic phenotype was controlled by a single recessive gene.</p><p>To map the <italic>siygl2</italic> locus, an F<sub>2</sub> mapping population was generated from a cross between <italic>siygl2</italic> and the cultivar SSR41. Using this F<sub>2</sub> population (883 yellow leaf plants), we generated a DNA pool of 40 individual mutant plants and preliminarily mapped the <italic>siygl2</italic> gene to a 948.3-kb genomic region on chromosome 9 by bulked segregation analysis. On this basis, a 31.3-kb genomic region between the SSR marker P44 and the CAPS marker zs912 was then defined. Within this region, eight open reading frames (ORFs) were predicted from the data on <italic>phytozome</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn04">4</xref></sup> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref></bold>). These ORFs were amplified and sequenced and only the fifth ORF (<italic>Seita.9G060500</italic>) was found to carry a 17-bp deletion (AATGTTTGACATATCAA) at the position 3,478,889&#x02013;3,478,905 of chromosome 9. The gene structure of <italic>Seita.9G060500</italic> is predicted to contain 11 exons and 10 introns. The identified deletion in this gene leads to a frameshift that results in a termination codon at the fifth exon (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref></bold>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Map-based cloning, gene structure of <italic>Seita.9G060500</italic>, and the mutant positions of <italic>siygl2</italic> and <italic>gh120.</italic>
<bold>(B&#x02013;D)</bold> are phenotypes of WT Yugu1 plants and mutants. <bold>(E)</bold> Chlorophyll content of <italic>siygl2, gh120</italic>, and F1 individuals. Means and standard deviations are obtained from five independent samples. Values connected by same letters are not statistically different; values not connected by same letters are statistically different at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g005"/></fig><p>We also identified another leaf chlorotic mutant, <italic>gh120</italic>, that shows the same phenotypes as <italic>siygl2</italic> (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">E</xref></bold>). Genome sequencing indicated that there is a single base change (G 3831 A) at the sixth exon of <italic>Seita.9G060500</italic> that leads to the alteration of Trp to a termination codon. The F<sub>1</sub> individuals of a cross between <italic>siygl2</italic> and <italic>gh120</italic> are hemizygous at both the mutation sites of their parents (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref></bold>) and display similar phenotypes to their parents (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B,D</xref></bold>). The chlorophyll content of F<sub>1</sub> plants is consistent with that of <italic>siygl2</italic> and <italic>gh120</italic> mutant (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref></bold>). These results suggest that the mutations in <italic>Seita.9G060500</italic> indeed cause the abnormal phenotype in the <italic>siygl2</italic> and <italic>gh120</italic>.</p><p>Amino acid sequence comparison indicated that SiYGL2 is most closely related to AtEGY1, with these proteins sharing 77.3% amino acid sequence identity. SiYGL2 was, therefore, proposed to be a homolog of AtEGY1, a S2P-like chloroplast membrane-located MP. Phylogenetic analysis further confirmed this relationship (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref></bold>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, there are three EGY proteins: AtEGY1, AtEGY2, and AtEGY3 (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005</xref>). Similarly, two homologs of SiYGL2, Seita.5G097600 (SiEGY2) and Seita.9G108100 (SiEGY3), were identified in <italic>S. italica</italic> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref></bold>).</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of EGY proteins in diverse species. Ath, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>; Cre, <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic>; Gm, <italic>Glycine max</italic>; Os, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>; Pt, <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic>; Sb, <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>; Si, <italic>S. italica</italic>; Vv, <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>; Zm, Zea mays. Protein IDs are listed in brackets and are archived in the UNIPROT database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/">http://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>). SiEGY2, Seita.5G097600. SiEGY3, Seita.9G108100.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g006"/></fig><p>SiYGL2 is predicted to encode a 548-aa protein, with a peptide chain that contains three conversed motifs, GNLR (aa 169&#x02013;178), HEXXH (aa 311&#x02013;315), and NPDG (aa 442&#x02013;454) (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref></bold>), that reportedly also occur in AtEGY1 (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005</xref>). However, the mutant SiYGL2 protein (&#x00394;SiYGL2) was predicted to lack 165 amino acid residues from the carboxyl terminus. Furthermore, frameshift mutation caused changes in the sequence from 362&#x02013;383 aa, leading to the loss of NPDG motif. This suggests that the protein structure and function of &#x00394;SiYGL2 is likely to differ significantly from that of SiYGL2.</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>FIGURE 7</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Amino acid sequence alignment of the homologous proteins. Red stars show the position of the conserved motifs GNLR, HEXXH, and NPDG, respectively. The red lines show lost amino acid sequence of &#x00394;SiYGL2. <bold>(B)</bold> Hydropathy plot of SiYGL2 and &#x00394;SiYGL2. Red boxes show the transmembrane helices. Blue lines and pink lines at the top of the figure indicate the inside and outside peptide chains, respectively. The arrow indicates the mutated position of <italic>siygl2.</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g007"/></fig><p>Hydropathy analysis revealed that the AtEGY1 protein is highly hydrophobic as it contains six predicted transmembrane (tm) helices in its C-terminus (tm1, aa 340&#x02013;362; tm2, aa 369&#x02013;387; tm3, aa 402&#x02013;424; tm4, aa 462&#x02013;484; tm5, aa 516&#x02013;538; tm6, aa 559&#x02013;576). Conversely, &#x00394;SiYGL2 lost four of these tm helices (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>Expression Analysis of <italic>SiYGL2</italic></title><p>As the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant showed chlorotic leaves, stems, and panicles, with this phenotype more apparent in older leaves, the expression pattern of <italic>SiYGL2</italic> was investigated in different organs and leaves at different developmental stages by qRT-PCR (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref></bold>). <italic>SiYGL2</italic> was more highly expressed in panicles and young leaves (1st leaves) than in stems and old leaves (10th leaves), suggesting that SiYGL2 is typically more active in young organs. However, <italic>SiYGL2</italic> expression in <italic>siygl2</italic> organs differed significantly; in panicle, stem, and the 10th leaf in <italic>siygl2, SiYGL2</italic> expression decreased to 27.7, 43.5, and 20.0% of those in WT, respectively. In the 10th leaf, in particular, transcript accumulation was very low. However, the expression <italic>SiYGL2</italic> in the first leaf of <italic>siygl2</italic> was higher (1.25-fold) than in the WT. These results suggest that the expression of <italic>SiYGL2</italic> in <italic>siygl2</italic> is not dependent on the function of the SiYGL2 protein.</p><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>FIGURE 8</label><caption><p>Transcript accumulation of <italic>SiYGL2</italic> in panicle, stem, and leaves. Black boxes, Yugu1; gray boxes, <italic>siygl2</italic>. Means and standard deviations are obtained from three independent samples and three independent assays. Statistics treatment was made with Welch&#x02019;s two-sample <italic>t</italic> test. <sup>&#x02217;</sup>Significantly different at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g008"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Subcellular Location Analysis of SiYGL2 Protein</title><p>To explore the subcellular location of SiYGL2, we generated a <italic>SiYGL2-GFP</italic> fusion gene. The fusion gene was placed under the control of the CaMV 35S promoter and introduced into protoplasts of Yugu1. The results obtained from confocal laser microscopy show that SiYGL2 is localized to the chloroplast (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref></bold>). This result is similar to that of AtEGY1 (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005</xref>). In the GFP transgenic control line, GFP fluorescence was found in the cytomembrane, the plasma, and the nucleus (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9B</xref></bold>).</p><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>FIGURE 9</label><caption><p>Subcellular localization of SiYGL2. <bold>(A)</bold> SiYGL2:GFP signal. <bold>(B)</bold> Empty GFP vector as a control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g009"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Complicated Regulation of Senescence-Related Genes in the <italic>siygl2</italic> Mutant</title><p>To further verify the influence of the <italic>SiYGL2</italic> mutation on leaf senescence, several senescence-related genes examined using qRT-PCR (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref></bold>). <italic>AtSAG12</italic>, encoding a putative cysteine protease, is a negative regulator of senescence. In <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, expression of <italic>AtSAG12</italic> is strictly associated with senescence progression, with expression levels increasing throughout leaf aging before decreasing at the end of the aging process (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Weaver et al., 1998</xref>). We used <italic>SiSAG12</italic>, a homolog of <italic>AtSAG12</italic> as a reporter to follow the progression of leaf senescence. In old 10th leaves of Yugu1, the expression level of <italic>SiSAG12</italic> was upregulated dramatically (approximately sevenfold), consistent with the reported expression of AtSAG12. While <italic>SiSAG12</italic> expression levels in both young and old leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic> were lower than those in the corresponding leaves of Yugu1. <italic>SiSAG12</italic> expression did increase by approximately threefold in 10th leaf than that in young leaf of <italic>siygl2</italic> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref></bold>). These results suggest that the expression of senescence-associated genes in <italic>siygl2</italic> is impaired, reflecting the variations in aging processes between <italic>siygl2</italic> and WT.</p><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>FIGURE 10</label><caption><p>Relative expression levels of chlorophyll degradation- and leaf senescence-associated genes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01308-g010"/></fig><p>SGR1 and NYC1 are reportedly involved in chlorophyll degradation and disassembly of the light-harvesting complex of PS II (LHC II) during leaf senescence (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Kusaba et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Sakuraba et al., 2012</xref>). In the young leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic>, the expression of these two genes was higher than in the young WT leaves. Furthermore, the transcript accumulation of these two genes in mutant old leaves also differed significantly from their expression in WT. These results indicate that chlorophyll metabolism and LHC II stability during the aging process may be affected in the mutant. Two other senescence-associated genes, RCCR and PAO, also reportedly participate in chlorophyll degradation (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Sakuraba et al., 2016</xref>). These two genes were upregulated in old WT leaves. In <italic>siygl2</italic>, however, the expression of these two genes differed significantly from the WT in both the 1st and 10th leaves. This suggests that chlorophyll degradation in <italic>siygl2</italic> is affected.</p><p>In summary, we conclude that changes in SiYGL2 function affects the regulation of several senescence-associated genes, with chlorophyll degradation and leaf senescence also affected.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>SiYGL2 Is Associated With the Regulation of Leaf Senescence, Chlorophyll Metabolism, and PS II Efficiency</title><p>Our study has shown that <italic>SiYGL2</italic> gene expression levels are higher in panicles and first leaves than in stems and old leaves (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref></bold>). The flag leaf and panicle are the most important source and sink organs, respectively, and should retain high chlorophyll levels and photosynthetic capacities to avoid premature aging and ensure their continued output. The high expression of <italic>SiYGL2</italic> in these organs suggests that <italic>SiYGL2</italic> may play a role in maintaining the physiological state of the leaf and its photosynthetic capacity. Mutation of <italic>SiYGL2</italic> results in premature chlorophyll degradation, chloroplast disintegration, and leaf senescence in the basal leaves (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>). Furthermore, aging of the leaves of the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant can be induced more easily by dark than in the WT (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B,C</xref></bold>). Taken together, these results suggest that SiYGL2 may be involved in delaying the onset of leaf senescence. This is consistent with the results reported for the SiYGL2 homolog AtEGY1 in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>The chlorophyll content of <italic>siygl2</italic> was lower than in WT in both the top and basal leaves (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref></bold>), indicating that SiYGL2 may be related to chlorophyll metabolism. The chlorophyll degradation-associated genes SiNYC1, SiSGR1, and SiRCCR were expressed more highly in young leaves of <italic>siygl2</italic> than in Yugu1 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref></bold>), suggesting that chlorophyll degradation is mobilized early in young <italic>siygl2</italic> leaves. We also find that the effects on Chl <italic>b</italic> caused by <italic>SiYGL2</italic> mutant, natural senescence, and dark treatment are stronger than that on Chl <italic>a</italic> (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A,B</xref></bold>). First, this may be explained by that the degradation of Chl <italic>b</italic> is prior to Chl <italic>a.</italic> And Chl <italic>b</italic> can converted into Chl <italic>a</italic> when undergoing degradation (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Schelbert et al., 2009</xref>). Thus, at the preliminary stage of senescence, Chl <italic>b</italic> is sharply decreased while Chl <italic>a</italic> seems to be not impaired. With the aging process, Chl <italic>a</italic> is also degraded. Therefore, both the Chl <italic>a</italic> and Chl <italic>b</italic> contents are reduced in later period of senescence. Second, the reduction in Chl <italic>b</italic> content but not Chl <italic>a</italic> suggesting that the light harvesting is altered. The mutant may not grow well under low light condition, but would be fine under moderately high light. Shading and light deficiency may be one of the reasons the bottom leaf had earlier senescence. This hypothesis could be tested with a light response curve in further study.</p><p>In all leaves at different ages, both &#x00394;&#x003a6;PS II and &#x00394;ETR were lower in <italic>siygl2</italic> than in WT (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref></bold>), indicating that the PS II function was impaired in <italic>siygl2</italic>. Thus, we propose that SiYGL2 plays a role in the regulation of PS II function. In conclusion, in monocotyledonous <italic>S. italica</italic>, SiYGL2 is associated with the regulation of leaf senescence, chlorophyll metabolism, and PS II efficiency. As described in previous studies, AtEGY1 participates in chlorophyll accumulation, leaf senescence, and PS II function (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). This indicates that the function of SiYGL2 in monocotyledonous <italic>S. italica</italic> is quite similar to that its homolog AtEGY1 in dicotyledonous <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>The HEXXH Motif May Be Essential for the Function of SiYGL2 in Chloroplast Development</title><p>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutant <italic>egy1-1</italic> displayed a defective chloroplast development phenotype (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005</xref>). However, the <italic>S. italica EGY1</italic> mutant <italic>siygl2</italic> has relatively normal chloroplasts (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref></bold>). Further analysis of the function of SiYGL2 in chloroplast development is therefore required. We compared the peptide chains of these two mutants and found that the mutant AtEGY1 protein lacks the HEXXH and NPDG motifs, while the mutant SiYGL2 protein lacks only the NPDG motif. Thus, we propose two hypotheses for the differences in chloroplast development between the <italic>egy1-1</italic> and <italic>siygl2</italic> mutants. First, it has been reported that for S2P family members in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, HEXXH and NPDG together form the catalytic center required for protease function (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Rudner et al., 1999</xref>). Furthermore, two other MPs, AtVAR2 and AtVIR3, which have the HEXXH motif but lack the NPDG motif, could regulate chloroplast development (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Qi et al., 2016</xref>). We, therefore, speculate that HEXXH is essential for chloroplast development-related function of EGY1 and alone can guarantee normal chloroplast development, but requires NPDG to regulate leaf senescence. Second, SiYGL2 and AtEGY1 share 77.3% amino acid sequence similarity, so the differences between remaining amino acids may lead to differences in function. Homologous proteins commonly show different functions in different species; EGY1 may potentially have changed its chloroplast development-related function in dicotyledonous C<sub>3</sub>
<italic>Arabidopsis</italic> relative to the monocotyledonous C<sub>4</sub> plant <italic>S. italica</italic> during evolution. These two hypotheses could be verified in future by removing the HEXXH motif of SiYGL2 and observing the chloroplast structure of the resulting plants.</p></sec><sec><title>Chlorophyll Content and PS II Efficiency May Be Not the Limiting Factors of Photosynthesis Capacity</title><p>Chlorophylls functions as the antenna pigment in the photosynthesis and as such is an essential component to PS II function (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Stirbet et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Kato et al., 2016</xref>). However, while chlorophyll content, &#x00394;&#x003a6;PS II, and &#x00394;ETR were lower in <italic>siygl2</italic> than in WT (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10B,C</xref></bold>), net photosynthetic rate of <italic>siygl2</italic> remained the same as in the WT (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref></bold>). Similar results have been reported in the <italic>S. italica ygl1</italic> mutant and rice <italic>ygl7</italic> mutant, which are two mutants of D submit of Mg-chelatase encoding gene, that show decreased chlorophyll levels and defective chloroplasts and, yet display increased photosynthetic rates and photosynthetic reaction center activity (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Deng et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2016</xref>). A previous report has stated that plants contain an abundance of light-harvesting pigments and absorb more light than they can use (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Ort et al., 2015</xref>). Following this, we speculate that in the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant leaves, even though chlorophyll accumulation is reduced, photosynthesis can still be maintained at the same level as in the WT because sufficient light is still harvested by the chlorophyll present. The fact that a reduction in PS II efficiency does not impair the photosynthetic rate of the mutant may suggest that the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant may have improvements in other photosynthesis-related components that compensate for the decrease in PS II efficiency. In addition, the induction of alternative electron transport (water&#x02013;water cycle, etc.) may be also a reason leading to the alteration in &#x00394;ETR but not photosynthetic rate. These should be confirmed by further experiments.</p></sec><sec><title>Accelerated Leaf Senescence and Panicle Chlorosis May Be Associated With Yield Decreases in <italic>siygl2</italic> Mutants</title><p>Despite the conserved photosynthetic rate, the yield of <italic>siygl2</italic> was significantly reduced when compared with WT plants. We propose two explanations for this phenomenon. On the one hand, yield is closely related to leaf senescence, so accelerated leaf senescence could influence the mobilization of nutrients to reproductive organs and reduce the grain yield. Alternatively, the panicle has photosynthetic carbon assimilation capabilities and plays an important role in grain formation. Glumes can ensure remobilization of nutrients to grains as a vital part of crop source&#x02013;sink translocation. Compared with the flag leaf, glumes are more crucial in the later period of grain filling (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kong et al., 2015</xref>). In our study, the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant panicle contained only 28% of the chlorophyll contained in the WT panicle at the heading stage (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). This suggests that the low chlorophyll content and impaired photosynthetic capability of the glume may be associated with the reduced yield in the <italic>siygl2</italic> mutant.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>XD conceived the project. SZ, WL, JS, and CT carried out the experimental work. HZ provided the materials and did the field trials. SZ did the data analysis and wrote the manuscript. XD, GJ, and ST guided the experimental work. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The reviewer RZ and handling editor declared their shared affiliation at the time of the review.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by Fundamental Research Funds of CAAS (CAAS-XTCX2016002), China Agricultural Research System (CARS06-13.5-A04), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31501324 and 31522040), and the Agricultural Science and Technology Innovation Program of the Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank Emma Tacken, Ph.D., from Liwen Bianji, Edanz Group China (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.liwenbianji.cn/ac">www.liwenbianji.cn/ac</ext-link>), for editing the English text of a draft of this manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/">https://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn02"><label>2</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn03"><label>3</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn04"><label>4</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz/portal.html">http://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz/portal.html</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01308/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01308/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><label>FIGURE S1</label><caption><p>The plastoglobulis areas of the young leaves and old leaves in Yugu1 and <italic>siygl2</italic>. Means and standard deviations are obtained from 10 plastoglobulis. Statistics treatment was made with Welch&#x02019;s two-sample <italic>t</italic> test. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup>Significantly different at <italic>P</italic> = 0.01.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image_1.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><label>FIGURE S2</label><caption><p>Sequences at the mutation sites of Yugu1, <italic>siygl2, gh120</italic>, and F<sub>1</sub> individuals. The red boxes and arrow show the mutant sites.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image_2.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><label>TABLE S1</label><caption><p>CAPS markers for fine mapping.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table_1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><label>TABLE S2</label><caption><p>Sequencing primers for the candidate region.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table_1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5"><label>TABLE S3</label><caption><p>Primers used for qRT-PCR analysis.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table_1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;lter</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nada</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulgosi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soll</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A chloroplastic inner envelope membrane protease is essential for plant development.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEBS Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>580</volume>
<fpage>789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>794</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2005.12.098</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16413549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16413549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Che</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bussell</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estavillo</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pogson</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Signaling from the endoplasmic reticulum activates brassinosteroid signaling and promotes acclimation to stress in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Signal.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>:<issue>ra69</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.2001140</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20876872?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20876872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Leaf senescence induced by EGY1 defection was partially restored by glucose in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bot. Stud.</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>:<issue>5</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40529-016-0120-3</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28510790?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28510790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Y. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>EGY1 encodes a membrane-associated and ATP-independent metalloprotease that is required for chloroplast development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>375</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02308.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15659096?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodermal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The yellow variegated mutant of Arabidopsis is plastid autonomous and delayed in chloroplast biogenesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Heredity</italic></source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>214</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/90.1.207</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9987930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9987930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Mapped clone and functional analysis of leaf-color gene Ygl7 in a rice hybrid (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. ssp. indica).</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>:<issue>e99564</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.00</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24932524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24932524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diaz-Mendoza</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco-Arroyo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santamaria</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Melendi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Plant senescence and proteolysis: two processes with one destiny.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genet. Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>338</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1678-4685-GMB-2016-0015</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27505308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27505308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doust</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellogg</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devos</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennetzen</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Foxtail millet: a sequence-driven grass model system.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>149</volume>
<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>141</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.129627</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19126705?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19126705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egli</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Time and the productivity of agronomic crops and cropping systems.</article-title>
<source><italic>Agron. J.</italic></source>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>743</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>750</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj2010.0508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffrey</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Structure of a site-2 protease family intramembrane metalloprotease.</article-title>
<source><italic>Science</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>1608</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1612</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1150755</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18063795?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18063795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golldack</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Popova</surname><given-names>O. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Mutation of the matrix metalloproteinase At2-MMP inhibits growth and causes late flowering and early senescence in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>277</volume>
<fpage>5541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5547</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M106197200</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11726650?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11726650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregersen</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Culetic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boschian</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupinska</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Plant senescence and crop productivity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>622</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-013-0013-8</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23354836?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23354836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregersen</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupinska</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Leaf senescence and nutrient remobilization in barley and wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Biol</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1438-8677.2008.00114.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18721310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18721310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>EGY1 plays a role in regulation of endodermal plastid size and number that are involved in ethylene-dependent gravitropism of light-grown Arabidopsis hypocotyls.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>360</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-007-9273-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18097640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18097640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Coupling of gel-based 2-DE and 1-DE shotgun proteomics approaches to dig deep into the leaf senescence proteome of Glycine max.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Proteom.</italic></source>
<volume>148</volume>
<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2016.07.025</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27474340?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27474340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>L. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>W. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Photosynthesis, chlorophyll fluorescence, and chlorophyll content of soybean seedlings unde combined stress of bisphenol a and cadmium.</article-title>
<source><italic>Environ. Toxicol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>2455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2462</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/etc.2720</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25113627?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25113627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>G. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A haplotype map of genomic variations and genome-wide association studies of agronomic traits in foxtail millet (<italic>Setaria italica</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>U167</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2673</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23793027?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23793027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Development and genetic mapping of SSR markers in foxtail millet [<italic>Setaria italica</italic> (L.) P. Beauv.].</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>829</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-008-0942-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19139840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19139840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagao</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Redox potential of the terminal quinone electron acceptor QB in photosystem II reveals the mechanism of electron transfer regulation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>113</volume>
<fpage>620</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>625</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1520211113</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26715751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26715751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinch</surname><given-names>L. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginalski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grishin</surname><given-names>N. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Site-2 protease regulated intramembrane proteolysis: sequence homologs suggest an ancient signaling cascade.</article-title>
<source><italic>Protein Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1110/ps.051766506</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16322567?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16322567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Photochemical and antioxidative responses of the glume and flag leaf to seasonal senescence in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>358</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00358</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26052333?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26052333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koussis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulielmaki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaliri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Withers-Martinez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siden-Kiamos</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matuschewski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Targeted deletion of a plasmodium site-2 Protease impairs life cycle progression in the mammalian host.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>:<issue>e0170260</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0170260</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28107409?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28107409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kusaba</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Rice non-yellow coloring1 is involved in light-harvesting complex II and grana degradation during leaf senescence.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1362</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1375</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.042911</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17416733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronzucker</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Arabidopsis plastid AMOS1/EGY1 integrates abscisic acid signaling to regulate global gene expression response to ammonium stress.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>160</volume>
<fpage>2040</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2051</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.206508</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23064408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23064408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Gene mapping and functional analysis of the novel leaf color gene siygl1 in foxtail millet [<italic>Setaria italica</italic> (L.) P. Beauv].</article-title>
<source><italic>Physiol. Plant.</italic></source>
<volume>157</volume>
<fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppl.12405</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26559175?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26559175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenthaler</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Chlorophylls and carotenoids: pigments of photosynthetic biomembranes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Methods Enzymol.</italic></source>
<volume>148</volume>
<fpage>350</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>382</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0076-6879(87)48036-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casaretto</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Y. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Overexpression of OsGATA12 regulates chlorophyll content, delays plant senescence and improves rice yield under high density planting.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-017-0604-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28342018?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28342018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mafra</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinecky</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Basso</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Selection of reliable reference genes for RT-qPCR analysis during developmental stages and abiotic stress in Setaria viridis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>28348</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep28348</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27321675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27321675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sureka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Novel role of Wag31 in protection of mycobacteria under oxidative stress.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>119</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06750.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19496931?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19496931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Chloroplast Proteases: updates on proteolysis within and across suborganellar compartments.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>171</volume>
<fpage>2280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2293</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.16.00330</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27288365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27288365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ort</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alric</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barkan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blankenship</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Redesigning photosynthesis to sustainably meet global food and bioenergy demand.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>112</volume>
<fpage>8529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8536</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1424031112</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26124102?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26124102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Y. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A putative chloroplast thylakoid metalloprotease VIRESCENT3 regulates chloroplast development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>291</volume>
<fpage>3319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3332</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M115.681601</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26702056?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26702056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>I. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Criado</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Senescence-associated proteases in plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Physiol. Plant.</italic></source>
<volume>145</volume>
<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>139</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.2012.01574.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22242903?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22242903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Losick</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A family of membrane-embedded metalloproteases involved in regulated proteolysis of membrane-associated transcription factors.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>14765</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14770</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.26.14765</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10611287?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10611287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hizukuri</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Post-liberation cleavage of signal peptides is catalyzed by the site-2 protease (S2P) in bacteria.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>13740</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13745</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1108376108</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21810987?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takami</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Nucleases in higher plants and their possible involvement in DNA degradation during leaf senescence.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>3835</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3843</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eru091</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24634485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24634485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakuraba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;rtensteiner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>N.-C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> NAC016 promotes chlorophyll breakdown by directly upregulating <italic>STAYGREEN1</italic> transcription.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>166</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-015-1876-8</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26441053?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26441053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakuraba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schelbert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>STAY-GREEN and chlorophyll catabolic enzymes interact at light-harvesting complex II for chlorophyll detoxification during leaf senescence in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>785</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.089474</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22366162?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22366162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schelbert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubry</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burla</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agne</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupinska</surname><given-names>N.-C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Pheophytin pheophorbide hydrolase (Pheophytinase) is involved in chlorophyll breakdown during leaf senescence in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>518</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.108.064089</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19304936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19304936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stirbet</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riznienko</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goindjee</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Modeling chlorophyll a fluorescence transient: relation to photosynthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biochem. Moscow</italic></source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>323</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1134/S0006297914040014</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24910205?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24910205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Hoorn</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Plant proteases: from phenotypes to molecular mechanisms.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>59</volume>
<fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>223</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.59.032607.092835</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18257708?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18257708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waditee-Sirisattha</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibato</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakwal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirisattha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The Arabidopsis aminopeptidase LAP2 regulates plant growth, leaf longevity and stress response.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>191</volume>
<fpage>958</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>969</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2011.03758.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21569035?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21569035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirino</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>A comparison of the expression patterns of several senescence-associated genes in response to stress and hormone treatment.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>469</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1005934428906</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9617813?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9617813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Transcriptome profiling of developmental leaf senescence in sorghum (Sorghum bicolor).</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol</italic></source>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-016-0532-1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27586543?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27586543</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Turnover of fatty acids during natural senescence of Arabidopsis, Brachypodium, and switchgrass and in Arabidopsis beta-oxidation mutants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>150</volume>
<fpage>1981</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1989</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.140491</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19561121?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19561121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshioka-Nishimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanba</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohba</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsumura</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Quality control of photosystem II: direct imaging of the changes in the thylakoid structure and distribution of FtsH proteases in spinach chloroplasts under light stress.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>1255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1265</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcu079</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24891560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24891560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronzucker</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The chloroplast protease AMOS1/EGY1 affects phosphate homeostasis under phosphate stress.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>172</volume>
<fpage>1200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1208</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.16.00786</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27516532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27516532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroos</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Evidence that SpoIVFB is a novel type of membrane metalloprotease governing intercompartmental communication during Bacillus subtilis sporulation.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Bacteriol.</italic></source>
<volume>182</volume>
<fpage>3305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3309</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.182.11.3305-3309.2000</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10809718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10809718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qie</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Development of highly polymorphic simple sequence repeat markers using genome-wide microsatellite variant analysis in foxtail millet [<italic>Setaria italica</italic> (L.) P. Beauv.].</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Genomics</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>:<issue>78</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-78</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24472631?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24472631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>