<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art550.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.5.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_HLY889 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEsi1 gif ?><?FILEsi2 gif ?><?FILEsi3 gif ?><?FILEsi4 gif ?><?FILEsi5 gif ?><?FILEsi6 gif ?><?FILEsi7 gif ?><?FILEsi8 gif ?><?FILEsi9 gif ?><?FILEsi10 gif ?><?FILEsi11 gif ?><?FILEsi12 gif ?><?FILEsi13 gif ?><?FILEsi14 gif ?><?FILEsi15 gif ?><?FILEsi16 gif ?><?FILEsi17 gif ?><?FILEsi18 gif ?><?FILEsi19 gif ?><?FILEsi20 gif ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6226563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(18)31292-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2018.e00889</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e00889</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Determinants of access and utilisation of seasonal climate information services among smallholder farmers in Makueni County, Kenya</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muema</surname><given-names>Emily</given-names></name><email>emilymuema89@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mburu</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coulibaly</surname><given-names>Jeanne</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mutune</surname><given-names>Jane</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Agricultural Economics, University of Nairobi, P.O. Box 29053-00625, Nairobi, Kenya</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>World Agroforestry Centre, Nairobi, Kenya</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Wangari Maathai Institute for Peace and Environmental Studies, University of Nairobi, Kenya</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>emilymuema89@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e00889</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Climate change is a major development challenge in sub-Saharan Africa. This region is highly vulnerable to negative impacts of climate change due to low adaptive capacity and overreliance on rain-fed agriculture for food security and livelihood. Climate information services (CIS) have been developed in Kenya to help enhance farmers' adaptation to climatic shocks, but their access and utilisation remain low. The factors that influence farmers' access and use of CIS are not well-known. Using survey data from a sample of 250 households in Makueni County, this study estimated a two-step Heckprobit model to analyse the determinants of access and use of CIS. Results showed that the age of the household head reduced the likelihood of accessing CIS whereas household size, income, farm size, livelihood activity, television ownership and group membership increased it. Age, sex of the household head, and frequent exposure to drought reduced the likelihood of using CIS whereas access to improved seed, household income, radio ownership, and livelihood activity increased it. Efforts promoting access to and utilisation of CIS would benefit by building trust among farmers through provision of accurate information; promoting adoption of improved varieties of crops; and providing incentives for formation and participation in farmers' groups.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Agriculture</kwd><kwd>Economics</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Climate variability poses tremendous challenges on sustainable agricultural production and livelihoods in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA). According to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), annual temperatures in Africa have increased steadily by 0.5 degrees Celsius with the drier subtropical regions warming more compared to moist tropics (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Eriksen and Rosentrater, 2008</xref>). This has resulted in decreased precipitation levels and increased evapotranspiration which amplify water scarcity and unprecedented threats to the region's rain-fed agriculture.</p><p id="p0015">Persistent climate-related shocks constrain socio-economic development in SSA's agro-based economies. The IPCC has predicted a 50 percent decline in rain-fed agriculture yields of major staples by 2020 and 90 percent drop in net crop revenues by 2100 in SSA (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">IPCC, 2007</xref>). Moreover, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Schlenker and Lobell (2010)</xref> predicted 8 to 22 percent decline in maize, sorghum, millet, groundnut and cassava production by 2050 attributed to climate change.</p><p id="p0020">Similar to majority of SSA countries, agriculture is the main contributor of Kenya's GDP and source of raw materials for local industries. Major climate shocks experienced in Kenya include floods, drought, variable precipitation levels and increased prevalence of pests and diseases. Among these climate shocks, drought is the most common with 28 major droughts recorded in the country in the past 100 years (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Gichangi et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">World Bank, 2016</xref>). To reduce the country's vulnerability to climate risks the government launched the National Climate Change Response Strategy (NCCRS) in 2010 and Kenya National Climate Change Action plan (NCCAP 2013-2017) in 2013 in efforts to identify and promote interventions geared towards enhancing resilience and adaptation to climate change.</p><p id="p0025">Adaptation is a response strategy which entails adjustments to enhance preparedness and response to current and future climate change adversities. Several adaptation options exist based on diversified agricultural practices which are determined by environmental, economic, institutional, cultural and demographic factors. Lack of relevant climate information is one of the major barriers to effective climate change adaptation. According to <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Jones et&#x000a0;al. (2000)</xref>, access to timely and accurate climate information services (CIS) of approximately three to six months before time is an adaptation initiative prerequisite for agricultural production and risk mitigation.</p><p id="p0030">Climate information services entail the provision of climate forecasts accompanied by agronomic advice meaningful for offsetting uncertainties that constrain farm decision making against climate risks (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">World Bank, 2016</xref>). Previous studies have emphasised that to realise the full potential of climate forecast in agriculture, climate information should be accompanied by strategically formulated response strategies for climate risks adaptation (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">O'Brien et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Klopper et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>). This information influence decisions such as; farmland preparation, planting dates, crop variety, when to harvest and market for output.</p><p id="p0035">Climate information services in Kenya are mainly provided by government agencies, international organisations, research and academia, community-based organisations and non-governmental organisations (CBOs and NGOs). The Kenya Meteorological Department (KMD) is the national meteorological agency mandated to collect and store national climate data and manage the climate information provision framework. The CIS are provided through newspapers, bulletins, radio, television, trained personnel/intermediaries, short media messages (SMS) and internet.</p><p id="p0040">Seasonal forecast is a major form of climate information which entails probabilistic estimations of precipitation and temperature indicators in the forthcoming seasons on two to three months' time scales (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Ziervogel and Calder, 2003</xref>). This forecast is important to smallholder farmers because seasonality shapes fluctuations in their vulnerability and resilience to impacts of climate change in Africa and the rest of the world (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Roncoli, 2006</xref>).</p><p id="p0045">However, the potential benefits of CIS can only be realized if they are accessible, accurate, and relevant for decision making of farmers, and if there exists institutional support to provision and actual use (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Hansen, 2002</xref>). Although the provision of CIS by the KMD alongside other CIS providers has been promising, their access and application to manage climate risks are limited (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">World Bank, 2016</xref>). Both access and use of climate information services are fraught with technical, social, economic and psychological challenges which compromise their benefits in climate change adaptation (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Serra and Mckune, 2016</xref>). Understanding the factors that inhibit access and use of CIS is imperative to enhance their application in farm decisions (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">O'Brien et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">McOmber et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0050">A few studies have assessed the state of access and use of climate information in Africa using different methods. For instance, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Mudombi and Nhamo (2014)</xref> used descriptives to analyse access to weather forecast in Zimbabwe, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Oyekale (2015)</xref> used two separate probit models to analyse factors explaining access and utilisation of extreme climate forecast in SSA and <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Coulibaly et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> used descriptive analysis to analyse the access and use of CIS in Rwanda. However, the findings of these previous studies are country specific and given the heterogeneity of the countries, the parameter estimates are of little importance in addressing the various constraints to access and utilisation of CIS in Kenya. Furthermore, the decision about whether or not to use CIS depends first on farmers' access to such services. Estimating two separate probit models when access to and use of CIS are sequentially related would bias the parameter estimates and generate misleading conclusions. Therefore, this study aimed at bridging these gaps by analysing the determinants of both access and use of climate information services among smallholder farmers in Makueni County, Kenya using a two-step selection procedure.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="p0055">This research used a qualitative and quantitative approach. Surveys were undertaken among farmers but before the actual survey, a pre-test of the household questionnaire was done. The overall research was undertaken in two weeks including a reconnaissance study.</p><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Study area</title><p id="p0060">Arid and semi-arid areas in Kenya occupy 83 percent of the total land and receive an annual rainfall of 200&#x02013;700 mm (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Macharia et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Mutua et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). These areas are most vulnerable to negative impacts of climate change due to extreme droughts and heavy reliance on rain-fed agriculture for livelihood. This study was conducted in Makueni County which is one of the arid and semi-arid lands of Kenya characterised by high water scarcity, declining food production and low resilience to climate variability. The county occupies 8,034.7 km<sup>2</sup> on the South Eastern part of Kenya bordering Kajiado, Kitui, Taita Taveta and Machakos counties with a population of 922,183 people (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Republic of Kenya, 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0065">Smallholder farmers dominate mixed farming in the county growing food crops (maize, beans, cowpeas, pigeon peas, sorghum, millet and green grams), fruit trees (citrus, mangoes) and livestock rearing (chicken, goats, donkey and cows). Rain-fed agriculture which is the main livelihood activity is highly responsive to drought and erratic rainfall which are the major climate shocks experienced in the county (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Kitinya et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Sampling and data collection</title><p id="p0070">The study used primary data which collected using farmer interviews and pre-tested structured questionnaires administered on household heads in charge of farm decisions. Multistage sampling was used to arrive at the sampling unit used for the survey. In the first stage, Makueni Sub County was purposively selected due to frequent exposure to drought and erratic rainfall. In the second stage, two wards (Muvau and Wote) were selected from the total of six wards with the help of county agricultural officer. Muvau ward had a total of six sub locations and Wote three sub-locations. In the third stage, two sub-locations were randomly selected from Wote ward and three from Muvau ward. In the fourth stage, a list of all the villages from the respective sub location was made and 5 villages randomly selected from each sub location. As a final step, systematic random sampling was employed to select ten households from each village to arrive at the desired sample of 250. The analysis was, however, based on 243 households from whom data were complete. Data were entered, cleaned and analysed using STATA version 14.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Econometric estimation</title><p id="p0075">The dependent variables of both access and use of seasonal CIS were dichotomous. Single equation probit models are often estimated when the dependent variable is binary. In the current case, however, the decision to use seasonal CIS was endogenously determined since farmers had to access CIS first so as to utilise them for farm decision making. In such cases, a Heckprobit model with sample selection is preferred in order to correct for selectivity bias since farmers with and without access to seasonal CIS may have different likelihoods of utilisig CIS (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Heckman, 1979</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Van De Ven and Van Praag, 1981</xref>). Various studies such as <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Deressa et&#x000a0;al. (2008)</xref>, <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Van den Broeck et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</xref> and <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Asrat and Simane (2018)</xref> also used Heckprobit in analysing climate change adaptation strategies.</p><p id="p0080">The Heckprobit model was implemented in a two-step procedure. In the first step, the selection equation analysed the determinants of access to seasonal CIS whereas in the second step the outcome equation analysed the determinants of use. To control for selectivity bias Inverse Mills Ratio (IMR) from the first step (selection equation) were included in the second step (outcome equation) (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Van De Ven and Van Praag, 1981</xref>). The Heckprobit models with sample selection assume the error terms of the selection equation and outcome equation are correlated. Formally, the model can be described as follows:<disp-formula id="ufd1"><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ASCIS</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>the</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>farmer had access to seasonal CIS 0, otherwise</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="ufd2"><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>USCIS</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>if the farmer used seasonal CIS in farm decision</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>making 0, otherwise</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x003b2;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x003bb;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x003b1;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>Main</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>Equation</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0085"><xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation 1</xref> is the second stage equation plus the inverse mills ratio as an additional explanatory variable to solve for selectivity bias. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>2 (use of CIS), was meaningfully observed if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si4.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>1 (access of CIS) = 1.<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si5.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Z</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>Selection</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>Equation</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si6.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>Latent</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>Equation</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0090"><italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x0223c; N[0,1]</p><p id="p0095"><italic>Corr</italic> [<italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub>1</sub>
<italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub>2</sub>] = <italic>&#x003c1;</italic></p><p id="p0100a"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si7.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si8.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>were the vector of coefficients associated with the independent variables, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si9.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si10.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub> represented the exogenous variables (socio-economic characteristics) that determined <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si4.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>2 and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si4.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>1 respectively, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si11.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub><bold>1</bold></sub> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si11.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub><bold>2</bold></sub> were the respective error terms normally distributed with zero mean, unit variance and correlation <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si12.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. When the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si12.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> &#x02260; 0 the standard probit model 3 would yield biased estimates. Therefore, to correct for selectivity bias this study considered that<disp-formula id="ufd3"><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si13.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Prob</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>(</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>)</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Prob</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>(</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mtext>i)</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Prob</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>(</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Z</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>)</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Whereby, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si14.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represented the cumulative distribution at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si15.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub>. Hence<disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si16.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>E</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x003bb;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0100">Where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si17.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub> = <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si18.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>(<inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si15.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub>)/<inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si14.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si15.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub>), with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si18.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> representing the probability density function at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si15.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si17.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub> is the inverse mills ratio (IMR) which is the ratio of value of density function of standard normal distribution <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si15.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub> and the probability of being in the sub sample with access to seasonal CIS which is similar to cumulative distribution valued at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si15.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><sub>i</sub> for the households with access and a complement of 1 for households without access. On the other hand <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si19.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the regression coefficient on the inverse mill ratio<inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si20.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Therefore, to correct for selectivity bias and achieve unbiased efficient estimates IMR was included in the second stage <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">equation (1)</xref>.</p><p id="p0105">In correspondence with previous studies on factors influencing access and utilisation of climate information such as <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Ingram et&#x000a0;al. (2002)</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Oyekale (2012)</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Kirui et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</xref>, <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Yong (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ochieng et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref>, the independent variables included in the selection equation (Determinants of access to CIS) were; <italic>farmer characteristics</italic> (Age of household head measured in years, sex of household head&#x02014;equal to1 if male and zero female, Household size&#x02014;number of resident household members, Year of completed formal education of household head, major livelihood activity&#x02014;equal to 1 if farming and 0 if otherwise, Household monthly cash income in Kenya Shillings)<bold>;</bold>
<italic>farm characteristics</italic> (Farm size in hectares, Frequency of exposure to drought)<bold>,</bold>
<italic>Institutional factors</italic>, (access to extension services&#x02014;equal to 1 for farmers with access to extension services and 0 if otherwise, access to credit&#x02014;equals 1 if household received credit and 0 if otherwise, Group membership&#x02014;equal to 1 if the household has a member who participated in a farmers' group and 0 if otherwise)<bold>,</bold>
<italic>communication assets</italic> (radio ownership&#x02014;equals 1 if household own a radio and 0 if otherwise, television ownership&#x02014;equals 1 if household owned a television and 0 if otherwise). Similar variables were used in the outcome equation. For identification purposes, however, group membership was omitted from the outcome equation but included in the selection equation. Additionally, <italic>farm characteristics</italic>, such as access to organic fertilizers&#x02014;a dummy variable equal to 1 if the household applied organic fertilizers and 0 if otherwise, access to improved seed&#x02014;a dummy variable equal to 1 if the household grew an improved variety of crop and 0 if otherwise, access to farm equipment&#x02014;a dummy variable equal to 1 if a household had access to farm equipment and 0 if otherwise were included in the outcome but not selection equation. Variables measuring access to farm inputs were included in the outcome equation (determinants of use of SCIS) because access to basic agricultural technologies such as new crop varieties, fertilizers and farm equipment are important to ensure farmers utilise and benefit from climate information services (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Ingram et&#x000a0;al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Klopper et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Socio-economic characteristics of smallholder farmers in Makueni County</title><p id="p0110"><xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the descriptive statistics of explanatory variables included in the model. The results showed that 65 percent of the sampled households were male-headed. The age of the household head ranged between 23 &#x02013; 90 years with a mean of 53 years. This finding concurs with the World Bank report that majority of youth do not participate in agriculture in Kenya (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Brooks et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). The expected direction of influence of age on access and use of CIS is ambiguous in that older farmers may have accumulated experience in farming which they may use to cope with climatic shocks hence risk-averse to new information. On the other hand, such farmers may understand the adverse effects of climatic shocks making them more receptive to new information.<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary statistics of sample households.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Variables</th><th>Mean</th><th>SD</th><th>Expected sign</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Age of Household Head (years)</td><td align="right">53.1</td><td align="right">14.2</td><td align="right">+/-</td></tr><tr><td>Sex of household head (% male)</td><td align="right">65.0</td><td/><td align="right">+/-</td></tr><tr><td>Household size (number of resident members)</td><td align="right">5.0</td><td align="right">1.9</td><td align="right">+/-</td></tr><tr><td>Education of the household head (years)</td><td align="right">9.7</td><td align="right">4.3</td><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Land allocated to farming (hectares)</td><td align="right">3.3</td><td align="right">2.8</td><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Households monthly Income (Ksh)</td><td align="right">21,481.4</td><td align="right">20,615.2</td><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Access to improved seed (% yes)</td><td align="right">74.0</td><td/><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Access to credit (% yes)</td><td align="right">60.0</td><td/><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Access to Extension services (% yes)</td><td align="right">27.0</td><td/><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Farming is the major income activity (% yes)</td><td align="right">50.0</td><td/><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Group Membership (% yes)</td><td align="right">78.0</td><td/><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Household applied organic fertilizers (%yes)</td><td align="right">82.3</td><td/><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Household owns a radio (%yes)</td><td align="right">86.8</td><td/><td align="right">+</td></tr><tr><td>Household owns a television (%yes)</td><td align="right">32.6</td><td/><td align="right">+</td></tr></tbody></table><attrib><italic>Source</italic>: Author's survey 2017.</attrib></table-wrap></p><p id="p0115">The education levels were categorized into three; primary education (1&#x02013;10 years), secondary education (11&#x02013;14 years) and tertiary level (above 15 years). The results showed that the average years of education was 9 years which implied that majority of household heads had attained primary education. This is supported by the <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">World Bank (2004)</xref> report that 87 percent of Kenya's population have gone through primary education. Moreover, the community believes education is the means to break poverty vicious cycle since farming is fraught with various climate shocks. The effect of education on access and use of CIS is also ambiguous and subject to empirical analysis. Whereas educated household head can be expected to actively search for, grasp, and apply information about CIS, such farmers may also have a greater incentive to work, at least part-time, off-farm in non-agricultural activities that are less sensitive to climatic shocks.</p><p id="p0120">The results also indicated that 78 percent of the sample households were members of development groups. Table banking, credit facilities, social welfare and agronomic services were the various services offered in the groups.</p><p id="p0125">Access to credit may ease liquidity constraints faced by farmers in accessing production resources. The results showed that 60 percent of households had access to credit facilities. Lack of collateral, inability to pay back borrowed loans, and lengthy procedures were the main hindrances to credit access.</p><p id="p0130">Majority of the households interviewed had access to improved seeds but only in small quantities due to high prices. Although Kenya has a more developed seed system compared to other African countries, their access by farmers is limited (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2015</xref>). This results in farmers using indigenous seeds from the previous harvest which compromises agricultural yields.</p><p id="p0135">Despite extension services being the major change agents towards the transformation of subsistence farming to modern agriculture, only 27 percent of the households accessed them (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Mwangangi et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref> also noted that the lack of extension services was a major hindrance to agricultural development in Makueni County. According to Makueni County Annual report (2017), the current ratio of extension officer to the farmer is 1: 1,700 which is very high compared to the recommended ratio 1:400 by the FAO hence compromising effective access and use of appropriate agricultural technologies.</p><p id="p0140">Mixed farming was the major income activity in the area. This was mainly practiced by smallholder farmers since the households interviewed had an average farm size of 3.3 ha.</p><p id="p0145">However, farming was mainly practiced for subsistence needs with only little surplus sold to meet non-food household needs. High dependence on rain-fed agriculture for livelihood increases the county's vulnerability to climate change. Therefore enhancing drought resilience agricultural practices and livelihood diversification will reduce the County's vulnerability to climate change and increase food security.</p><p id="p0150">Irrespective of maize been highly sensitive to climate change, it was grown by all households interviewed in the area. This is because maize is the main staple food in the study area. The other cereals grown were; beans, pigeon peas, cowpeas, sorghum, millet, greengrams and fruit trees. This portrays high diversification in food production in the study area.</p><p id="p0155">Among the livestock kept were; chicken, goats, donkey and humped cattle breed (zebu) which is adaptable to hot tropics. These were mainly kept as a source of food, wealth, manure and income to enhance household sustainability. The indigenous zebu cattle also provided draft power for the cultivation of crops.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Access and use of seasonal climate information services</title><p id="p0160">Descriptive statistics on the access and use of CIS are summarised in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>. As shown 94 percent of sample households had access to seasonal forecast. Out of these, 78 percent reported that seasonal forecast was accompanied by agronomic advice. Among the farmers who accessed seasonal CIS only 40 percent utilised it in farm management decisions. This finding concurs with that of (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Serra and Mckune, 2016</xref>) who established that despite the wide dissemination of climate information services the rate of utilisation in farms to manage climate-related risks is minimal. Lack of trust and unreliability of the climate information services were reported as the main hindrances to the utilisation of climate information services. This finding is supported by that of <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Ziervogel et&#x000a0;al. (2005)</xref> who indicated that household use of climate information was dependent on the trust placed on the forecast. Moreover, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Mudombi and Nhamo (2014)</xref> indicated that climate information should be reliable, trusted and understandable for farmers to utilise it in climate change adaptation<bold>.</bold><fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Access to seasonal climate information services.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig.&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/><attrib><italic>Source</italic>: Authors' survey in 2017</attrib></fig></p><p id="p0165">The various agronomic advice that accompanied seasonal forecast included introduction of new crop varieties, growing of early maturing varieties, adoption of drought-tolerant varieties of crops, early land preparation and adjusting planting dates. Change in planting dates, time of land preparation, type of crop grown, a shift in crop variety, area allocated to crops were the various farm practices influenced by seasonal climate information services. These findings are similar to those of <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Serra and Mckune (2016)</xref> and <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Mudombi and Nhamo (2014)</xref> who found that crop rotation, intercropping, conservation tillage, manure management, change in crop type and variety and change in planting dates were the various farm changes influenced by climate information.</p><p id="p0170">Results in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref> showed that majority of households accessed climate information services through radio and television dissemination channels. High access to climate information via radio has been linked to low cost, wide coverage, use of vernacular language and low maintenance cost (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Ingram et&#x000a0;al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Oyekale, 2015</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Sources of climate information services (CIS).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig.&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/><attrib><italic>Source</italic>: Authors' survey in 2017</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Determinants of access and use of seasonal CIS</title><p id="p0175">A test for independence was done to justify the use of Heckprobit over standard probit model using STATA software. A formal test of independence rejected the null hypothesis that the correlation in errors terms of the selection and outcome equations was significantly different from zero (Wald Chi-square = 4&#x000b7;44, <italic>p</italic>-value = 0&#x000b7;035) hence justifying the use of Heckprobit model. The log likelihood of the model was also significant at 1 percent (Wald Chi-square = 58&#x000b7;89, with <italic>p</italic>-value&#x0003c;0&#x000b7;00) indicating a high explanatory power of the model. Moreover, access to improved seed and organic fertilizers were potential suspects of endogeneity. Hausman test was done to test for endogeneity. The results showed that both variables were exogenous.</p><p id="p0180"><xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents Heckprobit results of the determinants of access (columns 2&#x02013;4) and use (columns 5&#x02013;7) of CIS. Average marginal effects are reported. The results of the selection equation showed that age of household head correlated with a reduced likelihood of access to CIS whereas household size, television ownership, income, farming and group membership correlated with an increased likelihood of access to CIS. Specifically, an increase in the age of the household head by one year resulted in a 0.9 percent decreased likelihood of accessing seasonal CIS. The age of the household head is correlated to farming experience. Therefore, older farmers have enhanced their climate monitoring and risk spreading skills which enable them to cope with climate change risks hence less demand for seasonal CIS (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Yong, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Uddin et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Moreover, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Kirui et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</xref> established that older farmers preferred indigenous knowledge over modern climate information services.<table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Marginal effects of access and use of seasonal climate information services.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Dependent Variable<hr/></th><th colspan="3">Selection equation (Access to SCIS)<hr/></th><th colspan="3">Outcome equation (Use of SCIS)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Variable</th><th>dy/dx</th><th>std Err</th><th>P value</th><th>dy/dx</th><th>std Err</th><th>P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Age</td><td align="right">-0.009</td><td align="right">0.002</td><td align="right">0***</td><td align="right">-0.006</td><td align="right">0.003</td><td align="right">0.037**</td></tr><tr><td>Gender of HH</td><td align="right">-0.060</td><td align="right">0.056</td><td align="right">0.284</td><td align="right">-0.162</td><td align="right">0.081</td><td align="right">0.045**</td></tr><tr><td>Household Size</td><td align="right">0.028</td><td align="right">0.015</td><td align="right">0.061*</td><td align="right">-0.020</td><td align="right">0.019</td><td align="right">0.283</td></tr><tr><td>Education</td><td align="right">-0.012</td><td align="right">0.008</td><td align="right">0.107</td><td align="right">0.000</td><td align="right">0.011</td><td align="right">0.968</td></tr><tr><td>Total farm land</td><td align="right">0.023</td><td align="right">0.008</td><td align="right">0.005***</td><td align="right">-0.006</td><td align="right">0.009</td><td align="right">0.517</td></tr><tr><td>Frequency of draught</td><td align="right">-0.042</td><td align="right">0.054</td><td align="right">0.439</td><td align="right">-0.146</td><td align="right">0.070</td><td align="right">0.036**</td></tr><tr><td>Extension services</td><td align="right">-0.055</td><td align="right">0.069</td><td align="right">0.427</td><td align="right">0.104</td><td align="right">0.082</td><td align="right">0.208</td></tr><tr><td>Credit facilities</td><td align="right">0.072</td><td align="right">0.059</td><td align="right">0.227</td><td align="right">0.021</td><td align="right">0.072</td><td align="right">0.769</td></tr><tr><td>Main income activity</td><td align="right">0.194</td><td align="right">0.066</td><td align="right">0.003***</td><td align="right">0.252</td><td align="right">0.080</td><td align="right">0.002***</td></tr><tr><td>Monthly Income</td><td align="right">0.072</td><td align="right">0.024</td><td align="right">0.003***</td><td align="right">0.236</td><td align="right">0.037</td><td align="right">0***</td></tr><tr><td>Ownership of radio</td><td align="right">0.082</td><td align="right">0.096</td><td align="right">0.389</td><td align="right">0.220</td><td align="right">0.071</td><td align="right">0.002***</td></tr><tr><td>Ownership of TV</td><td align="right">0.098</td><td align="right">0.049</td><td align="right">0.046**</td><td align="right">0.039</td><td align="right">0.065</td><td align="right">0.553</td></tr><tr><td>Access to improved seed</td><td align="right">0.125</td><td align="right">0.073</td><td align="right">0.88</td><td align="right">0.133</td><td align="right">0.072</td><td align="right">0.066*</td></tr><tr><td>Group membership</td><td align="right">0.132</td><td align="right">0.050</td><td align="right">0.008***</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Access to organic fertilizers</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="right">0.131</td><td align="right">0.080</td><td align="right">0.103</td></tr><tr><td>Access to farm equipment</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="right">0.200</td><td align="right">0.274</td><td align="right">0.466</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0020"><p><bold>Notes:</bold> The coefficient of total income was zero which implied high variance in the variable, therefore natural log was taken and used for analysis in the model. Number of obs 231, Censored obs 52, Uncensored obs 179, Log likelihood = -187 Wald chi2 (16) 58.89 Prob &#x0003e; chi2 0.0000. LR test of indep. eqns. (rho = 0): chi2 (1) = 4.44 Prob &#x0003e; chi2 = 0.035.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0025"><p>Notes: ***, ** and * represent 1%, 5% and 10% significance levels respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0185">An increase in household size by one member increased the likelihood of access to seasonal CIS by 2.8 percent. This implied that households with more members had a higher chance of accessing CIS from different sources. According to <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Deressa et&#x000a0;al. (2008)</xref>, households with more members were more likely to adapt to climate change due to readily available labour hence a higher demand for climate information services.</p><p id="p0190">A unit increase in farm size increased the likelihood of accessing climate information services by 2.3 percent. This is because households with large farm size are able to diversify crops options and spread risks associated with unpredictable climate hence high demand for CIS. This finding concurs with that of <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Rehman et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</xref> who established that an increase in farm size resulted in increased access to agricultural information. Moreover, farmers with large farms have a higher demand for climate information due to the enormity of expected loss attributed to climate change (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Oyekale, 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0195">Television ownership increased household's likelihood of access to seasonal climate information services. Television was the main dissemination channel of climate I formation after radio. This finding is similar to that of <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Oyekale (2012)</xref> who established that in television ownership increased access to climate forecast in Limpopo river in South Africa.</p><p id="p0200">A unit increase in household monthly income significantly increased the likelihood of accessing seasonal CIS by 7 percent. Lack of finances constrains farmers from accessing the required resources to use seasonal forecast in their farm management decisions against climate risks (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Ingram et&#x000a0;al., 2002</xref>). Therefore, higher household income increase household adaptive capacity to climate change. Similarly, households that relied on farming as the main livelihood activity had a higher likelihood of accessing seasonal CIS. This is because these households may be compelled to seek information and technologies that increase their yields compared to other farmers with alternative sources who take farming as a mere tradition (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Mulinya, 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0205">Group membership increased household's likelihood of access to CIS. This is because these groups promote farmers' social capital which enhances networking and information flow. <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Roncoli et&#x000a0;al. (2009)</xref> reported similar finding in Burkina Faso that farmers who participated in farmer workshops accessed climate information and understood better probabilistic climate forecast compared to the farmer who did not attend.</p><p id="p0210">As shown in column 5&#x02013;7 of <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, age, sex of the household head and previous exposure to drought reduced the likelihood of utilising CIS while household income, farming, access to improved seed and radio ownership correlated with an increased likelihood of using CIS. Specifically, an increase in the age of the household head by one year correlated with a 0.6 percent reduced likelihood of utilising seasonal CIS.</p><p id="p0215">The results also showed that female-headed households had a higher likelihood of utilising seasonal climate information services compared to their male counterparts. This is attributed to the fact that women contribute the highest percentage of rural agriculture compared to men in Africa (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2015</xref>). This finding concurs with those of <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">McOmber et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</xref> and <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Shongwe (2014)</xref> who reported that women are the main agents in climate change adaptation.</p><p id="p0220">A unit increase in household monthly income significantly increased the likelihood of utilising seasonal CIS by 24 percent. The results further showed that households which relied on farming as the main livelihood activity had a higher likelihood of using seasonal CIS. This finding corroborates with that of <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Frisvold and Murugesan (2013)</xref> who reported that households that derived a higher percentage of their income from farming had a higher chance of utilising climate data.</p><p id="p0225">Frequent exposure to drought reduced household's likelihood of utilising seasonal climate information services in their farm decision making by 15 percent. This finding agrees to that of <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Ziervogel and Calder (2003)</xref> who found that farmers who were exposed to previous climate shocks were reluctant to use climate information in farm decision due to reduced or lack of confidence in them. The limited use of CIS could be linked to the fact frequent exposure to climate shocks forced farmers to seek alternative livelihood options that were not vulnerable to climate change (Ogara, 2016).</p><p id="p0230">Radio ownership increased the likelihood of utilising seasonal climate information services. This relates to the fact that radio was the preferred dissemination channel of climate information services in the study area. This finding is supported by that of <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hampson et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</xref> who established that majority of the farmers used climate information disseminated through radio which was the most trusted and preferred channel. Moreover, majority of radios stations disseminate information in vernacular languages which enhance the utilisation of climate information by all farmers.</p><p id="p0235">Access to improved seed increased households' likelihood of utilising climate information services. This finding is supported by that of <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Patt et&#x000a0;al. (2005)</xref> who found that access to climate information services was less valuable in farm management decisions without access to farm inputs. Farmer's ability to utilise climate information services in farm decision making is dependent on their access to required farm inputs to maximise benefits of climate information services (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">O'Brien et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0240">The access and utilisation of climate information services for climate change adaptation is limited. This study analysed the various factors that affect both access and use of climate information services. The Heckprobit model was used for analysis to correct for selectivity bias since the farmers who utilised CIS were non-randomly selected from those who accessed it. The results showed that more than half of households accessed seasonal climate information services. Among these households that accessed CIS less than half used in it their farms for climate change adaptation. Lack of trust and unreliability of climate information services were reported as the main barriers to their utilisation in farm decisions against climate risks.</p><p id="p0245">The results of the heckprobit model showed that age of household age correlated with reduced likelihood of access to CIS while, farming, household income, television ownership, group membership, farm size and household size increased it. On the other hand age, sex of household head and frequent exposure to drought were correlated to reduced likelihood of utilising CIS whereas household income, access to improved seed, farming and television ownership increase it.</p><sec id="sec4.1"><label>4.1</label><title>Recommendations</title><p id="p0250">A limited number of households utilised climate information services in farm management decisions. Lack of trust and unreliability of CIS were reported by farmers as the main constraints to use of CIS. Therefore, provision of accurate, timely and usable information should be the priority of the Kenya Meteorological Department and other providers of climate information services.</p><p id="p0255">Household's access to improved seed enhanced the utilisation of CIS. Therefore, resources should be provided to ensure access of improved seed at low cost by all farmers to enhance climate change adaptation. Moreover, female-headed households were more likely to utilise climate information services compared to men-headed households. Therefore, this study suggests policies that promote women access to production resources to enhance utilisation of CIS. In addition, the providers of CIS should enhance dissemination of the information through channels that favour women.</p><p id="p0260">Younger farmers had a higher likelihood of accessing and using climate information services. Therefore the providers of CIS should target younger farmers in formulation and dissemination to enhance climate change adaptation. Television and Radio ownership also increased the likelihood of access and use of climate information services. Therefore, the providers of climate information services should enhance timely and frequent dissemination of detailed climate information to ensure majority of farmers' access and utilise it.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec5.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0265">Emily Muema: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0270">John Mburu: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p><p id="p0275">Jeanne Coulibaly: Conceived and designed the experiments; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p><p id="p0280">Jane Mutune: Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0285">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1">African Economic Research Consortium (AERC)</funding-source> (2000 USD for data collection).</p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0290">The authors declare no conflict of interest</p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0295">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asrat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simane</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Farmers&#x02019; perception of climate change and adaptation strategies in the Dabus watershed, North-West Ethiopia</article-title><source>Ecological Processes</source><volume>7</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>7</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zorya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Agriculture as a Sector of Opportunity for Young People in Africa</chapter-title><comment>Policy research working Paper Report number WPS 6473</comment><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coulibaly</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Birachi</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagabo</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutua</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Climate Services for Agriculture in Rwanda: Baseline Survey Report</chapter-title><comment>CCAFS Working Paper no. 202. Copenhagen, Denmark: CGIAR Research Program on Climate Change, Agriculture and Food Security (CCAFS). Available online at</comment><year>2017</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccafs.cgiar.org" id="intref0015">www.ccafs.cgiar.org</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deressa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alemu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yesuf</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringler</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Analysing the Determinants of Farmers&#x02019; Choice of Adaptation Methods and Perceptions of Climate Change in the Nile Basin of Ethiopia</chapter-title><comment>IFPRI Discussion Paper 00798</comment><year>2008</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eriksen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosentrater</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Climate Change in Eastern and Southern Africa Impacts, Vulnerability and Adaptation Climate Change in Eastern and Southern Africa Impacts, Vulnerability and Adaptation</chapter-title><year>2008</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO)</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>The Economic Lives of Smallholder Farmers</chapter-title><year>2015</year><publisher-name>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frisvold</surname><given-names>G.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murugesan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of weather information for agricultural decision making</article-title><source>Weather Climate and Society</source><volume>5</volume><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gichangi</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatheru</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Njiru</surname><given-names>E.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mungube</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wambua</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wamuongo</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of climate variability and change in semi-arid eastern Kenya</article-title><source>Climatic Change</source><volume>130</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>297</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hampson</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapota</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmanuel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tall</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huggins-Rao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leclair</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Delivering Climate Services for Farmers and Pastoralists through Interactive Radio: Scoping Report for the GFCS Adaptation Programme in Africa</chapter-title><comment>CCAFS Working Paper no. 111. CGIAR Research Program on Climate Change, Agriculture and Food Security (CCAFS). Copenhagen, Denmark. Available online at</comment><year>2014</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccafs.cgiar.org" id="intref0025">www.ccafs.cgiar.org</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Realizing the potential benefits of climate prediction to agriculture: issues, approaches</article-title><source>Agric. Syst.</source><volume>74</volume><issue>2002</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>330</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heckman</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sample selection bias as a specification error</article-title><source>Econometrica</source><volume>47</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1979</year><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>162</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roncoli</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirshen</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opportunities and constraints for farmers of West Africa to use seasonal precipitation forecasts with Burkina Faso as a case study</article-title><source>Agric. Syst.</source><volume>74</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>349</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>IPCC</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Climate change 2007: impacts, adaptation and vulnerability</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canziani</surname><given-names>O.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palutikof</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Linden</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Contribution of Working Group II to the Fourth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source><year>2007</year><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc><comment>976 pp</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Royce</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential benefits of climate forecasting to agriculture Agriculture</article-title><source>Ecosystems and Environment</source><volume>82</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>184</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirui</surname><given-names>V.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waiganjo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheplogoi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating access and use of dissemination pathways for delivering climate information and services to women farmers in semi-arid Kenya</article-title><source>Int. J. Adv. Res.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitinya</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onwonga</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onyango</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbuvi</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change and variability: farmers&#x02019; perception, experience and adaptation strategies in Makueni county Kenya</article-title><source>Asian Economic and Social Society</source><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><comment>ISSN (P): 2304-1455, ISSN (E): 2224-4433</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klopper</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landman</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal climate forecasts &#x02013; potential agricultural-risk management tools?</article-title><source>Climatic Change</source><volume>76</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macharia</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thuranira</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng&#x02019;ang&#x02019;a</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lugadiru</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakori</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perceptions and adaptation to climate change and variability by immigrant farmers in semi-arid regions of Kenya</article-title><source>Afr. Crop Sci. J.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>Supplement s2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>296</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McOmber</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Panikowski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKune</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Investigating Climate Information Services through a Gendered Lens</chapter-title><comment>CCAFS Working Paper no. 42, CGIAR Research Program on Climate Change, Agriculture and Food Security (CCAFS). Copenhagen, Denmark. Available online at</comment><year>2013</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccafs.cgiar.org" id="intref0030">www.ccafs.cgiar.org</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mudombi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nhamo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Access to weather forecasting and early warning information by communal farmers in seke and murewa districts, Zimbabwe</article-title><source>J. Hum. Ecol.</source><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>366</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mulinya</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting small scale farmers coping strategies to climate change in Kakamega county in Kenya</article-title><source>IOSR J. Humanit. Soc. Sci.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><comment>Ver. II, PP 100-109 e-ISSN: 2279-0837, p-ISSN: 2279-0845</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iosrjournals.org" id="intref0035">www.iosrjournals.org</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mutua</surname><given-names>L.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Omuterema</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gweyi</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the nature of drought experienced in Makueni county, Kenya</article-title><source>Res. Humanit. Soc. Sci.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mwangangi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mango</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Summary of Baseline Household Survey Results: Makueni, Kenya</chapter-title><comment>CGIAR Research Program on Climate Change, Agriculture and Food Security (CCAFS). Copenhagen, Denmark. Available online at</comment><year>2012</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccafs.cgiar.org" id="intref0040">www.ccafs.cgiar.org</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sygna</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x000e6;ss</surname><given-names>L.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingamkono</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochobeb</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><series>Is Information Enough? User Responses to Seasonal Climate Forecasts in Southern Africa</series><volume>3</volume><year>2000</year><publisher-name>Center for International Climate and Environmental Research</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochieng</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Recha</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bebe</surname><given-names>B.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enabling conditions for improved use of seasonal climate forecast in arid and semi-arid Baringo county&#x02014;Kenya</article-title><source>Open Access Library Journal</source><volume>4</volume><year>2017</year><comment>e3826ISSN Online: 2333-9721 ISSN Print: 2333-9705</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oyekale</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing access to climate forecasts in the Limpopo River Basin of South Africa</article-title><source>J. Food Agric. Environ.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>3&#x00026;4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1058</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oyekale</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors explaining farm households &#x02019; access to and utilization of extreme climate forecasts in sub-saharan Africa ( SSA )</article-title><source>Environ. Econ.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>103</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwata</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of seasonal climate forecasts and participatory workshops among subsistence farmers in Zimbabwe</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>102</volume><issue>35</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>12623</fpage><lpage>12628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16116076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of farmers&#x02019; socioeconomic characteristics on access to agricultural information: empirical evidence from Pakistan</article-title><source>Young</source><volume>52</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Republic of Kenya, Makueni County</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>First County Integrated Development Plan 2013-2017, August</chapter-title><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roncoli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnographic and participatory approaches to research on farmers &#x02019; responses to climate predictions</article-title><source>Clim. Res.</source><volume>33</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>99</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roncoli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirshen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Som&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouattara</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanfo</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaka</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogenboom</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From accessing to assessing forecasts: an end-to-end study of participatory climate forecast dissemination in Burkina Faso (West Africa)</article-title><source>Climatic Change</source><volume>92</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>460</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlenker</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobell</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust negative impacts of climate change on African agriculture</article-title><source>Environ. Res. Lett.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>014010</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKune</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Climate Information Services and Behavioural Change: the Case of Senegal</chapter-title><comment>Sahel Research Group Working Paper No. 010</comment><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shongwe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing the choice of climate change adaptation strategies by households: a case of mpolonjeni area development programme (ADP) in Swaziland</article-title><source>J. Agric. Stud.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokelmann</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Entsminger</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting farmers' adaptation strategies to environmental degradation and climate change effects: a farm level study in Bangladesh</article-title><source>Climate</source><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>241</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van De Ven</surname><given-names>W.P.M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Praag</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The demand for deductibles in private health insurance: a probit model with sample selection</article-title><source>J. Econom.</source><volume>17</volume><year>1981</year><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>252</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Broeck</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez Grovas</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maertens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deckers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhulst</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Govaerts</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adoption of conservation agriculture in the mexican Baj&#x000ed;o</article-title><source>Outlook Agric.</source><volume>42</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>World Bank</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Strengthening the Foundation of Education and Training in Kenya: Opportunities and Challenges in Primary and General Secondary Education</chapter-title><comment>Report No.28064-KE</comment><year>2004</year><publisher-name>The World Bank</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC, USA</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>World Bank</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Climate Information Services Providers in Kenya</chapter-title><comment>Report Number 103186-KE</comment><year>2016</year><publisher-name>World Bank</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC, USA</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting the choice of adaptation measures to climate change: the case of famers in the sudano-sahelian area of Cameroon</article-title><source>Tanzanian Economic Review</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1 &#x00026; 2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziervogel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bithell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agent-based social simulation: a method for assessing the impact of seasonal climate forecast applications among smallholder farmers</article-title><source>Agric. Syst.</source><volume>83</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziervogel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calder</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate variability and rural livelihoods: assessing the impact of seasonal climate forecasts in Lesotho</article-title><source>Area</source><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>417</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors highly acknowledge the <funding-source id="gs2">University of Nairobi</funding-source> colleagues for their comments on this paper, Makueni County Ministry of Agriculture's field officer, County chiefs, village elders and the smallholder farmers in Makueni County who assisted with area logistics and data for this study</p></ack></back></article>