<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vet World</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Vet World</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Veterinary World</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0972-8988</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2231-0916</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Veterinary World</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6141298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2018.1127-1134</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Potency of lactic acid bacteria isolated from balinese bovine (<italic>Bos sondaicus</italic>) intestinal waste from slaughterhouse to improve nutrient content of wheat pollard as animal feedstuff by fermentation process</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lokapirnasari</surname><given-names>Widya Paramita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sahidu</surname><given-names>Adriana Monica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soepranianondo</surname><given-names>Koesnoto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Supriyanto</surname><given-names>Agus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yulianto</surname><given-names>Andreas Berny</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Al Arif</surname><given-names>Anam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Animal Husbandry, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Jl. Mulyorejo, Kampus C, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Marine, Faculty of Fisheries and Marine, Jl. Mulyorejo, Kampus C, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Biology, Faculty of Science and Technology, Jl. Mulyorejo, Kampus C, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Doctoral of Veterinary Science, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Jl. Mulyorejo, Campus C, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Widya Paramita Lokapirnasari, e-mail: <email xlink:href="widyaparamitalokapirnasari@gmail.com">widyaparamitalokapirnasari@gmail.com</email> Co-authors: AMS: <email xlink:href="adriana_monica16@yahoo.co.id">adriana_monica16@yahoo.co.id</email>, KS: <email xlink:href="koesnotosp@yahoo.com">koesnotosp@yahoo.com</email>, AS: <email xlink:href="bio_asp@yahoo.co.id">bio_asp@yahoo.co.id</email>, ABY: <email xlink:href="bernyjuliantomiroen@gmail.com">bernyjuliantomiroen@gmail.com</email>, AA: <email xlink:href="a_alarif@yahoo.com">a_alarif@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1127</fpage><lpage>1134</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Lokapirnasari, <italic>et al</italic>.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->Open Access. This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Aim:</title><p>The purpose of this study was to know the genetic and biochemical identification of isolated lactic acid bacteria (LAB) from Balinese bovine (<italic>Bos sondaicus</italic>) intestinal waste, acidity, and ox bile salts and to inhibit the growth pathogen of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and the potential of those isolated to improve nutrient value of wheat pollard as animal feed ingredient by fermentation process.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>This research was divided into three stages. The first stage, isolated LAB were obtained from the bovine intestines at a slaughterhouse in Indonesia. Small intestinal samples were collected from 10 healthy Balinese beef cattle (<italic>B. sondaicus</italic>). The isolated LAB were identified by VITEK 2, polymerase chain reaction, and 16S rDNA. The basic local alignment search tool (BLAST) was performed to determine the phylogenetic tree. The second stage, the LAB were screened for their tolerance at pH 2, 3, and 4; bile salt, and antagonistic to enteric pathogen. In the third stage, to determine the potency of this isolate to increase nutrient content of wheat pollard by facultative anaerobe fermentation for 3 and 5 days.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>The result of the first stage showed that the isolate could be identified as <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>
<italic>casei</italic> WPL 315. The result of the second stage showed that the isolate tolerance to low pH (pH 2, pH 3, and pH4) for 90 min and 24 h, and this isolate had viability tolerance in 0.3% bile salt. The isolate can inhibit <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic>. The result of the third stage by proximate analysis showed that crude protein increased by 23.08% after fermentation, while crude fiber decreased by 61.24% on the level 0.5% <italic>L. casei</italic> subsp. WPL 315 in the 3-day fermentation.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Based on the results, it showed that <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 derived from indigenous intestinal Balinese beef cattle (<italic>B. sondaicus</italic>) has tolerant characteristic on acidity and ox bile salts, has antagonistic effect against <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic>, and has the ability to increase crude protein and decrease crude fiber content of wheat pollard. It would be interesting to determine whether the strain has a probiotic candidate.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Lactobacillus casei</italic></kwd><kwd>probiotics</kwd><kwd><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></kwd><kwd>wheat pollard</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Feeding cost is the biggest component in the production cost of the poultry industry. To decrease feeding costs, some efforts have been taken by poultry farmers such as the addition of feed additive. The addition of various feed additives to the poultries has an important role in stimulating growth and decreasing number of feed conversion that can give positive effect on chicken growth [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Probiotic is one of the feed additives that have been recently developed in the poultry industries, non-pathogen living organism that has mechanism to preserve microbiota balance in the digestive tract by influencing gastric microbiota as well as eliminating microorganism of host-pathogen by creating an inconvenient atmosphere for pathogenic bacterial growth [<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The most common microorganism species used as probiotics are <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] <italic>Lactococcus, Leuconostoc</italic>, <italic>Enterococcus</italic>, and <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus sporogenes</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>
<italic>plantarum</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>
<italic>rhamnosus</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>
<italic>delbrueckii</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>
<italic>reuteri</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>
<italic>fermentum</italic>, <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic>, Lactobacillus cellobiosus, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> brevis, and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>
<italic>casei</italic> [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Probiotic ability can be explained through various mechanisms. The microorganism can produce an antimicrobial substance, compete, and colonize in the gastrointestinal tract [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Probiotic can modulate immune cells. Probiotic is directly taken up through transcytosis by microfold epithelial cells and engulfed by macrophages or dendritic cells, which eventually triggers an immune response. Cytokines modulate the immune functions of dendritic, T and B cells [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Probiotic has a role in increased feed consumption for most livestock. The condition is caused by the increasing of feed digestibility in an animal that causes digestive tract that can be emptied soon so feed efficiency can be achieved. Probiotic not only increases feed consumption but also promotes growth so that it can enhance the feed conversion [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>The use of other alternative feed ingredient from agricultural by-products (i.e., wheat pollard, rice bran, and maize bran) or agricultural wastes (i.e., S rice straws, maize straws, maize leaf, and sugarcane leaves) was needed to maintain the availability of feed supply. Agricultural by-products or agricultural wastes that are available all years have low crude protein and high crude fiber content [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], such as rice bran, wheat pollard, cotton, and tofu wastes. Wheat pollard is agricultural by-products that are mostly used in livestock feeding because it is easy to get and costs lower. The limitation of wheat pollard utilization as the mixture in the livestock feed because of its low protein content, high crude fiber, and low digestibility.</p><p>To increase the feed quality based on exploration of indigenous lactic acid bacteria (LAB) from bovine intestine in the slaughterhouse, we isolated and identified LAB on acidity survival, ox bile salts survival, and to inhibit the growth of pathogen <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and the potential of the isolate, and to improve nutrient value of wheat pollard as animal feed ingredient by fermentation process.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The research does not need ethical approval. However, samples were collected as per standard collection methods without any harm or stress to the animals.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Research procedure</title><p>This research was divided into three stage. In the first stage, LAB isolate was obtained from the bovine intestines which were identified by VITEK 2, polymerase chain reaction (PCR), and nucleotide sequencing of 16S rDNA by comparing them to the GenBank database. The basic local alignment search tool (BLAST) was performed to determine the kinship arrangement based on the phylogenetic tree. This research only determined one species of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>. In the second stage, the LAB isolate was screened further for their tolerance to low pH, at pH 2, 3, and 4 as well as ox bile salts tolerance. In the third stage, to know further the ability of this isolate to animal feed ingredient (wheat pollard) conducted fermentation process was conducted on facultative anaerobe condition for 3 days and 5 days.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>First stage</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Genotypic identification</title><p>DNA amplification with PCR and identifying coding genes based on nucleotide sequence of 16S rDNA genomes.</p><p>Isolation of strain from the small intestine of bovine</p><p>Small intestinal samples were collected from 10 healthy Balinese beef cattle from a slaughterhouse in Indonesia. All samples were cultivated using a modified de Man Rogosa and Sharp (MRS) broth and agar. Bacterial colonies which showed clear zone surrounding their colonies were selected to biochemical identification by VITEK 2, PCR, and 16S rDNA, and a further test of basic probiotic properties including acid and ox bile salts tolerance assay, and antagonistic to enteric pathogen.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>DNA isolation</title><p>Ingredients used in the DNA isolation process were as follows: Lysozyme 10 mg/mL, buffer TE 50 mM (50 mMtris Cl [pH 8.0]; 50 mM EDTA), buffer STEP (sodium dodecyl sulfate 0.5%, 50 mMtris Cl [pH 8.0], 0.4 M EDTA, and proteinase K), Na-acetate 3M, Phenol: chloroform:isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1), ethanol 70%, cold absolute ethanol, and distilled water.</p><p>Ingredients used in the 16S rDNA gene amplification were buffer 2.5 &#x000b5;l, dNTP 2.0 &#x000b5;l, MgSO<sub>4</sub> 1.0 &#x000b5;l, DNA template 2.0 &#x000b5;l, primer forward PB 36 (10 pmol) 1.0 &#x000b5;l, primer reverse PB 38 (&#x003c1;mol) 1.0 &#x000b5;l, distilled water 10.3 &#x000b5;l, enzyme high fidelity Taq polymerase 0.2 &#x000b5;l, and PCR product detection with electrophoresis: Buffer TBE (tris base/boric acid/EDTA) 0.5&#x000d7;, agarose, and ethidium bromide. DNA isolation was performed using Ausubel methods [<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>DNA Amplification with PCR</title><p>High fidelity platinum Taq DNA polymerase (Invitrogen&#x02122; Platinum&#x02122; <italic>Taq</italic> DNA Polymerase High Fidelity, US) kit with primer forward PB36 5&#x02019;-AGR GTT TGA TCM TGG CTC AG-3&#x02019; (Invitrogen) and primer reverse PB38 5&#x02019;-GMT ACC TTG TTA CGA CTT-3&#x02019; (Invitrogen) that produced &#x000b1; 1400pb were used for PCR.</p><p>Master mix of used amplification reaction was 10&#x000d7; high fidelity PCR buffer 2.5 ml, 10 mM dNTP mix 2 ml, 50 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub> 1 ml, primer forward 1 ml (10 pmol/&#x000b5;l), primer reverse 1 ml (10 pmol/&#x000b5;l), template cDNA 2 ml, platinum tag high fidelity 0.2 ml, and distilled water until it reached total volume of 20 ml. The used PCR condition was pre-denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min, denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 1 min, annealing at 50&#x000b0;C for 1 min, extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 1 min, 30 cycles, and a final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 10 min. PCR result was analyzed by electrophoresis gel on 2% of an agarose gel that contains ethidium bromide. 5 &#x000b5;l DNA added with 2 &#x000b5;l loading dye was added into agarose holes, and then run in the 100-volt tension for more or less 30 min.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Analysis of DNA sequence coding 16S rDNA</title><p>DNA sequencing coding 16S rDNA was performed by 1<sup>st</sup> Base Serdang, Malaysia. Analysis of sequencing result was performed through BLAST nucleotide sequencing from 16S rDNA sequencing result with the available database on www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Biochemical identification</title><p>Biochemical identification by VITEK 2 microbial identification system version: 05.01 (BioM&#x000e9;rieux) was applied in examining WPL 315 isolates. The VITEK 2 system (bioM&#x000e9;rieux) is an integrated modular system that consists of a filling-sealer unit, a reader-incubator, a computer control module, a data terminal, and a multicopy printer. The system detects bacterial growth and metabolic changes in the microwells of thin plastic cards using a fluorescence-based technology. Different microwell cards contain biochemical substrates [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Second stage</title><sec id="sec3-6"><title>LAB survival test on acidity and survival test on ox bile salts, antagonistic test, on enteric pathogen bacteria</title><p>Ingredients used in this research included an antagonistic test on enteric pathogen microbe used in MRSB/de MRS Broth (Oxoid) media, nutrient agar media (NA and Oxoid), and nutrient broth (NB and Oxoid). Media used in the survival test on acidity were MRSB (Oxoid), MRSA (Oxoid), 0.85% of sterile NaCl, as well as HCl. Media used in the bile salts test were MRSB (Oxoid), MRSA (Oxoid), 0.85% of sterile NaCl, as well as ox gall 0.3% (Oxoid). Media used to test crude protein proximate analysis were Tablet Kjeldhal (Merck), H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (Merck), NaOH 40% (Merck), boric acid (Merck), methyl red (Merck) indicator, Brom cresol green (Merck), H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> 0.01 N (Merck), and Aquadest.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-7"><title>Selection of LAB as a probiotic candidate</title><p>The isolate assumed to have the ability as probiotic was selected through various tests, so superior isolate of LAB was chosen to be tested <italic>in vitro</italic>. The tests were as follows.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-8"><title>LAB survival test on acidity and survival test on ox bile salts</title><p>Acid tolerance was assayed as reported by Succi <italic>et al</italic>. with modification [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], in 10 mL of MRS broth adjusted to pH values of 2.0, 3.0, and 4.0 with 3.0 M HCl. MRS broth at pH 7 served as control. All tests were carried out in duplicate.</p><p>The modification method of Gilliland and Kim [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] was employed in this study to know the effects of ox bile salts 0.3% (w/v) (Sigma, Milan, Italy) in MRS broth. All the samples were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C, 24 h. The aliquots were 10-fold diluted and viable bacteria (CFU/mL) were enumerated by spot plating on MRS agar (48 h, 37&#x000b0;C, and anaerobic conditions) [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec3-9"><title>Antagonistic test on enteric pathogen bacteria</title><p>The antagonistic test was assayed as reported by Jin <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] with modification. Antagonistic test on enteric pathogen was performed with an agar diffusion method with modification in the pouring of pathogenic bacteria culture. LAB culture was grown on MRSB medium at 37&#x000b0;C for 18-20 h. After that, pathogenic bacteria were inoculated as much as 1 ose in the NB media, to be incubated for 24 h at 37&#x000b0;C. After incubation ended, 0.2 mL of the incubated bacteria was taken and placed into 100 mL NA media (0.2%) to be mixed well (homogeneous), and then placed into Petri dish with 1-20 mL for each dish until solid. After agar media became solid, a hole was created in the agar media with 6 mm diameter. Five holes were created for each Petri dish.</p><p>LAB culture from MRSB was spotted into the hole as much as 50 &#x000b5;l and then incubated for 24 h at 37&#x000b0;C. MRSB medium without LAB was used as the control. The observation was performed by measuring the clear zone around the hole using Vernier calipers. LAB antagonistic activity on enteric pathogen was shown as the diameter of created clear zone.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Third Stage: Potency of L. casei WPL 315 on fermented wheat pollard</title><sec id="sec3-10"><title>Inoculation of L. casei WPL 315 on fermented wheat pollard</title><p>To know isolate ability on the nutritional content changes of crude protein and crude fiber, fermentation process was performed through following treatment P0: 100 g of wheat pollard without <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 + molasses 4% addition (as control), treatment P1: 100 g of wheat pollard with addition of 0.5% <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 + molasses 4% (3-day fermentation), treatment P2: 100 g of wheat pollard with addition of 1.0% <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 + molasses 4% (3-day fermentation), treatment P3: 100 g of wheat pollard with addition of 0.5% <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 + molasses 4% (5-day fermentation), and treatment P4: 100 g of wheat pollard with addition of 1.0% <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 + molasses 4% (5-day fermentation). The fermentation process was done in anaerobe condition. The experimental design used in this research was a completely randomized design in triplicate for each treatment. The molasses was mixed with Aquadest as much as 20% from sample weight, and the isolate based on treatment level was poured in the mixture (molasses + Aquadest) and then sprayed evenly on the wheat pollard. The mixture was then fermented in anaerobe condition in the plastic bag for 3 days and 5 days. The isolate concentration of <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 used in this research was 1.2&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL. After incubation ended, it was dried and continued into the proximate analysis of crude fiber and crude protein according to AOAC [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). If the significant differences were found, the test would be continued using Duncan&#x02019;s multiple range test on 5% significance level.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Genotypic and biochemical identification</title><sec id="sec3-11"><title>DNA amplification with PCR and identifying coding genes based on nucleotide sequence of 16S rDNA genomes</title><p>In this research, a colony of WPL 315 LAB was capable of growing on MRSA medium. Based on Gram staining, this LAB isolate was Gram-positive (GP), rod-shaped, and positive motility.</p><p>An advanced test was conducted on code WPL 315 LAB isolate with 16S rDNA and phylogenetic tree structure with 91-98% similarity. The majority of bacteria resembling WPL 315 isolate originated from <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> genus. Based on the degree of similarity of nucleotide structure, the closeness in position with <italic>L. casei</italic> ATCC 334 (accession NC_008526.1; 98% identity, <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table-1</xref>), and inherited traits in congruence with microbe identification system, the isolated strain was identified as <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table-1</label><caption><p>Similarity identity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identities</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession (sequence ID):</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillus casei</italic> ATCC 334 chromosome, complete genome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_008526.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG whole genome sequence, strain GG (ATCC 53103)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_013198.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillus sakei strain</italic> 23K complete genome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_007576.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pediococcus claussenii</italic> ATCC BAA344, complete genome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_016605.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pediococcus pentosaceus</italic> ATCC 25745, complete genome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_008525.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillus buchneri</italic> CD034, complete genome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_018610.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillus reuteri</italic> DSM 20016, complete genome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_009513.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> WCFS1, complete genome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_004567.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> IFO 3956 DNA, complete genome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_010610.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillus brevisATCC</italic> 367, complete genome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref|NC_008497.1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Biochemical assay of LAB isolate WPL 315 was investigated using the VITEK 2 Compact system. The GP card of the VITEK 2 system includes biochemical tests to determine carbohydrate usage, enzyme activity, and resistance to certain compounds that can be used to identify GP, non-spore-forming bacteria [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The result of phenotypic identification of LAB isolates WPL 315 by VITEK 2 microbial identification system <italic>version</italic>: 05.01 (BioM&#x000e9;rieux) as shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table-2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table-2</label><caption><p>Biochemical test of LAB isolate WPL 315 by VITEK 2</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biochemical test</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biochemical test</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LAC (Lactose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dRIB (d-Ribose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAC (Saccharose/Sucrose) Sucrose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dGAL (D-Galactose) Galactose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gluconate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Celobiose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dRIB (D-Rybosa) (Ribose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dRAF (D-Raffinose) Raffinose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dXYL (D-Xylose) Xylose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mannitol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARG (Arginin)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ramnose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arabinose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esculin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BXYL (beta-xylosidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LeU (leucinearylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BGAL (beta-galactosidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AlaA (alanine arylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APPA (Ala-Phe-Pro Arylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLYG (Glycogene)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELLM (Ellman)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MTE (Maltotriose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dMNE (D-Mannose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLE (Palatinose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMAN (Beta-mannosidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGLU (alpha-glucosidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INU (Inulin)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSCNa (putrescine assimilation)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLD (oleandomycin resistance)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POLYB_R (Polymixin_B resistance)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LysA (L-lysine Arylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PheA (phenylalanine arylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PyrA (L-pyrrolidonylarylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TyrA (Tyrosine Arylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDEX (cyclodextrin)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INO (Inositol)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MdX (Methyldxyloside)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GlyA (glycine arylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dMLZ (D-melezitose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRHA (L-rhamnose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHC (phosphoryl choline)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dTAG (dTagatose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dGLU (D-glucose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaCl 6.5% (growth in 6.5% NaCl)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESC (esculin hydrolyze)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ProA (L-prolinearylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AspA (L-aspartate arylamidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BNAG (beta-N-acetyl-glucosaminidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGAL (alphagalactosidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MdG (methyl-A-D Glucopyranoside acidification)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dGAL (D-Galactose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dMAN (D-Mannitol)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMAN (alpha-mannosidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BGLU (beta-glucosidase)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAG (N-acetyl-Dglucosamine)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dTRE (D-Trehalose)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PVATE (pyruvate)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KAN (kanamycin resistance)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTZ (tetrazolium red)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LAB=Lactic acid bacteria</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-12"><title>LAB survival test on acidity</title><p>In the digestive tract, bactericidal effect from acid happened at pH under 2.5 [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The result of survival test on acidity showed that <italic>L. cassei</italic> WPL 315 tolerance to low pH (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table-3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table-3</label><caption><p>LAB survival test on acidity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Survival test on acidity of <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRS agar (control) (CFU/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRS agar pH 2 (CFU/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRS agar pH 3 (CFU/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRS agar pH 4 (CFU/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (min)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duplicate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (h)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duplicate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LAB=Lactic acid bacteria, <italic>L. casei=Lactobacillus casei</italic></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-13"><title>Survival test on ox bile salts</title><p>The results of this research showed that <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 has viability tolerance in ox bile salts 0.3% and the concentration of <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 in ox bile salts 0.3% (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table-4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table-4</label><caption><p>LAB survival test on oxbile salts after 24 h, starting inoculums 2.90&#x000d7;10<sup>8</sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactide acid bacteria viability isolate (ox bile tolerance 0.3%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolate</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup> CFU/ml</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LAB=Lactic acid bacteria, <italic>L. casei=Lactobacillus casei</italic></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-14"><title>Antagonistic test on enteric pathogen bacteria</title><p>The result of the antagonistic test on enteric bacteria shows that <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 has an antagonistic effect against <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic>. The index antibacterial is shown in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table-5</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table-5</label><caption><p>LAB survival test on <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antagonistic test on enteric bacteria</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diameter inhibition (mm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. aureus</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LAB=Lactic acid bacteria, <italic>L. casei=Lactobacillus casei, E. coli=Escherichia coli, S. aureus=Staphylococcus aureus</italic></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-15"><title>Inoculation of L. casei WPL 315 on fermented wheat pollard</title><p>The result of statistical analysis using one-way ANOVA showed that the use of <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 on wheat pollard fermentation had a significant effect in the pH, crude protein, and crude fiber content of wheat pollard (p&#x0003c;0.05). The result of wheat pollard fermentation showed the decreasing of crude fiber content and the increasing of crude protein content at 0.5% <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 isolate within 3-5-day fermentation as shown in <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table-6</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T6" position="float"><label>Table-6</label><caption><p>Analysis result on nutrient content changes in wheat pollard fermentation using <italic>L. casei</italic>WPL 315 isolate</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude protein</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude fiber</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P0 (control)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<sup>a</sup>&#x000b1;0.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0<sup>a</sup>&#x000b1;0.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9<sup>a</sup>&#x000b1;0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1 (0.5%, 3 days)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<sup>b</sup>&#x000b1;0.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3<sup>c</sup>&#x000b1;0.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0<sup>c</sup>&#x000b1;0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2 (1.0%, 3 days)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<sup>b</sup>&#x000b1;0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0<sup>ab</sup>&#x000b1;0.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2<sup>ab</sup>&#x000b1;0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P3 (0.5%, 5 days)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<sup>b</sup>&#x000b1;0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0<sup>b</sup>&#x000b1;0.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0<sup>b</sup>&#x000b1;0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P4 (1.0%, 5 days)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<sup>b</sup>&#x000b1;0.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5<sup>ab</sup>&#x000b1;0.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0<sup>ab</sup>&#x000b1;0.47</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a,b,c</sup>Means in the same column with the different superscript are significantly different at (p&#x02264;0.05). <italic>L. casei=Lactobacillus casei</italic></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Genotypic and phenotypic identification</title><sec id="sec3-16"><title>DNA amplification with PCR and identifying coding genes based on nucleotide sequence of 16S rDNA genomes</title><p>To identify and determine the taxonomy of bacteria from several environment sources and identify the phylogenetic characterization, 16S rDNA gene sequencing can be applied since this molecule exists in every organism with identical function in all organisms [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>-<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The BLAST nucleotide (BLASTn) program (available at http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov) was used to screen candidate genes based on sequence similarity [<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. An advanced assay was conducted on code WPL 315 LAB isolate with 16S rDNA and phylogenetic tree structure with 91-98% similarity. The majority of bacteria resembling WPL 315 isolate originated from <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> genus. Based on the degree of similarity of nucleotide structure, the closeness in position with <italic>L. casei</italic> ATCC 334 (accession NC_008526.1; 98% identity, <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table-1</xref>), and inherited traits in congruence with microbe identification system, the isolated strain was identified as <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315.</p><p>VITEK2 Compact (bioMerieux, France) is an automated system able to identify microorganisms by testing 59 biochemical properties and also handle many samples in one reaction. VITEK2 compact was used for this study to differentiate isolates at a strain level by analyzing and comparing the phenotypes. Strains were individually grown on MRS agar. Colonies were picked and mixed in a 0.45% NaCl solution until the McFarland standard measured 0.50-0.63 on the VITEK 2 DensiCheck instrument (bioMerieux). GP colorimetric identification cards (bioMerieux) and the tubes containing the bacteria were assembled in a cassette and assayed using the VITEK2 compact system. Data were analyzed using the VITEK 2 software version VT2-R03.1.</p><p>LAB isolated from the intestine of local beef cattle produced several enzymatic activities: Beta-xylosidase, beta-galactosidase, Ala-Phe-Pro Arylamidase, l-lysine arylamidase, l-pyrrolidonyl arylamidase, alpha-galactosidase, leucine arylamidase, alanine arylamidase, alpha-glucosidase, phenylalanine arylamidase, tyrosine arylamidase, and beta-n-acetylglucosaminidase. The proteolytic system of LAB is composed of a cell envelope-associated proteinase, peptide transport systems, and intracellular peptidases. It can hydrolyze proteins to small peptides and amino acids which are essential for rapid microbial growth [<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><p>&#x003b2;-glucosidases enzymes are responsible for the catalyze of &#x003b2;-1,4-glycosidic bonds of various oligosaccharides, disaccharides, and alkyl- and aryl-&#x003b2;-d-glucosides [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], responsible for the hydrolysis of ce-lo-oligosaccharides and cellobiose, an important fiber source in cereal feeds. In addition, these enzymes hydrolyze toxic and/or bitter glucosides, release aromatic compounds, and synthesize various oligosaccharides, glycoconjugates, and alkyl- and amino-glucosides [<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec3-17"><title>LAB survival test on acidity</title><p>The result of survival test on acidity showed that <italic>L.cassei</italic> WPL 315 tolerance to low pH (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table-3</xref>). This was comparable with <italic>L. casei</italic> IS-7257 has viability as much as 5.22&#x000b1;0.31 log CFU/mL. The survival on acid tolerance indicated the ability of the isolate to survive in stomach that has extreme pH (pH 2) and could survive in the gastrointestinal tract process where hydrolytic and gastric juice are secreted [<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>These results are in agreement with those obtained from previous similar studies, where <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> strains were able to survive when exposed by pH 2.5-4.0 but displayed loss of viability at lower pH values [<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Lactic acid produced by <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> creates an acid environment that can inhibit the growth of pathogenic bacteria [<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Other research showed that some LAB strains have function as competitive inhibitors on pathogenic organism [<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], the strains include L. casei 99p, L. <italic>rhamnosus</italic> GG, L. <italic>casei</italic> Shirota, <italic>Bifidobacterium breve</italic> Yacult, and L. <italic>acidophilus</italic> [<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec3-18"><title>Survival test on bile salts</title><p>Bile tolerance and acid tolerance are required for bacterial growth in the small intestine and survive passage through the stomach. The result of this research shows that <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 has viability tolerance in 0.3% bile salts. The results showed that the concentration of <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 in 0.3% bile salts was 9.6&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup> CFU/mL in MRS agar (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table-4</xref>). Similar observations were also reported by Srinu <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and Balasingham <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] that LAB strains survived and tolerated at 0.3-2.0% bile salts (Oxgall). The viability tolerance in the bile salts condition is one of the main criteria for <italic>in vitro</italic> selection of potentially probiotic bacteria and microbes [<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Because the bacterial cell wall is comprised mainly of phospholipids, bile salts which are an emulsifier and solubilizes the lipid that can damage the bacterial cells [<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec3-19"><title>Antagonistic test on enteric pathogen bacteria</title><p>Inhibition of pathogens by the intestinal microbiota has been called bacterial antagonism, bacterial interference, barrier effect, colonization resistance, and competitive exclusion. Mechanisms by which the indigenous intestinal bacteria inhibit pathogens include competition for colonization sites, competition for nutrients, production of toxic compounds, or stimulation of the immune system [<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. LAB strains have potency in creating bactericidal bioactive peptides. Bacteriocins are also produced by species from <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, L. acidophilus produces lactacin B or F, and L. <italic>casei</italic> B80 produces casein 80 [<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Antimicrobial activity produced by LAB strain is not correlated with the acidity level in the medium. It has been reported that LAB strain has a strong inhibitory effect on <italic>S. aureus</italic> growth in milk. The inhibition ability is correlated with the existence of bacteriocins production, hydrogen peroxide production, and organic acids production such as lactic acid and acetic acid [<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec3-20"><title>Inoculation of L. casei WPL 315 on fermented wheat pollard</title><p>The result of wheat pollard fermentation showed the increase of nutrient that was shown by the decreasing of crude fiber content and the increasing of crude protein content at 0.5% level within 3-5-day fermentation as shown in <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table-6</xref>. The result of the statistical analysis showed that the use of <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 on wheat pollard fermentation had a significant effect in the content of pH wheat pollard (p&#x0003c;0.05). The result of pH level analysis showed the decrease of pH within the incubation process for all treatment groups compared to that in the control group (P0). <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 treatment showed that the lowest pH was achieved in the treatment that used 0.5% isolate addition in the fermentation process because it was caused by LAB activity in recasting activity on water-soluble carbohydrate contained in the wheat pollard in the form of lactic acid. The decrease in pH level was followed by the decrease in carbohydrate level.</p><p>The result of the statistical analysis showed that the use of <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 on wheat pollard fermentation had a significant effect on the content of crude fiber in wheat pollard (p&#x0003c;0.05). The result of the analysis showed a decreasing level of crude fiber content for all treatment compared to that in the control group (P0). The lowest crude fiber content was achieved in the treatment group that used 0.5% isolate within 3 days&#x02019; fermentation process. The decrease of crude fiber content was correlated with the isolate ability to degrade organic matter derived from complex molecules becoming simplest molecules: Cellulose was degraded into cello-oligosaccharide to be then degraded into cellobiose; in the end, cellobiose was degraded into glucose [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Probiotics also stimulate activities of cellulolytic bacteria to degrade crude fiber [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>The result of the statistical analysis showed that the use of <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 on wheat pollard fermentation had a significant effect on crude protein content (p&#x0003c;0.05). The result showed an increasing level of crude protein content for all treatment compared to the control group (P0). The highest crude protein content was achieved by adding 0.5% isolate within 3-day fermentation. This was caused by increased activity of <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 in binding N as the basic matter to synthesize protein. Thus, the increase of nitrogen level allowed bacteria to grow and perform activity optimally that made crude protein level in wheat pollard increased higher compared to that in other treatment groups because bacteria are a single cell protein. The increase of crude protein content was also caused by the decrease of other compounds including nitrogen-free extract produced by fermented crude fiber [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Enzyme &#x003b2; galactosidase, glycols, and lactate dehydrogenase could be produced by LAB. It has a role in decreasing pH in the gastrointestinal tract, so it will inhibit <italic>E. coli</italic> growth and other pathogenic bacteria that need pH 6-7 [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The result of the research showed that <italic>L. casei</italic> WPL 315 derived from indigenous intestinal Balinese beef cattle (<italic>Bos sondaicus</italic>) has tolerant characteristic on acidity and ox bile salts and has antagonistic effect against <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-6"><title>Authors&#x02019; Contributions</title><p>The work was done by WPL who designed the research and WPL, AS, as well as ABY who conducted the experimental work. WPL, AMS, and AA analyzed and interpreted the data and drafted the manuscript. WPL, KS, and AA participated in doing data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, and writing the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to thank the Ministry of Research, Technology, and Higher Education, Indonesia, Rector and Director of Research and Innovation Department, Airlangga University, that have funded the Excellent Research Universities (PTUPT) No. 004/ADD/SP2H/LT/DRPM/VIII/2017</p></ack><sec id="sec1-7"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waldroup</surname><given-names>P.W</given-names></name><name><surname>Oviedo-Rondon</surname><given-names>E.O</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritts</surname><given-names>C.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of bio-mos and antibiotic feeding programs in broiler diets containing copper sulfate</article-title><source>Int. J. Poult. Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Astini</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><source>Potential of Commercial Probiotic on Body Weight Gain, Feed Consumption, Feed Conversion Ratio</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Surabaya</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Universitas Airlangga</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dongarr&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizzello</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Muccio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fries</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cascio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonaccorsi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferlazzo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mucosal immunology and probiotics</article-title><source>Curr Allergy Asthma Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23054627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Besseling-van der Vaart</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>M.D</given-names></name><name><surname>Guagnini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>M.F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> evidence for efficacy in food intolerance for the multispecies probiotic formulation ecologic&#x000ae;tolerance (Syngut&#x02122;)</article-title><source>Benef. Microbes</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26565083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz-Atienza</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Sala</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Campanero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Campo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>P.E</given-names></name><name><surname>Herranz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cintas</surname><given-names>L.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity, antibiotic susceptibility and virulence factors of lactic acid bacteria of aquatic origin intended for use as probiotics in aquaculture</article-title><source>BMC Microbial</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amara</surname><given-names>A.A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of probiotics in health improvement, infection control and disease treatment and management</article-title><source>Saudi Pharm. J</source><year>2015</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25972729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buffie</surname><given-names>C.G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pamer</surname><given-names>E.G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiota-mediated colonization resistance against intestinal pathogens</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Immunol</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>790</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24096337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vuong</surname><given-names>C.N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>W.K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hargis</surname><given-names>B.M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berghman</surname><given-names>L.R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielke</surname><given-names>L.R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of probiotics on immune function and their relationship to antibiotic growth promoters in poultry, a brief review</article-title><source>Int. J. Probiotics Prebiotics</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dicks</surname><given-names>L.M.T</given-names></name><name><surname>Botes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotic lactic acid bacteria in the gastrointestinal tract: Health benefits, safety and mode of action</article-title><source>Benef. Microbes</source><year>2010</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21831747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bidarkar</surname><given-names>V.K</given-names></name><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>P.S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominic</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotics: Potential alternative to antibiotics in ruminant feeding</article-title><source>Trends Vet. Anim. Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Victor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>du Preez James</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cactus pear biomass, a potential lignocellulose raw material for single-cell protein production (SCP): A review</article-title><source>Int. J. Curr. Microbiol. Appl. Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>F.M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingston</surname><given-names>R.E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mppre</surname><given-names>D.D</given-names></name><name><surname>Seldman</surname><given-names>J.G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J.A</given-names></name><name><surname>Struhl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>Short Protocols in Molecular Biology</source><year>1992</year><edition>2nd ed</edition><publisher-loc>New York, Chichester, Brisbane, Toronto, Singapore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Willey &#x00026;Sons</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Benzinger</surname><given-names>M.J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Juenger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Agin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the VITEK 2 Gram-negative (GN) microbial identification test card: Collaborative study</article-title><source>J AOAC Int</source><year>2012</year><volume>95</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>778</fpage><lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22816270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Succi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremonte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Reale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrentino</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grazia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacifico</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bile salt and acid tolerance of <italic>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> strains isolated from parmigiano reggiano cheese</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett</source><year>2005</year><volume>244</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15727832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>S.E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of viable starter culture bacteria in yogurt on lactose utilization in humans</article-title><source>J. Dairy Sci</source><year>1984</year><volume>67</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solieri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mottolese</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemmetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Giudici</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tailoring the probiotic potential of non-starter <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> strains from ripened parmigiano reggiano cheese by <italic>in vitro</italic> screening and principal component analysis</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24290648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L.Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Y.W</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jalaludin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic effects of intestinal <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> isolates on pathogens of chicken</article-title><source>Lett. Appl. Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8987444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>AOAC</collab><source>Official Methods of Analysis</source><year>1990</year><edition>15th ed</edition><publisher-loc>Washington, DC, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Association of Official Analytical Chemists</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pincus</surname><given-names>D.H</given-names></name></person-group><source>Microbial Identification using the BioM&#x000e9;rieux Vitek 2 System. Encyclopedia of Rapid Microbiological Methods</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Parenteral Drug Association</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Surono</surname><given-names>I.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> probiotic properties of indigenous dadih lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>Asian Aust. J. Anim. Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>726</fpage><lpage>731</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation, identification and cellulase production of a cellulolytic bacterium from intestines of giant panda</article-title><source>Acta Microbial. Sin</source><year>2012</year><volume>52</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>11121</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and identification of cellulolytic bacteria from the gut of <italic>Holotrichia parallela</italic> larvae (<italic>Coleoptera Scarabaeidae</italic>)</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>2563</fpage><lpage>2577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22489111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>A.R</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>W.L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cursino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hungria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotegher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostasso</surname><given-names>F.L</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>J.L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity of endophytic enterobacteria associated with different host plants</article-title><source>J. Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18758726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S.B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J.S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>S.Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>N.S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J.H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of species-specific PCR primers and polyphasic characterization of <italic>Lactobacillus sanfranciscensis</italic> isolated from Korean sourdough</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>200</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25702881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zotta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricciardi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzymatic activities of lactic acid bacteria isolated from Cornetto di Matera sourdoughs</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>115</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17174429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>T.R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y.H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of an extracellular &#x003b2;-glucosidase II with high hydrolysis and transglucosylation activities from <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic></article-title><source>J. Agr. Food Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10554258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisaria</surname><given-names>V.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial &#x003b2;-glucosidases: Cloning, properties, and applications</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Biotechnol</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12487426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Surono</surname><given-names>I.S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Probiotik Susu Fermentasi dan Kesehatan</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Jakarta</publisher-loc><publisher-name>YAPMMI</publisher-name><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>151</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>C.N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>V.R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayford</surname><given-names>A.E</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000f8;ller</surname><given-names>P.L</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaelsen</surname><given-names>K.F</given-names></name><name><surname>Paerregaard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tvede</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of probiotic activities of forty-seven strains of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> spp. by <italic>in vitro</italic> techniques and evaluation of the colonization ability of five selected strains in humans</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microb</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>4949</fpage><lpage>4956</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Mahony</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Halloran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Feeney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiely</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> selection criteria for probiotic bacteria of human origin: Correlation with <italic>in vivo</italic> findings</article-title><source>Am. J. Clin. Nutr</source><year>2001</year><volume>73</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>386s</fpage><lpage>392s</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernardeau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernoux</surname><given-names>J.P</given-names></name><name><surname>Henri-Dubernet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gueguen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety assessment of dairy microorganisms: The <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> genus</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microb</source><year>2008</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>285</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massi</surname><given-names>M.B.V.F</given-names></name><name><surname>Federici</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Matteuzzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification e based on PCR combined with automated ribotyping for tracking probiotic <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> strains colonizing the human gut and vagina</article-title><source>J. Appl. Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>96</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nomoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention of infection by probiotics</article-title><source>J. Biosci. Bioeng</source><year>2005</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16473765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>T.M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>P.V.M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>K.K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of different lactic acid bacterial strains for probiotic characteristics</article-title><source>Vet. World</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>788</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balasingham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Valli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasuramanyam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotic characterization of lactic acid bacteria isolated from swine intestine</article-title><source>Vet. World</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28831230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and identification of probiotic lactic acid bacteria from curd and <italic>in vitro</italic> evaluation of its growth inhibition activities against pathogenic bacteria</article-title><source>Afr J. Microbiol. Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1419</fpage><lpage>1425</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Musikasang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>H-kittikun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maneerat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotic potential of lactic acid bacteria isolated from chicken gastrointestinal digestive tract</article-title><source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1337</fpage><lpage>1345</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>J.A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkholder</surname><given-names>K.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of prebiotics and probiotics in poultry production</article-title><source>Poult. Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>82</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12710484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rammelsberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Radler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial polypeptides of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> species</article-title><source>J. Appl. Bacteriol</source><year>1990</year><volume>69</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>184</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klaenhammer</surname><given-names>T.R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of bacteriocins produced by lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev</source><year>1993</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1-3</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8398217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Even</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Loir</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acidification is not involved in the early inhibition of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> growth by <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> in milk</article-title><source>Int. Dairy J</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>203</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W.H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>C.F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsen</surname><given-names>H.Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viable counts, characteristic evaluation for commercial lactic acid bacteria products</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16942989</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>