<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5829081</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">21954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-21954-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of strain distribution, migratory potential, and invasion history of fall armyworm populations in northern Sub-Saharan Africa</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>Rodney N.</given-names></name><address><email>rodney.nagoshi@ars.usda.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goergen</surname><given-names>Georg</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tounou</surname><given-names>Kodjo Agbeko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agboka</surname><given-names>Komi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koffi</surname><given-names>Djima</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>Robert L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0404 0958</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.463419.d</institution-id><institution>Center for Medical, Agricultural and Veterinary Entomology, </institution><institution>United States Department of Agriculture-Agricultural Research Service, </institution></institution-wrap>Gainesville, Florida United States of America </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419367.e</institution-id><institution>International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA), </institution></institution-wrap>Cotonou, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0647 9497</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12364.32</institution-id><institution>Ecole Sup&#x000e9;rieure d&#x02019;Agronomie, </institution><institution>Universit&#x000e9; de Lom&#x000e9;, </institution></institution-wrap>Lom&#x000e9;, Togo </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 1485</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8652.9</institution-id><institution>Africa Regional Postgraduate Programme in Insect Science, </institution><institution>University of Ghana, </institution></institution-wrap>Accra, Ghana </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>3710</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Fall armyworm (<italic>Spodoptera frugiperda</italic> J.E. Smith) is a noctuid moth pest endemic throughout the Western Hemisphere that has recently become widespread in sub-Saharan Africa. There is a strong expectation of significant damage to African maize crop yield and a high likelihood of further dispersal, putting the rest of the Eastern Hemisphere at risk. Specimens from multiple locations in six countries spanning the northern portion of the infested region were analyzed for genetic markers. The similarity of haplotypes between the African collections was consistent with a common origin, but significant differences in the relative frequency of the haplotypes indicated limitations in migration. The mitochondrial marker frequently used to identify two host strains appears to be compromised, making uncertain previous reports that both strains are present in Africa. This more extensive study confirmed initial indications based on Togo populations that Florida and the Greater Antilles are the likely source of at least a subset of the African infestation and further suggest an entry point in western Africa. The origin of a second subgroup is less clear as it was rarely found in the collections and has a haplotype that has not yet been observed in the Western Hemisphere.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The fall armyworm, <italic>Spodoptera frugiperda</italic> (J.E. Smith), is a noctuid moth indigenous to the Western Hemisphere where it has long been a major agricultural problem for both continents<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. It is primarily a pest of maize but has a wide host range and is capable of feeding on over 80 plant species, periodically causing significant economic damage to rice, sorghum, millet, soybean, wheat, alfalfa, cotton, turf, and fodder crops.</p><p id="Par3">Fall armyworm has recently become established in Africa, the first major introgression into the Eastern Hemisphere. The initial detection was on the island nation of S&#x000e3;o Tom&#x000e9; and Pr&#x000ed;ncipe in April 2016, followed by outbreaks in the western African countries of Benin, Nigeria, Ghana, and Togo reported in June 2016<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. As of October 2017, fall armyworm is present throughout most of sub-Saharan Africa<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. The infested region is predominated by smallholder farming with maize typically the most important staple food and a major component of livestock feed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. The damage from fall armyworm to African maize production could total $3 billion (USD) over the next year<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, with the potential for losses in other crops still to be determined.</p><p id="Par4">The apparent rapid spread of the pest in Africa suggests robust migratory movements that would be consistent with fall armyworm behavior in North America. Infestations extend as far north as Canada, the result of annual long-distance migrations from wintering areas limited in North America to the southern portions of Florida and Texas, the Caribbean, and Mexico<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. The timing of this behavior corresponds to the seasonal northward progression of warmer temperatures and maize planting that follows the winter season, and air transport systems favorable to northward long-distance flight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Projections from a migration model based on these factors accurately predicted fall armyworm migration patterns as validated by genetic haplotype studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. However, because climate, farming practices, and wind patterns are substantially different from North America, fall armyworm migratory behavior in Africa is uncertain, which is a considerable limitation to the development of regional and area-wide strategies for sustainable pest management.</p><p id="Par5">Western Hemisphere fall armyworm consists of two subpopulations that are morphologically indistinguishable but differ in their host plant distribution and certain physiological features<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. The rice-strain (R-strain) is most consistently found in millet and grass species associated with pasture habitats while the corn-strain (C-strain) prefers maize and sorghum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. The strains can only be identified using molecular markers whose association with specific host plants is generally consistent but not absolute<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. It is not known whether this variability reflects inaccuracy of the markers or plasticity in strain behavior. Contributing to the uncertainty is evidence that the strains are capable of cross-hybridization in the field, though at a significantly reduced frequency relative to within strain matings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. The behavior of these hybrids is not well understood, but they are preferentially found in maize habitats and so appear to retain a C-strain host bias<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">The C-strain can be subdivided into two geographically divided subgroups (FL-type and TX-type) on the basis of differences in the frequency of mitochondrial haplotypes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. The TX-type profile is found in most of the Western Hemisphere, with the FL-type limited to Florida and the Caribbean, as well as populations that migrate from Florida to annually infest the eastern coast of the U.S.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. The C-strain fall armyworm collected from the African country of Togo had a haplotype pattern most consistent with the FL-type<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Analogous haplotype differences for the R-strain have not yet been found, so it is unclear whether this group shows a similar geographical segregation.</p><p id="Par7">In this paper we expand on the previous Togo study to include specimens from multiple locations in the island nations of S&#x000e3;o Tom&#x000e9; and Pr&#x000ed;ncipe (Sao Tome) that lies approximately 300&#x02009;km from the Africa mainland, Burundi, Democratic Republic of Congo (D.R. Congo), Tanzania, and Kenya (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Genetic analysis was performed to confirm the fall armyworm species identification, determine host strain identity, and identify polymorphisms that can distinguish between geographically separated African populations. Comparisons between the haplotypes found in the different African locations and with those prevalent in the Western Hemisphere were used to extrapolate likely migratory source locations and the magnitude of fall armyworm population movements. The implications of these results on the origins of the fall armyworm introduction into Africa, the behavior and presence of the host strains, and migration patterns are discussed.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Source information for fall armyworm collections used in this study (DRC: Democratic Republic of Congo; Sao Tome: S&#x000e3;o Tom&#x000e9; and Pr&#x000ed;ncipe).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Country</th><th>Region/Province</th><th>Year</th><th>Latitude</th><th>Longitude</th><th>n</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Burundi</td><td>Cibitoke</td><td>2016</td><td>&#x02212;2.8869</td><td>29.1248</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Burundi</td><td>Bujumbura Mairie</td><td>2017</td><td>&#x02212;3.3065</td><td>29.3251</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>Burundi</td><td>Bubanza</td><td>2017</td><td>&#x02212;3.1393</td><td>29.2896</td><td>14</td></tr><tr><td>Burundi</td><td>Rumonge</td><td>2017</td><td>&#x02212;3.9731</td><td>29.4382</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>DRC</td><td>Haut-Katanga</td><td>2017</td><td>Multiple sites</td><td/><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>DRC</td><td>Sud-Ubangi</td><td>2017</td><td>Multiple sites</td><td/><td>27</td></tr><tr><td>Kenya</td><td>Meru</td><td>2017</td><td>&#x02212;0.0579</td><td>37.4681</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Kenya</td><td>Nakuru</td><td>2017</td><td>&#x02212;0.5214</td><td>36.0907</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Kenya</td><td>Homa Bay</td><td>2017</td><td>&#x02212;0.5046</td><td>34.4345</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>Kenya</td><td>Kirinyaga</td><td>2017</td><td>&#x02212;0.3099</td><td>37.2696</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Kenya</td><td>Kericho</td><td>2017</td><td>&#x02212;0.1241</td><td>35.3361</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Kenya</td><td>Narok</td><td>2017</td><td>&#x02212;0.9776</td><td>35.0463</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Sao Tome</td><td>Caue</td><td>2016</td><td>0.0351</td><td>6.5315</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Sao Tome</td><td>Cantagalo</td><td>2016</td><td>0.2853</td><td>6.7162</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Tanzania</td><td>Morogoro</td><td>2017</td><td>Multiple sites</td><td/><td>69</td></tr><tr><td>Togo</td><td>Maritime</td><td>2016</td><td>Multiple sites</td><td/><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Togo</td><td>Plateaux</td><td>2016</td><td>6.9889</td><td>0.6537</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">
<underline>Published Collections</underline>
</td><td colspan="3">
<underline>Reference</underline>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Togo</td><td colspan="3">Nagoshi <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Peru, Puerto Rico, Dominican Republic</td><td colspan="3">Nagoshi <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Florida, Texas</td><td colspan="3">Nagoshi <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par8">Fall armyworm identified by morphological criteria were analyzed by sequence analysis of segments from the presumptive coding region of the mitochondrial <italic>Cytochrome Oxidase Subunit I</italic> (<italic>COI</italic>) gene and the sex-linked <italic>Triosephosphate isomerase</italic> (<italic>Tpi</italic>) gene. All sequence variations observed were single base substitutions that did not alter the predicted amino acid sequence (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>DNA segments from the <italic>COI</italic> and <italic>Tpi</italic> genes analyzed in this study are described showing sites with base substitutions with the observed alternatives indicated by IUPAC symbols. Sites in bold and underlined show strain-specific variation in Western Hemisphere populations. Three sites in the <italic>Tpi</italic> fragment showed additional variation in the African populations (underlined and italicized) and two sites had variations that were not strain-specific. Sites 165, 168, and 183 had been previously described as 352, 355, and 370, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Primers used for PCR amplification and DNA sequencing are displayed at the ends of each DNA segment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_21954_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e826"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Little <italic>COI</italic> variation in Africa</title><p id="Par9">The CO1A segment was used to confirm species identification by comparisons with barcode sequences in GenBank. Of the 188 African specimens analyzed for CO1A, three displayed barcodes inconsistent with fall armyworm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Two from Togo (TogAL12.5 and TogAL13.2) shared a haplotype most similar to <italic>Sesamia calamistis</italic> Hampson (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) and one from Kenya (KenAL65.1) clustered with <italic>Busseola fusca</italic> Fuller (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae). Both species are native to Africa and are pests of maize and sorghum. The remaining specimens contained two CO1A haplotypes identical to that found in a previous study of Togo fall armyworms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. One sequence was identical to a variant of the C-strain group (<italic>COI</italic>-CS01) and the other to a R-strain haplotype (<italic>COI</italic>-RS09) that are both common in the Western Hemisphere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. The <italic>COI</italic> strain grouping determined by CO1A was confirmed by analysis of the downstream segment COIB. Again, only two haplotypes were observed, one for each strain. These differed at the same 12 sites that differentiate the consensus <italic>COI</italic>-CS and <italic>COI</italic>-RS haplotypes derived from Western Hemisphere populations (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Strict consensus phylogenetic tree derived from neighbor- joining analysis comparing the two African <italic>COI</italic> haplotypes (<italic>COI</italic>) with those from fall armyworm host strains and related <italic>Spodoptera</italic> species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. <italic>COI</italic>-CS01 and <italic>COI</italic>-RS09 are fall armyworm haplotypes common to the Western Hemisphere fall armyworm. The analogous <italic>COI</italic> barcode segment from <italic>Helicoverpa armigera</italic> was use as the outgroup. The tree is based on Kimura-2-Parameter distances. Numbers at branch points indicate 2000X bootstrap values. Scale bar represents substitutions per site. GenBank accession numbers are provided for each species.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_21954_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e906"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Single nucleotide differences between the consensus <italic>COI</italic>-CS and <italic>COI</italic>-RS haplotypes based on Western Hemisphere (W.H.) fall armyworm for the COIA and COIB segments compared to that found in Africa (AFR). The numbers of each haplotype found in the Africa and Western Hemisphere collections from maize and sorghum habitats are listed.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Haplotype</th><th colspan="5">COIA</th><th colspan="7">COIB</th><th rowspan="2">Africa</th><th rowspan="2">W.H.</th></tr><tr><th>489</th><th>564</th><th>570</th><th>600</th><th>634</th><th>1125</th><th>1164</th><th>1176</th><th>1182</th><th>1197</th><th>1216</th><th>1287</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>W.H. <italic>COI</italic>-CS</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td>R</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>T</td><td>R</td><td/><td>427</td></tr><tr><td>W.H. <italic>COI</italic>-RS</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>A</td><td>A</td><td>A</td><td/><td>272</td></tr><tr><td>AFR <italic>COI</italic>-CS</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td>G</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>T</td><td>G</td><td>70</td><td/></tr><tr><td>AFR <italic>COI</italic>-RS</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>A</td><td>A</td><td>A</td><td>180</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>COIB haplotype suggests a Florida-Caribbean origin</title><p id="Par10">Variants of two sites in the COIB segment, mCOI1164D and mCOI1287R, show geographical differences in frequency. In the Western Hemisphere <italic>COI</italic>-CS subgroup both sites vary by either an A or a G, producing the configurations of A<sub>1164</sub>A<sub>1287</sub>, A<sub>1164</sub>G<sub>1287</sub>, G<sub>1164</sub>A<sub>1287</sub>, and G<sub>1164</sub>G<sub>1287</sub>. The A<sub>1164</sub>G<sub>1287</sub> subtype predominates in South America and Texas while G<sub>1164</sub>G<sub>1287</sub> is the majority form in Florida and the Greater Antilles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A,B</xref>). In comparison, the 70 C-strain fall armyworm specimens characterized from Africa were all of the G<sub>1164</sub>G<sub>1287</sub> haplotype, consistent with the results of 43 specimens previously examined from Togo<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3C</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Frequency distributions of the COIB haplotype that differentiates geographical populations in the Western Hemisphere are described for Africa. The Y-axis indicates proportion of the population sampled. Numbers in parenthesis are total samples tested. Asterisk indicates data from previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_21954_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1267"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Disagreement between <italic>COI</italic> and <italic>Tpi</italic> markers</title><p id="Par11">All specimens from Africa were collected from maize or sorghum, host plants associated with the C-strain population. Yet surprisingly the majority of specimens (72%, 180/250) carried the R-strain <italic>COI</italic>-RS haplotype rather than the expected <italic>COI</italic>-CS majority observed in the Western Hemisphere collections (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). A subset of these was additionally tested for the <italic>Tpi</italic> strain markers, which gave a very different result. The C-strain <italic>Tpi-</italic>C haplotype as defined by C<sub>183</sub> was found in 86% (203/243) of the African specimens with only three displaying the R-strain <italic>Tpi-</italic>R marker (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3A</xref>). These frequencies were comparable to that observed in the previous study of Togo fall armyworm and similar to that found in Western Hemisphere collections from analogous C-strain host plants (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3A</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><italic>Tpi</italic> haplotypes observed in Africa (AFR) are defined based on differential base substitutions and their frequencies are compared with that observed in the Western Hemisphere (W.H.). Variants shown to be strain-specific in W.H. populations are italicized and in bold. Togo data from Nagoshi <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">A. Tpi categories</th><th colspan="11">Tpi SNPs</th></tr><tr><th>129</th><th>144</th><th>
<italic>165</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>168</italic>
</th><th>180</th><th>
<italic>183</italic>
</th><th>192</th><th>198</th><th>Togo</th><th>AFR</th><th>W.H.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>a. <italic>Tpi-</italic>C</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>C</td><td/><td/><td>58</td><td>203</td><td>435</td></tr><tr><td>b. <italic>Tpi-</italic>R</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>174</td></tr><tr><td>c. <italic>Tpi-</italic>H (a/b)</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>Y</td><td/><td/><td>2</td><td>37</td><td>90</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12">B. <italic>Tpi</italic>-C category</td></tr><tr><td>d. <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca1</td><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>0.37</td><td>0.60</td><td>0.33</td></tr><tr><td>e. <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ca2</td><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td>0.27</td><td>0.07</td><td>0.22</td></tr><tr><td>f. <italic>Tpi</italic>-CaH (d/e)</td><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>0.37</td><td>0.33</td><td>0.37</td></tr><tr><td>other</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.08</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12">C. <italic>Tpi-</italic>R category</td></tr><tr><td>g. <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ra1</td><td>T</td><td>A</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>1.00</td><td>1.00</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>W.H. Variants</td><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.79</td></tr><tr><td/><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.08</td></tr><tr><td/><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td/><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>A</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td/><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>G</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td/><td>A</td><td>G</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.01</td></tr><tr><td/><td>C</td><td>A</td><td>T</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.01</td></tr><tr><td/><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.01</td></tr><tr><td/><td>C</td><td>G</td><td>G</td><td>C</td><td>T</td><td>T</td><td/><td/><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12">D. <italic>Tpi-</italic>h category</td></tr><tr><td>TpiHafrCC (d/g)</td><td>Y</td><td>R</td><td>C</td><td>Y</td><td>S</td><td>Y</td><td>C</td><td>C</td><td>0.09</td><td>0.59</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>TpiHafrYY (e/g)</td><td>Y</td><td>R</td><td>C</td><td>Y</td><td>S</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>0.91</td><td>0.41</td><td>0.00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Geographical differences in the distribution of <italic>COI</italic> and <italic>Tpi</italic> haplotypes</title><p id="Par12">The sex-linked <italic>Tpi</italic> gene segregates independently from the maternally-inherited mitochondrial <italic>COI</italic> gene. Despite this, Western Hemisphere fall armyworm populations consistently displayed high levels of concordance between the markers, i.e., marker configurations of <italic>CO1</italic>-CS <italic>Tpi-</italic>C and <italic>COI</italic>-RS <italic>Tpi-</italic>R, which suggests strong biases for mating within rather than between strains (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref>). In pooled collections from C-strain host plants in the Americas, 51% were <italic>CO1</italic>-CS Tpi-<italic>C</italic> and 26% <italic>COI</italic>-RS <italic>Tpi-</italic>R, giving a concordance frequency of 77%. This Western Hemisphere profile showed a significant positive correlation with that found for the two western Africa nations of Togo and Sao Tome, where the pooled collections also had a majority (53%) concordance (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). In contrast, the Western Hemisphere profile showed no significant correlation with profiles from the central or eastern collection sites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C,D</xref>). The central collections from Burundi and D. R. Congo appeared to give an intermediate pattern with roughly equal amounts of the concordant and discordant types (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>), while the most eastern sites (Tanzania, Kenya) were dominated by the discordant <italic>COI</italic>-RS <italic>Tpi-</italic>C configuration (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4D</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Frequencies of <italic>COI</italic> and <italic>Tpi</italic> haplotype combinations for different regions in Africa are described and compared to those found in fall armyworm from the Americas. Haplotypes are configurations represent those found in all collections and can be categorized as concordant, <italic>COI</italic>-CS <italic>Tpi</italic>-C and <italic>COI</italic>-RS <italic>Tpi</italic>-R; discordant, <italic>COI</italic>-CS <italic>Tpi</italic>-R and <italic>COI</italic>-RS <italic>Tpi</italic>-C, and hybrid, <italic>COI</italic>-CS <italic>Tpi</italic>-h, and <italic>COI</italic>-RS <italic>Tpi</italic>-h. The Western Hemisphere (W.H.) graph includes data from South America (Argentina, Brazil, Bolivia) and North America (Florida, Texas). Statistical metrics are from Pearson correlation tests comparing the pooled W.H. profile with the pooled frequency profiles from each region. The value for Togo (*) combines new data with that previously published<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Numbers after locations denote total samples analyzed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_21954_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2165"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">The distribution of the <italic>COI</italic>-CS haplotype showed substantial differences between collections that also appeared to be aligned along an east-west axis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The <italic>COI</italic>-CS group was the majority in collections from the two most western African nations tested (Togo, Sao Tome) and progressively declined eastward, with the two most eastern locations (Kenya and Tanzania) showing a frequency of less than 10%. The mean frequency for Togo and Sao Tome was significantly different from that of the more eastern collections.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Frequencies of <italic>COI</italic>-CS and <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ca2 haplotype frequencies for different regions are indicated on a map of Africa. Togo (<bold>B</bold>) data are from previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, Togo (<bold>B</bold>) data from this study. Numbers above columns indicate total specimens for each collection. Means for groupings are indicated above horizontal line with Standard Error of the Mean. Statistical metrics are from two-tailed parametric <italic>t</italic>-test comparing the two means (West and Rest) for each haplotype. Circles on map approximate locations of sample collections. The map was created using Quantum Geographic Information System version 2.18.2 (QGIS Development Team (2016). QGIS Geographic Information System. Open Source Geospatial Foundation Project. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://qgis.osgeo.org">http://qgis.osgeo.org</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_21954_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2210"/></fig></p><p id="Par14">Two additional sites in the <italic>Tpi</italic> exon were previously shown to be highly variable in the Western Hemisphere but with much reduced strain specificity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Sites gTpi192Y and gTpi198Y were similarly polymorphic in the Africa collection, subdividing the <italic>Tpi-</italic>C group into two haplotypes designated <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca1 (with C<sub>192</sub>C<sub>198</sub>) and <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca2 (T<sub>192</sub>T<sub>198</sub>), as well as a third group, <italic>Tpi-</italic>CaH (Y<sub>192</sub>Y<sub>198</sub>) whose DNA chromatograph pattern was consistent with a <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca1/<italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca2 heterozygote (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2B</xref>). All three of these haplotype groups were also found in the Western Hemisphere at similar proportions. Once again there is evidence of east-west differences in frequency, with populations from Togo and Sao Tome showing the highest <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ca2 frequencies that were significantly different from the other collections (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>The African <italic>Tpi</italic>-R haplotype appears unique</title><p id="Par15">Comparisons between <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca1 and <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca2 with the African <italic>Tpi-</italic>R variant (designated <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1) identified five differing sites in addition to the strain diagnostic gTpi183Y. Two sites, gTpi165Y and gTpi168Y, exhibit strain-specific variation in Western Hemisphere populations with &#x0003e;80% of <italic>Tpi</italic>-R specimens showing a different nucleotide than found in <italic>Tpi</italic>-C (Table 3BC). In contrast, only gTpi168Y differed between the African <italic>Tpi-</italic>C and <italic>Tpi-</italic>R variants (Table 3BC). In addition, <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1 differed from both <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ca1 and <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ca2 at three sites (gTpi129Y, gTpi144R, and gTpi180S) that are not strain-specific and are infrequently variable in the Western Hemisphere collections. To date the African <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1 haplotype has not been found in a survey of 699 specimens from the Western Hemisphere (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3C</xref>).</p><p id="Par16">The DNA sequence chromatographs for the <italic>Tpi-</italic>h group showed overlapping peaks at each of the sites that differed between the two African strain haplotypes (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3D</xref>). This pattern is consistent with heterozygosity between <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1 and either <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca1 or <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca2, indicating that the two African host strains as defined by <italic>Tpi</italic> can productively hybridize.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par17">In this and a previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, approximately 300 specimens from six African nations have been genetically characterized for markers in the <italic>COI</italic> and <italic>Tpi</italic> genes. The results show very little genetic variability in the African fall armyworm population with only two <italic>COI</italic> and three <italic>Tpi</italic> haplotypes found. Both <italic>COI</italic> variants and the two <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ca haplotypes were observed in all Africa locations and are common forms in the Western Hemisphere. In contrast, the African <italic>Tpi-</italic>R variant, <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1, is so far unique to Africa (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Only four <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1 specimens were found, two from Togo (both <italic>COI</italic>-RS), one from D. R. Congo (<italic>COI</italic>-CS), and one from Kenya (<italic>COI</italic>-RS), while the putative <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1/<italic>Tpi-</italic>CSa heterozygotes (the <italic>Tpi</italic>-h category) were present in all locations. Therefore, while the <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1 haplotype is rare in the collections from maize and sorghum, it is widely disseminated. These results in conjunction with the first detection of African fall armyworm infestations in 2016&#x02013;2017<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> are consistent with a recent introduction of a small invasive C-strain population that migrated rapidly throughout the northern Sub-Saharan region of the African continent. The history of the <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ra1 subgroup is less clear, as too few have been collected to test for regional differences and its presence in the Western Hemisphere has yet to be demonstrated.</p><p id="Par18">While the fall armyworm in the surveyed portion of Africa shared a common source, geographical differences in haplotype frequencies suggest that long distance movements between distant locations were not of sufficient magnitude or consistency to homogenize geographically distant populations. Geographical structure is indicated by three haplotype distributions, each consistent with dispersion along an east-west axis (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). If these differences persist over time it would indicate that annual migrations in Africa tend to be more regional than continental, with the described marker combinations providing a means to define migratory limits and the area sharing a common population.</p><p id="Par19">Current data are too preliminary to make definitive conclusions about either the Western Hemisphere source(s) of the invasive population or their site(s) of introduction into Africa. Multiyear data are needed as well as surveys from southern Africa. Nevertheless, the results provide some preliminary indications. The distribution of concordant and discordant <italic>COI</italic> and <italic>Tpi</italic> marker combinations vary considerably across Africa, with the frequency profile of the Western Hemisphere positively correlating with that of the most western collection sites (Togo and Sao Tome) but not to the other more eastern locations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). This finding is most consistent with fall armyworm from the Western Hemisphere first entering through western Africa.</p><p id="Par20">There is also evidence that identify the likely Western Hemisphere source of the Africa fall armyworm. All 108 of the <italic>CO1</italic>-CS fall armyworm from Africa analyzed at COIB have the G<sub>1164</sub>G<sub>1287</sub> SNP configuration. This is the predominant <italic>CO1</italic>-CS variant found in the Greater Antilles and Florida, with the latter being the source of migratory infestations in the eastern United States, but is rare in South America and relatively infrequent in Texas and the central regions of the United States. Therefore, we believe that the most likely source of the surveyed <italic>COI</italic>-CS fall armyworm in at least northern Sub-Saharan Africa are populations that normally winter in the Caribbean or Florida. This was first indicated by our earlier genetic survey of Togo<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, with the additional collections confirming that finding and suggestive of a single introduction for the northern Sub-Saharan region. If multiple introductions occurred, it appears they all originated from the same Western Hemisphere source.</p><p id="Par21">The origin of the <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1 haplotype is not clear and its apparent scarcity in the Western Hemisphere is surprising. The few <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ra1 specimens found carry the same two <italic>CO1</italic> haplotypes as the African <italic>CO1</italic>-CS group, suggesting that both originated from a common source. Therefore, we believe the most parsimonious explanation is a single introduction of both strains into Africa with a subset happening to carry a rare <italic>Tpi</italic> haplotype variant. However, we cannot completely discount the possibility that the <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1 subgroup may not be present in the Western Hemisphere and so has a different origin, perhaps even representing a fall armyworm population native to Africa. Furthermore, it is not clear whether the <italic>Tpi-</italic>Ra1 group is simply a variant of the African C-strain population (<italic>i.e</italic>., the gTpi183Y site is not strain-specific in Africa) or is representative of a more abundant R-strain that is present in habitats not yet surveyed. Characterization of additional <italic>Tpi-</italic>R specimens from Africa and surveys of different habitats should clarify this issue.</p><p id="Par22">This and other studies have shown that the <italic>COI</italic>-RS haplotype is present throughout Africa and is the predominant group in some locations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. However, two observations indicate that <italic>COI</italic>-RS is not behaving as an accurate marker of the R-strain. The first is its high frequency in collections from traditional C-strain host plants (maize, sorghum), particularly in the central and eastern collection sites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). While such events have been reported in the Western Hemisphere, they are not the norm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. The second is the predominance of the discordant configuration in parts of Africa, indicating dissociation between the <italic>COI</italic> and <italic>Tpi</italic> strain haplotypes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C,D</xref>). The reason for this loss of <italic>COI</italic> strain specificity can only be speculated, but could result from interstrain hybridization producing discordant configurations that by chance became predominant. Overall, we believe the data to date leaves uncertain whether the R-strain is present in Africa, particularly since the collections were limited to host plants preferred by the C-strain and so may not be representative of the total African population.</p><p id="Par23">In conclusion, genetic characterization of portions of the <italic>COI</italic> and <italic>Tpi</italic> genes demonstrate a common origin for the recent infestation of fall armyworm over the northern portion of Sub-Saharan Africa and provide preliminary indications of where in Africa fall armyworm was first introduced and the likely Western Hemisphere source population. Haplotype distribution profiles identify differences between geographical populations that have the potential for defining fall armyworm migration patterns. This will have important ramifications for the design of area-wide strategies to mitigate infestations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Specimen Collections and DNA preparation</title><p id="Par24">Specimens were obtained as larvae from corn (maize) or sorghum plants at various locations in northern Sub-Saharan Africa at various times in 2016 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Specimens were stored either air-dried or in ethanol at room temperature. A portion of each specimen was excised and homogenized in a 5-ml Dounce homogenizer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) in 800&#x02009;&#x000b5;l Genomic Lysis buffer (Zymo Research, Orange, CA, USA) and incubated at 55&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02013;30&#x02009;min. Debris was removed by centrifugation at 10,000&#x02009;rpm for 5&#x02009;min. The supernatant was transferred to a Zymo-Spin III column (Zymo Research, Orange, CA, USA) and processed according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The DNA preparation was increased to a final volume of 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;l with distilled water. Genomic DNA preparations of fall armyworm samples from previous studies were stored at &#x02212;20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Genetic markers and nomenclature</title><p id="Par25">The genetic markers are all single nucleotide substitutions. Sites in the <italic>COI</italic> gene are designated by an &#x0201c;m&#x0201d; (mitochondria) while <italic>Tpi</italic> sites are designated &#x0201c;g&#x0201d; (genomic). This is followed by the gene name, number of base pairs from the predicted translational start site (<italic>COI</italic>) or 5&#x02032; start of exon (<italic>Tpi</italic>), and the nucleotides observed using IUPAC convention (R: A or G, Y: C or T, W: A or T, K: G or T, S: C or G, D: A or G or T). Sites gTpi165Y, gTpi168Y, and gTpi183Y were previously described as 352, 355, and 370<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Characterization of the <italic>CO1</italic> and <italic>Tpi</italic> gene segments</title><p id="Par26">The <italic>COI</italic> markers are from the maternally inherited mitochondrial genome. Two adjacent segments of <italic>CO1</italic> were analyzed by DNA sequencing. The <italic>COI</italic>A segment was amplified by the <italic>COI</italic> primers <italic>JM76</italic> and <italic>JM77</italic> and used to confirm species identity and to determine the fall armyworm <italic>COI</italic> strain haplotypes <italic>COI</italic>-CS (C-strain) and <italic>CO1</italic>-RS (R-strain)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. The DNA sequences of the fall armyworm host strains and other <italic>Spodoptera</italic> species were previously described and available in GenBank<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. DNA alignments and consensus building were performed using MUSCLE (multiple sequence comparison by log-expectation), a public domain multiple alignment software incorporated into the Geneious Pro 10.1.2 program (Biomatters, New Zealand, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneious.com">http://www.geneious.com</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Phylogenetic trees were graphically displayed in a neighbor-joining (NJ) tree analysis also included in the Geneious Pro 10.1.2 program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The adjacent COIB segment was amplified by <italic>CO1</italic> primers 891&#x02009;F and 1472&#x02009;R and used to confirm host strain identity and determine the region-specific haplotypes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">Variants in the <italic>Triosephosphate isomerase</italic> gene (<italic>Tpi</italic>) can also be used to identify host strain identity with results generally comparable with the <italic>CO1</italic> marker [30, 31]. The gTpi183Y site is on the fourth exon of the predicted <italic>Tpi</italic> coding region and was PCR amplified using the <italic>Tpi</italic> primers 412&#x02009;F and 850&#x02009;R (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The C-strain allele (<italic>Tpi</italic>-C) is indicated by a C<sub>183</sub> and the R-strain (<italic>Tpi</italic>-R) by T<sub>183</sub><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. The <italic>Tpi</italic> gene is located on the <italic>Z</italic> sex chromosome that is present in one copy in females and two copies in males. Since males can be heterozygous for <italic>Tpi</italic>, there is the potential for the simultaneous display of both alternative nucleotides at <italic>Tpi</italic><sub>183</sub> (denoted as <italic>Tpi-</italic>h), which would be indicated by an overlapping C and T DNA sequence chromatograph<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par28">PCR amplification for all segments was performed in a 30-&#x000b5;l reaction mix containing 3&#x02009;&#x000b5;l 10X manufacturer&#x02019;s reaction buffer, 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;l 10&#x02009;mM dNTP, 0.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;l 20-&#x000b5;M primer mix, 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;l DNA template (between 0.05&#x02013;0.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;g), 0.5 unit Taq DNA polymerase (New England Biolabs, Beverly, MA). The thermocycling program was 94&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (1&#x02009;min), followed by 33 cycles of 92&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (30&#x02009;s), 56&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (45&#x02009;s), 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (45&#x02009;s), and a final segment of 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;min. Typically 96 PCR amplifications were performed at the same time using either 0.2-ml tube strips or 96 well microtiter plates. All primers were obtained from Integrated DNA Technologies (Coralville, IA). Amplification of the <italic>CO1</italic> barcode region was performed using primers <italic>JM76</italic> (5&#x02032;-GAGCTGAATTAGGGACTCC-3&#x02032;) and <italic>JM77</italic> (5&#x02032;-ATCACCTCCACCTGCAGGATC-3&#x02032;) to produce a 569-bp fragment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Amplification of the <italic>CO1</italic> segment used to determine haplotypes used the primer pair <italic>891&#x02009;F</italic> (5&#x02032;-TACACGAGCATATTTTACATC-3&#x02032;) and <italic>1472&#x02009;R</italic> (5&#x02032;-GCTGGTGGTAAATTTTGATATC-3&#x02032;) to produce a 603-bp fragment. Amplification of the <italic>Tpi</italic> gene segment used the primers <italic>412&#x02009;F</italic> (5&#x02032;-CCGGACTGAAGGTTATCGCTTG-3&#x02032;) and <italic>850&#x02009;R</italic> (5&#x02032;-AATTTTATTACCTGCTGTGG-3&#x02032;) to produce a fragment containing most of the fourth exon with an approximate length of 199&#x02009;bp.</p><p id="Par29">For fragment isolations, 6&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of 6X gel loading buffer was added to each amplification reaction and the entire sample run on a 1.8% agarose horizontal gel containing GelRed (Biotium, Hayward, CA) in 0.5X Tris-borate buffer (TBE, 45&#x02009;mM Tris base, 45&#x02009;mM boric acid, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA pH 8.0). Fragments were visualized on a long-wave UV light box and manually cut out from the gel. Fragment isolation was performed using Zymo-Spin I columns (Zymo Research, Orange, CA) according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The University of Florida Interdisciplinary Center for Biotechnology (Gainesville, FL) and Genewiz (South Plainfield, NJ) performed the DNA sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Data Availability</title><p id="Par30">All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article. Sequences deposited into GenBank include COIA haplotypes TogAL12.5 (MG603699), TogA13.2 (MG603700), KenAL65.1 (MG603701), and <italic>Tpi</italic> haplotypes <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ca1 (MG603702), <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ca2 (MG603703), and <italic>Tpi</italic>-Ra1 (MG603704).</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Moses Ndotono (ICIPE) for important specimen collections, Dr. Paul Shirk (USDA-ARS) and Dr. Steven Valles (USDA-ARS) for advice on the manuscript, Mr. Mawuko Anani Kossi Adjevi for assistance in collecting and preparing specimens, and Ms. Jean Thomas for technical assistance. Support came from the Agricultural Research Service of the United States Department of Agriculture, USAID, and the United States Department of Agriculture National Institutes for Food and Agriculture (2011-67003-30209). The use of trade, firm, or corporation names in this publication is for the information and convenience of the reader. Such use does not constitute an official endorsement or approval by the United States Department of Agriculture or the Agricultural Research Service of any product or service to the exclusion of others that may be suitable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>R.N.N., G.G., R.L.M. designed the experiment; G.G., K.A.T., K.A., R.L.M. and D.K. collected field specimens and field data (K.A.T, K.A., and D.K. contributed equally); R.N.N. collected the genetic data, analyzed the results, and wrote the manuscript; all authors reviewed the manuscript</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par31">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay-Roe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring the annual migration patterns of fall armyworm (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) in the United States from mitochondrial haplotypes</article-title><source>Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1458</fpage><lpage>1467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.268</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22957154?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22957154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goergen, G., Kumar, P. L., Sankung, S. B., Togola, A. &#x00026; Tamo, M. First report of outbreaks of the fall armyworm <italic>Spodoptera frugiperda</italic> (J E Smith) (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae), a new alien invasive pest in West and Central Africa. <italic>Plos One</italic><bold>11</bold> (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cock, M. J. W., Beseh, P. K., Buddie, A. G., Cafa, G. &#x00026; Crozier, J. Molecular methods to detect Spodoptera frugiperda in Ghana, and implications for monitoring the spread of invasive species in developing countries. <italic>Sci Rep-Uk</italic><bold>7</bold> (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">FAO. <italic>Briefing Note on FAO Actions on Fall Armyworm in Africa, Oct. 1, 2017</italic>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/3/a-bt415e.pdf">http://www.fao.org/3/a-bt415e.pdf</ext-link> (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranum</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pena-Rosas</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Casal</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global maize production, utilization, and consumption</article-title><source>Ann Ny Acad Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>1312</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nyas.12396</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24650320?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24650320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stokstad</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FOOD SECURITY New crop pest takes Africa at lightning speed</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.356.6337.473</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28473543?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28473543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Seasonal periodicity of fall armyworm, (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) in the Caribbean basin and northward to Canada</article-title><source>J Entomol Sci</source><year>1991</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18474/0749-8004-26.1.39</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pair</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Raulston</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fall armyworm (Lepidoptera:Noctuidae) outbreak originating in the lower Rio-Grande Valley, 1989</article-title><source>Florida Entomologist</source><year>1991</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3495298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischer</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jairam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling seasonal migration of fall armyworm moths</article-title><source>Int J Biometeorol</source><year>2016</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00484-015-1022-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26045330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26045330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pashley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host-associated genetic differentiation in fall armyworm (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae) - a sibling species complex</article-title><source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source><year>1986</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>898</fpage><lpage>904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aesa/79.6.898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pashley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative genetics, development, and physiological adaptation in host strains of fall armyworm</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1988</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28563847?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28563847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pashley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproductive isolating mechanisms in fall armyworm host strains (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae)</article-title><source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source><year>1992</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aesa/85.4.400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ju&#x000e1;rez</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Population structure of <italic>Spodoptera frugiperda</italic> maize and rice host forms in South America: are they host strains?</article-title><source>Entomol Exp Appl</source><year>2014</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eea.12215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavior and distribution of the two fall armyworm host strains in Florida</article-title><source>Florida Entomologist</source><year>2004</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1653/0015-4040(2004)087[0440:BADOTT]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pashley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Quisenberry</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamjanya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowd</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two fall armyworm strains feed on corn, rice and bermudagrass</article-title><source>Louisiana Agriculture Magazine</source><year>1987</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population dynamics and occurrence of <italic>Spodoptera frugiperda</italic> host strains in southern Florida</article-title><source>Ecol Entomol</source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0307-6946.2004.00629.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prowell</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>McMichael</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvain</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multilocus genetic analysis of host use, introgression, and speciation in host strains of fall armyworm (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)</article-title><source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source><year>2004</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1034</fpage><lpage>1044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0013-8746(2004)097[1034:MGAOHU]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kost</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckel</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshido</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marec</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Groot</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Z-linked sterility locus causes sexual abstinence in hybrid females and facilitates speciation in <italic>Spodoptera frugiperda</italic></article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2016</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1418</fpage><lpage>1427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/evo.12940</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27149933?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27149933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nagoshi, R. N., Fleischer, S. J. &#x00026; Meagher, R. L. Demonstration and quantification of restricted mating between fall armyworm host strains in field collections by SNP comparisons. <italic>J Econ Entomol</italic> in press (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fall armyworm Triosephosphate Isomerase (<italic>Tpi</italic>) gene as a marker of strain identity and interstrain mating</article-title><source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source><year>2010</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/AN09046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Haplotype profile comparisons between Sp<italic>odoptera frugiperda</italic> (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) populations from Mexico with those from Puerto Rico, South America, and the United States and their implications to migratory behavior</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>2015</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/tou044</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26470113?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26470113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of haplotype frequencies differentiate fall armyworm (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) corn-strain populations from Florida and Brazil</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>2007</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>954</fpage><lpage>961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/100.3.954</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17598561?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17598561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fall armyworm migration across the Lesser Antilles and the potential for genetic exchanges between North and South American populations</article-title><source>Plos One</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0171743</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0171743</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28166292?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28166292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using haplotypes to monitor the migration of fall armyworm (Lepidoptera:Noctuidae) corn-strain populations from Texas and Florida</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>2008</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>742</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/101.3.742</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18613574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18613574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Puerto Rico fall armyworm has only limited interactions with those from Brazil or Texas but could have substantial exchanges with Florida populations</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>2010</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/EC09253</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20429449?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20429449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nagoshi, R. N. <italic>et al</italic>. Comparative molecular analyses of invasive fall armyworm in Togo reveal strong similarities to populations from the eastern United States and the Greater Antilles. <italic>Plos One</italic><bold>12</bold> (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nagoshi, R. N., Brambila, J. &#x00026; Meagher, R. L. Use of DNA barcodes to identify invasive armyworm <italic>Spodoptera</italic> species in Florida. <italic>J Insect Sci</italic> 11:154 available online: 431 insectscience.org/11.154 (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mur&#x000fa;a</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Demonstration using field collections that Argentina fall armyworm populations exhibit strain-specific host plant preferences</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>2015</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>2305</fpage><lpage>2315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/tov203</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26453719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26453719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvements in the identification of strains facilitate population studies of fall armyworm subgroups</article-title><source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source><year>2012</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/AN11138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Maruniak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruniak</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strain identification of Spodoptera frugiperda (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) insects and cell line: PCR-RFLP of cytochrome oxidase C subunit I gene</article-title><source>Florida Entomologist</source><year>2002</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1653/0015-4040(2002)085[0186:SIOSFL]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kearse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geneious Basic: An integrated and extendable desktop software platform for the organization and analysis of sequence data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1647</fpage><lpage>1649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts199</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22543367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22543367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Neighbor-Joining method - a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title><source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><year>1987</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3447015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>