<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5960721</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.00597</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Absorption and Bio-Transformation of Selenium Nanoparticles by Wheat Seedlings (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Huafen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/515996/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jixiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Guishen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Wenliang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Liping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Yanbin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/505306/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>College of Resources and Environmental Sciences, China Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Beijing Key Laboratory of Biodiversity and Organic Farming, China Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Beijing Key Laboratory of Diagnostic and Trace Ability Technologies for Food Poisoning, Beijing Center for Disease Prevention and Control</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Victoria Fernandez, Universidad Polit&#x000e9;cnica de Madrid (UPM), Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Swati Rawat, The University of Texas at El Paso, United States; Yuhui Ma, Institute of High Energy Physics (CAS), China; Jose R. Peralta-Videa, The University of Texas at El Paso, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Yanbin Guo <email>guoyb@cau.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Nutrition, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>597</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Hu, Li, Li, Zhao, Wu, Liu, Wang and Guo.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hu, Li, Li, Zhao, Wu, Liu, Wang and Guo</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Elemental selenium is one of the dominant selenium species in soil, but the mechanism of its uptake by plants is still unclear. In this study, nanoparticles of elemental selenium (SeNPs) with different sizes were prepared, and their uptake and transformation in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) were analyzed in hydroponic experiments by HPLC-ICP-MS. We found that the SeNPs can be absorbed by wheat seedlings, and the process is energy independent. The addition of aquaporins inhibitor caused 92.5 and 93.4% inhibition of chemosynthesized SeNPs (CheSeNPs) and biosynthesized SeNPs (BioSeNPs) absorption by wheat roots, respectively. The 40 nm SeNPs uptake by wheat roots was 1.8-fold and 2.2-fold higher than that of 140 and 240 nm, respectively. The rate of SeNPs uptake in wheat was much slower than that of selenite [Se (IV)], and CheSeNPs were more efficiently absorbed than BioSeNPs. The SeNPs were rapidly oxidized to Se (IV) and converted to organic forms [selenocystine (SeCys<sub>2</sub>), se-methyl-selenocysteine (MeSeCys), and selenomethionine (SeMet)] after they were absorbed by wheat roots. Additionally, we demonstrated that the aquaporin function in some way is related to the absorption of SeNPs. The particle size and synthesis method of the SeNPs affected their uptake rates by plants. Taken together, our results provide a deep understanding of the SeNPs uptake mechanism in plants.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>HPLC-ICP-MS</kwd><kwd>selenium nanoparticles</kwd><kwd>selenium speciation</kwd><kwd>transformation</kwd><kwd>uptake</kwd><kwd>wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="54"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="8329"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Selenium (Se) is an essential trace element for mammals, and has important physiological functions such as antioxidation, anticarcinogenic effects, and immunity stimulation (Fairweather-Tait et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Selenium is found ubiquitously but is geographically variable in the environment, and is transferred through the geochemical cycle rock-soil-water-plants-mammals (Peters et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The daily intake of Se varies geographically, in the world, 0.5&#x02013;1 billion people have a Se intake below the recommended 55 &#x003bc;g day<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and have been estimated to be Se-deficient, including the people living in south island of New Zealand, and parts of China and Europe (Combs Jr, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Rayman, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Pappas et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Lv et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) is one of the principal cereal grains produced and consumed globally. Supplement of Se into the food chain is one of the effective measures to solve Se deficient situation. Thus, there is potential for it to make a substantially larger contribution of grain Se could be raised to levels found in overseas. Besides that, wheat provides the main source of Se in the world, and people in most European countries such as England and Finland uptake Se from bread (Broadley et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Lee et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p><p>Selenium is a metalloid element that occurs in different forms, including as selenide [Se (-II)], elemental selenium [Se (0)], selenite [Se (IV)], and selenate [Se (VI)], all of these organic or inorganic Se compounds occur naturally in the environment and accumulates in many organisms (Dissanayake and Chandrajith, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Elemental selenium is one of the dominant Se species in both aerobic and anaerobic soils which contribute 26&#x02013;66% of the total Se in soil (Fox et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). Under oxidizing conditions (&#x0003e;300 mV) and moderately reducing conditions (0&#x02013;200 mV) selenate and selenite will be the most dominant species in soil, respectively (Zhang and Moore, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Martens and Suarez, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Gao et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). In plant metabolism, selenate is absorbed through a sulfate transporter in the root plasma membrane into the cell, and is then converted into Se-amino acids (Terry et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Sors et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Schiavon and Pilon-Smits, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Selenite likely enters via a phosphate transport pathway into the plant root, which is a metabolically-dependent active process (Li et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Kaur et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In the process of Se assimilation, selenite is reduced to selenide, and then incorporated into selenocysteine (SeCys). The synthesis of SeCys probably occurs in chloroplasts, the cytosol, and mitochondria, and SeCys can be converted into selenomethionine (SeMet) (White and Broadley, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Plants probably take up organic forms of Se via amino acid permease, and the rate of uptake of SeCys and SeMet by wheat and canola is 20-fold higher than that of selenate or selenite (Schiavon and Pilon-Smits, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). However, plants uptake and transformation of elemental Se have not been well study.</p><p>Gray and black elemental Se are insoluble and have no bioactivity, while the red selenium nanoparticles (SeNPs) have scavenging effects on different free radicals <italic>in vitro</italic> (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Huang et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). SeNPs have found applications in medicine as antimicrobial, antioxidant, and anticancer agents (Hariharan et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Forootanfar et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Torres et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Yang et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). SeNPs were more effective in increasing the activities of glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px), thioredoxin reductase (TrxR), and glutathione S-transferase (GST) than SeMet in experiments with rodents and crucian carp, and SeNPs had low cytotoxicity compared with selenite in mice (Shi et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Domokos-Szabolcsy et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Wadhwani et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). SeNPs can be chemosynthesized by chemical reducing agents or be biosynthesized by organisms. Compared with chemosynthesized SeNPs (CheSeNPs), the biosynthesized SeNPs (BioSeNPs) are more stable due to natural coating of organic molecules or proteins (Lenz et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Currently, the supplementation of plants with Se is usually limited to selenite or selenate, and it is still unclear how plants absorb SeNPs. Previous research has demonstrated that tobacco can take up SeNPs in callus culture and through the root, and that the biological effects of SeNPs are different from selenate in plant tissue culture (Domokos-Szabolcsy et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>Here we compared the uptake, translocation and transformation of CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs in wheat seedlings in a controlled hydroponic system. The aim of this work was to identify the key absorption mechanism of SeNPs in wheat seedlings, which has so far remained unclear, and provide a theoretical basis for enhancing the quality and safety of the human diet and ensure the long-term use of new Se resources.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Wheat seedling culture</title><p>Wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L. cv. Luyuan 502, Shandong Academy of Agricultural Sciences) caryopses were surface-sterilized with 70% (v:v) ethanol for 90 s, washed three times with deionized water, and germinated in 0.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> solution at 25&#x000b0;C in the dark. The wheat seedlings were cultured in plastic containers with 2-liter modified 1/5 strength of Hoagland's nutrition solution (1.0 mM KNO<sub>3</sub>, 1.0 mM Ca(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>, 0.457 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.1 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 1.0 &#x003bc;M MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 3 &#x003bc;M H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 1 &#x003bc;M (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>6</sub>Mo<sub>7</sub>O<sub>24</sub>, 1 &#x003bc;M ZnSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.2 &#x003bc;M CuSO<sub>4</sub>, and 60 &#x003bc;M Fe(III)-EDTA) with 2 mM 2-morpholonoethanesulphonic acid (MES), and the pH was adjusted with KOH to 6.0 (Hogland and Arnon, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">1950</xref>). The culture solution was renewed every 5 days. The wheat seedlings were grown in a greenhouse under the following conditions: 16 h photoperiod per day with a light intensity at 280 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>s<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, 25/18&#x000b0;C day/ night temperature, relative humidity of 60&#x02013;80%, and 24 h of continuous ventilation.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation and characterization of SeNPs</title><p>Chemosynthesized SeNPs (CheSeNPs) with nominal diameters of 40, 140, and 240 nm were prepared according to previously described methods (Lin and Wang, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Briefly, CheSeNPs were synthesized from selenous acid with sodium thiosulfate (Na<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) as the reducing agent, and sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) as a surfactant stabilizer. The CheSeNPs with different particle sizes were collected by centrifugation, washed three times with 10 mM SDS, and suspended with deionized water to 1 mM, respectively. Biosynthesized SeNPs (BioSeNPs) were isolated from <italic>Rahnella aquatilis</italic> HX2 via a modified method described by Dobias et al. (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Briefly, HX2 was incubated in Luria-Bertani broth (containing 1% tryptone, 1% NaCl, and 0.5% yeast extract) supplemented with filter-sterilized Na<sub>2</sub>SeO<sub>3</sub> to a final concentration of 5 mM for 48 h at 28&#x000b0;C. The HX2 cells with SeNPs were collected by centrifugation at 8,000 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min. The precipitates were washed three times with deionized water, suspended with 1 M NaOH solution, boiled for 20 min in a water bath, and amended with a 1/2 volume of n-hexane. The aqueous phase which contained the SeNPs was taken and adjusted the pH to 7.2 using 6 M HCl. The BioSeNPs were collected by centrifugation at 8,000 <italic>g</italic> for 30 min, washed three times and suspended to 1 mM with deionized water for further use.</p><p>A transmission electron microscope (TEM) (Hitachi H7500, Tokyo, Japan) and an energy dispersive X-ray (EDX) detector (Hitachi HT7700, Tokyo, Japan) were used to analyze the elemental composition of the CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs. The TEM and EDX analyses were both performed at the National Center for Nanoscience and Technology (Beijing, China) according to the methods of manufacturer's instruction. The SeNPs were observed with the TEM system, and then selected areas within the TEM sections were subjected to elemental composition analysis using an EDX microanalysis system coupled to the TEM. The particle sizes of CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs were measured from manual counting of 200 individual particles from 9 different TEM images, respectively. The voltage was 100 kV and the signal acquisition time was 120 s. The hydrodynamic diameter and zeta potential of the CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs were measured by a dynamic light scattering (DLS) and particle size analyzer (SZ-100, Horiba, Japan).</p></sec><sec><title>Stability and desorption of SeNPs in the wheat root</title><p>The roots of 6-week-old wheat seedlings were washed twice with desorption solution (1 mM CaSO<sub>4</sub>, 2 mM MES, pH 6.0) for 30 min, and transferred to 100 ml 2 mM MES (pH 6.0) solution with 5 &#x003bc;M CheSeNPs. Each treatment was replicated three times. After 60 min absorption, the root about 1 g treated with SeNPs was washed three times by 10 ml desorption solution. The Se concentrations in washed desorption solution were detected.</p><p>Pretreated wheat seedlings were transferred to 300 ml containers (two plants per container) with 100 ml 5 &#x003bc;M CheSeNPs or BioSeNPs. Solutions containing 5 &#x003bc;M CheSeNPs or BioSeNPs without plants served as controls. Each treatment was replicated three times. Two milliliter aliquots were collected at 0, 2, 4, 8, 16, and 24 h during the incubation, filtered through 0.22-&#x003bc;m mixed cellulose nitrate filters (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA), and stored at 4&#x000b0;C for selenite analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Kinetics of SeNPs absorption</title><p>The roots of 6-week-old wheat seedlings were washed twice with desorption solution (1 mM CaSO<sub>4</sub>, 2 mM MES, pH 6.0) for 30 min, and the plants were transferred to 100 ml 2 mM MES (pH 6.0) solution with a series Se concentrations (0, 0.1, 0.5, 1.0, 5.0, 10.0, 20.0 &#x003bc;M selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs, respectively). Each treatment was replicated three times (two plants per pot), and the experiment was repeated three times. After 60 min absorption, the roots were rinsed with deionized water and then transferred into ice-cold desorption solution for 15 min with three times to remove the Se adhering to the root surfaces. Then, the shoots and roots of wheat seedlings were separated, lyophilized and analyzed for Se.</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of a respiratory inhibitor on SeNPs uptake</title><p>The respiratory inhibition assay was performed according to the reported method (Li et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) with slight modification. Carbonyl cyanide between chlorobenzene hydrazone (CCCP) known as a protonophore or uncoupler of oxidative phosphrylation was used as a respiratory inhibitor in this experiment (Volkov et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>). Wheat seedlings were pretreated as described above, and then the roots were transferred to 100 ml 2 mM MES (pH 6.0) solution with 5 &#x003bc;M CheSeNPs or BioSeNPs, with or without 1 &#x003bc;M carbonyl cyanide between chlorobenzene hydrazone (CCCP), which was initially dissolved in ethanol; the final ethanol concentration was 0.01% (v/v). Solutions containing 5 &#x003bc;M CheSeNPs or BioSeNPs with 0.01% (v/v) ethanol served as controls. Each treatment was replicated three times (two plants per pot), and the experiment was repeated three times. After 60 min absorption, the wheat roots were treated as described above in the kinetics section.</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of aquaporin inhibition on SeNPs uptake</title><p>The aquaporin inhibition assay was performed according to the reported method (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) with slight modification. Wheat seedlings were prepared as described above in the kinetics section, then transferred to 100 ml 2 mM MES (pH 6.0) solution with 5 &#x003bc;M CheSeNPs or BioSeNPs, with or without 0.1 mM AgNO<sub>3</sub>. Each treatment was replicated three times (two plants per pot), and the experiment was repeated three times. After 60 min absorption, the wheat seedlings were treated as described above.</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of particle size on SeNPs uptake</title><p>Pretreated wheat seedlings were transferred to 100 ml 2 mM MES (pH 6.0) solution with 5 &#x003bc;M 40, 140, or 240 nm CheSeNPs. Each treatment was replicated three times (two plants per pot), and the experiment was repeated three times. After 60 min absorption, the wheat seedlings were treated as described above.</p></sec><sec><title>Uptake and transfer of SeNPs in wheat</title><p>Prepared wheat seedlings were transferred to 100 ml 2 mM MES (pH 6.0) solution with 5 &#x003bc;M selenite, CheSeNPs, or BioSeNPs. Each treatment was replicated three times (two plants per pot). The seedlings were harvested at 24, 48, and 72 h and treated as described above. To evaluate the transfer potential of Se from roots to shoots, the transfer factor (TF) (defined as the ratio of Se concentration in shoots to roots) was calculated (Huang et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Total selenium analysis</title><p>The total Se concentration in the treated wheat tissues was determined with a AFS-920 hydride generation flame atomic fluorescence spectrometer (HG-AFS) (Beijing Jitian Analysis Instruction Co., Beijing, China). Powdered seedling samples (250 mg) were digested with 8 ml 15.3 M HNO<sub>3</sub> under the microwave digestion program described by Baldwin et al. (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). After cooling down, 2.5 ml 6 M HCl was added to each tube, and the contents were heated to 100&#x000b0;C for 1 h to reduce selenate to selenite (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). The obtained solutions were diluted with deionized water to a final volume of 50 ml. Two milliliter samples were injected into the HG-AFS system, and each sample was prepared and analyzed in triplicate for linear estimation based on regression analysis of the effects of Se treatments using Microsoft Excel. Blanks and a certified reference material (Chinese cabbage material, GBW 10014) were included in each batch of samples for quality control. The recovery for GNW-10014 was 85.2&#x02013;119.7%.</p></sec><sec><title>Selenium species transformation and analysis</title><p>Prepared wheat seedlings were transferred to 100 ml 2 mM MES (pH 6.0) solution with 10 &#x003bc;M selenite, CheSeNPs, or BioSeNPs. Each treatment was replicated three times (two plants per treatment). After 24 h absorption, the shoots and roots were separated, lyophilized and analyzed for Se species.</p><p>A powdered sample (250 mg) was mixed with 8 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> protease XIV (Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO, USA), and shaken for 24 h at 37&#x000b0;C, filtered through a filter paper and then through 0.22-&#x003bc;m mixed cellulose nitrate filters. Samples of nutrient solution were diluted appropriately and filtered through 0.22-&#x003bc;m mixed cellulose nitrate filters.</p><p>The Se species were separated using an anion-exchange column (Hamilton PRP-X100) in conjunction with ICP-MS (Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">S1</xref>). The 100 &#x003bc;l samples were injected into an HPLC-ICP-MS system (Agilent LC 1260 series and ICP-MS 7700; Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA) and eluted with 30 mM (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> (pH 6.0) at a flow rate of 1 ml min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Peaks were identified according to the retention times of standard compounds [i.e., selenocystine (SeCys<sub>2</sub>), Se-methyl-selenocysteine (MeSeCys), Se (IV), SeMet, and Se (VI)] purchased from the National Research Center for Certified Reference Materials, Beijing, China. The identified Se species were quantified based on the peak areas of the calibration curves using an HPLC workstation.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All analyses were performed in triplicate, and the results were expressed as mean values and standard error (SE). The data were processed using SigmaPlot 12.0. One-way ANOVA with multiple comparisons using Duncan's test was employed to compare the means among different treatments (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) using the SAS software (version 9.0; SAS Inc., Cary, NC, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>SeNPs characterization</title><p>To verify the SeNPs produced by chemosynthesis and biosynthesis, the characteristics of the SeNPs were examined using a TEM and an EDX detector. Under the TEM, the prepared NPs synthesized by chemical and biological methods both appeared as well-dispersed spherical particles with average diameters of 140 &#x000b1; 10 nm and 140 &#x000b1; 40 nm (Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1A,C</xref>), respectively. The hydrodynamic diameter of the CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs were carried out by DLS, as shown in the Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2A,B</xref>. The hydrodynamic diameter of the CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs was 157.8 &#x000b1; 30.6 nm and 151.6 &#x000b1; 41.9 nm, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). The zeta potential of CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs were &#x02212;46.5 and &#x02212;51.1 mV, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). The EDX results demonstrated that the NPs had specific absorption peaks for Se at 1.37 (peak SeL&#x003b1;), 11.22 (peak SeK&#x003b1;), and 12.49 (peak SeK&#x003b2;) keV (Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1B,D</xref>). These results indicated that the chemosynthesized and biosynthesized NPs were SeNPs (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>SeNPs absorption by wheat roots</title><p>To verified the elutability of the desorption solution, the desorption experiment was preformed. The Se concentration in the first two times washed desorption solution was 30.8 &#x000b1; 0.1 &#x003bc;g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 4.2 &#x000b1; 0.1 &#x003bc;g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S4</xref>). In the third washed desorption solution, selenium could not be detected (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S4</xref>). This result indicated that the desorption solution could remove SeNPs adhered on roots surface efficiently.</p><p>To assess the absorption of selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs by plants, the absorption kinetics were assayed using a series of Se concentrations in hydroponic experiments. The Michaelis-Menten equations for selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs influx into wheat roots are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. The <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> for selenite influx was 2.5- and 3.3-fold higher than for CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs, and the K<sub>m</sub> value of selenite was 2.3- and 2.6-fold higher than for CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). SeNPs absorption by wheat roots increased with the external SeNPs concentration and reached a plateau at 10 &#x003bc;M of Se, while selenite absorption into wheat roots increased with the external selenite concentration, but did not reach a plateau in this experiment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Concentration-dependent kinetics for selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs absorption within 60 min. Data are means &#x000b1; standard error (SE) (<italic>n</italic> = 3). The curves represent the fitted Michaelis-Menten kinetics.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00597-g0001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Concentration-dependent kinetics parameters for selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs influx into wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) roots within 60 min.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Uptake kinetics parameters</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Different treatments</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Selenite</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CheSeNPs</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BioSeNPs</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> (nmol g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> root h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">324.7 &#x000b1; 58.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.6 &#x000b1; 21.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.5 &#x000b1; 17.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> (&#x003bc;M)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9 &#x000b1; 4.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 &#x000b1; 2.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5 &#x000b1; 2.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9787</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9425</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9236</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Kinetic parameters were calculated from mean Se influx (n = 3) using Michaelis-Menten function nonlinear regression model</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>SeNPs uptake was unaffected by CCCP and disrupted by AgNO<sub>3</sub></title><p>CCCP is known as a protonophore or uncoupler of oxidative phosphrylation, which is believed to be inhibition of ATP formation by uncoupling oxidative phosphorylation (Volkov et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>). Thus, it can be used to eliminate the effect of root respiration. To determine whether the uptake of SeNPs by wheat was a passive diffusion process or consumed energy, 1 &#x003bc;M CCCP was included in the experiment. The uptake of CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs was measured after wheat roots were exposed to the two Se species for 60 min. Compared with the control treatment, the addition of ethanol or CCCP to the nutrient solution did not significantly affect the uptake of CheSeNPs or BioSeNPs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). To examine the uptake of SeNPs by plants through water channels, 0.1 mM AgNO<sub>3</sub> was used as a water channel blocker (Niemietz and Tyerman, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The AgNO<sub>3</sub> treatment resulted in 92.5 and 93.4% inhibition of CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs uptake, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>); these results indicated that the uptake of SeNPs could be disrupted by AgNO<sub>3</sub>.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Effect of the metabolic inhibitor carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone (CCCP) on the influx of CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs into wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) roots within 60 min. <bold>(B)</bold> Effect of the aquaporin inhibitor AgNO<sub>3</sub> on the influx of CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs into wheat roots. SeNPs were supplied at 5 &#x003bc;M. Data are means &#x000b1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3); different letters differ significant at <italic>p</italic> = 0.05 (Duncan's test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00597-g0002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>SeNPs uptake was correlated with particle sizes</title><p>SeNPs of different sizes were prepared, and the effects of particle size on SeNPs uptake by wheat were analyzed. The results indicated that the SeNPs uptake by wheat roots was affected by the particle size in the CheSeNPs treatments (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The Se absorption by wheat roots under 40 nm CheSeNPs treatment was significantly increased compared with 140 and 240 nm CheSeNPs treatments, being 1.8- and 2.2-fold higher, respectively. There was non-significant difference between the 140 and 240 nm CheSeNPs treatments.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Accumulation of CheSeNPs of different sizes in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) roots within 60 min. Data are means &#x000b1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3); different letters indicate significant difference at <italic>p</italic> = 0.05 (Duncan's test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00597-g0003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Selenium accumulation and translocation in wheat</title><p>To confirm that the wheat absorbed the SeNPs and not other Se species in the experimental system, the stability of SeNPs in the plant culture solution with or without wheat seedlings was monitored. The SeNPs concentration remained steady during the wheat absorption process (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S5</xref>). The measured concentrations of selenite accounted for 2.2 and 0.5% of the CheSeNPs- or BioSeNPs-treatment concentrations in the initial solution, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S5</xref>). The concentration of selenite in the CheSeNPs or BioSeNPs plus wheat root treatments did not significantly change with treatment time (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S5</xref>). Additionally, the selenite concentration did not markedly increase with exposure time in the solutions of CheSeNPs or BioSeNPs alone (without wheat seedlings) (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S5</xref>).</p><p>The uptake and translocation of Se in wheat under selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs treatments was detected by HG-AFS. The Se concentration in wheat roots did not show a significant difference among the selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs treatments at 24, 48, and 72 h (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). However, the concentration of Se in wheat roots significantly increased (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) with the exposure duration from 24 to 72 h under all treatments. Generally, the Se concentration in wheat roots and shoots increased with increasing exposure time (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). In the BioSeNPs treatment, the Se concentration in wheat shoots was significantly lower than in the CheSeNPs and selenite treatments, whereas there was no significant difference in the Se concentration between the CheSeNPs and selenite treatments (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). Compared with the selenite treatment, the Se concentration decreased by 16.3&#x02013;47.3% in BioSeNPs-treated wheat shoots, but showed a slight increase in the CheSeNPs treatment at earlier exposure times (24 and 48 h).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Selenium accumulation in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) <bold>(A)</bold> shoots and <bold>(B)</bold> roots in response to selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs treatments for 24, 48, and 72 h. Data are means &#x000b1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3); different letters indicate significant difference at <italic>p</italic> = 0.05 (Duncan's test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00597-g0004"/></fig><p>The TF, defined as the ratio of the Se concentration in shoots to that in roots, can be used to evaluate the transfer potential of Se from roots to shoots. The TF values in all treatments were generally below 0.1, which indicated that, like selenite, BioSeNPs, and CheSeNPs had low translocation rates from roots to shoots (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Among the treatments, BioSeNPs showed the lowest translocation rate and CheSeNPs the highest. The TF value of the CheSeNPs treatment at 48 h was 1.4 and 1.9 times higher than those of the selenite and BioSeNPs treatments, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). However, there was no significant difference in the TF values between the treatments at 24 and 72 h.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Selenium transfer factor (TF) in wheat under selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs treatments for 24, 48, and 72 h. Data are means &#x000b1; SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3); different letters indicate significant at <italic>p</italic> = 0.05 (Duncan's test); * differs significantly at <italic>p</italic> = 0.011.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00597-g0005"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Selenium species in wheat seedlings</title><p>Selenium species were extracted from wheat root and shoot tissues by enzymatic hydrolysis and detected with HPLC-ICP-MS. The analysis results showed that the BioSeNPs and CheSeNPs were absorbed and converted to organic forms by wheat plants (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). In total, eight Se species were observed, but only five were identified, including SeCys<sub>2</sub>, MeSeCys, SeMet, Se (IV), and Se (VI). SeCys<sub>2</sub>, MeSeCys, Se (IV), Se (VI) and an unidentified peak (1) eluted at a retention time of 116 s (RT <sub>116</sub>) were detected in wheat roots and shoot tissues under all treatments (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Examples of chromatograms of selenium (Se) speciation in protease XIV extracts of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) roots and shoots, as determined by anion exchange HPLC-ICP-MS. The intensity (count per second, cps) is for m/z 78. <bold>(A&#x02013;C)</bold> Se species in wheat shoots under selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs treatment, respectively. <bold>(D&#x02013;F)</bold> Se species in wheat roots under selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs treatment, respectively. 1 (Unknown Se species); 2 (SeCys<sub>2</sub>, Selenocystine); 3 (MeSeCys, Se-methyl-selenocysteine); 4 [Se (IV), Selenite]; 5 (SeMet, Selenomethionine); 6 (Unknown Se species); 7 (Unknown Se species); 8 [Se (VI), Selenate].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00597-g0006"/></fig><p>HPLC-ICP-MS analysis revealed that the extraction procedure extracted 50.2&#x02013;60.1% of the total Se from the roots and shoots of the treated wheat, except in the shoot under BioSeNPs treatment (33.4%) (Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM7">S2</xref>). In the wheat roots, Se (IV) was the dominant species under the CheSeNPs- (34.0% of the total Se) and BioSeNPs treatments (17.6%) whereas SeMet was the dominant Se species (18.0%) under the selenite treatment and was found at a concentration of 8.71 &#x003bc;g g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Se (VI) was also present in wheat roots under all treatments, but had a relatively lower concentration, representing only &#x0003c;2.5% of the total Se (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In the root extracts, an unidentified peak (7) was eluted at a retention time of 637 s (RT <sub>637</sub>) for the BioSeNPs treatment plants, whilst another unidentified peak (6) was eluted at a retention time of 435 s (RT <sub>435</sub>) for the selenite treatment plants (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). The Se speciation in wheat shoots showed difference to that in roots. SeCys<sub>2</sub> (11.4%) was the dominant species in wheat shoots for CheSeNPs treatment plants, whilst Se (VI) accounted for 7.4% of the Se in the BioSeNPs treatment plants. In the selenite treatment plants, the most abundant organic Se compound was SeMet, which occupied 18.4% of the total Se in wheat shoots (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of selenium (Se) species supplied on Se speciation in protease XIV extracts from wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) roots and shoots.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Species</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="6" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Se species supplied</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Selenite</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>CheSeNPs</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>BioSeNPs</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x003bc;g g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Percentage %<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>*</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x003bc;g g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Percentage %</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x003bc;g g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Percentage %</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shoot</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SeCys<sub>2</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.06<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 &#x000b1; 0.06<italic>a</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 &#x000b1; 0.01<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 &#x000b1; 0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MeSeCys</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 &#x000b1; 0.08<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 &#x000b1; 0.05<italic>c</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 &#x000b1; 0.04<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Se (IV)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 &#x000b1; 0.15<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 &#x000b1; 1.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 &#x000b1; 0.01<italic>c</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 &#x000b1; 0.02<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SeMet</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 &#x000b1; 0.73<italic>a</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 &#x000b1; 0.11<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 &#x000b1; 0.04<italic>a</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 &#x000b1; 0.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Se (VI)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 &#x000b1; 0.04<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 &#x000b1; 0.00<italic>c</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 &#x000b1; 0.01<italic>a</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4 &#x000b1; 0.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SeCys<sub>2</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36 &#x000b1; 1.09<italic>ab</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 &#x000b1; 2.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12 &#x000b1; 0.13<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6 &#x000b1; 2.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 &#x000b1; 0.03<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 &#x000b1; 0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MeSeCys</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#x000b1; 0.21<italic>ab</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 &#x000b1; 0.04<italic>c</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 &#x000b1; 0.07<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Se (IV)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55 &#x000b1; 1.02<italic>ab</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7 &#x000b1; 2.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.00 &#x000b1; 0.15<italic>a</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.0 &#x000b1; 6.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36 &#x000b1; 1.00<italic>a</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6 &#x000b1; 3.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SeMet</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.45 &#x000b1; 2.27<italic>a</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0 &#x000b1; 5.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 &#x000b1; 0.13<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 &#x000b1; 1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 &#x000b1; 0.22<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 &#x000b1; 0.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Se (VI)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 &#x000b1; 0.10<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.06<italic>d</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 &#x000b1; 0.14<italic>b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Mean values (n = 3) &#x000b1; standard error (SE). Selenite, sodium selenite; CheSeNPs, chemogenic selenium nanoparticels; BioSeNPs, biogenic elemental selenium nanoparticles; SeCys<sub>2</sub>, selenocystine; MeSeCys, Se-methyl-selenocysteine; Se (IV), selenite; SeMet, selenomethionine; Se (VI), selenate</italic>.</p><fn id="TN1"><label>*</label><p><italic>The percentage was calculated by the concentration of Se species / the concentration of Se in tissues &#x000d7; 100%. The different letters indicate statistically significant differences between the treatments as the p &#x0003c; 0.05</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Mechanisms of SeNPs uptake</title><p>On account of most NPs have a proportionately very large surface area and this surface can have a high affinity for plants roots (Cheng et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Aslani et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S4</xref> indicated that the desorption solution could remove SeNPs adhered on roots surface efficiently. In addition, the results in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> will also give evidence to SeNPs desorption from roots. If the SeNPs could not be removed from root efficiently by desorption solution, Se concentration of root in AgNO<sub>3</sub> treatment could not significantly decreased compared to the control.</p><p>The phytouptake of several metal nanoparticles including Se has been investigated, and these studies have demonstrated that nanoparticles can adhere to plant roots and induce chemical or physical uptake (Domokos-Szabolcsy et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Aslani et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). However, the uptake mechanism of SeNPs is not well understood. The uptake kinetics of selenite, CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs showed that CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs influx into wheat roots was much slower than selenite influx (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The lower <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> values for both CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs suggested a distinct difference in the uptake and affinity for these Se species compared with selenite.</p><p>A previous study reported that the metabolic inhibitor CCCP inhibited the uptake of selenite by 80%, and demonstrated that selenite uptake was a metabolically-dependent active process (Li et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). However, neither the uptake of CheSeNPs nor BioSeNPs was sensitive to the metabolic inhibitor CCCP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). CCCP is used as an oxidative phosphorylation inhibitor to reduce the operation of the ATP synthase, and eliminate the effect of wheat root respiration (Volkov et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>). Thus, it is likely that wheat root absorption of SeNPs is a passive diffusion process, and does not consume energy. Furthermore, our results demonstrated that AgNO<sub>3</sub> significantly disrupted the wheat root absorption of CheSeNPs, and BioSeNPs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). AgNO<sub>3</sub> is a potential inhibitor of aquaporins of plant origin (Niemietz and Tyerman, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The mechanism of AgNO<sub>3</sub> inhibits aquaporin function is that the pore diameter of an aquaporin is 2.8 &#x000c5; and the ionic radius of Ag<sup>+</sup> is 2.5 &#x000c5;. Hence elements with ionic radii similar to silver may be potent inhibitors of aquaporins. Silver reacts with the sulfhydryl group of a cysteine and also with a histidine, resulting in gating by the targeted aquaporin (Niemietz and Tyerman, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The inhibition of CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs uptake by AgNO<sub>3</sub> was due to its effect on aquaporins. It was reported that AgNO<sub>3</sub> blocked the water channels and inhibited selenite absorption by rice roots at low pH by 73% (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Earlier literature has documented that water channels do not completely exclude small uncharged molecules, and they can transmit considerable amounts of water as solutes diffuse across channels (Hertel and Steudle, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). The aquaporins inhibiter resulted in 92.5 and 93.4% inhibition of CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs uptake, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). The diameter of aquaporins is about 2.8 &#x000c5;, it seems too small for SeNPs to pass though (Niemietz and Tyerman, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The aquaporins play important roles in the physiological processes, including transport of water, mineral nutrition, carbon, nitrogen fixation, promote cell elongation, differentiation, and stomata movement (Maurel et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Thus, we speculate that the inhibiter of aquaporin function in some way influenced the wheat seedlings absorb of SeNPs.</p><p>Evidences have suggested that only NPs or NPs aggregates with a diameter less than the pore diameter of the cell wall can easily pass through and reach the plasma membrane (Moore, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Dietz and Herth, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Because of the limited sizes of the cells pore, only NPs smaller than 5 nm may traverse an intact cell wall (Carpita et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>; Li et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). As the size of SeNPs is greater than the pore size of cell walls, this hypothesis is refuted by the results of the present study. This study demonstrated that smaller CheSeNPs were more easily absorbed than larger ones (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Thus, the uptake of SeNPs is not solely dependent on the pore diameter of the cell wall; other mechanisms may be involved. Furthermore, NPs below 100 nm in size possess unique physico-chemical, electrical, optical, and biological activities, compared with their bulkier counterparts (Ingle et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Transformation of SeNPs in wheat plants</title><p>The CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs were synthesized using selenite in our experiments (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). The CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs have a relatively higher zeta potential (&#x02212;46.5 and &#x02212;51.1 mV, respectively) in water solution and thus form a stable dispersion, enabling the application possible for plant. We monitored the dynamics of Se concentrations in the solutions in the SeNPs treatments with or without wheat seedlings, and found little (0.05&#x02013;2.2%) selenite in the initial treatment solution. The selenite concentration did not significantly increase during the experiment, which indicated that the SeNPs appeared stable and were not oxidized to selenite in the solution (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S5</xref>). The results indicated that the plants absorbed the SeNPs and not the selenite in the experiment.</p><p>The selenium species were extracted with protease XIV. Because of the limited availability of standard Se compounds, the SeCys<sub>2</sub>, MeSeCys, Se (IV), SeMet, Se (VI) were quantitatively and qualitatively measured in this study (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Unknown compounds and the low extraction efficiencies accounted for the difference between the total Se content and the sum of the identified peaks. Previous studies have demonstrated that inorganic Se (i.e., selenate and selenite) can be taken up by plants and then transformed into organic Se compounds (i.e., SeCys<sub>2</sub>, SeMet, and MeSeCys) and bound within proteins (Vogrincic et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Schiavon and Pilon-Smits, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). However, little information is available on SeNPs transformation in plants. Our study showed that SeNPs could also be taken up by plants and then transformed into organic Se compounds, selenite, and selenate in roots and shoots, which demonstrated the the bioavailability of SeNPs in plants. The root extracts contained a number of Se species with Se (IV) being the dominant species in wheat roots under the CheSeNPs and BioSeNPs treatments (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). By contrast, when wheat plants were supplied with selenite, it was rapidly converted to organic forms in the roots, although a tiny portion of selenite was remained. Similarly, Li et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) found that selenite supplied to wheat roots was rapidly assimilated into organic forms and detected a relatively small concentration of Se (IV) in wheat root extracts. Because Se (IV) was the most abundant species in the root extracts of CheSeNPs- and BioSeNPs-treated plants, we hypothesize that the oxidation reactions occurred in the root cells. In wheat shoots, SeMet (18.4%) was the dominant species in the selenite treatment plants, SeCys<sub>2</sub> (11.4%), and SeMet (7.8%) were the main species in the CheSeNPs treatment plants, and Se (VI) (7.4%) and SeMet (5.4%) were the main species in the BioSeNPs treatment plants (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The transformation of Se species in plants is a dynamic process, and SeCys, selenocystathionine, selenohomoserine, and SeMet are all considered likely intermediates in the assimilation of selenite into selenoproteins (Shrift, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">1969</xref>). Duncan et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) reported that SeMet was the major Se species in wheat grain samples, and Vogrincic et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) found that SeMet and MeSeCys were the most abundant species in Se-enriched plants. Another interesting phenomenon was that under the BioSeNPs treatment, the percentage of Se (VI) was 7.4%, which was 4.4- and 3.4-fold higher than that in the CheSeNPs and selenite treatments, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). This suggests that some complex metabolic process occurs in plants based on the special biological characteristics of BioSeNPs. In contrast to the synthesis of CheSeNPs, BioSeNPs are synthesized by complex microbial communities and capping agents (i.e., proteins, polysaccharides, phenols, amines and alcohols) are present on the surfaces of BioSeNPs (Dwivedi et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Husen and Siddiqi, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Jain et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The BioSeNPs synthesized by HX2 which coated two main proteins <italic>Rahnella aquatilis</italic> flagellin C (FliC) and the outer membrane protein porin (Data no shown). Thus, the extracellular polymeric substances of BioSeNPs may be one of the unfavorable factors influencing their transport and accumulation in wheat plants.</p></sec><sec><title>SeNPs translocation from roots to shoots</title><p>The TF, defined as the ratio of Se concentration in shoots to roots is generally used to evaluate the translocation potential of Se from plant roots to shoots (Huang et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). CheSeNPs and selenite showed similar translocation of Se from roots to shoots during the longer exposure period (72 h), while the BioSeNPs were rarely translocated to shoots (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The TF values were below 0.1 in all treatments, which indicated that little SeNPs and selenite were transported to the shoots. The low TFs of SeNPs and selenite from roots to shoots may be due to their rapid conversion to organic Se compounds (SeCys<sub>2</sub>, MeSeCys, and SeMet) and retention in wheat roots. The shape, size, chemical composition, concentration, surface structure, aggregation and solubility of NPs are critical factors influencing the plant uptake (Aslani et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, the present study has provided physiological evidence that SeNPs can be actually absorbed by wheat seedlings. SeNPs influx into wheat roots is a passive diffusion process, and the uptake rate of SeNPs is lower than for selenite. CheSeNPs below 50 nm in size were more easily absorbed into wheat roots. The aquaporin function is in some way involved in the SeNPs uptake by wheat seedlings. Few SeNPs were transported from roots to shoots, and they were rapidly assimilated into Se (IV) and organic forms in both wheat roots and shoots. Thus, water management and smaller diameter of SeNPs produced by microorganisms may improve the wheat absorption of SeNPs in the field. Thus, SeNPs could be used as a new fertilizer to produce Se-biofortified plants, which might improve Se supplementation for humans and domestic animals.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Author contributions</title><p>YG and HL: Conceived and designed the experiments; TH, JL, and QW: Performed the experiments; YG, HL, and TH: Analyzed the data; GZ, WW, and LL: Contributed reagents, materials, and analysis tools; YG, HL, and TH: Wrote the paper.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31470531) and the Special Fund for Agro-scientific Research in the Public Interest (201303106).</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.00597/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.00597/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>TEM images of <bold>(A)</bold> CheSeNPs [the ratio of the concentration of sodium selenite (Na<sub>2</sub>SeO<sub>3</sub>) to sodium thiosulfate (Na<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) is 1:4] and <bold>(C)</bold> BioSeNPs (formed by strain HX2 with 15 mM Na<sub>2</sub>SeO<sub>3</sub> for 48 h) and EDX spectra of the chemosynthesized nanoparticles <bold>(B)</bold> and biosynthesized nanoparticles <bold>(D)</bold>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image_1.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>Hydrodynamic diameter of <bold>(A)</bold> CheSeNPs and <bold>(B)</bold> BioSeNPs.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image_2.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>Zeta potential of <bold>(A)</bold> CheSeNPs and <bold>(B)</bold> BioSeNPs.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image_3.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>Concentration of Se in the desorption solution with the wash times.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image_4.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p>Selenite concentration in SeNPs treatments solutions (CheSeNPs; BioSeNPs).</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image_5.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM6"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>ICP-MS parameters for analysis of Se species in wheat roots and shoots.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table_1.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM7"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>Extraction efficiency of selenium in wheat roots and shoots by protease XIV.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table_2.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aslani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagheri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Julkapli</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juraimi</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>F. S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghdadi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Effect of engineered nanomaterials on plants growth: an overview</article-title>. <source>Sci. World J.</source>
<volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>641759</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/641759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deaker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Low-volume microwave digestion of marine biological tissues for measurement of trace elements</article-title>. <source>Analyst</source>
<volume>119</volume>, <fpage>1701</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1704</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/an9941901701</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7978323?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7978323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broadley</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meacham</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Biofortification of UK food crops with selenium</article-title>. <source>Pro. Nutr. Soc.</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/PNS2006490</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16672078?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16672078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpita</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabularse</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montezinos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delmer</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Determination of the pore size of cell walls of living plants cells</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>205</volume>, <fpage>1144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.205.4411.1144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17735052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomson</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Naphthalene adsorption and desorption from aqueous C60 fullerene</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Eng. Data</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>675</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>683</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.102/je030247m</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Combs Jr</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Selenium in global food systems</article-title>. <source>Brit. J. Nutr.</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>547</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/BJN2000280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11348568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herth</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Plant nanotoxicology</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>582</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>589</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2011.08.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21906987?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21906987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dissanayake</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrajith</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Introduction to Medical Geology</source>, <publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press, Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobias</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suvorova</surname><given-names>E. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernier-Latmani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Role of proteins in controlling selenium nanoparticle size</article-title>. <source>Nanotechnology</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>195605</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0957-4484/22/19/195606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21430311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domokos-Szabolcsy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marton</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sztrik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Babka</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokisch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Accumulation of red elemental selenium nanoparticles and their biological effects in <italic>Nicotinia tabacum</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Growth Regul.</source>
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>531</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s1072-012-9735-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagtap</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krikowa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roper</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Selenium speciation in wheat grain varies in the presence of nitrogen and sulphur fertilizers</article-title>. <source>Environ. Geochem. Health</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>955</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>966</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-016-9857-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27443882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bajaj</surname><given-names>P. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>An organic acid-induced synthesis and characterization of selenium nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>J. Nanotechnology</source>
<volume>D14</volume>, <fpage>762</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>770</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2011/651971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fairweather-Tait</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broadley</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collings</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesketh</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Selenium in human health and disease</article-title>. <source>Antioxid. Redox Sign.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1383</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ars.2010.3275</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20812787?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20812787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forootanfar</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adeli-Sardos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikkhoo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrabani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amir-Heidari</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahverdi</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant and cytotoxic effect of biologically synthesized selenium nanoparticles in comparison to selenium dioxide</article-title>. <source>J. Trace Elem. Med. Bio.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtemb.2013.07.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24074651?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24074651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>LeDuc</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Selenium speciation in soils and plants</article-title>. <source>ACS Symposium</source>
<volume>835</volume>, <fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>354</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bk-2003-0835.ch022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanji</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbel</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Water selenium speciation and sediment fractionation in California flow-through wetland system</article-title>. <source>J. Environ. Qual.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1283</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/jeq2000.00472425002900040034x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hariharan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Dhabi</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karuppiah</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajaram</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Microbial synthesis of selenium nanocomposite using <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> and its antimicrobial activity against pathogens causing nosocomial infection</article-title>. <source>Chalcogenide Lett.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hertel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steudle</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The function of water channels in <italic>Chara</italic>: the temperature dependence of water and solute flows provides evidence for composite membrane transport and for a slippage of small organic solutes across water channels</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>202</volume>, <fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hogland</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>). <article-title>The water culture method for growing plants without soil</article-title>. <source>Calif Agric Exp. Stn. Circ</source>. <volume>347</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>359</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Free radical scavenging efficiency of nano-se <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Free Radic. Bio. Med.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>805</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>813</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(03)00428-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14583345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14583345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Uptake kinetics and translocation of selenite and selenate as affected by iron plaque on root surfaces of rice seedlings</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>241</volume>, <fpage>907</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>916</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-014-2227-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25526963?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25526963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Husen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqi</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Plants and microbes assisted selenium nanoparticles: characterization and application</article-title>. <source>J. Nanotechnology</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/PREACCEPT-4680053311297707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingle</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Bioactivity, mechanism of action, and cytotoxicity of copper-based nanoparticles: a review</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnolo.</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>1001</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1009</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-013-5422-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24305741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24305741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foerstendorf</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kacker</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Extracellular polymeric substances govern the surface charge of biogenic elemental selenium nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>1713</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1720</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es5043063</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25536371?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25536371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laur</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nayyar</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Selenium in agriculture: a nutrient or contaminant for crops?</article-title>
<source>Arch. Agron. Soil Sci.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>1593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1624</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03650340.2014.918258</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15092151?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15092151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodard</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doolittle</surname><given-names>W. J. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Selenium uptake response among selected wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) varieties and relationship with soil selenium fractions</article-title>. <source>Soil Sci. Plant Nutr.</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>823</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>832</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00380768.2011.641909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolvenbach</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygax</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corvini</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Shedding light on selenium biomineralization: proteins associated with bionanominerals</article-title>. <source>Appl. Envir. Microbio.</source>
<volume>77</volume>, <fpage>4676</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4680</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01713-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21602371?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21602371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Selenium uptake, translocation and speciation in wheat supplied with selenate or selenite</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>178</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>102</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02343.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18179602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Z. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Toxicity of nanomaterials to plants</article-title>, in <source>Nanotechnology and Plant Science</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Whaibi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer; Cham Press</publisher-name>), <fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. R. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Evidence on the size-dependent absorption spectral evolution of selenium nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>Mater. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>594</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matchemphys.2005.02.023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Constraint on selenium bioavailability caused by its geochemical behavior in typical Kaschin-Beck disease areas in Aba, Sichuan province of China</article-title>. <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
<volume>493</volume>, <fpage>737</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>749</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2014.06.050</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24995640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24995640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Selenium speciation of marine shales, alluvial soils, and evaporation basin soils of California</article-title>. <source>J. Environ. Qual.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>424</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>432</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/jeq1997.00472425002600020013x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdouc</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoni</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Plant aquaporins: membrane channels with multiple integrated functions</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>624</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.59.032607.092734</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18444909?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18444909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Do nanoparticles present ecotoxicological risks for the health of the aquatic environments?</article-title>
<source>Environ. Int.</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>976</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2006.06.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16859745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niemietz</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyerman</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>New potent inhibitors of aquaporins: silver and gold compounds inhibit aquaporins of plant and human orgin</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<volume>531</volume>, <fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>447</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(02)03581-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12435590?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12435590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoidis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Surai</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zervas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Selenoproteins and maternal nutrition</article-title>. <source>Comp. Biochem. Phys. B</source>
<volume>151</volume>, <fpage>361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>372</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbpb.2008.08.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18790070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18790070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galinn</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Seleium: dietary sources, human nutritional requirements and intake across populations</article-title>, in <source>Selenium</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweizer</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer; Cham Press</publisher-name>), <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rayman</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The use of high-selenium yeast to raise selenium status: how does it measure up?</article-title>
<source>Brit. J. Nutr.</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>557</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>573</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/BJN20041251</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15522125?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15522125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schiavon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilon-Smits</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The fascinating facets of plant selenium accumulation-biochemistry, physiology, evolution and ecology</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>213</volume>, <fpage>1582</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1596</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14378</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27991670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27991670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xun</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Effect of elemental nano-selenium on semen quality, glutathione peroxidase activity, and testis utrastructure in male Boer goats</article-title>. <source>Anim. Reprod. Sci.</source>
<volume>118</volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>254</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anireprosci.2009.10.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19914014?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19914014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shrift</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>). <article-title>Aspects of selenium metabolism in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Ann. Rev. Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>475</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>494</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pp.20.060169.002355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sors</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salt</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Selenium uptake, translocation, assimilation and metabolic fate in plants</article-title>. <source>Photosyn. Res.</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11120-005-5222-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16307305?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16307305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zayed</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarun</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Selenium in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Plant Phys. Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>432</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.51.1.401</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15012198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Llamazares</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis of selenium nanoparticles by <italic>Pantoea agglomerans</italic> and their antioxidant activity</article-title>. <source>J. Nanopart. Res.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1236</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11051-012-1236-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogrincic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuderman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreft</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stibilj</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Selenium and its species distribution in above-ground plant parts of selenium enriched buckwheat (<italic>Fagopyrum esculentum</italic> Moench)</article-title>. <source>Anal. Sci.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1363</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2116/anaisci.25.1357</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19907095?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19907095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volkov</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deamer</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanelian</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Markin</surname><given-names>V. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Markin, Liquid interfaces in Chemistry and Biology</source>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wadhwani</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shedbalkar</surname><given-names>U. U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chopade</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Biogenic selenium nanoparticles: current status and future prospects</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biot.</source>
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>2555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2566</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-016-7300-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26801915?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26801915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broadley</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Biofortification of crops with seven mineral elements often lacking in human diets-iron, Zinc, Copper, calcium, magnesium, selenium and iodine</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>182</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02738.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19192191?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19192191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Surface decoration by Spirulina polysaccharide enhances the cellular uptake and anticancer efficacy of selenium nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Nanomed.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>835</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>844</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S28278</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22359460?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22359460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Y. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Biological effects of a nano red elemental selenium</article-title>. <source>Biofactors</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/biof.5520150103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11673642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11673642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Elemental selenium at nano size (Nano-Se) as a potential chemopreventive agents with reduced risk of selenium toxicity: comparison with Se-Methylselenocysteine in mice</article-title>. <source>Toxicol. Sci.</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/toxsci/kmf221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17728283</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Che</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>OsPT2, a phosphate transporter, is involved in the active uptake of selenite in rice</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>201</volume>, <fpage>1183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12596</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24491113?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24491113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Difference in selenite absorption between high- and low-selenium rice cultivars and its mechanism</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>
<volume>282</volume>, <fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-005-5706-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Selenium fractionation and speciation in a wetland system</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2619</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es960046l</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>