<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biotechnol Biofuels</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biotechnol Biofuels</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biotechnology for Biofuels</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1754-6834</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6211429</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-018-1298-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A novel FC17/CESA4 mutation causes increased biomass saccharification and lodging resistance by remodeling cell wall in rice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Fengcheng</given-names></name><address><email>lifc_1983@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Sitong</given-names></name><address><email>1519150658@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Hai</given-names></name><address><email>chinaxuhai@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8387-101X</contrib-id><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Quan</given-names></name><address><phone>86-88487184</phone><email>kobexu34@live.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9886 8131</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412557.0</institution-id><institution>Rice Research Institute, </institution><institution>Shenyang Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shenyang, 110866 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>298</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Rice not only produces grains for human beings, but also provides large amounts of lignocellulose residues, which recently highlighted as feedstock for biofuel production. Genetic modification of plant cell walls can potentially enhance biomass saccharification; however, it remains a challenge to maintain a normal growth with enhanced lodging resistance in rice.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">In this study, rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) mutant <italic>fc17</italic>, which harbors the substitution (F426S) at the plant-conserved region (P-CR) of cellulose synthase 4 (CESA4) protein, exhibited slightly affected plant growth and 17% higher lodging resistance compared to the wild-type. More importantly, the mutant showed a 1.68-fold enhancement in biomass saccharification efficiency. Cell wall composition analysis showed a reduction in secondary wall thickness and cellulose content, and compensatory increase in hemicelluloses and lignin content. Both X-ray diffraction and calcofluor staining demonstrated a significant reduction in cellulose crystallinity, which should be a key factor for its high saccharification. Proteomic profiling of wild-type and <italic>fc17</italic> plants further indicated a possible mechanism by which mutation induces cellulose deposition and cell wall remodeling.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">These results suggest that CESA4 P-CR site mutation affects cell wall features especially cellulose structure and thereby causes enhancement in biomass digestion and lodging resistance. Therefore, CESA4 P-CR region is promising target for cell wall modification to facilitate the breeding of bioenergy rice.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13068-018-1298-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Biomass saccharification</kwd><kwd>Cell wall</kwd><kwd>Cellulose CrI</kwd><kwd>CESA</kwd><kwd>Lodging resistance</kwd><kwd>Rice</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par18">Plant cell walls are essential for plant growth and development and provide renewable biomass feedstock for biofuels production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The recalcitrance of plant cell walls leads to a costly biomass process. To reduce recalcitrance, genetic modifications of wall polymers have been applied to enhance biomass saccharification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. However, alterations in wall polymers are mostly associated with defects in plant growth and development; it becomes critical to identify a key gene for cell wall modification that could not substantially affect plant growth but leads to an enhancement in biomass saccharification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">Plants typically contain two different types of cell walls: namely, primary cell walls (PCWs) and secondary cell walls (SCWs). During growth, plant cells are surrounded by a strong yet adaptable primary cell wall, which is mainly composed of cellulose, hemicelluloses, pectins, and proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Once growth has ceased, an additional secondary wall may be deposited, which is mainly composed of cellulose, hemicelluloses, and lignin. Cellulose, consisting of linear chains of &#x003b2;-1,4-linked glucan, is the principal substrate for bioethanol production. Through intra- and inter-chain hydrogen bonding, parallel linear glucan chains are crystalized to form cellulose microfibrils that provide plants with excellent toughness for normal plant growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Crystallinity index (CrI) is a parameter commonly used to quantify cellulose microfibrils crystallinity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], which is one of the most important characteristics of cellulose negatively affecting biomass enzymatic hydrolysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Hemicelluloses are a heterogeneous class of polysaccharides with various sugar units, and arabinoxylans comprise the majority of hemicelluloses in the mature tissues of rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Lignin is a complex phenolic polymer that provide plants with great stiffness for resistance of biotic or abiotic stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">Cellulose biosynthesis is a tightly regulated process that is performed by plasma membrane-spanning cellulose synthase (CESA) complexes (CSCs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The CESA protein in different plant species shares common domains and motifs, such as the zinc fingers, the central cytoplasmic domain with D,D,D,QXXRW motif, and eight transmembrane domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The central cytoplasmic domain contains the plant-conserved region (P-CR) and class-specific region (CSR), which may play a role in CESA protein association and assembly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Genetic and biochemical studies suggest that at least three distinct CESA isoforms are required to form functional CSCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, CesA1, CesA3, and CesA6-like (i.e., CesA2, 5, 6, and 9) CesAs synthesize primary wall cellulose, and CesA4, CesA7, and CesA8 comprise the CSCs necessary for secondary wall cellulose production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Bioinformatics and mutational analysis have shown that OsCesA1, 3, 8 and OsCesA4, 7, 9 are involved in the cellulose synthesis of the primary and secondary cell walls in rice, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">Up to date, three <italic>OsCesA4</italic> mutants have been identified in rice, and all of them show brittleness due to reductions of cellulose content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Apart from the brittleness phenotype, <italic>Tos17</italic> insertional mutant of CESA4 displays the semi-dwarfism and withering of leaf apex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Bc7 (t) has a two-base deletion in exon 10 and a five-base deletion in intron 10 and shows indistinguishable phenotypes from the wild-type plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Different from BC7, BC11 mutation occurs in the fifth transmembrane domain of CESA4 and causes severe dwarfism and low pollen fertility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. These studies demonstrate that mutations in different sites of CESA4 lead to diverse effects on plant growth, indicating a complex role of CESA4 in plant morphological development.</p><p id="Par22">Rice is a major global food crop that produces enormous biomass residues for biofuels and chemical products [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. In this study, we report on a novel CESA4 conserved site mutation that leads to increased lignocellulose enzymatic hydrolysis and lodging resistance by reducing cellulose CrI and remodeling cell wall.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>The <italic>fc17</italic> mutant has a brittleness phenotype caused by a CESA4 conserved site mutation</title><p id="Par23">A <italic>fragile culm 17</italic> (<italic>fc17</italic>) mutant was isolated from a natural population of the <italic>Japonica</italic> cultivar <italic>ShenNong265</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). The extension forces of culms and leaves in <italic>fc17</italic> were respectively reduced to&#x02009;~&#x02009;20% and&#x02009;~&#x02009;30% of those in the wild-type (WT) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). Despite brittleness and reduced extension force, <italic>fc17</italic> did not show significant reduction in breaking force of basal stem internode, an important physiological properties associated with plant lodging resistance (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Phenotypic observations and map-based cloning of the gene for <italic>fc17</italic>. <bold>a</bold> Brittleness of leaves and culms. <bold>b</bold> Measurements of the extension forces (Newtons) of leaves and culms. <bold>c</bold> Measurements of the breaking forces (Newtons) of basal stem internodes. <bold>d</bold> Location of <italic>fc17</italic> mutation with substitutions of Phe residues with Ser at the 426th position of the CESA4 protein. <bold>e</bold> Schematic diagram of domains and the location of <italic>fc17</italic> mutation in CESA4. <bold>f</bold> Protein sequences alignment of FC17 protein family. Black asterisk represents the mutated amino acid. <bold>g</bold> Expression pattern of <italic>CESA4</italic> in various tissues and organs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par24">Using 950 F<sub>2</sub> mutant plants generated from a cross between <italic>fc17</italic> and an <italic>indica</italic> cultivar <italic>MH63</italic>, we identified via map-based cloning a 91-kb region on chromosome 1 that contains the candidate gene. The region includes four putative candidate genes. The first putative is ORF1 (TIGR ID: LOC_Os01g54620), which encodes cellulose synthase catalytic subunit 4 (<italic>OsCESA4</italic>), involving in secondary wall cellulose biosynthesis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d). Sequencing analysis revealed a single-base substitution at the eighth exon, changing TTT to TCT, and resulting in a change in the 426th amino acid from Phe to Ser (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d). This substitution occurred at the P-CR region (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>e), which is conserved in all CESA family proteins of rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>f). Quantitative PCR analysis of CESA4 in multiple tissues and organs revealed that CESA4 primarily expressed in the secondary wall-rich tissues (stem, hull and spikelet) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>g). The <italic>fc17</italic> phenotypes were further complemented by transgenic expression of WT <italic>CESA4</italic> in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant background (<italic>fc17</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>CESA4</italic>), confirming that the missense mutation of CESA4 was responsible for the mutant phenotypes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Agronomic traits observation. <bold>a</bold> Phenotypes and physical properties of the wild-type (WT), <italic>fc17</italic> mutant, and complementary lines (<italic>fc17</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>CESA4</italic>) at the mature stage (scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;10&#x000a0;cm). <bold>b</bold> Plant height. <bold>c</bold> Lodging index. <bold>d</bold> Dry biomass. <bold>e</bold> Tiller numbers. <bold>f</bold> Dry spike. <bold>g</bold> 1000-grain weight. **Indicate significant differences between WT and <italic>fc17</italic> mutant by <italic>t</italic>-test at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, with the increased or decreased percentage (%) calculated by subtraction of the values between the mutant and WT and divided by WT. The error bar indicates SD values (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>The <italic>fc17</italic> mutant exhibits a normal plant growth with higher lodging resistance</title><p id="Par25">Apart from brittleness, the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant exhibited a normal plant growth, similar to that in the WT (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). Despite the relatively short height (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b), 2-year field experiments showed that the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant had significantly improved plant lodging resistance (lodging index was reduced by 17%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). In addition, no significant differences in other important agronomic traits of the WT and <italic>fc17</italic>, including dry biomass, tiller number, dry spike, and 1000-grain weight, were observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d&#x02013;g).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>The <italic>fc17</italic> mutant displays enhanced biomass enzymatic saccharification</title><p id="Par26">Using mature stem materials, we measured biomass enzymatic digestibility (saccharification) in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant by calculating the hexose yields released from enzymatic hydrolysis of pretreated biomass. The <italic>fc17</italic> mutant exhibited significantly higher hexoses yields by up to 1.45-fold than that of the WT, with pretreatments using three concentrations of alkali (0.5%, 1%, and 4% NaOH) and acid (0.5%, 1%, and 2% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Biomass enzymatic saccharification of the wild-type (WT) and <italic>fc17</italic> plants. <bold>a</bold> Hexose yields released from enzymatic (mixed-cellulase) hydrolysis after pretreatment with NaOH and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> at three concentrations. <bold>b</bold> Hexose yields released from three dosages of mixed-cellulase hydrolysis after pretreatment with 1% NaOH and 1% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. **Indicate significant differences between WT and <italic>fc17</italic> mutant by <italic>t</italic>-test at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, with the increased percentage (%) calculated by subtraction of the values between mutant and WT and divided by WT. The error bar indicates SD values (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par27">To evaluate the effect of enzyme dosage on the saccharification of <italic>fc17</italic> and WT plants, enzymatic hydrolysis was performed with different cellulase loadings of 3, 6, and 12 filter paper unit (FPU) per gram of cellulose. A more efficient conversion of lignocellulosic biomass to hexose was observed in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutants, which was up to 1.68-fold higher than that of WT plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b).</p><p id="Par28">To confirm the enhanced biomass enzymatic digestibility of the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant, we evaluated their stem cell tissues in situ and biomass residues in vitro under SEM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Without any pretreatment and enzymatic digestion, no visible in situ differences between stems of the mutant and WT were observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). However, the mutant exhibited more severe destruction and cell loss than that of the WT after 1% NaOH or 1% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> pretreatment and sequential enzymatic hydrolysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). In addition, the biomass residues of the mutant showed rougher surfaces in vitro compared to the WT under 1% NaOH or 1% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> pretreatments and sequential enzymatic hydrolysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b), which agrees with the findings in other grass plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Both in situ and in vitro observations thus confirm that the mutant has high biomass enzymatic digestibility.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Observation of biomass digestion. <bold>a</bold> Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) images of in situ enzymatic digestion of stems at heading stage after 1% NaOH or 1% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> pretreatment and sequential enzymatic hydrolysis. <bold>b</bold> SEM images of in vitro enzymatic digestion of biomass residues released from enzymatic hydrolysis after 1% NaOH or 1% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> pretreatment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>The <italic>fc17</italic> mutant shows altered cell wall structure and composition</title><p id="Par29">To understand the improved lodging resistance and enhanced biomass digestibility in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant, we examined its cell wall structure and composition. Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) showed that the <italic>fc17</italic> had no alterations in the culm cross section structure and cell size, but exhibited reduced wall thickness (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) further revealed that the <italic>fc17</italic> plants displayed thinner and uneven secondary cell walls compared to the WT plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Observations of stem tissues and cell wall structures. <bold>a</bold> Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) images of the second-internode stem at the heading stage of rice. <bold>b</bold> Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) images of the sclerenchyma cell walls. <italic>PCW</italic> primary cell wall, <italic>SCW</italic> secondary cell wall. <bold>c</bold> Cell wall polymer determination. <bold>d</bold> Hemicellulosic monosaccharides composition. <bold>e</bold> Determination of galacturonic acid (GalA) and glucuronic acid (GlcA). <bold>f</bold> Immunodetection of transverse sections of <italic>fc17</italic> and wild-type (WT) culm internodes. Representative micrographs of equivalent sections of mature culm internodes immunolabeled with antibodies directed to xylan (LM10, LM11, and CCRC-M147), homogalacturonan (HG; JIM5 and JIM7) and rhamnogalacturonan-I (RG-1; CCRC-M35) (scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m). *, ** Indicated significant differences between the WT and <italic>fc17</italic> mutant by <italic>t</italic>-test at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and 0.01, respectively, with the increased percentage (%) calculated by subtraction of the values between mutant and WT and divided by WT. The error bar indicates SD values (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par30">To investigate the underlying cause of the altered cell wall structure in <italic>fc17</italic> plants, we performed chemical measurement of three wall polymers in secondary cell wall-rich stems of <italic>fc17</italic> and WT plants. The <italic>fc17</italic> mutant showed a 19% reduction in cellulose levels and a 16% increase in hemicelluloses level and a 14% increase lignin level compared to that in the WT (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c). Furthermore, GC&#x02013;MS analyses revealed that the increase of hemicelluloses content in <italic>fc17</italic> was mainly contributed by the increase in hemicellulosic arabinose and xylose levels (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). In addition, the <italic>fc17</italic> exhibited similar content of galacturonic&#x000a0;acid (GalA) and&#x000a0;glucuronic&#x000a0;acid (GlcA) as compared with WT (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e).</p><p id="Par31">To confirm the wall polymer content detected by chemical approach, we compared equivalent transverse sections of <italic>fc17</italic> and WT culm internodes labeled with antibodies against xylan (LM10, LM11, and CCRC-M147), homogalacturonan (HG; JIM5 and JIM7) and rhamnogalacturonan-I (RG-I; CCRC-M35). All antibodies directed to xylan showed a significantly increased occurrence of their epitope in <italic>fc17</italic>, while HG and RG-1 did not show significant difference between the <italic>fc17</italic> and WT plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>f).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>The <italic>fc17</italic> mutant produces structurally aberrant cellulose microfibrils</title><p id="Par32">Mutations involving CESA proteins not only affect cellulose level but also influence cellulose structure features [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. To explain the increased biomass saccharification in <italic>fc17</italic>, we measured the cellulose crystallinity of both the WT and mutant using the mature stem. X-ray diffraction analysis estimated a 20.8% reduction in cellulose crystallinity in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant compared to the WT (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). As cellulose CrI is positively correlated with its degree of polymerization (DP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], we further examined the cellulose DP of mature stem in both the WT and mutant plants. A 17.7% reduction in the cellulose DP was observed in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant compared to the WT, suggesting that this may have contributed to the observed lower CrI (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Detection of cellulose structural features. <bold>a</bold> Lignocellulose CrI of mature stems using the X-ray diffraction (XRD) method. <bold>b</bold> Cellulose DP of mature stems using viscometry method. <bold>c</bold> Root lengths of the germinated seedlings treated with Calcofluor for 48&#x000a0;h (scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x000a0;cm). *, **Indicate significant differences between the wild-type (WT) and <italic>fc17</italic> mutant by <italic>t</italic>-test at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and 0.01, respectively, with the decreased percentage (%) calculated by subtraction of the values between mutant and WT and divided by WT. The error bar indicates SD values (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par33">Cellulose crystallization can be prevented using dyes that interact with cellulose chains such as Calcofluor White [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. To confirm the observed decrease in cellulose CrI in <italic>fc17</italic> in vitro, we treated the mutant and WT seedlings after germination with three concentrations of calcofluor and then measured the lengths of their root. Calcofluor dramatically repressed root growth in the WT using the intermediate (0.1%) concentration and completely prevented root elongation using a high (0.2%) concentration (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c). However, the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant was highly resistant to calcofluor even at the highest concentration (0.2%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c). The observed greater resistance of <italic>fc17</italic> to high-concentration calcofluor demonstrates that its root growth was insensitive to calcofluor (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c). The differences in the response of <italic>fc17</italic> and WT to calcofluor support that <italic>fc17</italic> possesses an altered cellulose microfibril structure.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Comparative proteomic analysis of WT and <italic>fc17</italic> plants</title><p id="Par34">To elucidate the molecular mechanism(s) by which FC17 regulates the cell wall formation and maintains plant growth, we used an iTRAQ-based (isobaric tags for relative and absolute quantification) proteomics analysis of rice stems at heading stage to identify changes in protein expression between the WT and <italic>fc17</italic> plants. After iTRAQ and liquid chromatography&#x02013;tandem mass spectrometry (LC&#x02013;MS/MS) analysis, a total of 237,056 spectra were identified, of which 57,121 spectra could be matched to peptides in the database and 23,687 were unique peptides (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a). A total of 6053 proteins were identified using the <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> UniProt database. We detected 695 differentially expressed proteins (DEPs) with expression changes&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5-fold between the WT and <italic>fc17</italic>. Of these proteins, 348 were upregulated and 347 were downregulated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b). Pearson correlation analysis showed good correlation among different replicates of the same sample, whereas significant differences were observed between the WT and <italic>fc17</italic> plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Proteome profile analysis of wild-type (WT) and <italic>fc17</italic> mutant by iTRAQ-based proteomic approach. <bold>a</bold> Results of mass spectrometry analysis and protein identification. <bold>b</bold> Number of proteins that are upregulated and downregulated in <italic>fc17</italic> compared with those in the WT. <bold>c</bold> Pearson correlation analysis among the samples from different biological replicate. <bold>d</bold> Western blot analysis of CESA4, CESA7, and CESA9 using specific antibody</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par35">Based on the considerable effects of the <italic>fc17</italic> mutation on cellulose content and CrI, we quantified the expression levels of proteins involved in cellulose production processes by iTRAQ proteasome profile. The protein levels of CESA4, CESA7, and CESA9 forming the secondary wall CSC were respectively reduced by 18%, 15%, and 11% in <italic>fc17</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), which was confirmed by western blot analysis of CESA4, CESA7, and CESA9 using specific antibody (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>d). In contrast, the other CESA proteins (CESA1/2/3/6/8) in <italic>fc17</italic> plants displayed similar expression level compared to that in the WT (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). We also examined the expression levels of BC (Brittle Culm) proteins which contribute to both mechanical strength and cellulose synthesis in rice (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Most of the BC proteins quantified by iTRAQ assay did not exhibited significant alterations between <italic>fc17</italic> and WT plants, with the exception of BC12 (KIF4 family protein) which was reduced by 12% in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Therefore, the <italic>fc17</italic> mutation probably regulates the cellulose production through impairing CESA subunits numbers or association of the secondary cell wall CSCs.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Expression levels of CESA and BC (Brittle Culm) proteins in the wild-type (WT) and <italic>fc17</italic> plants by iTRAQ analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Name</th><th align="left">Locus</th><th align="left">WT</th><th align="left">
<italic>fc17</italic>
</th><th align="left"><italic>fc17</italic>/WT ratio</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="left">Change</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">CESA4</td><td align="left">LOC_Os01g54620</td><td char="." align="char">122.87</td><td char="." align="char">100.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td><td align="left">Down</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CESA7</td><td align="left">LOC_Os10g32980</td><td char="." align="char">135.27</td><td char="." align="char">115.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.85</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td><td align="left">Down</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CESA9</td><td align="left">LOC_Os09g25490</td><td char="." align="char">111.27</td><td char="." align="char">99.57</td><td char="." align="char">0.89</td><td char="." align="char">0.016</td><td align="left">Down</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CESA1</td><td align="left">LOC_Os05g08370</td><td char="." align="char">2783.43</td><td char="." align="char">2965.9</td><td char="." align="char">1.07</td><td char="." align="char">0.622</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">CESA2</td><td align="left">LOC_Os03g59340</td><td char="." align="char">420.27</td><td char="." align="char">410.33</td><td char="." align="char">0.98</td><td char="." align="char">0.084</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">CESA3</td><td align="left">LOC_Os07g24190</td><td char="." align="char">1978.77</td><td char="." align="char">1949.47</td><td char="." align="char">0.99</td><td char="." align="char">0.888</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">CESA6</td><td align="left">LOC_Os07g14850</td><td char="." align="char">386.27</td><td char="." align="char">409.43</td><td char="." align="char">1.06</td><td char="." align="char">0.126</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">CESA8</td><td align="left">LOC_Os07g10770</td><td char="." align="char">1506.37</td><td char="." align="char">1607.2</td><td char="." align="char">1.07</td><td char="." align="char">0.626</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">BC3</td><td align="left">LOC_Os02g50550</td><td char="." align="char">14299.03</td><td char="." align="char">13301.97</td><td char="." align="char">0.93</td><td char="." align="char">0.067</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">BC10</td><td align="left">LOC_Os05g07790</td><td char="." align="char">1273.9</td><td char="." align="char">1179.7</td><td char="." align="char">0.92</td><td char="." align="char">0.052</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">BC12</td><td align="left">LOC_Os09g02650</td><td char="." align="char">71.5</td><td char="." align="char">63.4</td><td char="." align="char">0.88</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td><td align="left">Down</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BC15</td><td align="left">LOC_Os09g32080</td><td char="." align="char">1211.83</td><td char="." align="char">1244.4</td><td char="." align="char">1.03</td><td char="." align="char">0.263</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par36">We further employed Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) enrichment analysis to reveal the pathway affected by the <italic>fc17</italic> mutation (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Although the detected DEPs may be involved in 83 pathways, the categories of carbon fixation and metabolism (ko00710, ko01200), starch and sucrose metabolism (ko00500), phenylpropanoid biosynthesis (ko00940), and phenylalanine metabolism (ko00360) were apparently affected (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Most of lignin biosynthesis-associated proteins that are involved in the phenylpropanoid biosynthesis and phenylalanine metabolism pathways were upregulated in <italic>fc17</italic> (Additional files <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). This result coincides with the higher lignin content in <italic>fc17</italic> relative to the WT. All of 54 DEPs that exist in both carbon fixation and carbon metabolism pathways were upregulated in <italic>fc17</italic> (Additional files <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>). In the starch and sucrose metabolism pathway, 12 of the 16 DEPs annotated as glycosyl hydrolase, sucrose synthase and glucanotransferase were upregulated in <italic>fc17</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>). These proteins produce more substrate for biosynthesis of hemicelluloses and other polysaccharides and might participate in hemicelluloses modification. In addition, two proteins IRX10 (LOC_Os01g70200) and IRX14 (LOC_Os06g47340) which have been reported to be involved in xyan biosynthesis were upregulated in <italic>fc17</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. These results coincides with the higher hemicelluloses content in <italic>fc17</italic> relative to the WT. These findings suggest that the <italic>fc17</italic> mutation probably triggers feedback responses to the cell wall defects, which in turn regulate the cell wall for the maintenance of plant growth and development.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>The altered pathways identified by DEPs between the wild-type (WT) and <italic>fc17</italic> plants using KEGG enrichment analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Pathway</th><th align="left">DEPs with pathway annotation</th><th align="left">All proteins with annotation pathway</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>q</italic>
</th><th align="left">Pathway identifier</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Photosynthesis</td><td char="(" align="char">27 (9.57%)</td><td char="(" align="char">44 (1.98%)</td><td align="left">1.89E&#x02212;14</td><td align="left">1.55E&#x02212;12</td><td align="left">ko00195</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phenylpropanoid biosynthesis</td><td char="(" align="char">29 (10.28%)</td><td char="(" align="char">82 (3.7%)</td><td align="left">6.37E&#x02212;08</td><td align="left">2.61E&#x02212;06</td><td align="left">ko00940</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phenylalanine metabolism</td><td char="(" align="char">12 (4.26%)</td><td char="(" align="char">24 (1.08%)</td><td align="left">9.29E&#x02212;06</td><td align="left">1.90E&#x02212;04</td><td align="left">ko00360</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Carbon fixation</td><td char="(" align="char">19 (6.74%)</td><td char="(" align="char">62 (2.79%)</td><td align="left">1.32E&#x02212;04</td><td align="left">2.16E&#x02212;03</td><td align="left">ko00710</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Starch and sucrose metabolism</td><td char="(" align="char">16 (5.67%)</td><td char="(" align="char">73 (3.29%)</td><td align="left">1.79E&#x02212;02</td><td align="left">1.20E&#x02212;01</td><td align="left">ko00500</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nitrogen metabolism</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (1.77%)</td><td char="(" align="char">14 (0.63%)</td><td align="left">2.42E&#x02212;02</td><td align="left">1.42E&#x02212;01</td><td align="left">ko00910</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Carbon metabolism</td><td char="(" align="char">35 (12.41%)</td><td char="(" align="char">205 (9.24%)</td><td align="left">3.49E&#x02212;02</td><td align="left">1.80E&#x02212;01</td><td align="left">ko01200</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mismatch repair</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (1.77%)</td><td char="(" align="char">21 (0.95%)</td><td align="left">1.18E&#x02212;01</td><td align="left">3.71E&#x02212;01</td><td align="left">ko03430</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DNA replication</td><td char="(" align="char">7 (2.48%)</td><td char="(" align="char">34 (1.53%)</td><td align="left">1.31E&#x02212;01</td><td align="left">3.83E&#x02212;01</td><td align="left">ko03030</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par37">In this study, we identified a novel CESA4 missense allele, <italic>fc17</italic>. Despite the defect in extension strength, <italic>fc17</italic> plants exhibited a relatively normally morphological phenotype compared to the WT, in contrast to previously reported <italic>CESA4</italic> alleles that showed significantly impaired plant growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Although the <italic>fc17</italic> mutation caused a reduction in CESA4 protein level, the cellulose content in mature stems of the <italic>fc17</italic> plants only decreased by 19%, indicating that the mutant might produce enough cellulose to maintain the normal plant growth. Except for CESA, the majority of proteins involved in carbon synthesis and metabolism are upregulated in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant, which might provide sufficient UDPG substrate for the production of hemicelluloses and other polysaccharides. Indeed, the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant exhibited increased hemicelluloses and lignin that partly complement the detrimental effect of reduced cellulose on cell wall structure. These data indicate that cell wall formation is relatively normal in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant, which is further supported by the results of SEM observation. Taken together, out results indicate that the CESA4 P-CR site mutation sustains normal plant growth by producing sufficient cellulose content and by triggering the feedback response to support cell wall formation.</p><p id="Par38">Notably, the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant has exhibited much higher plant lodging resistance than did the wild-type. Plant lodging resistance is a major and integrated agronomic trait, which is predominantly influenced by plant height and stem stiffness (breaking force) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Hence, the relatively short height of <italic>fc17</italic> might causes its enhanced lodging resistance. The <italic>fc17</italic> mutant displays reduced cellulose content, which provides plants with toughness, but its lignin content is significantly increased, which provides plants with excellent stiffness for resistance of biotic and abiotic stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The increase of lignin content in <italic>fc17</italic>, therefore, is an important contributor for its high lodging resistance, which is consistent with previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Importantly, cellulose crystallinity has also been recently demonstrated as the main factor negatively determining plant lodging resistance in rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Therefore, the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant showing much higher lodging resistance should be due to shorter height, increased lignin content and lower cellulose CrI.</p><p id="Par39">Cellulose CrI has been considered to be a negative factor for lignocellulose digestibility because the reduced cellulose CrI increases the accessibility of the enzyme to the lignocellulose substrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Similarly, it is apparent from the data presented here that the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant that exhibited a reduction in CrI displayed significantly improved (30&#x02013;70% increase) lignocellulose enzymatic digestibility after various chemical pretreatments compared to the WT. These results have been confirmed by observations of increased stem digestion of the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant in situ using SEM. Furthermore, <italic>fc17</italic> requires approximately three- to fourfold fewer enzymes or two-fold lower concentration of NaOH and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> to release an equal or greater amount of fermentable sugar than that in the WT plants. These data demonstrate that the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant will be more environmentally friendly and can be an economical option as biofuel feedstock compared with the WT.</p><p id="Par40">The observed reduction in lignocellulose CrI in the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant may be interpreted in three ways. First, as the <italic>fc17</italic> mutation occurs in the P-CR region, it may affect the stability of the plasma membrane-localized CSC particles, thereby causing shorter cellulose chain lengths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Indeed, <italic>fc17</italic> has exhibited a reduced cellulose DP that is negatively correlated with cellulose CrI. Second, the CESA4 subunit mutation may result in intermittent synthesis and inconsistent cellulose chain lengths, thereby disrupting the ability of neighboring cellulose chains to form crystalline structures. Third, it has been reported that hemicelluloses content negative affects cellulose CrI, and thus the increase in hemicelluloses level in the <italic>fc17</italic> should be an additional contributor to its lower lignocellulose CrI.</p><p id="Par41">Genetic modification of plant cell walls has been considered to be a promising solution for reducing biomass recalcitrance and maintaining normal plant growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Since the transgenic approach has been used successfully, utilization of the beneficial target gene in various varieties is a more likely way to be taken. The <italic>fc17</italic> is a promising mutation due to its positive effects on biomass digestibility without any major adverse effects on plant growth. Based on these results, we could further introduce the mutated CESA4 into energy crops such as poplar and switchgrass to improve biomass conversion efficiency. Hence, our findings on the CESA4 P-CR region mutation may offer us a potential way for breeding energy crops.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par42">A new CESA4 allele, <italic>fc17</italic>, shows the substitution (F426S) mutation at the plant-conserved region of CESA4 protein. Despite reduction in cellulose content and cell wall thickness, <italic>fc17</italic> plants displayed relatively normal plant growth and higher lodging resistance compared to the wild-type. Multiple techniques further demonstrated that this mutation significantly reduces cellulose crystallinity, thereby enhancing biomass saccharification. Proteomic profiling based on iTRAQ assay suggested that this mutation triggers feedback response by forming a relatively integrated cell wall to maintain normal plant growth. These results suggest that the plant-conserved region of CESA4 is a promising target for genetic modification for breeding energy crop and cost-effective biomass processing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Plant materials</title><p id="Par43">The <italic>fc17</italic> was isolated from a natural population of the <italic>Japonica</italic> cultivar <italic>ShenNong265</italic>. The homozygous <italic>fc17</italic> mutant and wild-type (WT) plants were grown in experimental fields at Shenyang Agricultural University (Shenyang, China). The mature stem tissues were harvested and dried at 55&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in an oven to a constant weight, and ground through 40-mesh screen (0.425&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.425&#x000a0;mm) and stored in a dry container until use.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Map-based cloning of <italic>fc17</italic></title><p id="Par44">A 5000 F<sub>2</sub> mapping population was generated from the cross between <italic>fc17</italic> and <italic>MH63</italic>, an <italic>indica</italic> cultivar in China. All plants were cultivated in the experimental fields at the Shenyang Agricultural University during the natural growing season. The segregation ratio in F<sub>2</sub> population showed that the normal plants and Brittle Culm plants segregated as 3:1. The <italic>fc17</italic> gene was localized to 91-kb genomic region that contains the <italic>CESA4</italic> gene. The <italic>CESA4</italic> gene of the mutant and its corresponding WT were PCR amplified with KOD-PLUS (TOYOBO) and sequenced with a 3730 sequencer (ABI). For complementation analysis, a 8.53-kb genomic DNA fragment containing the entire <italic>CESA4</italic> coding region, a 1.8-kb upstream sequence, and a 1.5-kb downstream sequence were cloned into the binary vector pCAMBIA 1305 to generate the transformation plasmid. The binary plasmids were introduced into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain <italic>EHA105</italic> and transformed into the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant plants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Measurements of plant mechanical properties and agronomic traits</title><p id="Par45">The extension force of rice culms and leaves were determined using a digital force/length tester (RH-K300, Guangzhou, China). The breaking force and plant lodging index were measured at 30&#x000a0;days after heading as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Rice dry spike, dry biomass, and 1000-grain weight were respectively weighed after the samples were dried in the oven at 60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. All measurements were conducted using nine independent biological duplicates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Plant cell wall fractionation and determination</title><p id="Par46">The plant cell wall fractionation procedure and total cellulose and hemicelluloses assay were conducted as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The soluble sugar, lipids, and starch of the samples were successively removed from the dry biomass power samples by potassium phosphate buffer, chloroform&#x02013;methanol (1:1, v/v), and DMSO-water (9:1, v/v). The remaining pellets were suspended in 4&#x000a0;M KOH containing 1.0&#x000a0;mg/mL sodium borohydride for 1&#x000a0;h at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, and the combined supernatants were regarded as hemicelluloses. The remaining pellets were regarded as total cellulose. All experiments were carried out in biological triplicate.</p><p id="Par47">Total lignin content including acid-insoluble (AIL) and acid-soluble lignin (ASL) were detected by a two-step acid hydrolysis method as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Hemicelluloses monosaccharide and uronic acids (GalA and GlcA) were determined by GC&#x02013;MS. The sample preparations and GC&#x02013;MS analysis were conducted as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Immunolabeling and fluorescence imaging</title><p id="Par48">The stem transverse section samples were incubated in PBS (pH 7.4) containing 5% (w/v) milk protein (MP/PBS) and a diluted antibody solution (1:50) for 1.5&#x000a0;h. Samples were then washed with PBS (pH 7.4) at least 3 times and incubated with a 300-fold diluted secondary antibody (GB21302, Wuhan servicebio technology Ltd., Wuhan, China) linked to fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC) in PBS (pH 7.4) for 1.5&#x000a0;h in darkness.</p><p id="Par49">Fluorescence was observed with a microscope equipped with epifluorescence irradiation and DIC optics (Eclipse C1, Nikon, Tokyo, Japan). Immunofluorescence (green) was observed at wavelength between 510 and 560. All micrographs were captured using equivalent settings, and representative micrographs were shown in this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Cellulose CrI and DP detections</title><p id="Par50">The lignocellulose crystallinity index (CrI) was detected by X-ray diffraction (XRD) method using Rigaku-D/MAX instrument (Ultima III; Japan) as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The relative DP of cellulose was measured by the viscometry method as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Microscopic observations</title><p id="Par51">The second stem internode tissues (0.5&#x000a0;cm sections above the node) at heading stages were cut into 1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;mm pieces, and were observed and photographed under a scanning electron microscope (SEM TM1000, Hitachi Ltd., Tokyo, Japan).</p><p id="Par52">Observation of biomass residues enzymatic digestion in vitro was conducted as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. For plant tissue in situ enzymatic digestion, the second-stem transverse sections at heading stages were treated with 1% NaOH or 1% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, washed with distilled water until pH 7.0 and incubated with 1&#x000a0;g/L mixed cellulase for 2&#x000a0;h at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. After enzymatic hydrolysis, the tissue samples were observed and photographed under a SEM. The mixed cellulase containing &#x003b2;-glucanase (&#x02265;&#x02009;6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup>&#x000a0;U), cellulase (&#x02265;&#x02009;600&#x000a0;U), and xylanase (&#x02265;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;U) was commercially available from Imperial Jade Bio-technology Co., Ltd (Ningxia, 750002, China).</p><p id="Par53">Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) was used to observe the cell wall structures in the third leaf veins of three-leave-old seedlings as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The samples were washed in the PBS buffer, and then post-fixed in 2% (w/v) osmium tetroxide (OsO4) for 1&#x000a0;h and embedded with Super Kit (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA). Sample sections were cut with an Ultracut E ultramicrotome (Leica) and picked up on formvar-coated copper grids. After post-staining with uranyl acetate and lead citrate, the specimens were viewed under a Hitachi H7700 (Hitachi Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) transmission electron microscope.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Biomass pretreatment and enzymatic hydrolysis</title><p id="Par54">The chemical (H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, NaOH) pretreatment and sequential enzymatic hydrolysis were performed as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. For NaOH pretreatment, the ground biomass powder was added with three concentration (0.5%, 1%, 4%; w/v) of NaOH. For H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> pretreatment, the biomass powder was added with three concentration (0.5%, 1%, 2%; v/v) of H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and heated at 121&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x000a0;min. The samples of chemical (NaOH, H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) pretreatments were shaken at 150&#x000a0;r/min for 2&#x000a0;h at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, and centrifuged at 3000<italic>g</italic> for 5&#x000a0;min. The remaining pellet was washed with distilled water until pH 7.0. The remaining residue was collected for enzymatic hydrolysis. All experiments were performed in the biological triplicates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Effect of calcofluor treatment on plant growth</title><p id="Par55">The germinated seeds of the <italic>fc17</italic> mutant and WT plants were transferred onto the MS media contained Calcofluor White dye (Sigma-Aldrich Co. LLC, California, USA) at different concentrations (0.05%, 0.1% and 0.2%). After 24-h incubation, the root length was measured every 12&#x000a0;h.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Protein extraction and western blot</title><p id="Par56">Fresh rice stem tissues at heading stage were ground to a fine powder in liquid nitrogen, and 0.5&#x000a0;g powder was extracted using Plant Total Protein Extraction Kit (Invent Biotech, Beijing, China; SD-008/SN-009) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The protein content was measured with a BCA protein assay reagent (Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology, Jiangsu, China). The protein level of CESA4, CESA7, and CESA9 was determined by western blot analysis as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The dilution of anti-CESA4, anti-CESA7, anti-CESA9, and anti-tubulin (Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology, Jiangsu, China) was performed as 1:500, 1:500, 1:500, and 1:1000, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Protein digestion</title><p id="Par57">Protein digestion was performed using the FASP method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. A total of 300&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g proteins from each sample were placed on an ultrafiltration filter (30&#x000a0;kDa cutoff, Sartorius, Gottingen, Germany) that had 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L UA buffer (8&#x000a0;M urea, 150&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, pH 8.0). It was then centrifuged at 14,000<italic>g</italic> for 30&#x000a0;min and washed with 200 &#x000b5;L of UA buffer. About 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of 50&#x000a0;mM iodoacetamide was added to the filter to block reduced cysteine residues. The samples were maintained at room temperature for 30&#x000a0;min in the dark, followed by centrifugation at a speed of 14,000<italic>g</italic> for 30&#x000a0;min. UA buffer (100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L) was used to wash the filters twice. Approximately 100 &#x000b5;L of a dissolution buffer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) was placed on the filter. This was centrifuged at 14,000<italic>g</italic> for 20&#x000a0;min, and then repeated twice. The protein suspensions were subjected to enzyme digestion with 40&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of trypsin (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) buffer (4&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g trypsin in 40&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of dissolution buffer) for 16&#x02013;18&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The final filter unit was transferred to a new tube that was spun at 14,000<italic>g</italic> for 30&#x000a0;min. The peptides were collected as a filtrate and the concentration of the peptides was measured at an optical density with a 280&#x000a0;nm wavelength (OD<sub>280</sub>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>iTRAQ labeling and fractionation by strong cation exchange chromatography</title><p id="Par58">Protein peptides (100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g) from each group were labeled using the 8plex iTRAQ reagents multiplex kit (ABI, Foster City, CA, USA) (isobaric tags 113, 114, and 116 for the group without CJD and isobaric tags 118, 119, and 121 for the sCJD group). The 8plex iTRAQ reagents were allowed to reach room temperature, centrifuged, and reconstituted with 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L isopropyl alcohol to dissolve the iTRAQ labeling reagent. The iTRAQ labeling reagents were added to the corresponding peptide samples and reacted at room temperature for 1&#x000a0;h. A 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L aliquot of water was added to stop the labeling reaction. A 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L aliquot of sample was removed from each group to test labeling and extraction efficiency, and the sample was subjected to a matrix assisted laser desorption ionization procedure after Ziptip desalting. The six sample groups were pooled and vacuum-dried. Each pool of mixed peptides was lyophilized and dissolved in solution A (2% acetonitrile [ACN] and 20&#x000a0;mM ammonium formate, pH 10). Then, the samples were loaded onto a reverse-phase column (Luna C18, 4.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;150&#x000a0;mm; Phenomenex, Torrance, CA, USA) and eluted using a step linear elution program: 0&#x02013;10% buffer B (500&#x000a0;mM KCl, 10&#x000a0;mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> in 25% ACN, pH 2.7) for 10&#x000a0;min, 10&#x02013;20% buffer B for 25&#x000a0;min, 20&#x02013;45% buffer B for 5&#x000a0;min, and 50&#x02013;100% buffer B for 5&#x000a0;min at a flow rate of 0.8&#x000a0;mL/min. The samples were collected each min and centrifuged for 5&#x02013;45&#x000a0;min. The fractions collected were finally combined into 10 pools and desalted on C18 Cartridges (Empore&#x02122; standard density SPE C18 Cartridges, bed I.D. 7&#x000a0;mm, 3&#x000a0;mL volume; Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Liquid chromatography&#x02013;tandem mass spectrometry (LC&#x02013;MS/MS) analysis</title><p id="Par59">The reconstituted peptides were analyzed with the Q-Exactive mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) coupled with a nano high-performance liquid chromatography (UltiMate 3000 LC Dionex; Thermo Fisher Scientific) system. The peptides were loaded onto a C18-reversed phase column (3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m-C18 resin, 75&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;15&#x000a0;cm) and separated on an analytical column (5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m C18 resin, 150&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;cm; Dr. Maisch GmbH, Ammerbuch, Germany) using mobile phase A: 0.5% formic acid [FA]/H<sub>2</sub>O and B: 0.5% FA/ACN at a flow rate of 300 nL/min, using a 150&#x000a0;min gradient. Spectra were acquired in data-dependent mode. The 10&#x000a0;most intense ions selected for MS scanning (300&#x02013;1800&#x000a0;<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic>, 60,000 resolution at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 400, accumulation of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;106 ions for a maximum of 500&#x000a0;ms, 1 microscan). The isolation window was 1.3&#x000a0;<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic>, and the MS/MS spectra were accumulated for 150&#x000a0;ms using an Orbitrap. MS/MS spectra were measured at resolution of 15,000 at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 400. Dynamic precursor exclusion was allowed for 120&#x000a0;s after each MS/MS spectrum measurement and was set to 17,500 at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 200. Normalized collision energy was 30&#x000a0;eV and the underfill ratio, which specifies the minimum percentage of the target value likely to be reached at the maximum fill time, was defined as 0.1%. The instrument was run with peptide recognition mode enabled.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Database search and protein quantification</title><p id="Par60">The raw mass data were processed for the peptide data analysis using Proteome Discoverer 1.4 (ver. 1.4.0.288; Thermo Fisher Scientific) with a false discovery rate (FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>N</italic>(decoy)*2/[(<italic>N</italic>(decoy)&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>N</italic>(target)]&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1% and expected cutoff or ion score&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 (with 95% confidence) for searching the <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> UniProt database. Protein probabilities were assigned using the Protein Prophet algorithm, and proteins with at least two unique peptides were identified. The upregulated or downregulated proteins in both replicates with relative quantification <italic>p</italic>-values&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and 1.5-fold-changes were selected as differentially expressed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Bioinformatics analysis</title><p id="Par61">The interactions among the differentially expressed proteins with a 1.5-fold change were determined using Pathway Studio software and the ResNet database (KEGG). The Pathway Maps tool was employed to enrich the pathways, and <italic>p</italic>-values were calculated based on a hypergeometric distribution, with the default database used as the background. Significant pathway enrichment was defined as a corrected FDR of <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05, and proteins with&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.5-fold change were considered differentially abundant proteins.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec27"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_MOESM1_ESM.pptx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1.</bold> Comparison of agronomic traits of <italic>fc17</italic> and its wild-type (WT) under field conditions (Shenyang, China, 2016&#x02013;2017).</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_MOESM2_ESM.pptx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2.</bold> 1.5-fold alterations of proteins involved in phenylpropanoid biosynthesis in comparison of <italic>fc17</italic> iTRAQ data to that of the WT.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_MOESM3_ESM.pptx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 3.</bold> 1.5-fold alterations of proteins involved in phenylalanine metabolism in comparison of <italic>fc17</italic> iTRAQ data to that of the WT.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_MOESM4_ESM.pptx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 4.</bold> 1.5-fold alterations of proteins involved in carbon fixation in comparison of <italic>fc17</italic> iTRAQ data to that of the WT.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_MOESM5_ESM.pptx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 5.</bold> 1.5-fold alterations of proteins involved in carbon metabolism in comparison of <italic>fc17</italic> iTRAQ data to that of the WT.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_MOESM6_ESM.pptx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 6.</bold> 1.5-fold alterations of proteins involved in starch and sucrose metabolism in comparison of <italic>fc17</italic> iTRAQ data to that of the WT.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1298_MOESM7_ESM.pptx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 7.</bold> Comparison of proteins involved in hemicelluloses biosynthesis in the <italic>fc17</italic> and WT based on iTRAQ assay.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CESA</term><def><p id="Par4">cellulose synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CrI</term><def><p id="Par5">crystallinity index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CSCs</term><def><p id="Par6">cellulose synthase complexes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CSR</term><def><p id="Par7">class-specific region</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GalA</term><def><p id="Par8">galacturonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GlcA</term><def><p id="Par9">glucuronic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p id="Par10">Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LC&#x02013;MS/MS</term><def><p id="Par11">liquid chromatography&#x02013;tandem mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>iTRAQ</term><def><p id="Par12">isobaric tags for relative and absolute quantification</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCWs</term><def><p id="Par13">primary cell walls</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P-CR</term><def><p id="Par14">plant-conserved region</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SCWs</term><def><p id="Par15">secondary cell walls</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SEM</term><def><p id="Par16">scanning electron microscope</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TEM</term><def><p id="Par17">transmission electron microscopy</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>LF and XQ designed this study and wrote the manuscript. XQ performed map-based cloning of the <italic>fc17</italic> gene. LF performed cell wall composition analysis and iTRAQ-based proteomic profiling. LS and XH performed agronomic traits measurement, biomass digestion analysis, and electron microscope view. XQ revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par62">We would like to thank all colleagues at the Rice Research Institute of Shenyang Agricultural University for reading and participating in the discussions relating to the preparation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par63">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par64">All data supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the manuscript and additional files.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par65">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par66">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par67">The National Natural Science Foundation of China (31700259) and the Doctoral Scientific Research Foundation of Liaoning Province (201601107) supported this study.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par68">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellulose synthesis in higher plants</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.22.022206.160206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16824006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biswal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Atmodjo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattathil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Amos</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkeler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Working towards recalcitrance mechanisms: increased xylan and homogalacturonan production by overexpression of <italic>GAlactUronosylTransferase12</italic> (<italic>GAUT12</italic>) causes increased recalcitrance and decreased growth in <italic>Populus</italic></article-title><source>Biotechnol Biofuels</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-017-1002-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29371885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkeler</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinchee</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jawdy</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of a domain of unknown function 231-containing protein increases <italic>O</italic>-xylan acetylation and cellulose biosynthesis in <italic>Populus</italic></article-title><source>Biotechnol Biofuels</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>311</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-017-0998-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29299061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattathil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Avci</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of function of folylpolyglutamate synthetase 1 reduces lignin content and improves cell wall digestibility in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Biotechnol Biofuels</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>224</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-015-0403-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26697113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic engineering of energy crops: a strategy for biofuel production in China</article-title><source>J Integr Plant Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2010.01022.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21205188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth of the plant cell wall</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm1746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16261190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavoine</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Desloges</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufresne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bras</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microfibrillated cellulose&#x02014;its barrier properties and applications in cellulosic materials: a review</article-title><source>Carbohydr Polym</source><year>2012</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2012.05.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22839998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Realff</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bommarius</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellulose crystallinity-a key predictor of the enzymatic hydrolysis rate</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><year>2010</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>1571</fpage><lpage>1582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2010.07585.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20148968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Zuhair</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of crystallinity of cellulose on the rate of reducing sugars production by heterogeneous enzymatic hydrolysis</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2008</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>4078</fpage><lpage>4085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2007.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17935980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-level hemicellulosic arabinose predominately affects lignocellulose crystallinity for genetically enhancing both plant lodging resistance and biomass enzymatic digestibility in rice mutants</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25418842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arabinose substitution degree in xylan positively affects lignocellulose enzymatic digestibility after various NaOH/H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> pretreatments in <italic>Miscanthus</italic></article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2013</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2012.12.107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23334020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three lignocellulose features that distinctively affect biomass enzymatic digestibility under NaOH and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> pretreatments in <italic>Miscanthus</italic></article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2013</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2012.12.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23298647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Realff</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bommarius</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multivariate statistical analysis of X-ray data from cellulose: a new method to determine degree of crystallinity and predict hydrolysis rates</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2010</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>4461</fpage><lpage>4471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2010.01.068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20172714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheller</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulvskov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hemicelluloses</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042809-112315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zha</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mild alkali-pretreatment effectively extracts guaiacyl-rich lignin for high lignocellulose digestibility coupled with largely diminishing yeast fermentation inhibitors in <italic>Miscanthus</italic></article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2014</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2014.07.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25079210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundquist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunow</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lignins: natural polymers from oxidative coupling of 4-hydroxyphenyl-propanoids</article-title><source>Phytochem Rev</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:PHYT.0000047809.65444.a4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant cellulose synthesis: cESA proteins crossing kingdoms</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2014.07.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25104231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pear</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawagoe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreckengost</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Delmer</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stalker</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Higher plants contain homologs of the bacterial <italic>celA</italic> genes encoding the catalytic subunit of cellulose synthase</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>12637</fpage><lpage>12642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.22.12637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8901635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olek</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Makowski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciesielski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The structure of the catalytic domain of a plant cellulose synthase and its assembly into dimers</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2996</fpage><lpage>3009</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.126862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25012190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sethaphong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Haigler</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubicki</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonetta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>DeBolt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tertiary model of a plant cellulose synthase</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>7512</fpage><lpage>7517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1301027110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23592721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Paredez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsdottir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Doblin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Poindexter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic evidence for three unique components in primary cell-wall cellulose synthase complexes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>15566</fpage><lpage>15571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0706592104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17878302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desprez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Juraniec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowell</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pochylova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Parcy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Organization of cellulose synthase complexes involved in primary cell wall synthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>15572</fpage><lpage>15577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0706569104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17878303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Howells</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Huttly</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions among three distinct CesA proteins essential for cellulose synthesis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>1450</fpage><lpage>1455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0337628100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OsCESA9 conserved-site mutation leads to largely enhanced plant lodging resistance and biomass enzymatic saccharification by reducing cellulose DP and crystallinity in rice</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1093</fpage><lpage>1104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28117552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression profiling and integrative analysis of the CESA/CSL superfamily in rice</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>282</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21167079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Onosato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirochika</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three distinct rice cellulose synthase catalytic subunit genes required for cellulose synthesis in the secondary wall</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.022442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12970476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A missense mutation in the transmembrane domain of CESA4 affects protein abundance in the plasma membrane and results in abnormal cell wall biosynthesis in rice</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-009-9536-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19697141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine mapping and isolation of bc7(t), allelic to OsCesA4</article-title><source>J Genet Genom.</source><year>2007</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>1027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1673-8527(07)60115-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dom&#x000ed;nguez-Escrib&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Porcar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rice straw management: the big waste</article-title><source>Biofuel Bioprod Biorefining.</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bbb.196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hemicelluloses negatively affect lignocellulose crystallinity for high biomass digestibility under NaOH and H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> pretreatments in <italic>Miscanthus</italic></article-title><source>Biotechnol Biofuels</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>58</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1754-6834-5-58</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22883929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Himmelspach</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittington</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasenbein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The anisotropy1 D604N mutation in the Arabidopsis cellulose synthase 1 catalytic domain reduces cell wall crystallinity and the velocity of cellulose synthase complexes</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.211565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23532584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertolo</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Petti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cellulose microfibril crystallinity is reduced by mutating C-terminal transmembrane region residues CESA1 A903V and CESA3 T942I of cellulose synthase</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>4098</fpage><lpage>4103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1200352109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22375033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haigler</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Benziman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calcofluor white ST alters the in vivo assembly of cellulose microfibrils</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1980</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.7434003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7434003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiniquy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Varanasi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harholt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Katnelson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three novel rice genes closely related to the <italic>Arabidopsis IRX9</italic>, <italic>IRX9L</italic>, and <italic>IRX14</italic> genes and their roles in xylan biosynthesis</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>83</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2013.00083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23596448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Vega-s&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhertbruggen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiniquy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Canlasa</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagerstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of OsIRX10 leads to decreased xylan content in rice culm cell walls and improved biomass saccharification</article-title><source>Mol Plant.</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/sss135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Visperas</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ereful</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhuiya</surname><given-names>MSU</given-names></name><name><surname>Julfiquar</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lodging-related morphological traits of hybrid rice in a tropical irrigated ecosystem</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2006.12.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ennos</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stem and root characteristics associated with lodging resistance in four winter wheat cultivars</article-title><source>J Agric Sci</source><year>1994</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0021859600068428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The expression of caffeic acid 3-O-methyltransferase in two wheat genotypes differing in lodging resistance</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2763</fpage><lpage>2771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ammonium oxalate-extractable uronic acids positively affect biomass enzymatic digestibility by reducing lignocellulose crystallinity in <italic>Miscanthus</italic></article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2015</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2015.07.099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26257050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisniewski</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zougman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraj</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universal sample preparation method for proteome analysis</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19377485</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>