<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biotechnol Biofuels</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biotechnol Biofuels</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biotechnology for Biofuels</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1754-6834</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6156916</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1259</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-018-1259-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mechanistic insight in the selective delignification of wheat straw by three white-rot fungal species through quantitative <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS and whole cell wall HSQC NMR</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Erven</surname><given-names>Gijs</given-names></name><address><email>gijs.vanerven@wur.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nayan</surname><given-names>Nazri</given-names></name><address><email>nazri.nayan@live.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>Anton S. M.</given-names></name><address><email>anton.sonnenberg@wur.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>Wouter H.</given-names></name><address><email>wouter.hendriks@wur.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>John W.</given-names></name><address><email>john.cone@wur.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kabel</surname><given-names>Mirjam A.</given-names></name><address><phone>+31 317 483209</phone><email>mirjam.kabel@wur.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0791 5666</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4818.5</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Food Chemistry, </institution><institution>Wageningen University &#x00026; Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Bornse Weilanden 9, 6708 WG Wageningen, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0791 5666</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4818.5</institution-id><institution>Animal Nutrition Group, </institution><institution>Wageningen University &#x00026; Research, </institution></institution-wrap>De Elst 1, 6708 WD Wageningen, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0791 5666</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4818.5</institution-id><institution>Plant Breeding, </institution><institution>Wageningen University &#x00026; Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Droevendaalsesteeg 1, 6708 PB Wageningen, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>262</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The white-rot fungi <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic> (<italic>Cs</italic>), <italic>Pleurotus eryngii</italic> (<italic>Pe</italic>), and <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic> (<italic>Le</italic>) have been shown to be high-potential species for selective delignification of plant biomass. This delignification improves polysaccharide degradability, which currently limits the efficient lignocellulose conversion into biochemicals, biofuels, and animal feed. Since selectivity and time efficiency of fungal delignification still need optimization, detailed understanding of the underlying mechanisms at molecular level is required. The recently developed methodologies for lignin quantification and characterization now allow for the in-depth mapping of fungal modification and degradation of lignin and, thereby, enable resolving underlying mechanisms.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">Wheat straw treated by two strains of <italic>Cs</italic> (<italic>Cs1</italic> and <italic>Cs12)</italic>, <italic>Pe</italic> (<italic>Pe3</italic> and <italic>Pe6)</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> (<italic>Le8</italic> and <italic>Le10)</italic> was characterized using semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS during fungal growth (1, 3, and 7&#x000a0;weeks). The remaining lignin after 7&#x000a0;weeks was quantified and characterized using <sup>13</sup>C lignin internal standard based py-GC&#x02013;MS and whole cell wall HSQC NMR. Strains of the same species showed similar patterns of lignin removal and degradation. <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> outperformed <italic>Pe</italic> in terms of extent and selectivity of delignification (<italic>Cs&#x02009;</italic>&#x02265;<italic>&#x02009;Le&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003e;&#x0003e;<italic>&#x02009;Pe)</italic>. The highest lignin removal [66% (w/w); <italic>Cs</italic>1] was obtained after 7&#x000a0;weeks, without extensive carbohydrate degradation (factor 3 increased carbohydrate-to-lignin ratio). Furthermore, though after treatment with <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> comparable amounts of lignin remained, the structure of the residual lignin vastly differed. For example, C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized substructures accumulated in <italic>Cs</italic> treated lignin up to 24% of the total aromatic lignin, a factor two higher than in <italic>Le</italic>-treated lignin. Contrarily, ferulic acid substructures were preferentially targeted by <italic>Le</italic> (and <italic>Pe</italic>). Interestingly, <italic>Pe</italic>-spent lignin was specifically depleted of tricin (40% reduction). The overall subunit composition (H:G:S) was not affected by fungal treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3"><italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> are both able to effectively and selectively delignify wheat straw, though the underlying mechanisms are fundamentally different. We are the first to identify that <italic>Cs</italic> degrades the major <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 ether linkage in grass lignin mainly via C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;<italic>O</italic>&#x02013;aryl cleavage, while C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> cleavage of inter-unit linkages predominated for <italic>Le.</italic> Our research provides a new insight on how fungi degrade lignin, which contributes to further optimizing the biological upgrading of lignocellulose.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13068-018-1259-9) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Lentinula edodes</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Pleurotus eryngii</italic></kwd><kwd>Selectivity</kwd><kwd>Lignin degradation</kwd><kwd>Lignin quantification</kwd><kwd>C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidation</kwd><kwd>Ligninolytic enzymes</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004891</institution-id><institution>Wageningen University Fund</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003093</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Higher Education, Malaysia</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par4">Lignocellulosic biomass, such as wheat straw, is a highly abundant, valuable source of polysaccharides for the production of animal feed or biofuels and biochemicals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The presence of lignin, however, hinders the conversion of these polysaccharides and, therefore, necessitates the use of pretreatments aimed at lignin removal or degradation. These physical and/or chemical hydrothermal pretreatments require extensive amounts of energy and chemicals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. A sustainable alternative is the use of white-rot fungi as a biological pretreatment and is increasingly receiving attention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Among these fungi, the species <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic> (<italic>Cs</italic>), <italic>Pleurotus eryngii</italic> (<italic>Pe</italic>), and <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic> (<italic>Le</italic>) were shown to be particularly promising as they extensively and selectively removed lignin over cell wall polysaccharides, in comparison with other more commonly studied white-rot fungi like <italic>P. chrysosporium</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Such fungal delignification results in a greatly enhanced enzymatic degradability of polysaccharides in further downstream processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. To optimize the pretreatment with these fungi, mainly in terms of selectivity and time efficiency, it is important to understand delignification and the underlying mechanisms at a molecular level. Such mechanistic insight facilitates the pinpointing of potential bottlenecks in the (enzymatic) process and might provide means to circumvent them, e.g., via supplementation of co-factors for the respective enzymes. Besides enabling control of the pretreatment process, mechanistic insight expands our understanding of how fungi function in nature and how they contribute to terrestrial carbon-recycling.</p><p id="Par5">Lignin is a heterogeneous phenolic polymer that, in grasses, is composed of <italic>p</italic>-hydroxyphenyl (H), guaiacyl (G), and syringyl (S) subunits, which are linked through a variety of carbon&#x02013;carbon and aryl-ether linkages, with the <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 ether as most abundant inter-unit linkage (~&#x02009;80%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Structural complexity of grass-type lignin is further enhanced by the incorporation of <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid, ferulic acid, and tricin in the macromolecule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. A schematic structure of wheat straw lignin is presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Wheat straw lignin model. The most abundant substructures are included, attempting to fairly represent the relative abundances of each moiety, based on literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. H: <italic>p</italic>-hydroxyphenyl unit; G: guaiacyl unit; S: syringyl unit; A: <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032;alkyl-aryl ether; A&#x02032;: <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032;alkyl-aryl-ether &#x003b3;-acylated; A<sub>ox</sub>: <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032;alkyl-aryl-ether C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized; B: phenylcoumaran; C: resinol; D: dibenzodioxocin; E: <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>,<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-diarylether; F: spirodienone; I: cinnamyl alcohol (or aldehyde); T: tricin; <italic>p</italic>CA: <italic>p</italic>-coumarate; FA: ferulate (R = H or arabinose). Note that &#x003b3;-acylation here is only shown on <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 linkages, while in fact any free &#x003b3;-OH can by acylated. For simplicity only monomeric 8-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032; linked FA is shown, though many other ferulate and diferulate linkages are known to exist. For more detailed structures, see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">Lignin degradation by white-rot fungi in general relies on a complex enzymatic machinery which is, depending on the species, mainly based on lignin peroxidases (LiP), manganese peroxidases (MnP), laccases (Lac), and the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> generating aryl-alcohol oxidases (AAO). Collectively, the catalytic performance of these enzymes results in the generation of radicals, i.e., aromatic or hydroxyl radicals, which can lead to various reactions such as C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> cleavage, breakdown of the <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 ether, aromatic ring cleavage, and demethoxylation, but also to polymerization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Although <italic>C. subvermispora</italic>, <italic>P. eryngii</italic>, and <italic>L. edodes</italic> all produce MnP, Lac, and AAO, they were shown to differ in the number of genes encoding for these enzymes, which suggests different dependencies on the particular enzymes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Interestingly, none of these fungi possesses genes encoding for LiP. Instead, versatile peroxidases were detected in <italic>Pe</italic>, whereas <italic>Cs</italic> was shown to produce two enzymes with lignin peroxidase and versatile peroxidase like activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. It is clear from this variation in ligninolytic enzyme-encoding genes that these fungi employ different strategies for delignification. However, whether these different strategies emerge into different underlying mechanisms remains unknown. Furthermore, it is poorly understood whether certain structural motifs of lignin are preferentially degraded or modified by the respective enzymatic machineries and, thus, lead to different residual lignin structures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">To the best of our knowledge, research on the conversion of grass lignin is limited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], and studies, where the fungi were compared under the same experimental conditions, are scarce [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Furthermore, lignin degradation was, contentwise, only determined using unspecific gravimetric analysis, which is thought to be particularly inaccurate for fungal-grown samples due to the presence of residual chitin and includes (acid) recalcitrant lignin only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Moreover, the scarce studies aimed at elucidating structural features of fungal-treated lignin in situ focused on using qualitative pyrolysis gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry (py-GC&#x02013;MS). Though considerable structural changes in fungal-treated wheat straw lignin could be revealed, mainly in terms of preference for phenolic lignin substructures and accumulation of C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized substructures, underlying mechanisms could not be elucidated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. More accurate and in-depth analysis of both lignin content as well as lignin structural features in fungal-treated biomass is expected to further resolve the employed lignin degrading mechanisms.</p><p id="Par9">The recent development of a highly accurate pyrolysis gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry (py-GC&#x02013;MS) method that uses <sup>13</sup>C lignin as internal standard (<sup>13</sup>C-IS) offers a great opportunity to specifically quantify residual lignin content in situ, while simultaneously providing structural insight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In addition, developments in the use of heteronuclear single quantum coherence (HSQC) nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) allow the analysis of whole cell wall samples in situ, without prior isolation or derivatisation of lignin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. In situ analysis avoids the need for laborious lignin isolation procedures that may lead to partial extraction and polymer modification, especially for fungal-treated lignin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">In this research, the combination of quantitative <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS and whole cell wall HSQC NMR was applied to fungal-treated wheat straw after growth of two strains of <italic>C. subvermispora</italic>, <italic>P. eryngii</italic>, and <italic>L. edodes</italic> to obtain a better understanding of their delignification mechanisms. We found that both <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> outperform <italic>Pe</italic> in terms of delignification effectivity and selectivity and, furthermore, vastly differed in residual lignin structures. We were able to identify that these lignin structures originated from fundamentally different delignification mechanisms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Materials</title><p id="Par11">All chemicals were obtained from commercial suppliers and used without further purification. Water used in all experiments was purified via a Milli-Q water system (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Preparation of the fungal-treated wheat straw</title><p id="Par12">Samples used in the present study were collected from a main experiment on selecting the best performing fungal strains based on their capability to improve the in vitro ruminal degradability of the treated straw [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Two high-potential strains from three different fungal species were selected: <italic>Cs</italic>1 (CBS 347.63) and <italic>Cs</italic>12 (ME-485) strains for <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic>, <italic>Pe</italic>3 (Mycelia2600) and <italic>Pe</italic>6 (AL04) for <italic>Pleurotus eryngii</italic> and <italic>Le</italic>8 (sh 03/08) and <italic>Le</italic>10 (LE75) for <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic>. Procedures for fungal strain preparation and pretreatment of the wheat straw have been previously described in detail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Briefly, all strains were maintained on malt extract agar before a piece of that agar (1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;cm) was used to prepare the spawn for each fungus. The spawn was prepared using sterilized sorghum grains and was incubated at 24&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for up to 5&#x000a0;weeks. Organic wheat straw (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) was purchased from a local farmer in The Netherlands (batch size 300&#x000a0;kg) and chopped into pieces of approximately 3&#x000a0;cm. Approximately 5&#x000a0;kg of the chopped wheat straw was soaked in water for 3&#x000a0;days at room temperature and excess water was drained for 5&#x000a0;h, resulting in a dry matter loss of 9.3% (w/w). Each container (185&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;185&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;78&#x000a0;mm, Combiness, Nevele, Belgium) was adjusted to contain 90.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3&#x000a0;g of dry matter with a moisture content of ~&#x000a0;74% (w/w). After autoclaving at 121&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;h, the straw was inoculated with the prepared spawn at 10% of the dry weight, thereby introducing negligible amounts of sorghum lignin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The wheat straw (treated and untreated with fungi) was incubated in triplicate under solid-state fermentation at 24&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in a climate-controlled chamber (relative humidity&#x02009;=&#x02009;75%) for 1, 3, and 7&#x000a0;weeks. After weighing and thorough mixing, ~&#x02009;5&#x000a0;g of fresh sample was taken for pH measurements. The remaining sample material was freeze-dried and ground over a 1&#x000a0;mm sieve using a cross beater mill (100AN, Peppink, Olst, The Netherlands). Since biological triplicates showed ~&#x02009;5% RSD in the conventional compositional feed analysis, they were thoroughly mixed in equal dry matter amounts (1&#x000a0;g each) to one replicate and ball-milled in a MM200 mixer mill (Retsch, Haan, Germany) for further analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. We previously showed that untreated straws were stable during incubation and showed minimal variation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Therefore, the untreated wheat straw without incubation was used as control sample in this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Carbohydrate content and composition</title><p id="Par13">Carbohydrate content and composition was determined in triplicate by a modified method reported by Englyst and Cummings using inositol as internal standard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Ten mg of each sample was treated with 72% (w/w) H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> for 1&#x000a0;h at 30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C followed by 1&#x000a0;M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> for 3&#x000a0;h at 100&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The constituent monosaccharides released were analyzed as their alditol-acetate derivatives using gas chromatography (Thermo Scientific, Synnyvale, CA, USA) and represented as anhydromonosaccharides. The uronic acids released after the acid hydrolysis step were determined in duplicate as anhydrouronic acid content by an automated meta-hydroxydiphenyl assay with the addition of sodium tetraborate using an auto-analyzer (Skalar Analytical BV, Breda, The Netherlands) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Glucuronic acid (Fluka AG, Busch, Switzerland) was used as a reference (0&#x02013;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g&#x000a0;mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Total carbohydrate content was calculated as the sum of neutral anhydrocarbohydrates and anhydrouronic acids.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS</title><p id="Par14">Pyrolysis was performed with an EGA/PY-3030D Multi-shot pyrolyzer (Frontier Laboratories, New Ulm, MN, USA) equipped with an AS-1020E Autoshot auto-sampler as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The pyrolyzer was coupled to a GC&#x02013;MS using a Trace GC equipped with a DB-1701 fused-silica capillary column (30&#x000a0;m &#x000d7; 0.25&#x000a0;mm i.d. 0.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m film thickness) coupled to a DSQ-II mass spectrometer (both Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). Samples were weighed using an XP6 excellence-plus microbalance (Mettler Toledo, Columbus, OH, USA). Pyrolysis of total biomass (~&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g) was performed at 500&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min with an interface temperature of 300&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Pyrolysis products were injected on the column via split/splitless injection (at 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) with a split ratio of 1:133 and helium was used as carrier gas with constant flow at 1.5&#x000a0;mL&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The GC oven was programmed from 70&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (2&#x000a0;min) to 270&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C at 5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and held at 270&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min. MS detection was used with EI at 70&#x000a0;eV, a source temperature of 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, a scan range of <italic>m/z</italic> 50&#x02013;550, and a scan rate of 4.0 scans&#x000a0;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Compounds were identified by comparing retention time and mass spectrum with standards, the NIST library and data published by Ralph and Hatfield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">For semi-quantitative analysis, pyrograms were processed by Xcalibur 2.2 software. The two most abundant fragments per compounds were automatically integrated using ICIS peak integration with optimized settings per compound. A manual correction was only applied when irregular peak shapes led to erroneous peak integration with method settings. Areas were normalized by dividing by corresponding relative response factors (RRF), as previously published, multiplied with the molecular weight of the respective compound and summed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Lignin content was estimated on the basis of total area of lignin-derived pyrolysis products and compared to a wheat straw reference sample with known Klason lignin content [acid-insoluble lignin + acid-soluble lignin = 20.5% (w/w)], as described by Jurak et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Relative abundances of lignin-derived pyrolysis products were based on areas without molecular weight correction as previously described by Del R&#x000ed;o et al. as relative response factor (RRF) values are mole-based [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Compounds were classified according to their structural feature (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1) and summed. All samples were prepared and analyzed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS with <sup>13</sup>C lignin as internal standard</title><p id="Par16">Pyrolysis was carried out as previously described in detail and in the section semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Briefly, 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of a <sup>13</sup>C lignin internal standard (IS) solution (1&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ethanol/chloroform 50:50 v/v) was mixed with ~&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g of sample and dried before analysis. Lignin-derived compounds of which fungal action increased the content above detection limits were identified by qualitative py-GC&#x02013;MS using full-MS detection and added to the existing SIM method. Lignin-derived pyrolysis products were monitored in selected ion-monitoring (SIM) mode on the two most abundant fragments per compound (both <sup>12</sup>C and <sup>13</sup>C). The compound vanilloyl acetaldehyde (VAL) was not properly detected in SIM due to a shifted segment and, therefore, was estimated from full-MS analysis. The relative area of VAL vs vanillin as measured by full MS was thereto multiplied by the area of vanillin as measured by SIM. For correction of matrix effects, similar behavior as syringoyl acetaldehyde (SAL) was assumed. Areas for each compound were normalized by dividing by the respective RRF. Relative response factor values were updated to system performance by recalculation to obtain an identical relative abundance of lignin-derived pyrolysis products of the <sup>13</sup>C IS added to a wheat straw reference sample (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Eq.&#x000a0;1). Lignin content [% (w/w)] was determined from the sum of lignin-derived pyrolysis products, where RRF corrected areas for each compound were multiplied with the molecular weight of the respective compound and summed instead of the application of the published correction factor of 1.057 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Eq.&#x000a0;2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Areas were not corrected for molecular weight before relative abundance determination as previously described by Del R&#x000ed;o et al. to allow direct comparison with data obtained by 2D-NMR analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Relative abundances of lignin-derived pyrolysis products were normalized for the <sup>13</sup>C analogues from the IS present in the same sample to distinguish matrix and treatment effects (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Eqs.&#x000a0;3&#x02013;5). Compounds were classified according to their structural feature (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1) and summed. All samples were prepared and analyzed in triplicate. Extractive-free samples were identical to total biomass samples for <italic>Cs</italic>1 and, therefore, not measured for the other fungi.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Whole cell wall 2D HSQC NMR spectroscopy</title><p id="Par17">For NMR analysis of the whole cell wall material, ground wheat straw (1&#x000a0;mm, 2&#x000a0;g) was successively extracted with acetone until the solvent became clear; followed by hot water treatment (100&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) for 3&#x000a0;h to remove low molecular weight compounds that would interfere with the analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The extractive-free residues were then freeze-dried before mixing biological replicates (1&#x000a0;g each) and fine milling in a PM100 planetary ball mill (Retsch, Haan, Germany). Though lignin became increasingly extractable as fungal action proceeded, the structural features of the remaining lignin were highly comparable to that of the total unextracted sample, allowing comparison of NMR and <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS analyses. Two grams of sample was milled in a 50&#x000a0;mL ZrO<sub>2</sub> beaker using 17 &#x003a6; 10&#x000a0;mm balls of the same material at a frequency of 600&#x000a0;rpm with a net milling time of 4&#x000a0;h. After every 15&#x000a0;min of milling, a pause of 10&#x000a0;min was set to avoid overheating of the sample. Around 100&#x000a0;mg of ball-milled sample was swollen in 0.75&#x000a0;mL DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>. 2D heteronuclear single quantum coherence (HSQC) NMR was performed according to previously described methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The spectra were recorded at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with Bruker&#x02019;s standard pulse sequence &#x0201c;hsqcetgpsisp2.2&#x0201d; on a Bruker AVANCE III 600&#x000a0;MHz NMR spectrometer (Bruker BioSpin, Rheinstetten, Germany) equipped with a 5&#x000a0;mm cryo-probe located at MAGNEFY (MAGNEtic resonance facilitY, Wageningen, The Netherlands). The spectral widths were 7200 and 30,000&#x000a0;Hz for the <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C dimensions, respectively. The number of collected complex points was 2018 in the <sup>1</sup>H dimension with a relaxation time of 1&#x000a0;s. The number of collected scans was 16 and 400 increments of time were recorded in the <sup>13</sup>C dimension. The <sup>1</sup><italic>J</italic><sub>CH</sub> used was 145&#x000a0;Hz. The data were processed with the Bruker TopSpin 3.5 software. Processing used Gaussian apodization in <sup>1</sup>H and a squared cosine function in the <sup>13</sup>C dimension. For <sup>13</sup>C, data were zero filled up to 1024 points prior to Fourier transformation. The solvent peak (DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>) was used as an internal reference (<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub> 39.5&#x000a0;ppm; <italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 2.49&#x000a0;ppm). HSQC correlation peaks were assigned by comparison with the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Semi-quantitative analysis of the volume integrals was performed according to Del R&#x000ed;o et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Alternatively, in the aliphatic oxygenated region, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 substructures were estimated from their C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;H<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> correlations, since they were shown to be interfered to a lesser extent by the presence of carbohydrates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. For phenylcoumaran and resinol substructures, their respective C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>&#x02013;H<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> correlations were used. Volume integrals for resinol substructures were logically halved. S<sub>2,6</sub>, G<sub>2,</sub> and H<sub>2,6</sub> signals were used for S, G, and H units, respectively, where S and H integrals were halved as well. Oxidized analogues were estimated in a similar manner. Tricin, <italic>p</italic>CA, and FA were similarly estimated from their respective T<sub>2&#x02019;,6&#x02019;</sub>, <italic>p</italic>CA<sub>2,6,</sub> and FA<sub>2</sub> signals. H<sub>2,6</sub> integrals were corrected for the overlapping phenylalanine cross peak (PHE<sub>3,5</sub>) by subtraction of the isolated PHE<sub>2,6</sub> cross-peak [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Volume integration was performed at equal contour levels. Amounts were calculated both as a percentage of total lignin (H + G + G<sub>ox</sub> + G<sub>mod</sub> + S + S<sub>ox</sub> + S<sub>mod</sub>) and total lignin including <italic>p</italic>CA, FA, and T [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par18">In earlier work, we showed that the biological variation in the delignification of wheat straw by the strains used in this study was low (pooled standard deviation of biological and analytical triplicates ~&#x02009;5% RSD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. For the purpose of this study, biological triplicates were thoroughly mixed (in equal dry matter amounts) and ball-milled (as explained in the section &#x02018;preparation of the fungal-treated straw&#x02019;), thereby ensuring homogeneous samples for analyses. Albeit low, biological variation was, therefore, not included in the outcomes of this study. Results are presented as average &#x000b1; standard deviation on the basis of analytical triplicates (when replicates were included). Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test (&#x003b1; = 0.05) was used to evaluate significant differences between strains in terms of lignin and carbohydrate removal.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Wheat straw delignification during fungal growth</title><p id="Par19">The extent of wheat straw delignification during growth of the different fungal strains was monitored by semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). This technique does not experience interference from fungal cell wall material and the entire lignin population is measured [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In comparison with conventional gravimetric analysis, semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS, therefore, is considered to provide a more accurate insight in the delignification characteristics of the studied fungi. Clear lignin removal was observed from the first week of growth and all strains extensively delignified the wheat straw within 7&#x000a0;weeks. <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> were the most effective species, which is in line with the initial evaluation of these fungi by conventional compositional feed analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS determination of lignin removal from wheat straw after 1, 3, and 7&#x000a0;weeks of fungal growth. <italic>Cs Ceriporiopsis subvermispora, Pe Pleurotus eryngii, Le Lentinula edodes</italic>. Square <italic>Cs</italic>1, filled square <italic>Cs</italic>12, triangle <italic>Pe</italic>3, filled triangle <italic>Pe</italic>6, circle <italic>Le</italic>8, and filled circle <italic>Le</italic>10. Average and standard deviation of analytical triplicates on pooled biological triplicates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par20">Not only were <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> more effective, compared to <italic>Pe</italic>, they also showed a distinct pattern of lignin removal in time. For <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic>, the major part (&#x0003e;&#x02009;70%) of the final lignin removal occurred within the first 3&#x000a0;weeks, whereas both <italic>Pe</italic> strains showed a more gradual lignin removal in time, reaching less than 50% of the final lignin removal within 3&#x000a0;weeks. No significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) were found in the extents of lignin removal after 7&#x000a0;weeks of growth between strains of the same species. Though the fungal species (and strains) varied considerably in growth pattern, as recently shown by Nayan et al., the extent of growth (amount of ergosterol formed) was not directly correlated with the extent of lignin degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">Though semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS clearly proved useful for the comparison of the delignification efficiency of the different fungi, we strived for more accurate and precise quantification and characterization of the residual lignin. At the end point of the treatment (7&#x000a0;weeks), the wheat straw was most affected by fungal growth and, for that reason, considered the most informative to further investigate the underlying delignification mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Therefore, lignin in fungal-treated wheat straw after 7&#x000a0;weeks of growth was quantified by the recently developed quantitative <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In this method, a <sup>13</sup>C lignin internal standard is mixed with the sample to correct for matrix effects and system performance, which was previously shown to improve the accuracy of lignin quantification in sound biomass samples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. From the total dry matter recovered and lignin contents in the treated material, the amount of lignin removed was calculated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Lignin, glucuronoarabinoxylan (GAX), and glucan (cellulose) removal after 7&#x000a0;weeks of fungal growth. <italic>Cs Ceriporiopsis subvermispora, Pe Pleurotus eryngii, Le Lentinula edodes</italic>. Compositional analysis by using quantitative <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS (lignin) and constituent monosaccharide analysis after H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> hydrolysis (carbohydrates). Average and standard deviation of analytical triplicates on pooled biological triplicates. It is important to take some limitations of the methods used for carbohydrate quantification into consideration. First, the hydrolysis of polysaccharides to constituent monosaccharides does not allow cellulose and fungal &#x003b2;-glucan to be distinguished. Cellulose determination was, however, not expected to be largely affected, since fungal biomass was present in minor amounts only, as estimated from ergosterol content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Second, fungal-treated cellulose and glucuronoarabinoxylan (GAX) were expected to be more completely acid-hydrolyzed than untreated material, thereby resulting in underestimation of the amount of degraded carbohydrates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par22">Although semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS gave fair estimates of lignin removal (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), the method overestimated lignin removal in all samples by approximately 15%, mainly due to overestimation of the lignin content of the starting material (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S2). The results of quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS confirmed the effectiveness of <italic>Cs</italic>, <italic>Le</italic>, and <italic>Pe</italic> in degrading lignin, where in the case of <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic>, more than 60% (w/w) of lignin was removed from the wheat straw within 7&#x000a0;weeks of treatment. <italic>Cs1</italic> outperformed both <italic>Le</italic> and <italic>Pe</italic> strains, whereas it was not significantly different from <italic>Cs</italic>12 in terms of lignin removal. <italic>Pe</italic>3 removed significantly more lignin than <italic>Pe6</italic>, while both <italic>Le</italic> strains were not significantly different.</p><p id="Par23">The three fungal species, furthermore, were capable of removing lignin highly selectively over cell wall carbohydrates (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S1). After 7&#x000a0;weeks of growth <italic>Pe</italic> strains were found to have degraded considerable amounts of glucan [8% (w/w) of initial glucan], whereas <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> less affected glucan. Instead, these species degraded glucuronoarabinoxylan (GAX), but to a lesser extent than lignin. <italic>Cs</italic>1 showed a remarkably higher degradation of GAX than <italic>Cs</italic>12 (21 vs 5% (w/w) of initial GAX), while both <italic>Le</italic> strains degraded approximately 12% (w/w) of initial GAX. The selective removal of lignin over carbohydrates has been described in the previous studies for the three fungi used. Though, more extensive hemicellulose degradation has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. This is due to the gravimetrical method that was used in these previous studies, in which solubilization and removal cannot be discriminated.</p><p id="Par24">Based on the removal of lignin, glucan and GAX after 7&#x000a0;weeks of fungal growth (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), it was concluded that <italic>Pe</italic> removed considerably more carbohydrates versus lignin than <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic>. In addition to the effectiveness of lignin removal, the latter fungi, thus, also seem to outperform <italic>Pe</italic> in terms of selectivity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Structural features of fungal-treated lignin</title><p id="Par25">Besides accurate lignin content, quantitative <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS simultaneously provided accurate insight in the structural features of the remaining lignin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. By correcting for any changes in the structural features of the <sup>13</sup>C-IS lignin, it was ensured that the observed changes in residual lignin were indeed fungal-induced. The same samples were also subjected to 2D-HSQC NMR analysis allowing comparison with the <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS data, which is discussed further on. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the relative abundances of the structural features of lignin of untreated and treated wheat straw (<sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS data). The bases of structural classification and relative abundances of individual lignin-derived pyrolysis products can be found in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1. The structural features of the untreated straw matched well with that of wheat straw that was previously analyzed in a similar manner, which confirmed that a representative wheat straw sample was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p><sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS relative abundance of residual lignin compounds of control and fungal-treated wheat straw after 7&#x000a0;weeks of growth</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Control</th><th align="left"><italic>Cs</italic>1</th><th align="left"><italic>Cs</italic>12</th><th align="left"><italic>Pe</italic>3</th><th align="left"><italic>Pe</italic>6</th><th align="left"><italic>Le</italic>8</th><th align="left"><italic>Le</italic>10</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="8">Lignin subunits (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;H</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;G</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">62.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">62.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">59.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">62.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">63.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">64.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">63.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;S</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">28.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">28.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;S/G</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8">Structural moieties (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Unsubstituted</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Methyl</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Vinyl</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">29.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">31.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">31.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">31.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;4-VP<sup>a</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;4-VG<sup>b</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-ox</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-ox G</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-ox S</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Acetaldehyde</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>-ox</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;C<sub>&#x003b3;</sub>-ox</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">54.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">45.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">43.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">52.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">51.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">48.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">48.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Miscellaneous</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;PhC<sub arrange="stack">&#x003b3;</sub><sup arrange="stack">c</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">58.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">48.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">56.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">55.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">53.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">53.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub>-acetaldehyde<sup>d</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">58.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">42.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">40.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">54.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">53.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Corrected for RRF and relative abundance of <sup>13</sup>C analogues. Sum on the bases of structural classification according to Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1. Average and standard deviation of analytical triplicates on pooled biological triplicates.&#x000a0;No statistical analysis was applied</p><p><italic>Cs</italic> &#x000a0;<italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic>, <italic>Pe</italic> &#x000a0;<italic>Pleurotus eryngii</italic>, <italic>Le</italic> &#x000a0;<italic>Lentinula edodes</italic></p><p><sup>a</sup>4-Vinylphenol</p><p><sup>b</sup>4-Vinylguaiacol</p><p><sup>c</sup>Phenols with intact &#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, and &#x003b3; carbon side chain</p><p><sup>d</sup>Phenols with intact &#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, and &#x003b3; carbon side chain, excluding acetaldehydes</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par26">Unexpectedly, fungal treatment was found to have a minimal effect on the overall composition of lignin subunits, with the largest effect observed for <italic>Le</italic>8 (H:G:S = 11:64:25) compared to control (H:G:S = 10:62:28), which indicates that all lignin units were targeted in the process of lignin degradation. Although minimal, all fungi except <italic>Cs</italic>12, showed a preference towards the removal of S units (over H and G units) as demonstrated by slightly lowered S/G (e.g., 0.45 to 0.38 by <italic>Le</italic>8; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This preference was less pronounced compared to a previous study, where a factor 2 decrease in S/G was found within 8&#x000a0;weeks of treatment by both <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. The main difference is the higher S/G of the wheat straw used in the previous study (S/G = 0.7) compared to our wheat straw (S/G = 0.45). Hence, the most likely explanation of the lower S/G preference in our study was the difference in wheat straw used, which differed not only in the overall subunit composition, but might also have differed in the way that these subunits were linked.</p><p id="Par27">Preferential degradation of (sub-)structures with a higher degree of methoxylation has been related to the corresponding lower redox potential and reduced frequency of carbon&#x02013;carbon (&#x02018;condensed&#x02019;) substructures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Still, as mentioned above, <italic>Cs</italic>, <italic>Pe</italic>, and <italic>Le</italic> did not show a clear preference for degrading the more methoxylated S units over G and H units in our research. Demethoxylation, due to which S units &#x02018;transform&#x02019; into G units, and likewise G units into H units, is known to occur due to fungal action, and might, hence, potentially have masked the preferential removal of certain subunits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">When categorized according to structural moiety, the residual lignin structures pointed out clear effects related to fungal growth (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Most pronounced was the increase of unsubstituted and C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized pyrolysis products at the expense of products with three carbons in the side-chain (PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub>) in fungal-treated straw. The relative abundances of these moieties greatly varied across species, with the <italic>Cs</italic> strains showing the highest increases in unsubstituted (twofold) and C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized (fivefold) substructures compared to untreated wheat straw. Again, minimal differences were found between strains of the same species.</p><p id="Par29">These observations are in line with the previous py-GC&#x02013;MS studies on fungal-treated biomass and have been suggested to indicate degradation of inter-unit linkages within the lignin macromolecule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. To add to the latter, we hypothesize that in particular, the relative abundance of PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> is a measure for the amount of intact inter-unit linkages present, which is substantiated by the NMR data shown below. To explain, it is well known that upon pyrolysis of lignin, the intact (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4) inter-unit linkages, consisting of C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> aliphatic chains, decompose into products with various structures and chain-lengths (unsubstituted, C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>, C<sub>&#x003b2;,</sub> and C<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> side-chains) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. At the pyrolysis conditions applied in our study, secondary reactions are absent. Therefore, lignin pyrolysis mainly yields monomeric products that are a direct result of bond-cleavage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Hence, the maximum chain length of the pyrolysis products equals the chain length of the substructures they originate from. PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> products can, thus, only form from structures in which the three-carbon side-chain was initially present, being mainly intact inter-unit linkages. Furthermore, since the content of pendant cinnamyl alcohol and cinnamyl aldehyde end-groups in wheat straw was found to be rather low [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], their contribution to PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> products is considered marginal.</p><p id="Par30">Interestingly, for both <italic>Cs</italic> strains, the increase in C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized pyrolysis products was for more than half determined by the two compounds vanilloyl acetaldehyde (VAL) and syringoyl acetaldehyde (SAL). These compounds are, respectively, G and S unit derivatives with three carbons in the side-chain and a ketone at the C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> position (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S2). Analogous to the explanation given above for PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> products, we hypothesize that VAL and SAL solely formed from oxidized <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 linkages and/or their cleavage products of which the three-carbon (&#x003b1;, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, and &#x003b3;) side chain remained intact. To challenge this hypothesis, it can be postulated that pyrolysis of tricin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) can result in SAL from the cleavage of the A-ring and rearrangement of the double bond. However, since we observed no SAL in the pyrograms of tricin-enriched extracts, tricin can be ruled out as potential (interfering) source of acetaldehyde products. If indeed acetaldehyde products originated from cleavage products of the inter-unit linkages, rather than intact oxidized <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 linkages, they should be subtracted from the PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> products for a more fair representation of the intact inter-unit linkages (PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub>-acetaldehyde in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Our results, thus, indicate that fungal-treated lignin was considerably reduced in intact inter-unit linkages, in particular for <italic>Cs</italic> strains (&#x02212;&#x02009;30% compared to control). As C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized products greatly accumulated, this reduction in intact inter-unit linkages was likely caused by oxidative cleavage.</p><p id="Par31">Semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS confirmed that the observed structures were a direct effect of lignin degradation, i.e., that they accumulated during fungal growth as lignin degradation proceeded (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Figure S3). Intriguingly, though <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> followed a highly similar pattern of lignin degradation in time (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), they vastly differed in the remaining lignin structures after their growth. To further substantiate these findings, we also assessed the residual lignin structures by whole cell wall 2D-NMR.</p><p id="Par32">Sample preparation for in situ whole cell wall gel state 2D-NMR requires finely divided, planetary ball-milled samples. Planetary ball milling is associated with structural changes in lignin, mainly with regard to the cleavage of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 inter-unit linkages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS analysis of the ball-milled samples showed that the milling did not induce structural changes in the lignin present and that the inter-unit linkages remained unaffected (PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> constant). Thus, 2D-NMR could be appropriately used.</p><p id="Par33">The aliphatic (<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 50&#x02013;90/2.5&#x02013;6.0) and aromatic/unsaturated (<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 90&#x02013;160/6.0&#x02013;8.0) regions of the recorded HSQC spectra of untreated and <italic>Cs</italic>1 treated wheat straw are presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, with structures of the assigned correlation peaks shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, of which chemical shift assignments were based on literature and shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Table S3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Aliphatic and aromatic/unsaturated regions of the HSQC spectra of the wheat straw treated by the other fungi are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: Figure S4. The aliphatic regions were dominated by polysaccharide signals, mainly derived from xylan and acetylated xylan moieties, which (partially) overlapped with <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02019; substructures. This overlap was more severe for fungal-treated samples, from which lignin was selectively removed. Despite this overlap, phenylcoumaran (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-5&#x02032;) and resinol (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02013;<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02032;) substructures were readily observed, whereas C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized (&#x003b1;-keto) <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032;, dibenzodioxocins (5&#x02013;5&#x02032;/4-<italic>O</italic>-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>&#x02032;), spirodienones (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-1&#x02032;/<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02032;) and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>,<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-diaryl-ether linkages were only observed at higher zoom levels. At these zoom levels, other contours were not resolved anymore, which would result in a lower accuracy of volume integration.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>HSQC NMR spectra of control and <italic>Cs</italic>1-treated wheat straw. <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> Aliphatic <italic>(&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 50&#x02013;90/2.5&#x02013;6.0) region, <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> aromatic/unsaturated (<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 90&#x02013;160/6.0&#x02013;8.0) region. Control (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold>), <italic>Cs</italic>1-treated (<bold>b</bold>, <bold>d</bold>). Structures of annotated correlation peaks are presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. GoxII<sub>2</sub> and G<sub>ox</sub>II<sub>6</sub> are tentatively assigned. G<sub>mod</sub> and S<sub>mod</sub>, being unknown derivatives of G and S units, respectively, are presented in a lighter color of the original subunit. Carbohydrate and unassigned signals are presented in gray. u: unassigned signal overlapping A<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>/A&#x02032;<sub>&#x003b1;</sub></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Structures annotated by HSQC NMR. A: <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032;alkyl-aryl ether (A&#x02032;: &#x003b3;-acylated <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032;alkyl-aryl ether); A<sub>ox</sub>: <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032;alkyl-aryl-ether C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized; B: phenylcoumaran; C: resinol; T: tricin; pCA: <italic>p</italic>-coumarate; FA: ferulate; G: guaiacyl unit; G<sub>ox</sub>: C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized guaiacyl unit; S: syringyl unit; S: C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized syringyl unit; H: <italic>p</italic>-hydroxyphenyl unit; S<sub>ald</sub>: syringaldehyde; dotted line represents &#x02013;H or &#x02013;OCH<sub>3</sub>. R in G<sub>ox</sub> and S<sub>ox</sub> can be a side chain in ketones or hydroxyl in carboxylic acids. Wavy lines indicate main positions of further coupling. Colors match the assigned contours in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par34">In the aromatic region, clear lignin signals, typical for wheat straw, were observed [S<sub>2,6</sub>, G<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>2,6,</sub> and several tricin (T), <italic>p</italic>CA, and FA-related signals] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Interestingly, in the fungal-treated samples, C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized aromatic units became more apparent, especially after treatment with <italic>Cs</italic> and is discussed in detail below. Although C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized S units (<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 106.6/7.2) are commonly found in NMR studies on (native) lignin, C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized G units (<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 111.2/7.5) are less often described and have, hitherto, never been observed at the levels shown here [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Notably, two different C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized G unit substructures could be distinguished, although their exact structures remained unidentified (GoxI<sub>2</sub>
<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 111.2/7.5, GoxII<sub>2</sub>
<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 112.4/7.4). Another structural aspect resulting from fungal action is the increased intensity of derivatives of both S (S<sub>mod</sub>, <italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 103.4/6.96) and G units (G<sub>mod</sub>, <italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 112.8/6.76). Though the NMR database of lignin and cell wall model compounds could confirm that these signals originated from either S or G units, their exact structures could not be elucidated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. To identify both the unidentified oxidized G units and S and G derivatives, future extensive NMR-research is needed, not being the aim of the current research. A summary of the semi-quantitative analysis of the volume integrals of aromatic units and inter-unit linkages (see &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>&#x0201d; for details) is given in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Main trends were observed by comparing species, though slight variations between strains of the same species could be recognized.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Semi-quantitative HSQC NMR structural characterization of residual lignin in control and fungal-treated wheat straw after 7&#x000a0;weeks of growth</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Control</th><th align="left"><italic>Cs</italic>1</th><th align="left"><italic>Cs</italic>12</th><th align="left"><italic>Pe</italic>3</th><th align="left"><italic>Pe</italic>6</th><th align="left"><italic>Le</italic>8</th><th align="left"><italic>Le</italic>10</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="8">Lignin subunits (%)<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;H</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (6)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (5)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (6)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (6)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (6)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (5)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;G</td><td char="(" align="char">52 (53)</td><td char="(" align="char">47 (49)</td><td char="(" align="char">42 (46)</td><td char="(" align="char">57 (57)</td><td char="(" align="char">53 (53)</td><td char="(" align="char">53 (54)</td><td char="(" align="char">57 (56)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;G<sub>ox</sub></td><td char="(" align="char">2 (1)</td><td char="(" align="char">11 (8)</td><td char="(" align="char">12 (9)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (2)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (3)</td><td char="(" align="char">6 (5)</td><td char="(" align="char">4 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;G<sub>mod</sub></td><td char="(" align="char">0 (0)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (2)</td><td char="(" align="char">4 (3)</td><td char="(" align="char">0 (0)</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (1)</td><td char="(" align="char">0 (0)</td><td char="(" align="char">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;S</td><td char="(" align="char">37 (34)</td><td char="(" align="char">25 (26)</td><td char="(" align="char">25 (26)</td><td char="(" align="char">31 (30)</td><td char="(" align="char">32 (31)</td><td char="(" align="char">30 (29)</td><td char="(" align="char">29 (30)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;S<sub>ox</sub></td><td char="(" align="char">5 (4)</td><td char="(" align="char">10 (7)</td><td char="(" align="char">12 (9)</td><td char="(" align="char">6 (5)</td><td char="(" align="char">6 (5)</td><td char="(" align="char">6 (5)</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;S<sub>mod</sub></td><td char="(" align="char">2 (1)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (2)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (2)</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (1)</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (1)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (2)</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;S/G</td><td char="(" align="char">0.81 (0.72)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.62 (0.60)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.67 (0.64)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.65 (0.59)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.69 (0.64)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.63 (0.60)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.58 (0.59)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8">Hydroxycinnamates (%)<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>&#x000a0;p</italic>-Coumarate</td><td char="(" align="char">6 (5)</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (3)</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (3)</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (4)</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (4)</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (3)</td><td char="(" align="char">4 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Ferulate</td><td char="(" align="char">21 (15)</td><td char="(" align="char">19 (14)</td><td char="(" align="char">18 (13)</td><td char="(" align="char">15 (12)</td><td char="(" align="char">15 (12)</td><td char="(" align="char">16 (13)</td><td char="(" align="char">17 (13)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lignan (%)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Tricin</td><td char="(" align="char">10 (7)</td><td char="(" align="char">11 (8)</td><td char="(" align="char">9 (7)</td><td char="(" align="char">6 (5)</td><td char="(" align="char">7 (5)</td><td char="(" align="char">8 (6)</td><td char="(" align="char">10 (8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8">Lignin inter-unit linkages (%)<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032; Aryl ethers</td><td char="(" align="char">43 (90)</td><td char="(" align="char">37 (93)</td><td char="(" align="char">32 (97)</td><td char="(" align="char">39 (90)</td><td char="(" align="char">39 (85)</td><td char="(" align="char">40 (86)</td><td char="(" align="char">40 (88)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Phenylcoumarans</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (6)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (4)</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (2)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (7)</td><td char="(" align="char">5 (11)</td><td char="(" align="char">4 (10)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Resinols</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (3)</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (3)</td><td char="(" align="char">0 (1)</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (3)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (4)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (4)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Total</td><td char="(" align="char">48 (100)</td><td char="(" align="char">40 (100)</td><td char="(" align="char">33 (100)</td><td char="(" align="char">43 (100)</td><td char="(" align="char">46 (100)</td><td char="(" align="char">46 (100)</td><td char="(" align="char">45 (100)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Volume integration of cross peaks in the aliphatic region likely suffered from overlap with carbohydrates, especially after extensive delignification</p><p><italic>Cs</italic> &#x000a0;<italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic>, <italic>Pe</italic> &#x000a0;<italic>Pleurotus eryngii</italic>, <italic>Le</italic> &#x000a0;<italic>Lentinula edodes</italic></p><p><sup>a</sup>Percentage of subunits (H&#x02009;+G&#x02009;&#x02009;+G<sub>ox</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;G<sub>mod</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;S&#x02009;+&#x02009;S<sub>ox</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;S<sub>mod</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100) and in parenthesis (subunits&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>p</italic>CA(H)&#x02009;+&#x02009;FA(G)&#x02009;+&#x02009;T(S)&#x02009;=&#x02009;100)</p><p><sup>b</sup>Percentage vs aromatic units and subunits&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>p</italic>CA&#x02009;+&#x02009;FA&#x02009;+&#x02009;T (see subscript a)</p><p><sup>c</sup>Percentage of inter-unit linkages vs total subunits and in parenthesis as percentage of total inter-unit linkages</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par35">Similar to <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), 2D-NMR showed minor changes in H:G:S composition after fungal treatment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). For instance, the H:G:S composition changed from 2:54:44 in control to 3:61:38 in <italic>Cs</italic>1-treated straw. Again, a (slight) preferential removal of S units was observed, thereby confirming our previous findings by py-GC&#x02013;MS. However, for a fair comparison of the H:G:S composition found by the two techniques, it should be considered that whereas the hydroxycinnamic acids (<italic>p</italic>&#x02013;CA and FA) and tricin (T) can be distinguished from &#x02018;core&#x02013;lignin&#x02019; substructures in 2D-NMR, in py-GC&#x02013;MS, they result in similar pyrolysis products. Upon pyrolysis, both <italic>p</italic>-CA and FA as well as inter-unit linkages result in the formation of 4-vinylphenol and 4-vinylguaiacol, respectively. Analogously, tricin is expected to result in S unit derivatives upon pyrolysis.</p><p id="Par36">To enable a comparison of both techniques in terms of H:G:S composition (mol based), <italic>p</italic>CA (H), FA (G) and T (S) were included in the determination of the subunit composition by NMR (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, numbers in parentheses). Besides analytical comparability, the obtained subunit composition is, in our opinion, more representative of &#x02018;true lignin&#x02019; as these substructures were shown to be an integral part of lignin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Upon inclusion of these substructures, the obtained subunit compositions found by both techniques matched better, though they remained different [<italic>Cs</italic>1 H:G:S (NMR) = 5:59:35, H:G:S (py-GC&#x02013;MS) = 12:62:26]. It cannot be expected that both techniques result in identical values, as different entities are measured [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Still, because similar trends were observed, complementary structural information can be obtained by comparing both techniques. One of the explanations for the observed difference is that the semi-quantitative nature of the NMR technique results in overestimation of end-units as a result of differences in relaxation behavior compared to &#x02018;core&#x02013;lignin&#x02019; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Another explanation is that hydroxycinnamic acids are pyrolyzed more efficiently compared to &#x02018;core&#x02013;lignin&#x02019;, which results in overestimation of their abundances and contributions to lignin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par37">The most pronounced change observed by NMR was the increase in C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized aromatic units in fungal-treated samples, with a threefold accumulation in <italic>Cs</italic> treated lignin (up to 19&#x02013;24% of total aromatic units; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). This increase coincides with the increase in C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized products in py-GC&#x02013;MS and these compounds, hence, were mostly derived from C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized units initially present in the polymer. Even relative abundances (% mol) of C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized substructures obtained by both techniques were in fairly good accordance [<italic>Cs</italic>1 C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-ox (NMR) = 15%, C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-ox (py-GC&#x02013;MS) = 14%]. It can be assumed that the C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized substructures accumulated in fungal-treated lignin due to the fact that, once oxidized, these units cannot be further oxidized (by the respective fungal oxidases present) and are, therefore, resistant to further degradation and further metabolization. C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized S units appeared more prone to accumulate than their C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized G unit counterparts (S<sub>ox</sub>/S &#x0003e; G<sub>ox</sub>/G) for all fungi. This might on the one hand be explained by their ease of formation, as discussed in the previous section. On the other hand, S units might be more difficult to be consumed and fully metabolized.</p><p id="Par38">Interestingly, while the C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized aromatic units clearly increased, no apparent increase in C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized (&#x003b1;-keto) &#x003b2;-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032; substructures could be observed. The latter observation shows that the C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized signals mainly originated from cleaved linkages, and simultaneously highlights the importance of corresponding VAL and SAL compounds in the py-GC&#x02013;MS analysis. The suggestion that cleaved linkages accumulated in the residual lignin is further substantiated by the reduced amounts of intact inter-unit linkages in fungal-treated lignin. Intact inter-unit linkages were severely reduced by <italic>Cs</italic> treatment (<italic>Cs</italic>1&#x02013;20%, <italic>Cs</italic>12&#x02013;34%; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), which was also observed by py-GC&#x02013;MS. The abundance of the pyrolysis PhC<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> products excluding acetaldehydes, thus, seems to be a highly valuable parameter for the investigation of intact &#x003b2;-<italic>O</italic>-4-linkages in the lignin structure by py-GC&#x02013;MS.</p><p id="Par39">The previous studies also reported on the reduction of inter-unit linkages in <italic>Cs</italic> treated lignin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. However, these studies were conducted on wood, of which the lignin is of a different structure. Still, in these biomasses, the <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 inter-unit linkage is most abundant and, therefore, can be used to compare fungal action. Guerra et al. found that <italic>Cs</italic> treated pine was preferentially reduced in <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4 linkages, while carbon&#x02013;carbon linked units were more resistant against fungal degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Our results indicated that all inter-unit linkages in wheat straw lignin were comparable in their susceptibility towards fungal degradation as their relative composition was rather stable (&#x0003c;&#x02009;10% different from control; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par40">Another clear result from the 2D-NMR analysis was the reduction in FA moieties after fungal treatment, particularly by the <italic>Pe</italic> strains (around 30% reduction; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Possibly, the lignin&#x02013;carbohydrate linkages in which FA participates were targeted in a more preferential manner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Though, the specific removal of glucuronoarabinoxylan (GAX) linked ferulates and crosslinked diferulates cannot be excluded. Such structures could be cleaved by feruloyl esterases, which have been shown to occur extracellularly for <italic>Pe</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>].</p><p id="Par41">The specific targeting of FA moieties is in line with the concurrent lignin and GAX degradation during fungal growth. The magnitudes of FA and GAX removal were, however, not directly linked (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S1). In contrast to FA, <italic>p</italic>CA moieties were not preferentially removed.</p><p id="Par42">Tricin was surprisingly shown to be specifically targeted during fungal growth, in particular by <italic>Pe</italic> strains (&#x02212;&#x02009;40% vs total lignin; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Tricin has recently been suggested to play an important role in the biosynthesis of lignin in poaceous crops by functioning as a nucleation site for lignin formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. The preferential removal of tricin suggests that, besides lignin formation, tricin may play a crucial role in the fungal degradation of lignin as well.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Mechanistic insight in fungal delignification by combining results of <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS and 2D-NMR</title><p id="Par43">The combination of 2D-NMR and <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS analysis provided more insight into the reaction mechanisms underlying delignification by the studied fungi, in particular for the <italic>Cs</italic> strains. The absence of C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized (&#x003b1;-keto) <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032; substructures in 2D-NMR combined with decreased amounts of intact inter-unit linkages (both techniques) confirmed that the C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized substructures were present in the fungal-treated lignin macromolecule as cleavage products of the inter-unit linkages. Upon pyrolysis, these cleavage products resulted in the formation of the acetaldehydes VAL and SAL. Since these pyrolysis products contain an intact &#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, and &#x003b3; carbon side chain, the structures that they originate from should contain this three-carbon side chain as well. Hence, we postulate that acetaldehyde pyrolysis products originated from the remaining structures after C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;<italic>O</italic> cleavage of the <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032; ether.</p><p id="Par44">C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized pyrolysis products with an &#x003b1;-carbon side-chain, like vanillin and syringaldehyde, were likewise, but not specifically, formed from cleavage products and thus are suggested to be the result of C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> cleavage.</p><p id="Par45">The high proportion of acetaldehyde pyrolysis products formed from <italic>Cs</italic> treated lignin suggests that C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;<italic>O</italic>&#x02013;aryl cleavage was the main underlying mechanism of lignin degradation, while for <italic>Pe</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> cleavage predominated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The latter two species, however, showed less accumulation of C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized substructures in treated lignin, at the respective levels of lignin removal. This might indicate that other cleavage reactions not yielding C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidation might be more dominant than previously thought [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. On the other hand, if C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;<italic>O</italic>&#x02013;aryl cleavage did occur, but the resulting intermediate products were further degraded in follow-up reactions, we cannot pick this up in residual lignin structures after 7&#x000a0;weeks of fungal growth. Collectively, the enzymes produced by <italic>Le</italic> and <italic>Pe</italic> might thus be able to degrade each lignin subunit further, without resulting in increased, contentwise, lignin degradation. Our results clearly put forward that the delignification mechanism of <italic>Cs</italic> is fundamentally different from <italic>Le</italic> and <italic>Pe</italic>. The explanation of the underlying delignification mechanisms likely lays in the type of enzymes involved. It is expected from genome sequencing of strains of <italic>Cs</italic>, <italic>Le</italic>, and <italic>Pe</italic> that all rely on manganese peroxidases (MnPs) and laccases (Lacs), though their dependency on the particular enzymes might vary [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In vitro, MnPs were shown to degrade lignin model compounds in the presence of unsaturated fatty acids via lipid peroxidation into products that, upon pyrolysis, could yield the acetaldehyde products we observed, in particular after <italic>Cs</italic> action [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Interestingly, a similar MnP-peroxidation reaction was suggested to involve alkylitaconic acids, secondary metabolites that are abundantly produced by <italic>Cs</italic> but not by <italic>Le</italic> and <italic>Pe</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. It can be postulated that the presence of alkylitaconic acids underlies the observed predominance of the C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;<italic>O</italic>&#x02013;aryl cleavage reaction of the <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032; ether by <italic>Cs.</italic> However, laccases and the recently identified enzymes with an LiP/VP like activity could have resulted in similar products, due to which unambiguity regarding the underlying enzyme system remains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. For further validation and interpretation of our observations, genomes of the particular strains should be sequenced next to the application of proteomic and transcriptomic approaches.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Proposed predominant linkages targeted by fungal action. For simplicity, only the most abundant <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>O</italic>-4&#x02032;alkyl-aryl-ether linkage is shown, where dotted lines represent &#x02013;H or &#x02013;OCH<sub>3</sub> and wavy lines indicate main positions of further coupling. <italic>Cs Ceriporiopsis subvermispora, Pe Pleurotus eryngii, Le Lentinula edodes. Cs</italic> C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;<italic>O</italic>&#x02013;aryl cleavage, <italic>Le</italic>/<italic>Pe</italic> C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> cleavage</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par46"><italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic> (<italic>Cs</italic>) and <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic> (<italic>Le</italic>) are more effective and selective wheat straw lignin degrading fungi than <italic>Pleurotus eryngii (Pe)</italic>. They degraded more than 60% (w/w) of lignin without extensive carbohydrate degradation within 7&#x000a0;weeks of treatment. Though <italic>Cs</italic> and <italic>Le</italic> followed a similar pattern of lignin degradation in time, the structural features of residual lignin as determined by quantitative <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS and in situ HSQC NMR were vastly different. Both techniques revealed that <italic>Cs</italic> treated lignin was exceptionally high in C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized substructures (up to 24% of aromatic units) and a factor two higher than <italic>Le</italic>-treated lignin. <italic>Le</italic> and <italic>Pe</italic>, on the other hand, more specifically targeted ferulic acid substructures, while <italic>Pe</italic> preferentially removed tricin up to 40% more than other substructures. Furthermore, <italic>Cs</italic> delignification mainly proceeded via C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;<italic>O</italic>&#x02013;aryl and C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> cleavage of the lignin inter-unit linkages, while inter-unit degradation by <italic>Le</italic> and <italic>Pe</italic> seemed dominated by C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> cleavage with C<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>&#x02013;<italic>O</italic>&#x02013;aryl cleavage occurring to lesser extents. We, therefore, suggest that the underlying delignification mechanisms of these fungi are fundamentally different.</p><p id="Par47">Besides assisting the further optimization of fungal pretreatment of plant biomass, we highlight that the choice of fungus impacts the structure of residual lignin and results in lignin with remarkable structure. Thus, fungal pretreatment not only enhances the degradability of plant cell wall polysaccharides, but also results in an interesting lignin fraction that can be exploited to further increase the sustainability of the process.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec15"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1.</bold> Formulae for calculation of lignin content and relative abundance by <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2: Table S1.</bold> Identity, structural classification and relative abundance of lignin-derived pyrolysis products by <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS. Control and fungal-treated wheat straw samples after 7&#x000a0;weeks of treatment. <italic>Cs Ceriporiopsis subvermispora, Pe Pleurotus eryngii,</italic> and <italic>Le Lentinula edodes</italic>. Average of analytical triplicates on pooled biological triplicates.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 3: Table S2.</bold> Lignin content and removal determined by semi-quantitative and quantitative <sup>13</sup>C-IS py-GC&#x02013;MS of control and fungal-treated wheat straw after 7&#x000a0;weeks of fungal growth <italic>Cs Ceriporiopsis subvermispora, Pe Pleurotus eryngii,</italic> and <italic>Le Lentinula edodes</italic>. Average and standard deviation of analytical triplicates on pooled biological triplicates.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 4: Figure S1.</bold> Residual lignin, glucuronoarabinoxylan (GAX) and glucan (cellulose) in fungal-treated wheat straw during growth (1, 3 and 7&#x000a0;weeks). <italic>Cs Ceriporiopsis subvermispora, Pe Pleurotus eryngii, Le Lentinula edodes</italic>. Average and standard deviation of analytical triplicates on pooled biological triplicates.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 5: Figure S2.</bold> EI&#x02013;MS (70&#x000a0;eV) spectra and structures of vanilloyl acetaldehyde (VAL) and syringoyl acetaldehyde (SAL) observed by py-GC&#x02013;MS. Compounds were identified on the basis of fragmentation pattern and retention time. Average mass spectrum across the chromatographic peak with noise subtraction at two sides.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_MOESM6_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 6: Figure S3.</bold> Structural changes of fungal-treated wheat straw lignin during fungal growth (1, 3, and 7&#x000a0;weeks) determined by semi-quantitative py-GC&#x02013;MS. <italic>Cs Ceriporiopsis subvermispora, Pe Pleurotus eryngii</italic>, and <italic>Le Lentinula edodes</italic>. S/G ratio (a) and relative abundances of unsubstituted (b), C<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>-oxidized (c), and Ph&#x02013;C<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> (d) substructures are based on the structural classification shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1. Square <italic>Cs</italic>1, filled square <italic>Cs</italic>12, triangle <italic>Pe</italic>3, filled triangle <italic>Pe</italic>6, circle <italic>Le</italic>8, filled circle <italic>Le</italic>10. Average and standard deviation of analytical triplicates on pooled biological triplicates.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_MOESM7_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 7: Table S3.</bold> Assignments of the lignin <sup>13</sup>C&#x02013;<sup>1</sup>H correlation peaks in the HSQC spectra of control and fungal-treated wheat straw. (t) Tentative assignment.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="13068_2018_1259_MOESM8_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 8: Figure S4.</bold> HSQC NMR spectra of fungal-treated wheat straw. <italic>Cs</italic>12 (a, b), <italic>Pe</italic>3 (c, d), <italic>Pe</italic>6 (e, f) <italic>Le</italic>8 (g, h) <italic>Le</italic>10 (i, j). a, c, e, g, i: Aliphatic <italic>(&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 50&#x02013;90/2.5&#x02013;6.0) region, b, d, f, h, j: aromatic/unsaturated (<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>C</sub>/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic><sub>H</sub> 90&#x02013;160/6.0&#x02013;8.0) region. Structures of annotated correlation peaks are presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. G<sub>mod</sub> and S<sub>mod</sub> are presented in a lighter color of G and S, respectively. Carbohydrate and unassigned signals are presented in gray. u: unassigned signal overlapping A<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>/A&#x02032;<sub>&#x003b1;.</sub></p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>GE, NN, AS, JC, WH, and MK designed research; GE and NN performed research and analyzed data; and GE, NN, AS, JC, WH, and MK wrote the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par48">The authors gratefully acknowledge the financial support from the University Fund Wageningen (UFW) as part of the project &#x0201c;More Meat and Milk from Straw&#x0201d; which is sponsored by DEKA, ForFarmers, and the Victam Foundation. The authors acknowledge the scholarship provided by the Ministry of Higher Education of Malaysia and the Universiti Putra Malaysia. All funding bodies had no involvement in planning and conduct of the research. Maud Pfeiffer is acknowledged for formatting NMR spectra.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par49">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of supporting data</title><p id="Par50">Additional data will be provided as additional files <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par51">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethical approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par52">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par53">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par54">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buranov</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignin in straw of herbaceous crops</article-title><source>Ind Crops Prod</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2008.03.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isroi</surname></name><name><surname>Millati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Syamsiah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Niklasson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahyanto</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludquist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biological pretreatment of lignocelluloses with white-rot fungi and its applications: a review</article-title><source>BioResources</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>5224</fpage><lpage>5259</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isikgor</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Becer</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignocellulosic biomass: a sustainable platform for the production of bio-based chemicals and polymers</article-title><source>Polym Chem.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>4497</fpage><lpage>4559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5PY00263J</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x00106;ilerd&#x0017e;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gali&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vukojevi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x0010d;eski</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Staji&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential of selected fungal species to degrade wheat straw, the most abundant plant raw material in Europe</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>249</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-017-1196-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29297329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandhagopal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of chemical pretreatment for bioconversion of lignocellulosic biomass</article-title><source>Renew Sustainable Energy Rev</source><year>2014</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2014.04.047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact and prospective of fungal pre-treatment of lignocellulosic biomass for enzymatic hydrolysis</article-title><source>Biofuels Bioprod Biorefin</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bbb.346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sindhu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Binod</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological pretreatment of lignocellulosic biomass&#x02014;an overview</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2016</year><volume>199</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2015.08.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26320388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>QA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial pretreatment of biomass</article-title><source>Appl Biochem Biotechnol</source><year>2003</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/ABAB:105:1-3:27</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12721473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Kuijk</surname><given-names>SJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>ASM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baars</surname><given-names>JJP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal treated lignocellulosic biomass as ruminant feed ingredient: a review</article-title><source>Biotechnol Adv</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2014.10.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25447421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuyen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baars</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal strain and incubation period affect chemical composition and nutrient availability of wheat straw for rumen fermentation</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2012</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2012.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22377477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Kuijk</surname><given-names>SJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>ASM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baars</surname><given-names>JJP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal treatment of lignocellulosic biomass: importance of fungal species, colonization and time on chemical composition and in vitro rumen degradability</article-title><source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>209</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2015.07.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Kuijk</surname><given-names>SJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>ASM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baars</surname><given-names>JJP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Del R&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemical changes and increased degradability of wheat straw and oak wood chips treated with the white rot fungi <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic> and <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic></article-title><source>Biomass Bioenergy</source><year>2017</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biombioe.2017.07.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of white-rot fungi for bioprocessing of wheat straw into ruminant feed</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.13894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29704882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanholme</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Demedts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Morreel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boerjan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignin biosynthesis and structure</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.155119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20472751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del R&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Prinsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural characterization of wheat straw lignin as revealed by analytical pyrolysis, 2D-NMR, and reductive cleavage methods</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>5922</fpage><lpage>5935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf301002n</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22607527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunow</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Boerjan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lattanzio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Daayf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignification: are lignins biosynthesized via simple combinatorial chemistry or via proteinaceous control and template replication?</article-title><source>Recent advances in polyphenol research</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Oxord</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydroxycinnamates in lignification</article-title><source>Phytochem Rev.</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11101-009-9141-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Regner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tricin, a flavonoid monomer in monocot lignification</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>1284</fpage><lpage>1295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.253757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25667313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragauskas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The occurrence of tricin and its derivatives in plants</article-title><source>Green Chem</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1439</fpage><lpage>1454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5GC03062E</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Speranza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Due&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Camarero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guill&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biodegradation of lignocellulosics: microbial, chemical, and enzymatic aspects of the fungal attack of lignin</article-title><source>Int Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16200498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16200498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ten Have</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Teunissen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative mechanisms involved in lignin degradation by white-rot fungi</article-title><source>Chem Rev</source><year>2001</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>3397</fpage><lpage>3414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr000115l</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11749405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatakka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hofrichter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal biodegradation of lignocelluloses</article-title><source>Industrial applications the mycota</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>340</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Ortega</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal aryl-alcohol oxidase: a peroxide-producing flavoenzyme involved in lignin degradation</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotech.</source><year>2012</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1395</fpage><lpage>1410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-011-3836-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camarero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding lignin biodegradation for the improved utilization of plant biomass in modern biorefineries</article-title><source>Biofuels Bioprod Biorefin</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bbb.1467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez-Fueyo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Due&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Floudas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibbett</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Canessa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic> and <italic>Phanerochaete chrysosporium</italic> provide insight into selective ligninolysis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>5458</fpage><lpage>5463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1119912109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22434909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakade</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of the gene encoding a manganese peroxidase from <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic></article-title><source>Mycoscience.</source><year>2007</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/S10267-006-0334-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakade</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Natsume</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Lentinula edodes</italic> genome survey and postharvest transcriptome analysis</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>e02990</fpage><lpage>e03016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02990-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28314725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S-G</given-names></name><name><surname>il Yoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-read transcriptome data for improved gene prediction in <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic></article-title><source>Data in brief</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>454</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dib.2017.09.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29845094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000e1;ng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J-N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C-L</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x00101;ng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genome of <italic>Pleurotus eryngii</italic> provides insights into the mechanisms of wood decay</article-title><source>J Biotechnol</source><year>2016</year><volume>239</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2016.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27737781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Fueyo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Due&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignin-degrading peroxidases from genome of selective ligninolytic fungus <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>16903</fpage><lpage>16916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.356378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22437835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camarero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Galletti</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preferential degradation of phenolic lignin units by two white rot fungi</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>4509</fpage><lpage>4516</lpage><?supplied-pmid 7811086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7811086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crestini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sermanni</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Argyropoulos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural modifications induced during biodegradation of wheat lignin by <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic></article-title><source>Bioorg Med Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0968-0896(98)00047-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9730232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Camarero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bocchini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Galletti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on wheat lignin degradation by <italic>Pleurotus</italic> species using analytical pyrolysis</article-title><source>J Anal Appl Pyrolysis</source><year>2001</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-2370(00)00116-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Almendros</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Camarero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Vares</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatakka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transformation of wheat straw in the course of solid-state fermentation by four ligninolytic basidiomycetes</article-title><source>Enzyme Microb Technol</source><year>1999</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0141-0229(99)00088-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jurak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Punt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Arts</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruppen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fate of carbohydrates and lignin during composting and mycelium growth of <italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic> on wheat straw based compost</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0138909</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26436656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Erven</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>de Visser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Merkx</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Strolenberg</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>De Gijsel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruppen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantification of lignin and its structural features in plant biomass using <sup>13</sup>C lignin as internal standard for pyrolysis-GC&#x02013;SIM&#x02013;MS</article-title><source>Anal Chem</source><year>2017</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>10907</fpage><lpage>10916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.7b02632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28926698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution-state 2D NMR of ball-milled plant cell wall gels in DMSO-d 6</article-title><source>BioEnergy Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12155-008-9004-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansfield</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole plant cell wall characterization using solution-state 2D NMR</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1579</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2012.064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22864199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on finely divided wood. Part 1. Extraction of lignin with neutral solvents</article-title><source>Sven Papperstidn.</source><year>1956</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>485</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative studies on cellulolytic enzyme lignin and milled wood lignin of sweetgum and spruce</article-title><source>Holzforschung</source><year>1975</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/hfsg.1975.29.5.153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decomposition of lignin by white-rot fungi. I. Isolation of heavily degraded lignins from decayed spruce</article-title><source>Holzforschung</source><year>1974</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/hfsg.1974.28.6.217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>ASM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences between two strains of <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic> on improving the nutritive value of wheat straw for ruminants</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.13494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28517113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>KEB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fiber and nonstarch polysaccharide content and variation in common crops used in broiler diets</article-title><source>Poult Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>93</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2380</fpage><lpage>2393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2014-03902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25012855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Kuijk</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Baars</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of particle size and amount of inoculum on fungal treatment of wheat straw and wood chips</article-title><source>J Anim Sci Biotechnol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40104-016-0098-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27418962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Englyst</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simplified method for the measurement of total non-starch polysaccharides by gas&#x02013;liquid chromatography of constituent sugars as alditol acetates</article-title><source>Analyst.</source><year>1984</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/an9840900937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blumenkrantz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Asboe-Hansen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New method for quantitative determination of uronic acids</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1973</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(73)90377-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4269305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyrolysis-GC&#x02013;MS characterization of forage materials</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>1991</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1426</fpage><lpage>1437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf00008a014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>T-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S-N</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>R-C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of lignin structures and lignin&#x02013;carbohydrate complex (LCC) linkages by quantitative <sup>13</sup>C and 2D HSQC NMR spectroscopy</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>10604</fpage><lpage>10614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf2031549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21879769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ralph SA, Ralph J, Landucci L. NMR database of lignin and cell wall model compounds. 2009. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.glbrc.org/databases_and_software/nmrdatabase/">www.glbrc.org/databases_and_software/nmrdatabase/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez-Barbero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Faulds</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lignin composition and structure in young versus adult <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> plants</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>110</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.167254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>del R&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;T</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delignification and saccharification enhancement of sugarcane byproducts by a laccase-based pretreatment</article-title><source>ACS Sustainable Chem Eng.</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>7145</fpage><lpage>7154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.7b01332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del R&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lino</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Colodette</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differences in the chemical structure of the lignins from sugarcane bagasse and straw</article-title><source>Biomass Bioenergy</source><year>2015</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biombioe.2015.07.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villaverde</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ligero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vega</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Native lignin structure of <italic>Miscanthus x giganteus</italic> and its changes during acetic and formic acid fractionation</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>6262</fpage><lpage>6270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf900483t</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19552425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulbrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alherech</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Motagamwala</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lignin conversion to low-molecular-weight aromatics via an aerobic oxidation-hydrolysis sequence: comparison of different lignin sources</article-title><source>ACS Sustainable Chem Eng.</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>3367</fpage><lpage>3374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.7b03541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Padmakshan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and elimination of undesirable protein residues in plant cell wall materials for enhancing lignin analysis by solution-state nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy</article-title><source>Biomacromol</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>4184</fpage><lpage>4195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.biomac.7b01223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wechselberger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Crestini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elucidation of lignin structure by quantitative 2D NMR</article-title><source>Chem Eur J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>9529</fpage><lpage>9535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.201003045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21721058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>B-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>R-C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in characterization of lignin polymer by solution-state nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) methodology</article-title><source>Materials.</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma6010359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28809313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Kuijk</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jos&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Baars</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selective ligninolysis of wheat straw and wood chips by the white-rot fungus <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic> and its influence on in vitro rumen degradability</article-title><source>J Anim Sci Biotechnol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>55</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40104-016-0110-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27688879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del R&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Speranza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignin attack during eucalypt wood decay by selected basidiomycetes: a Py-GC/MS study</article-title><source>J Anal Appl Pyrolysis.</source><year>2002</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-2370(02)00043-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of trembling aspen wood (<italic>Populus tremuloides L</italic>.) degraded with the white rot fungus <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic> and MWLs isolated thereof</article-title><source>Holz Roh Werkst</source><year>2006</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00107-006-0133-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patwardhan</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanks</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the fast pyrolysis of lignin</article-title><source>Chemsuschem</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1629</fpage><lpage>1636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cssc.201100133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21948630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantification of wheat straw lignin structure by comprehensive NMR analysis</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2013</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>10848</fpage><lpage>10857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf4030486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24143908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meshitsuka</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative evaluation of milling effects on lignin structure during the isolation process of milled wood lignin</article-title><source>J Wood Sci.</source><year>2005</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10086-004-0682-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jos&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Laccase-mediator pretreatment of wheat straw degrades lignin and improves saccharification</article-title><source>BioEnergy Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>917</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12155-016-9745-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlen</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tricin-lignins: occurrence and quantitation of tricin in relation to phylogeny</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2016</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>1046</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27553717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendon&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferraz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural characterization of lignin during <italic>Pinus taeda</italic> wood treatment with <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>4073</fpage><lpage>4078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.70.7.4073-4078.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15240285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rancour</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marita</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grass cell walls: a story of cross-linking</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2056</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.02056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28149301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haase-Aschoff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Linke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of feruloyl-and cinnamoyl esterases from basidiomycetes in the presence of interfering laccase</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2013</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2012.12.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23306132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crestini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurasek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Argyropoulos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the mechanism of the laccase&#x02013;mediator system in the oxidation of lignin</article-title><source>Chem Eur J.</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5371</fpage><lpage>5378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.200304818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14613147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Srebotnik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manganese-dependent cleavage of nonphenolic lignin structures by <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic> in the absence of lignin peroxidase</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>3679</fpage><lpage>3686</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16535418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16535418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative degradation of non-phenolic lignin during lipid peroxidation by fungal manganese peroxidase</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1994</year><volume>354</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(94)01146-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7957943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jos&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-&#x000cd;&#x000f1;igo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of new unsaturated lipids during wood decay by ligninolytic basidiomycetes</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1344</fpage><lpage>1350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.3.1344-1350.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11872486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrasa</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlos del R&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal screening for biological removal of extractives from <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> wood</article-title><source>Can J Bot</source><year>2000</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1513</fpage><lpage>1522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b99-127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seike</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alkadienyl and alkenyl itaconic acids (ceriporic acids G and H) from the selective white-rot fungus <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic>: a new class of metabolites initiating ligninolytic lipid peroxidation</article-title><source>Org Biomol Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>6432</fpage><lpage>6442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c2ob25415h</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22739503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srebotnik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence that <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic> degrades nonphenolic lignin structures by a one-electron-oxidation mechanism</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>4435</fpage><lpage>4440</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16535732?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16535732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yelle</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapich</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Houtman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Timokhin</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A highly diastereoselective oxidant contributes to ligninolysis by the white rot basidiomycete <italic>Ceriporiopsis subvermispora</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>7536</fpage><lpage>7544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02111-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25261514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation mechanisms of a nonphenolic &#x003b2;-<italic>O</italic>-4 lignin model dimer by <italic>Trametes versicolor</italic> laccase in the presence of 1-hydroxybenzotriazole</article-title><source>Enzyme Microb Technol</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0141-0229(01)00523-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantarella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentili</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free radical versus electron-transfer routes of oxidation of hydrocarbons by laccase/mediator systems: catalytic or stoichiometric procedures</article-title><source>J Mol Catal B Enzym</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1381-1177(03)00014-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>