<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Res Notes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Res Notes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Research Notes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-0500</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6323729</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4041</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-018-4041-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Note</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Development of a new method for collecting hemolymph and measuring phenoloxidase activity in <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1823-9952</contrib-id><name><surname>Tabunoki</surname><given-names>Hiroko</given-names></name><address><email>h_tabuno@cc.tuat.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dittmer</surname><given-names>Neal T.</given-names></name><address><email>ndittmer@ksu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>Maureen J.</given-names></name><address><email>mgorman@ksu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kanost</surname><given-names>Michael R.</given-names></name><address><email>kanost@ksu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.136594.c</institution-id><institution>Department of Science of Biological Production, Graduate School of Agriculture, </institution><institution>Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>3-5-8 Saiwai-cho, Fuchu, Tokyo 183-8509 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0737 1259</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.36567.31</institution-id><institution>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics, </institution><institution>Kansas State University, </institution></institution-wrap>141 Chalmers Hall, Manhattan, KS 66506-3702 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>7</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Objective</title><p id="Par1">Hemolymph plays many important roles in the physiology of an insect throughout its lifetime; however, for small-bodied insects, studies are lacking because of the difficulties encountered while collecting hemolymph. The objective of our study was to develop a method to collect hemolymph plasma from various stages of <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> and to evaluate phenoloxidase activity in the plasma samples. We first designed a procedure for easily and quickly collecting clear hemolymph plasma from <italic>T. castaneum</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">By using this method, we collected approximately 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l plasma from 30 individuals at the larval, pupal or adult stages. And then, we studied the expression of phenoloxidase by performing western blot analysis of the plasma samples and found that phenoloxidase is present in hemolymph in each developmental stage. We also measured phenoloxidase activity in control plasma and plasma treated with Gram-positive bacteria, <italic>Micrococcus luteus</italic>. Phenoloxidase activity was greater in some of the <italic>M. luteus</italic>-treated plasma samples compared with control samples. Thus, we developed a method to collect hemolymph plasma that is suitable for studies of phenoloxidase activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13104-018-4041-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Phenoloxidase</kwd><kwd>Melanization</kwd><kwd>Hemolymph</kwd><kwd>Small insects</kwd><kwd>Innate immune response</kwd><kwd>Melanin</kwd><kwd>Dopamine</kwd><kwd><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</institution></funding-source><award-id>18H02212</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Tabunoki</surname><given-names>Hiroko</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Institute of General Medical Sciences grant R37</institution></funding-source><award-id>GM41247</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>Maureen J.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par6">Insect hemolymph plays many important roles in the physiology of an insect, such as transporting nutrients and hormones to cells and tissues, maintaining the correct moisture ratio and optimal body temperature, maintaining body shape, and protecting the insect from pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In addition, some protein components in hemolymph plasma can differ between females and males throughout the developmental process and thus play specific roles in females and males. By investigating the biochemical components of hemolymph, the insect species can be better characterized. In the case of a honeybee, methods for collecting hemolymph were sought, and antennae method for hemolymph sampling (AMHS) is propounded as the quickest and most reliable method for collecting hemolymph [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. However, for many insects the collection and analysis of hemolymph has been difficult because of their tiny body size relative to the honeybee, and more methods need to be developed to resolve this issue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">The red flour beetle (<italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic>) is a model insect of the order Coleoptera. The genome of this species is well characterized, and methods to induce systemic RNA interference (RNAi) are available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. We were interested in understanding the immune response system in <italic>T. castaneum</italic> hemolymph; however, <italic>T. castaneum</italic> is a small-size insect, and collection of enough hemolymph for biochemical assays has been difficult.</p><p id="Par8">Phenoloxidase (PO) is one of the plasma proteins in hemolymph [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. It is expressed as an inactive zymogen, and is activated through specific proteolytic cleavage in response to wounding or infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Activated phenoloxidase hydroxylates tyrosine and oxidizes DOPA, dopamine, and dopamine derivatives, and subsequent chemical reactions lead to the formation of melanin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Melanin participates in wound healing and immune-related melanization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Because we are interested in melanization, one of the goals of this study was to develop a plasma collection process that is compatible with phenoloxidase activity assays.</p><p id="Par9">Here, we report a new method to easily and quickly collect clear hemolymph plasma from larval, pupal, and adult <italic>T. castaneum</italic>. Importantly, this method is compatible with analyses of phenoloxidase activity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Main text</title><sec id="Sec3" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Insects</title><p id="Par10">The <italic>T. castaneum</italic> GA-1 strain was used in all experiments. The insects were reared on whole-wheat flour containing 5% brewer&#x02019;s yeast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. All insects were kept at 30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with a 16-h light/8-h dark cycle. We used last instar larvae which were selected using No. 25 sieve (Fisher scientific Inc., Waltham, MA, USA), pupae (0&#x02013;4-day-old pupa), and adults (0&#x02013;7-day-old) in this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Bioinformatics</title><p id="Par11">The signal peptide sequences were analyzed using the SignalP 4.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and the molecular weights for PPO I (GenBank AY884063) and PPO II (GenBank AY884064) were predicted using Genetyx 13.0 (Genetyx Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Hemolymph collection from <italic>T. castaneum</italic></title><p id="Par12"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> larvae, pupae, and adults were counted (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;30) and transferred to a small handmade sieve (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). The sieve was made by attaching a Nitex Nylon screen 630&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., Waltham, MA, USA) to part of a 50&#x000a0;ml plastic centrifuge tube (Corning Co. Ltd., One Riverfront Plaza, NY, USA). The larvae, pupae, and adults were washed with distilled water containing 0.1% Tween, then washed with tap water for 1&#x000a0;min, and finally rinsed with 70% ethanol. Moisture was removed using a paper towel. The insects were then transferred to a glass dish containing a slightly moist and flat paper tissue on the bottom. The glass dish was kept on ice to anesthetize the insects (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). To prepare for collecting the hemolymph plasma, a hole was punctured in a 0.5-ml tube using a 23-gauge needle (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.,) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). To separate the males from the females, the sex of the pupal and adult insects was determined according to USDA Beetle Wrangling Tips, Sexing Tribolium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Method for collecting hemolymph. <bold>a</bold> Creating a handmade sieve for washing <italic>T. castaneum.</italic> The 50&#x000a0;ml tube drawing (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://g86.dbcls.jp/%7etogoriv/">http://g86.dbcls.jp/~togoriv/</ext-link>) is licensed under the HYPERLINK <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.ja">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.ja</ext-link>. Creative commons display 4.0 license <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.ja">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.ja</ext-link>. <bold>b</bold> Set up of stereomicroscope. <bold>c</bold> Structure of handmade collection tube, which consisted of a 0.5&#x000a0;ml tube with a hole at the bottom placed inside a 1.5&#x000a0;ml tube. <bold>d</bold> Location of punctures created in the larvae, pupae, and adults. Larvae were pinched at the root of their legs using two forceps, and the legs were pulled in opposite directions. The black broken circle indicates the location for creating a small tear. The forceps drawings (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://g86.dbcls.jp/%7etogoriv/">http://g86.dbcls.jp/~togoriv/</ext-link>) are licensed under the HYPERLINK <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.ja">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.ja</ext-link> Creative commons display 4.0 license <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.ja">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.ja</ext-link>. Pupae and adults were pierced with a needle at the points indicated by the black arrow. All protocols for collecting hemolymph from <italic>T. castaneum</italic> were performed on ice under a stereomicroscope</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2018_4041_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par13">To collect hemolymph from the larvae, pupae, and adults, <italic>T. castaneum</italic> individuals were handled as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d. The larvae were grasped at the base of their legs using two forceps (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d, larva), and the legs were pulled in opposite directions to create a tear in the cuticle between them, with care to avoid damaging the gut. Pupae were pierced through the anterior region of an elytron (which in the pupa is on the ventral surface) using a 28 gauge needle (BD 1/2&#x000a0;cc U-100 Insulin Syringe #329461) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d, pupa indicated by a black arrow). The adults were pierced on the dorsal side, between the pronotum and elytron (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d, adult black arrow). The insects were then transferred to the ice-cold collection tubes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). The collection tubes were centrifuged using the 5418 centrifuge (Eppendorf Inc. Co. Ltd. Hamburg, Germany) at 12,000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> for 10&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, and the supernatant, which we refer to as plasma, was transferred to a new tube. For some experiments, this protocol was modified to prevent hemolymph melanization. For experiments measuring phenoloxidase activity, 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l bleeding buffer (100&#x000a0;mM trisodium citrate, 17.8&#x000a0;mM citric acid, pH 5.5) was placed at the bottom of the 1.5&#x000a0;ml collection tubes. For samples used in immunodetection, 2&#x000a0;mg phenylthiourea (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) was added to the 1.5&#x000a0;ml tube.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Measurement of phenoloxidase activity</title><p id="Par14">The plasma collected using bleeding buffer was used to measure phenoloxidase activity. Two microliters of plasma were added to a 1.5-ml tube containing 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l filter-sterilized deionized water (control) or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l <italic>Micrococcus luteus</italic> (1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l suspension, Sigma-Aldrich), and the tubes were incubated for 10&#x000a0;min at room temperature (RT). After incubation, these plasma samples were transferred to separate wells of a 96-well plate, after which 4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of a 50&#x000a0;mM dopamine hydrochloride solution in 1&#x000a0;mM HCl (Sigma-Aldrich), and 93&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of 20&#x000a0;mM 3-(<italic>N</italic>-morpholino)propanesulfonic acid (MOPS) (pH 7.0) containing 25&#x000a0;mM calcium chloride (Sigma-Aldrich) were added to each well. The absorbance at 470&#x000a0;nm was monitored once/minute for 1&#x000a0;h at 30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C using a microplate spectrophotometer (Synergy HT, BioTek co. ltd., Winooski, VT USA). The reaction curves started with a lag phase followed by a linear phase. Linear regression was used to calculate the changes in absorbance per minute during the linear phase of each reaction. One unit of phenoloxidase activity was defined as &#x00394;A<sub>470</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.001/min [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The assay was performed in triplicate. Statistical significance was determined by two-tailed Student&#x02019;s t-test using Excel (Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA). p values of &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were considered to be significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Western blotting</title><p id="Par15">Plasma samples (0.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l) containing phenylthiourea were heated in SDS-PAGE sample buffer and then separated by electrophoresis on 4&#x02013;12% BisTris gels with MOPS running buffer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.) under reducing conditions according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The proteins were then transferred to nitrocellulose membranes (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc., Hercules, CA, USA) using the method described by Towbin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The membranes were incubated in blocking buffer composed of 3% milk and Tris-buffered saline (TBS) at pH 7.4, including 0.1% Tween 20 (TBS-T) for 1&#x000a0;h at RT, incubated in rabbit anti-phenoloxidase polyclonal antiserum (KSU37) as the primary antibody (diluted 1:2000) in blocking buffer for 1 h, and washed three times with TBS-T for 5&#x000a0;min. The polyclonal antiserum KSU37 used for immunoblot analysis detects both the PPOI and PPOII subunits of <italic>Manduda sexta</italic> prophenoloxidase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The washed membranes were incubated with goat anti-rabbit immunoglobulin (Ig)G (H+L) alkaline phosphatase (AP) conjugate 1:3000 (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc.) in blocking buffer for 1&#x000a0;h at RT and then washed twice with TBS-T for 5&#x000a0;min and with TBS for 5&#x000a0;min. The membranes were developed using an AP Conjugate Substrate Kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc.) for 6&#x000a0;min.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results and discussion</title><p id="Par16">In this study, we developed methods for easily and quickly collecting clear plasma from <italic>T. castaneum</italic> and assessed the presence and activity of phenoloxidase in the plasma. First, we collected approximately 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of hemolymph from 30 individuals at each developmental stage (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1).</p><p id="Par17"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> expresses two phenoloxidase genes: PPOI and PPOII [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. PPOI has a predicted molecular weight of 79,099&#x000a0;Da and PPOII has a predicted molecular weight of 79,338&#x000a0;Da. We examined the utility of available antisera against <italic>M. sexta</italic> phenoloxidase to identify phenoloxidase in <italic>T. castaneum</italic> plasma. <italic>M. sexta</italic> anti-phenoloxidase antibody reacted with one or two polypeptides of approximately 80&#x000a0;kDa in all <italic>T. castaneum</italic> plasma samples (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Because phenoloxidase bands of the expected size were detected, we conclude that the plasma samples were not significantly contaminated with gut contents (which contain proteolytic enzymes) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). Also, we found that collected hemolymph plasma may include some cellular proteins because our samples contained many more protein bands than plasma from <italic>Tenebrio molitor,</italic> which is a larger Coleopteran insect than <italic>T. castaneum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Dectection of phenoloxidase in larvae, pupae and adults. Plasma protein samples (0.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l) from <italic>T. castaneum</italic> larva, lane 1; male pupa, lane 2; female pupa, lane 3; male adult, lane 4; and female adult, lane 5; <italic>M. sexta</italic> larval plasma, lane 6 (as a positive control) were separated by SDS-PAGE, transferred to nitrocellulose, and probed with anti-<italic>M. sexta</italic> phenoloxidase antibody. <bold>a</bold> Coomassie blue staining of the separated proteins. <bold>b</bold> Immunoblotting. Lane M represents molecular weight markers. Arrows indicate bands of the expected size for prophenoloxidase detected by prophenoloxidase antiserum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2018_4041_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par18">It has been reported that neither PPO mRNA was expressed from the late pupa stage to the early adult stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. However, phenoloxidase was found in adult plasma in this study. These results suggest that <italic>T. castaneum</italic> phenoloxidase is a stable protein, persisting from the pupal stage into the adult stage.</p><p id="Par19">We attempted to measure phenoloxidase activity in <italic>T. castaneum</italic> plasma by monitoring the oxidation of the substrate dopamine according to a previously described phenoloxidase assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. However, this method was not suitable for <italic>T. castaneum</italic> plasma because of rapid hemolymph melanization that occurred in the larval and adult samples before the assay could be performed.</p><p id="Par20">To circumvent this problem, we tested several bleeding and assay buffers to determine which combinations would best suppress oxidation of endogenous catechols during the collection process but give reliable results during the activity assay; these buffer combinations are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2. Buffer combinations 1 to 3 were not suitable for measuring phenoloxidase activity as the change in absorbance did not progress linearly with time (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figures S2, S3, S4, Table S3).</p><p id="Par21">The assay was slightly improved using buffer combination 4 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S5, Table S3), as this prevented premature melanization in the larval plasma but not the adult plasma. Previous reports for <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic>, <italic>Alphitobius diaperinus</italic>, and <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> indicated that oxidation of endogenous dopamine was inhibited using a bleeding buffer at pH 4.0; however, phenoloxidase activity was highest at approximately pH 6.0 in these species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Thus, we assessed additional buffer combinations according to our previous findings. Buffer combination 5 completely blocked early plasma melanization, however phenoloxidase activity was very low in all samples (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S6, Table S3). Finally, we found that buffer combination 6, with collecting hemolymph into citrate buffer at pH 5.5, was suitable for minimizing melanization during hemolymph collection while still allowing for sufficient dopamine oxidation for measuring phenoloxidase activity (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S7, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Phenoloxidase activity of plasma samples from <italic>T. castaneum</italic>. Control, no added bacteria; <italic>M. luteus</italic> indicates plasma samples treated with <italic>M. luteus</italic> prior to PO assay. <bold>a</bold> Larva (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.183), <bold>b</bold> male pupa (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.065), <bold>c</bold> female pupa (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.003), <bold>d</bold> male adult (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.008), and <bold>e</bold> female adult (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.007). Error bars indicate standard errors (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2018_4041_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par22">For some studies of insect immunity, phenoloxidase in hemolymph or plasma is intentionally activated by the addition of an immune elicitor. To verify that the plasma collection method we developed is suitable for these kinds of studies, we observed whether phenoloxidase activity was higher after incubating the plasma with Gram-positive bacteria, <italic>M. luteus</italic>. For these experiments, we used buffer combination 6. We found that phenoloxidase activity increased after treatment with <italic>M. luteus</italic> in plasma samples from female pupae and male and female adults, but the increase observed in plasma from larvae and male pupae was not statistically significant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). It is possible that the phenoloxidase in those samples was already partially activated by the collection process.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par23">We developed an easy method to collect hemolymph plasma from <italic>T. castaneum</italic>. Our methods allow for the conducting of experiments which have previously been challenging due to the difficulty in collecting sufficient amounts of hemolymph from this insect. Also, we were able to clarify that prophenoloxidase protein is a stable protein, persisting from the pupal stage into the adult stage of the <italic>T. castaneum</italic> hemolymph. This new method could be helpful for various analyses of <italic>T. castaneum</italic> hemolymph, for example, biochemical assays, other enzyme assays, proteome analysis, metabolomic analysis, and tracking of labeled substances or proteins in the hemolymph in <italic>T. castaneum</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par24">This method may not be suitable for studying hemocytes as they are removed and possibly damaged during the centrifugation step. This method may also damage other cells whose contents may then contaminate the plasma sample.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional file</title><sec id="Sec12"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13104_2018_4041_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Figure S1.</bold> Identifying the sex of pupal and adult <italic>T. castaneum.</italic> The structure of the genital papillae is markedly different between female and male pupae. The pupae were sexed by examining the structure of the genital papillae (on the last abdominal segment), which are markedly different between female and male pupae (indicated with black arrow). For adults, sex was determined by the presence (male) or absence (female) of a patch of bristles (&#x0201c;sex patch&#x0201d;; indicated by white arrow) on the femur of the prothoracic legs. <bold>Figure S2.</bold> Observation of the reaction curve in experimental condition&#x000a0;1. The absorbance (A470) was monitored, and calculated as mO.D./min (&#x00394;A470 = 0.001/min), and plotted on the graph. Control, no added bacteria; <italic>M. luteus</italic> indicates plasma samples treated with <italic>M. luteus</italic> prior to PO assay. A; larva control, B; larva <italic>M. luteus</italic>, C; Adult control, D; Adult <italic>M. luteus</italic>. <bold>Figure S3.</bold> Observation of the reaction curve in Experimental condition&#x000a0;2. The absorbance (A470) was monitored, and calculated as mO.D./min (&#x00394;A470 = 0.001/min), and plotted on the graph. Control, no added bacteria; <italic>M. luteus</italic> indicates plasma samples treated with <italic>M. luteus</italic> prior to PO assay. A; larva control, B; larva <italic>M. luteus</italic>, C; Adult control, D; Adult <italic>M. luteus</italic>. <bold>Figure S4.</bold> Observation of the reaction curve in Experimental condition&#x000a0;3. The absorbance (A470) was monitored, and calculated as mO.D./min (&#x00394;A470 = 0.001/min), and plotted on the graph. Control, no added bacteria; <italic>M. luteus</italic> indicates plasma samples treated with <italic>M. luteus</italic> prior to PO assay. A; larva control, B; larva <italic>M. luteus</italic>, C; Adult control, D; Adult <italic>M. luteus</italic>. <bold>Figure S5.</bold> Observation of the reaction curve in Experimental condition&#x000a0;4. The absorbance (A470) was monitored, and calculated as mO.D./min (&#x00394;A470 = 0.001/min), and plotted on the graph. Control, no added bacteria; <italic>M. luteus</italic> indicates plasma samples treated with <italic>M. luteus</italic> prior to PO assay. A; larva control, B; larva <italic>M. luteus</italic>, C; Adult control, D; Adult <italic>M. luteus</italic>. <bold>Figure S6.</bold> Observation of the reaction curve in Experimental condition&#x000a0;5. The absorbance (A470) was monitored, and calculated as mO.D./min (&#x00394;A470 = 0.001/min), and plotted on the graph. Control, no added bacteria; <italic>M. luteus</italic> indicates plasma samples treated with <italic>M. luteus</italic> prior to PO assay. A; larva control, B; larva <italic>M. luteus</italic>, C; Adult control, D; Adult <italic>M. luteus</italic>. <bold>Figure S7.</bold> Observation of the reaction curve in Experimental condition&#x000a0;6. The absorbance (A<sub>470</sub>) was monitored, and calculated as mO.D./min (&#x00394;A470 = 0.001/min), and plotted on the graph. Control, no added bacteria; <italic>M. luteus</italic> indicates plasma samples treated with <italic>M. luteus</italic> prior to PO assay. A; larva control, B; larva M. luteus, C; Pupa-male control, D; Pupa-male <italic>M. luteus</italic>, E; Pupa-female control, F; Pupa-female <italic>M. luteus</italic>, G; Adult-male control, H; Adult-male <italic>M. luteus</italic>, I; Adult-female control, J; Adult-female <italic>M. luteus</italic>. <bold>Table S1.</bold> Plasma collected from different developmental stages (n = 30). <bold>Table S2.</bold> Assay buffer combinations tested for measuring phenoloxidase (PO) activity. <bold>Table S3.</bold> Phenoloxidase activity in experimental combination 1 to 5.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AMHS</term><def><p id="Par3">antennae method for hemolymph sampling</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNAi</term><def><p id="Par4">RNA interference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PO</term><def><p id="Par5">phenoloxidase</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>Conceived and designed the experiments HT, MJG, NTD and MRK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools MJG, NTD and MRK. Performed the experiments HT. Analyzed the data HT, MJG, NTD and MRK. Contributed to the writing of the paper HT, MJG, NTD and MRK. All authors ensure that this is the case. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par25">We thank Dr. Karl Kramer for advice about hemolymph plasma proteins in <italic>T. castaneum</italic>, and Ms. Lisa Brummett for helping with the Western blotting experiment. This work was supported by Science and Technology of Japan and Overseas travel assistance program supported by TUAT president discretionary expenses to HT.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par26">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par27">All experimental data in this study were included in this article. Additional figures and tables are available in this article.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par28">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par29">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par30">This work was supported by Funds by the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research B (18H02212) and by National Institute of General Medical Sciences Grant R37 GM41247. The funders did not have a role in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par31">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nation</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Insect physiology and biochemistry</source><year>2016</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-loc>Florida</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>424</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x00141;o&#x0015b;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Strachecka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and cost-effective biochemical spectrophotometric analysis of solution of insect &#x0201c;blood&#x0201d; and body surface elution</article-title><source>Sensors (Basel)</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1494</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s18051494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borsuk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ptaszy&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Olszewski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Domaciuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krutmuang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Paleolog</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new method for quick and easy hemolymph collection from apidae adults</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e0170487</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0170487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28125668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental evolution of external immune defences in the red flour beetle</article-title><source>J Evol Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>27</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1562</fpage><lpage>1571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jeb.12406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24835532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Minakuchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochiai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prophenoloxidase genes and antimicrobial host defense of the model beetle, <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title><source>J Invertebr Pathol</source><year>2015</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2015.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26519623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rafaluk-Mohr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Joop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cryptic changes in immune response and fitness in <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> as a consequence of coevolution with <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic></article-title><source>J Invertebr Pathol</source><year>2018</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2017.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29273219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Caragea</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BeetleBase in 2010: revisions to provide comprehensive genomic information for <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>D437</fpage><lpage>D442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19820115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Tribolium Genome Sequencing Consortium</collab></person-group><article-title>The genome of the model beetle and pest <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>452</volume><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18362917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knorr</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingsohn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanost</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilcinskas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> as a model for high-throughput RNAi screening</article-title><source>Adv Biochem Eng Biotechnol</source><year>2013</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23748349?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23748349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitt-Engel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultheis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwirz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Str&#x000f6;hlein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Troelenberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The iBeetle large-scale RNAi screen reveals gene functions for insect development and physiology</article-title><source>Nat Commun.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>7822</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms8822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26215380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanost</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Beckage</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenoloxidases in insect immunity</article-title><source>Insect immunology</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press/Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerenius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Soderhall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prophenoloxidase-activating system in invertebrates</article-title><source>Immunol Rev</source><year>2004</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0105-2896.2004.00116.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15199959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nappi</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melanization immune responses in mosquito vectors</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2005.02.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15780842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nappi</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melanogenesis and associated cytotoxic reactions: applications to insect innate immunity</article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2005.01.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15804578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lasley</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>William</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tribolium information bulletin</article-title><source>Agricultural research institute</source><year>1960</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chazy</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The SignalP 4.1 server: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/SignalP/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/SignalP/</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Jun 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">USDA beetle wrangling tips, sexing Tribolium: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ars.usda.gov/plains-area/mhk/cgahr/spieru/docs/tribolium-stock-maintenance/#sexing">https://www.ars.usda.gov/plains-area/mhk/cgahr/spieru/docs/tribolium-stock-maintenance/#sexing</ext-link>. Accessed 15 Jun 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanost</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of tyrosine hydroxylase from <italic>Manduca sexta</italic></article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1327</fpage><lpage>1337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2007.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17967351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Towbin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Staehelin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrophoretic transfer of proteins from polyacrylamide gels to nitrocellulose sheets: procedure and some applications</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1979</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>4350</fpage><lpage>4354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.76.9.4350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">388439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanost</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subunit composition of pro-phenol oxidase from <italic>Manduca sexta</italic>: molecular cloning of subunit ProPO-P1</article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>835</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0965-1748(97)00066-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9474780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arakane</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Muthukrishnan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanost</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Laccase 2 is the phenoloxidase gene required for beetle cuticle tanning</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>11337</fpage><lpage>11342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0504982102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16076951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><name><surname>Osaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization and properties of a 1,3-beta-<sc>d</sc>-glucan pattern recognition protein of <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic> larvae that is specifically degraded by serine protease during prophenoloxidase activation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><issue>43</issue><fpage>42072</fpage><lpage>42079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M307475200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12923175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakemond</surname><given-names>CMM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fogliano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Renzone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Scaloni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincken</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of phenoloxidase in browning during grinding of <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic> larvae</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e0189685</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0189685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29244828</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>