<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6115472</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">29784</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-29784-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is Involved in Rice Seminal Root Elongation by Regulating Root Apical Meristem Activity in Response to Low Nitrogen and Phosphate</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Huwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Jinyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Mengmeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Jiajing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xinni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xuhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Le</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Xiaonan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4930-035X</contrib-id><name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>Koichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Quanzhi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Guohua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yali</given-names></name><address><email>ylzhang@njau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9750 7019</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27871.3b</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Crop Genetics and Germplasm Enhancement, and Key Laboratory of Plant Nutrition and Fertilization in Low-Middle Reaches of the Yangtze River, </institution><institution>Ministry of Agriculture, Nanjing Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Nanjing, 210095 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.108266.b</institution-id><institution>College of Agronomy, </institution><institution>Collaborative Innovation Center of Henan Grain Crops, Key Laboratory of Rice Biology in Henan Province, Henan Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Zhengzhou, 450002 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0722 4435</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.267687.a</institution-id><institution>Center for Bioscience Research &#x00026; Education, </institution><institution>Utsunomiya University, </institution></institution-wrap>350 Mine-machi, Utsunomiya, 321-8505 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>13014</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The response of plant root development to nutrient deficiencies is critical for crop production. Auxin, nitric oxide (NO), and strigolactones (SLs) are important regulators of root growth under low-nitrogen and -phosphate (LN and LP) conditions. Polar auxin transport in plants, which is mainly dependent on auxin efflux protein PINs, creates local auxin maxima to form the basis for root initiation and elongation; however, the <italic>PIN</italic> genes that play an important role in LN- and LP-modulated root growth remain unclear. qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>OsPIN</italic> family genes showed that the expression of <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is most abundant in root tip and is significantly downregulated by LN, LP, sodium nitroprusside (SNP, NO donor), and GR24 (analogue of SLs) treatments. Seminal roots in <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants were shorter than those of the wild type; and the seminal root, [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport, and IAA concentration responses to LN, LP, SNP, and GR24 application were attenuated in <italic>ospin1b-1</italic> mutants. <italic>pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> expression was upregulated by LN, LP, SNP, and GR24 treatments in wild type, but not in the <italic>ospin1b-1</italic> mutant, suggesting that <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is involved in auxin transport and acts as a downstream mediator of NO and SLs to induce meristem activity in root tip in rice under LN and LP.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Nitrogen (N) and phosphate (P) are required for plant growth and development; however, the natural supply of soil N and P limits plant growth and development in most agricultural cropping systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Therefore, the response of the root system architecture to N and P deficiencies is critical for plant growth and crop productivity. Increases in the root-to-shoot ratio and root surface area regulated by deficiencies of N and P have been studied in several plant species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, most of which focused on the responses of the root system to P deficiency. Two contrasting reactions of root growth to P deficiency have been recorded: 1) reduction of primary root growth and enhancement of lateral root (LR) density in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>; and 2) elongation of primary roots in other plant species (such as rice)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, suggesting that P deficiency-related changes in the root morphology are complex and vary according to the experimental conditions and plant species. Moreover, in maize and rice, elongation of primary roots and inhibition of LR are typical responses to N deprivation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Root architecture is a highly plastic trait, and its plasticity is strongly controlled by environmental conditions and plant regulators. Polar auxin transport and auxin signaling pathways play essential roles in root development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Polar auxin transport in plants creates local auxin maxima that form the basis for root initiation and elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Polar auxin transport is mainly mediated by auxin efflux carrier PIN family proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Some lines of evidence suggest that the <italic>OsPIN</italic> family genes participate in root formation and elongation in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Moreover, the inhibited auxin transport from the shoot to root, which is largely dependent on reduced expression of <italic>OsPIN</italic> genes, plays an important role in low nitrogen (LN)- and low phosphate (LP)-modulated LR formation and seminal root elongation in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Few studies have assessed the <italic>PIN</italic> genes involved in auxin polar transport and LN- and LP-mediated modulation of root development.</p><p id="Par4">Root development involves cross-talk among several plant hormones. Auxins play an important role in regulating root growth and development under low N and low P conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. In addition to auxin, strigolactones (SLs) and nitric oxide (NO) are associated with the regulation of root development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Several lines of evidence suggest that the SL pathway is involved in rice root elongation under LN and LP conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. NO, as a signaling molecule, plays a pivotal role in root growth modulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. NO participates in LN- and LP-induced seminal root elongation in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. SL signaling genes are required for NO-induced elongation of seminal root in response to LN and LP in rice plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Moreover, SLs are believed to modulate auxin transport to regulate root formation and elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Although NO is closely associated with auxin by regulating <italic>PIN</italic> family genes and root elongation in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, whether auxin transport plays a role in NO-modulated root elongation under LN- and LP-deficient conditions remains unclear.</p><p id="Par5">In this study, phenotypic, cellular, and genetic analyses of rice were performed to explore the role of the <italic>OsPIN</italic> gene in regulating auxin polar transport and root development, and the crosstalk between SLs and NO under LN and LP conditions. We found that SLs are required for NO-mediated modulation of LN- and LP-induced seminal root elongation (similar responses of seminal and adventitious roots to LN and LP) and function by inhibiting auxin transport to the root tip. Of 10 <italic>OsPINs</italic>, the expression of <italic>OsPIN1b</italic>, which encodes an auxin efflux carrier, was highest in rice root tip, and so might be involved in auxin transport and elongation of seminal root by regulating meristem activity in the root tips of rice plants under LN and LP conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>NO regulates root elongation by inhibiting polar auxin transport</title><p id="Par6">LN- and LP-enhanced NO production resulted in the elongation of seminal roots (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1a,c,d</xref>), as reported previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. The effects of NO on auxin status in rice were investigated using transgenic plants expressing the <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> construct. Compared with the control, <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> intensity and IAA concentrations decreased in LN- and LP-treated root tips of WT plants (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1b&#x02013;e</xref>). The application of sodium nitroprusside (SNP, NO donor) under normal nutrition conditions decreased <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression and IAA concentration in root tips to a level similar as that under nutrient-deficient conditions. Application of cPTIO (2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4,4,5,5- tetramethylimidazoline-1-oxyl-3-oxide, NO scavenger) under low-nutrient conditions markedly increased <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression and IAA concentration in root tips to a level similar to that under control conditions (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1b&#x02013;e</xref>). However, <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression and seminal root length showed no differences between control and control&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIIO (Fig. S1f&#x02013;h), suggesting that the LN- and LP-mediated increase in NO levels reduced auxin levels in rice root tips.</p><p id="Par7">As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a,b</xref>, the application of naphthylacetic acid (NAA; an analogue of IAA) under LN and LP conditions reduced seminal root length and increased <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression to levels similar to those under normal nutrition conditions. Moreover, application of NAA and SNP under control conditions markedly relieved the inductive effect of SNP application on seminal root elongation and its inhibitory effect on <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression. Therefore, NO modulates LN- and LP-induced seminal root elongation by reducing auxin levels. In rice plants treated with N-1-naphthylphthalamic acid (NPA, a polar auxin transport inhibitor) under control conditions, the length of seminal roots markedly increased and the <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression in the root tip significantly decreased to levels similar to those under low-nutrient conditions. Furthermore, application of NPA and cPTIO under LN and LP conditions suppressed the inhibitory effect of cPTIO [2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4,4,5,5-tetramethylimidazoline-1-oxyl-3-oxide, an scavenger of NO] on seminal root elongation and its inductive effect on <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression. These results suggested that NO negatively regulates auxin polar transport and reduces auxin levels in the root tip.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The seminal root length and histochemical localization of <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression in the root tip of wild-type (WT) rice seedlings (Shiokari). Seedlings were grown in hydroponic medium containing normal nutrition (control; 2.5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;N, 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;M&#x02009;P), low N, or low P (LN, 0.02&#x02009;mM; LP, 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), or subjected to treatment with sodium nitroprusside (SNP, 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), 2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4,4,5,5- tetramethylimidazoline-1-oxyl-3-oxide (cPTIO, 80&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), or a-naphthylacetic acid (NAA, 10&#x02009;nM), or localized application of N-1-naphthylphthalamic acid (NPA, 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) by dispensing diluted agar onto the root-shoot junction for 14 days. (<bold>a</bold>) Seminal root length; (<bold>b</bold>) histochemical localization of <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression in root tip. Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;mm. Data are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of eight replicates and bars with different letters indicate significant differences at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, as determined by ANOVA followed by the LSD test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_29784_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e542"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">We evaluated the effects of SNP, cPTIO, and GR24 (an analogue of SLs) on [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA activity was lower in LN- and LP-treated root tips than in the control, suggesting that LN and LP decreased [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport from shoots to roots. Moreover, application of SNP and GR24 under control conditions markedly reduced [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport to root tips to the same extent as LP and LN; conversely, treatment with cPTIO under LN and LP conditions markedly increased [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport to root tips to the same extent as under control conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) analysis showed that <italic>OsPIN1a-b</italic>, <italic>OsPIN2</italic>, and <italic>OsPIN10a-b</italic> expression levels in WT root were significantly reduced by SNP treatment compared with those in the control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression was downregulated by LN and LP and restored by cPTIO in WT roots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). These findings confirmed that NO modulates LN- and LP-induced seminal root elongation by suppressing polar auxin transport.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>[<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport and <italic>PIN</italic> family expression in root of WT rice seedlings (Shiokari). Seedlings were grown in hydroponic medium containing normal nutrition (control; 2.5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;N, 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;M&#x02009;P), low N, or low P (LN, 0.02&#x02009;mM; LP, 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M&#x02009;P), or subjected to treatment with sodium nitroprusside (SNP, 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), 2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4,4,5,5- tetramethylimidazoline-1-oxyl-3-oxide (cPTIO, 80&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), or GR24 (analog of SLs, 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) for 14 days. (<bold>a</bold>) [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport; (<bold>b</bold>) <italic>PIN</italic> family expression; and (<bold>c</bold>), Os<italic>PIN1b</italic> expression. Data are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of eight replicates (<bold>a</bold>) and three replicates (<bold>b</bold>,<bold>c</bold>). Bars with different letters indicate significant differences at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, as determined by ANOVA followed by the LSD test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_29784_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e628"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Strigolactones and strigolactone signaling are required for NO-mediated suppression of polar auxin transport</title><p id="Par9">SLs are required for the role of NO in LN- and LP-induced seminal root elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Under control conditions, application of SNP or GR24 reduced <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression in WT root tips (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). However, LN and LP treatments and application of SNP did not affect <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression in SL synthetic and signaling mutants (<italic>d10</italic> and <italic>d3</italic>). Compared with control conditions, no change in [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport from shoots to root tips was observed in the <italic>d10</italic> mutant under low-nutrient conditions with the application of cPTIO (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). However, application of GR24 under control conditions markedly reduced [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport to root tips (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). No difference in the expression of <italic>OsPIN</italic> family genes was observed in the roots of the <italic>d10</italic> mutant between control and SNP conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). In comparison to control conditions, <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression in the <italic>d10</italic> mutant was unchanged under LN, LP, and cPTIO treatments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). These results confirmed that SLs and SL signaling are required for NO-mediated suppression of polar auxin transport in rice plants under LN and LP conditions.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Histochemical localization of <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression in root tip. Seedlings were grown in hydroponic medium containing normal nutrition (control; 2.5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;N, 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;M&#x02009;P), low N, or low P (LN, 0.02&#x02009;mM; LP, 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), or subjected to treatment with sodium nitroprusside (SNP, 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), 2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4,4,5,5-tetramethylimidazoline-1-oxyl-3-oxide (cPTIO, 80&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), or GR24 (analog of SLs, 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) for 14 days. Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;mm; n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_29784_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e703"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>[<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport and <italic>PIN</italic> family expression in root of the <italic>d10</italic> mutant. Seedlings were grown in hydroponic medium containing normal nutrition (control; 2.5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;N, 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;M&#x02009;P), low N, or low P (LN, 0.02&#x02009;mM; LP, 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) in addition to sodium nitroprusside (SNP, 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), 2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4,4,5,5-tetramethylimidazoline-1-oxyl-3-oxide (cPTIO, 80&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), or GR24 (analog of SLs, 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) for 14 days. (<bold>a</bold>) [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport; (<bold>b</bold>) <italic>PIN</italic> family expression; and (<bold>c</bold>) Os<italic>PIN1b</italic> expression. Data are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of eight replicates (<bold>a</bold>) and three replicates (<bold>b</bold>,<bold>c</bold>). Data are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of eight replicates and bars with different letters indicate significant differences at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, as determined by ANOVA followed by the LSD test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_29784_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e750"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is involved in NO- or SL-induced root elongation under LN and LP conditions</title><p id="Par10">We analysed 10 <italic>OsPIN</italic> family genes in root tip of rice plants (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Relative expression of <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> was the highest of the <italic>OsPINs</italic> in rice root tip, consistent with a previous study of other rice cultivars<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Therefore, <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> was used as the target gene in subsequent analyses. Compared with control conditions, <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression in root tip was significantly reduced by SNP treatment; however, application of abamine (an SL inhibitor) ameliorated this effect (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). Moreover, <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression was significantly upregulated by cPTIO application under LN or LP conditions in the WT compared with mock treatments, to a level similar to that in the <italic>d10</italic> mutant under LN and LP conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b,c</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression and localization of <italic>pPIN1b::GUS</italic> expression in root tip. Seedlings were grown in hydroponic medium containing normal nutrition (control; 2.5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;N, 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;M&#x02009;P), low N, or low P (LN, 0.02&#x02009;mM; LP, 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M&#x02009;), or subjected to treatment with sodium nitroprusside (SNP, 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), 2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4,4,5,5- tetramethylimidazoline-1-oxyl-3-oxide (cPTIO, 80&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), GR24 (analog of SLs, 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), or abamine (100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) for 14 days. (<bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>c</bold>) <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression under control (<bold>a</bold>), LN (<bold>b</bold>), and LP (<bold>c</bold>) conditions. (<bold>d</bold>) Localization of <italic>pPIN1b::GUS</italic> expression. mRNA levels were normalized to that of <italic>OsACT</italic>. Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;mm. Data are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three replicates and bars with different letters indicate significant differences at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, as determined by ANOVA followed by the LSD test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_29784_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e835"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">Next, <italic>GUS</italic> expression driven by the <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> promoter in root tip was evaluated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>). Compared with control conditions, <italic>pPIN1b::GUS</italic> expression in root tip was significantly reduced by SNP and GR24 treatments; however, the application of abamine ameliorated this effect. Moreover, under LN and LP conditions, the expression of <italic>pPIN1b::GUS</italic> was significantly upregulated by the application of cPTIO or abamine in comparison with that in the mock treatments, consistent with the gene expression results. Therefore, <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is involved in the NO- and SL-induced elongation of seminal root under LN and LP conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants are less sensitive to LN and LP conditions, and SNP and GR24 treatments</title><p id="Par12">The effect of LN and LP conditions on seminal root length of <italic>ospin1b-1</italic> and <italic>ospin1b-2</italic> and the WT (Dongjin) was assessed. Molecular characterisation revealed that T-DNAs were inserted into the promoter and 5&#x02032;-URT regions, respectively, of the two <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants. Compared with WT plants, <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression was almost completely suppressed in both <italic>ospin1b</italic> lines (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>).</p><p id="Par13">[<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport and auxin concentration in the root tip, as well as the seminal root length of <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants, were unaffected by LN, LP, SNP, and GR24 (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Compared with WT plants, shorter seminal root length was recorded in two <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants under different treatments. Compared with the control, the length of WT was increased under LN, LP, SNP, and GR24 treatments. However, the length of <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants was not affected under control, LN, LP, SNP, or GR24 treatments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). These findings confirmed that <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is involved in LN and LP in NO- and SL-mediated regulation of seminal root length.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Seminal root length in the wild type (WT, Dongjin) and <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants. Seedlings were grown in hydroponic medium containing normal nutrition (control; 2.5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;N, 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;M&#x02009;), low N, or low P (LN, 0.02&#x02009;mM; LP, 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M&#x02009;P), or subjected to treatment with sodium nitroprusside (SNP, 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) or GR24 (analog of SLs, 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) for 14 days. (<bold>a</bold>), Morphology and (<bold>b</bold>,<bold>c</bold>) seminal root lengths of rice plants. Data are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of eight replicates (<bold>b</bold>,<bold>c</bold>) and bars with different letters indicate significant differences at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, as determined by ANOVA followed by the LSD test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_29784_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e934"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>LN and LP conditions, and SNP and GR24 application, do not influence <italic>pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> expression in the <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants</title><p id="Par14">NO influences root elongation primarily by regulating root meristem activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. In this study, the relative expression of <italic>OsCYCB1;1</italic> was significantly decreased in <italic>d10</italic> and <italic>d3</italic> mutants relative to WT under control, LN, LP, and SNP treatments. However, application of GR24 markedly increased the levels of <italic>OsCYCB1;1</italic> in <italic>d10</italic>, but not in <italic>d3</italic> mutants, to the same extent as in WT (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><italic>OsCYCB1;1</italic> gene and <italic>pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> expression in rice seedlings. Seedlings were grown in hydroponic medium containing normal nutrition (control; 2.5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;N, 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;M&#x02009;P), low N, or low P (LN, 0.02&#x02009;mM; LP, 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), or subjected to treatment with sodium nitroprusside (SNP, 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) or GR24 (analog of SLs, 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) for 14 days. (<bold>a</bold>) The expression of <italic>OsCYCB1;1</italic> gene in WT, <italic>d10</italic> and <italic>d3</italic> mutants. (<bold>b</bold>) <italic>pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> expression in WT and <italic>ospin1b-1</italic> mutant. Cell cycle activity of the root meristem, as monitored by the <italic>pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> reporter, is shown. Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;500&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. Data are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three replicates (<bold>a</bold>) and bars with different letters indicate significant differences at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, as determined by ANOVA followed by the LSD test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_29784_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1013"/></fig></p><p id="Par15"><italic>ospin1b-1</italic> transgenic plants expressing the <italic>pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> construct were used to assess cell cycle activity in the root meristem (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>). Compared to control conditions, <italic>pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> expression in WT plants was greater under LN and LP conditions and following application of SNP and GR24. However, no significant change in <italic>pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> expression was recorded in the root tip of the <italic>ospin1b-1</italic> mutant. These findings suggested that <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is involved in the role of NO and SLs in LN- and LP-induced root apical meristem activity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Strigolactones and strigolactone signaling are required for NO-mediated suppression of auxin transport to root apex</title><p id="Par16">Auxin acts as a signaling intermediate in the response of root architecture to low phosphate supply<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. An auxin transport-independent pathway is involved in the changes in primary roots induced by phosphate stress in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Studies in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> have provided insight into the crosstalk between auxin and the root elongation response to P deficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. Moreover, auxin participates in the regulation of root elongation under N- and P-deficient conditions in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par17">SLs, NO, and auxin transport are closely linked in the regulation of primary root elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. NO functions as a signaling molecule in the inhibition of auxin transport to the root apex and restrains primary root elongation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. In addition to NO, SLs may act as modulators of auxin transport to regulate root elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, SLs modulate local auxin levels in a manner dependent on the auxin status of the plant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In rice, the application of SLs markedly reduces auxin transport under N- and P-deficient conditions, which in turn increases seminal root length<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par18">In this study, compared with those in the control conditions, <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> intensity, [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA activity, and IAA concentration in root tips were significantly reduced under LP and LN conditions (Supplementary Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1b</xref>,e and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2a</xref>), consistent with a previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. The application of SNP and GR24 under normal nutrition conditions and the application of cPTIO under low-nutrient conditions decreased and increased <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> intensity and [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA activity in root tips, respectively, to levels similar to those under low-nutrient or control conditions (Supplementary Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1c</xref>,e and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2a</xref>). Furthermore, the application of NAA or NPA reversed the effect of SNP and cPTIO on seminal root length and <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). These results suggested that NO and SLs participate in LN- and LP-induced rice seminal root elongation by downregulating polar auxin transport from the shoot to the root tip.</p><p id="Par19">We reported previously that SLs participate in LN- and LP-modulated seminal root elongation by inhibiting auxin transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. In this study, <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> expression, [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport, and <italic>OsPIN</italic> family expression were unaffected by SNP application, and <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression was unaffected by LN, LP, LN&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO, and LP&#x02009;+&#x02009;cPTIO application, in the root tips of the <italic>d10</italic> mutants (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>; Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). These results suggested that SL synthesis and signaling are required for the effect of NO on polar auxin transport from the shoot to root tip in rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is involved in NO- and SL-induced root elongation in response to low N and P</title><p id="Par20">The localisation of PINs in rice roots was reported by Wang <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>: among rice 10 <italic>PIN</italic> genes, only <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> was expressed in the root cap; <italic>OsPIN1b/1c/5a/5b</italic> were expressed in the meristem; <italic>OsPIN1b/1c/9</italic> were detected mainly in stele; <italic>OsPIN1a/1c/9/10a/10b</italic> were found in the LR cap region and <italic>OsPIN1c</italic> was also expressed in lateral root primordia (LRP); and <italic>OsPIN9</italic> has higher activity in LRP and stele<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. AtPIN1 was the first putative auxin efflux carrier to be characterised in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Subsequently, OsPIN1, ZmPIN1a, and ZmPIN1b were characterised in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and maize<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Phylogenetic analysis showed that AtPIN1 is a highly conserved gene that may play a key role in polar auxin transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Gene structure analysis showed that rice has four <italic>OsPIN1</italic> genes (<italic>OsPIN1a/1b/1c/1d</italic>), the distribution of each of which is similar to that of AtPIN1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. AtPIN1 and OsPIN1b regulate root growth in different plant species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Mutation of <italic>atpin1</italic> decreased the length of primary root by influencing the root tip cell meristem<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. <italic>ospin1b</italic> RNAi transgenic plants have fewer adventitious roots, but a similar root length, compared to WT plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. However, we found that [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport and IAA concentration in root tips of <italic>ospin1b</italic> were unaffected by LN, LP, SNP, and GR24 (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>), and seminal root length was shorter than that of WT plants under LN and LP conditions, and following SNP and GR24 application, which is inconsistent with a previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. This is likely due to our use of knockout T-DNA mutants while their RNAi transgenic plants are knockdown of <italic>OsPIN1b</italic>.</p><p id="Par21">The influence of NO and SLs on auxin transport involves regulation of PIN proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. For example, the transcriptional and translational levels of AtPIN1 in root tip were reduced by the application of NO donors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Strigolactones act by increasing the rate of AtPIN1 removal from the plasma membrane in shoot, but not in root<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. <italic>OsPIN1a</italic>, <italic>1b</italic>, 9, and <italic>10a</italic> expression in rice root was significantly decreased under LN and LP conditions, and following GR24 application<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. In this study, <italic>OsPIN1a-b</italic>, <italic>OsPIN2</italic>, and <italic>OsPIN10a-b</italic> expression in the WT was significantly reduced by SNP treatment compared with that in the control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Therefore, the expression of only <italic>OsPIN1a/1b/10a</italic> was downregulated under LN and LP conditions and following application of SNP and GR24. The expression of <italic>OsPIN2</italic>/<italic>10b</italic> was decreased under SNP treatment but not under LN and LP conditions, suggesting <italic>OsPIN2</italic>/<italic>10b</italic> was not involved in NO-mediated regulation of auxin transport under LN and LP. <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> was strongly expressed in root cap and meristem in transgenic rice plants with OsPIN-promoter-driven GUS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Similarly, <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression was strongest in rice tips; <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression was at least 12- and 1,000-fold higher than that of <italic>OsPIN1a</italic> and <italic>OsPIN10a</italic>, respectively, in rice root tips (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). These findings suggested that <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is involved in the role of LN and LP in the regulation of auxin transport by SL and NO.</p><p id="Par22">The seminal root of <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants was shorter than that of WT plants and root development in <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutants was less affected by low-nutrient conditions and application of SNP and GR24 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Moreover, abamine relieved the inhibitory effect of SNP on <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>); <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> expression was significantly upregulated by cPTIO application under LN and LP conditions to a level similar to that in the <italic>d10</italic> mutant subjected to mock treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). These findings confirmed that <italic>OsPIN1b</italic> is involved in the role of LN and LP in SL- and NO-mediated elongation of seminal root by affecting root meristem activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title><p id="Par23">SL-deficient mutant (<italic>d10</italic>), SL signaling mutant (<italic>d3</italic>), and wild-type (WT, Shiokari) plants were provided by Shinjiro Yamaguchi of the Riken Plant Science Center. The T-DNA insertion <italic>ospin1b</italic> mutant lines (<italic>ospinib-1</italic> and <italic>ospin1b-2</italic>) and the WT (cv. Dongjin) plants were obtained from the Rice Functional Genomics Express Database (RiceGE, Pohang City, South Korea).</p><p id="Par24">Plants were grown in a greenhouse under natural light at day/night temperatures of 30/18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Seven-day-old seedlings of uniform size and vigour were transplanted into holes in a lid placed over the top of pots (four holes per lid and three seedlings per hole). Nutrient solutions varying from one-quarter to full strength were applied for 1 week, followed by full-strength nutrient solution for a further week. Pots receiving normal nutrition (control) were filled with 2.5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;N (NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub>) and 300&#x02009;&#x000b5;M&#x02009;P (KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>), and those receiving N- and P-deficient nutrition were filled with 0.02&#x02009;mM&#x02009;N (LN) and 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M&#x02009;P (LP). To exclude any potential effects of potassium (K<sup>+</sup>) on the treatments, the low-P treatment solutions were supplemented with K<sup>+</sup> to the same levels as those under sufficient P conditions (300&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) using K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. The full chemical composition of the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) nutrient solution was (mM): 0.35 K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 1.0 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.0 MgSO<sub>4</sub>&#x000b7;7H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.5 Na<sub>2</sub>SiO<sub>3</sub>; and (&#x000b5;M), 20.0 Fe-EDTA, 9.0 MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.39 (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>6</sub>Mo<sub>7</sub>O<sub>24</sub>, 20.0 H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 0.77 ZnSO<sub>4</sub>, and 0.32 CuSO<sub>4</sub> (pH 5.5). The nutrient solution was replaced with fresh solution daily. Each treatment consisted of four replicates arranged in a completely randomised design to avoid edge effects. In addition, all experiments included three independent biological replicates.</p><p id="Par25">Pharmacological treatments comprising 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M SNP (NO donor), 80&#x02009;&#x000b5;M cPTIO (a NO scavenger), 10&#x02009;nM NAA (an analogue of IAA), 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M GR24 (an analogue of SLs), and 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M abamine (SL synthesis inhibitor) were applied to the hydroponic media. Since NAA is more stable than IAA in nutrient solution, NAA was used as the analogue of IAA in this study. Localised application of NNPA (a polar auxin transport inhibitor) was performed by dispensing diluted agar containing 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;M NPA directly from a pipette across the root-shoot junction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Measurement of root system architecture</title><p id="Par26">Seminal roots were significantly longer than adventitious roots under our experimental conditions. Our preliminary experiment showed similar responses of seminal and adventitious roots to LN and LP treatments, and the number of adventitious roots did not change significantly under the different nutrient conditions during the experimental period<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Therefore, seminal roots were selected to study the effects of LN and LP on the rice root system. Seminal root lengths were measured using a ruler.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Determination of IAA</title><p id="Par27">IAA concentrations in root tips were determined as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. The fresh weight of samples was first determined, followed immediately by freezing in liquid N<sub>2</sub>. Measurement of free IAA by high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) was carried out as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. An IAA standard was obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> construct</title><p id="Par28">To assess IAA distribution in rice plants, a <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> construct was transformed into WT and <italic>d10</italic> and <italic>d3</italic> mutants using <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> (strain EHA105). The <italic>pDR5::GUS</italic> construct was provided by Professor Ping Wu&#x02019;s group at Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China. The samples used for IAA analysis were also used for histochemical GUS staining. The root tips were stained for GUS activity for 2&#x02009;h at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The stained tissues were photographed using an Olympus SZX2-ILLK stereomicroscope with a colour charge-coupled device (CCD) camera (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><italic>pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> construct</title><p id="Par29"><italic>The pCYCB1;1::GUS</italic> fusion construct was transformed into rice plants. The <italic>pCYCB1; 1::GUS</italic> construct was provided by Professor Chuanzao Mao&#x02019;s group at Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China. The root tips were used for histochemical GUS staining, and were photographed using an SZX2-ILLK microscope with a colour CCD camera.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Measurement of NO in root tips</title><p id="Par30">NO was imaged by diaminofluorescein-FM diacetate (DAF-FM DA) and epifluorescence microscopy. The root tips were loaded with 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M DAF-FM DA in 20&#x02009;mM HEPES-NaOH buffer (pH 7.5). After incubating in the dark for 30&#x02009;min, the root tips were washed three times in fresh buffer and immediately visualised using a stereomicroscope (Olympus MVX10) equipped with a colour CCD camera, with excitation and emission at 488 and 495&#x02013;575&#x02009;nm, respectively. Green fluorescence intensity was quantified using Photoshop software (Adobe Systems, San Jose, CA, USA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Data are presented as mean fluorescence intensities.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>[<sup>3</sup>H]IAA transport</title><p id="Par31">Shoot-to-root auxin transport in intact plants was assayed as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. Polar transport of [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA was assayed using eight replicate root samples. The [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA solution contained 0.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA (20 Ci mmol-1) in 2% DMSO, 25&#x02009;mM MES (pH 5.2), and 0.25% agar.</p><p id="Par32">Shoot-to-root auxin transport in intact plants was monitored as follows. [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA solution (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;L) was applied to the cut surface after removal of rice shoots 2&#x02009;cm above the root-shoot junction. The root tips were incubated in 4&#x02009;mL of scintillation solution for 18&#x02009;h (overnight) in the dark, and then sampled and weighed. [<sup>3</sup>H]IAA radioactivity was detected using a multipurpose scintillation counter (LS6500; Beckman-Coulter, Fullerton, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>qRT-PCR</title><p id="Par33">Total RNA was isolated from the root tips (0&#x02013;0.5&#x02009;cm) of rice seedlings. RNA extraction, reverse transcription, and qRT-PCR were performed as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Primer sets for the <italic>OsPIN</italic> genes are listed in Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par34">Data were pooled for calculation of the means and standard errors (SE) and subjected to one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by a least significant difference (LSD) test at P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 to determine the significance of differences between treatments. All statistical evaluations were conducted using SPSS software (ver. 11.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec21"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_29784_MOESM1_ESM.doc"><caption><p>Supplementary Dataset 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Huwei Sun and Jinyuan Tao contributed equally.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-29784-x.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was funded by the National Nature Science Foundation of China (grant no. 31672225, 31471936, 31601821 and 31401937). The Province Nature Science Foundation of Jiangsu (grant no. 20140694). Innovative Research Team Development Plan of the Ministry of Education of China (No. IRT1256), the 111 Project (No. 12009), the Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions Project, China Scholarship Council (CSC). The <italic>d10</italic> and <italic>d3</italic> mutants were provided by Shinjiro Yamaguchi of RIKEN Plant Science Center, Japan. The English in this document has been checked by at least two professional editors, both native speakers of English. For a certificate, please see: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.textcheck.com/certificate/Ihwjlk">http://www.textcheck.com/certificate/Ihwjlk</ext-link>.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Y.L.Z., H.W.S. and J.Y.T. designed the experiments and wrote the manuscript. H.W.S. and J.Y.T., Y.B. and M.M.H. conducted the measurements, data analysis. J.J.L., X.N.C., X.H.Z. and L.L. assisted with the experiment. X.N.X., K.Y., Q.Z.Z. and G.H.X. assisted with the manuscript. These authors reviewed the manuscript before the submission.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitousek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen in agriculture: balancing the cost of an essential resource</article-title><source>Annu Rev Environ Resour.</source><year>2009</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.environ.032108.105046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex regulation of plant phosphate transporters and the gap between molecular mechanisms and practical application: What is missing?</article-title><source>Mol Plant.</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2015.12.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26714050?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26714050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Bucio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz-Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera-Estrella</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of nutrient availability in regulating root architecture</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(03)00035-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12753979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of maize root characteristics in response to low nitrogen stress</article-title><source>Plant Soil.</source><year>2005</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-005-5876-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Giehl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wir&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasticity of the Arabidopsis root system under nutrient deficiencies</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.218453</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23852440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23852440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribrioux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphate availability regulates root system architecture in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.126.2.875</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11402214?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linkohr</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrate and phosphate availability and distribution have different effects on root system architecture of Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2002</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2002.01251.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12148533?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12148533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nacry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Doumas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossignol</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of phosphate availability on the root system architecture: large-scale analysis of the natural variation between Arabidopsis accessions</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>2003</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1839</fpage><lpage>1850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3040.2003.01100.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Torres</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phosphate availability alters lateral root development in Arabidopsis by modulating auxin sensitivity via a mechanism involving the TIR1 auxin receptor</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>3258</fpage><lpage>3272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.108.058719</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19106375?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19106375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physiological and transcriptome analysis of iron and phosphorus interaction in rice seedlings</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>262</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.141051</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19605549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19605549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Iron availability affects phosphate deficiency-mediated responses, and evidence of cross-talk with auxin and Zinc in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant cell Physiol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>56</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>1123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcv035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25759329?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25759329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones are involved in phosphate and nitrate deficiency-induced root development and auxin transport in rice</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2014</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>6735</fpage><lpage>6746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eru029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24596173?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24596173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of maize root growth by high nitrate supply is correlated to reduced IAA levels in roots</article-title><source>J Plant Physiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>942</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2007.02.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17928098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17928098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulating the root elongation by phosphate/nitrogen starvation in an OsGLU3 dependant way in rice</article-title><source>Plant Signal Behav.</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1144</fpage><lpage>1145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.21334</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22899054?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22899054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casimiro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Auxin transport promotes Arabidopsis lateral root initiation</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.13.4.843</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11283340?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benkova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Local, efflux dependent auxin gradients as a common module for plant organ formation</article-title><source>Cell.</source><year>2003</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00924-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14651850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14651850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casimiro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dissecting Arabidopsis lateral root development</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2003</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(03)00051-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12711228?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12711228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and cellular aspects of auxin-transport-mediated development</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2007</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2007.03.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17369077?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petr&#x000e1;sek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Auxin transport routes in plant development</article-title><source>Development.</source><year>2009</year><volume>136</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>2675</fpage><lpage>2688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.030353</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19633168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19633168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peret</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AUX/LAX genes encode a family of auxin influx transporters that perform distinct functions during Arabidopsis development</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2874</fpage><lpage>2885</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.097766</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22773749?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22773749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Auxin transport-shaping the plant</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369526602000031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12495745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12495745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A PIN1 family gene, OsPIN1, involved in auxin-dependent adventitious root emergence and tillering in rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1674</fpage><lpage>1681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pci183</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16085936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16085936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Over-expression of OsPIN2 leads to increased tiller numbers, angle and shorter plant height through suppression of OsLAZY1</article-title><source>Plant Biotech J.</source><year>2012</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-7652.2011.00637.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The putative auxin efflux carrier OsPIN3t is involved in the drought stress response and drought tolerance</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2012</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2012.05121.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22882529?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22882529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OsPIN5b modulates rice (Oryza sativa) plant architecture and yield by changing auxin homeostasis, transport and distribution</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2015</year><volume>83</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12939</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26213119?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26213119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagnussat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanteri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamattina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide and cyclic GMP are messengers in the indole acetic acid-induced adventitious rooting process</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.022228</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12857806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12857806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Correa-Aragunde</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamattina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide plays a central role in determining lateral root development in tomato</article-title><source>Planta.</source><year>2004</year><volume>218</volume><fpage>900</fpage><lpage>905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-003-1172-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14716561?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14716561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lombardo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Polacco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamattina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide functions as a positive regulator of root hair development</article-title><source>Plant Signal Behav.</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.1.1.2398</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19521473?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19521473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide is involved in nitrate-induced inhibition of root elongation in Zea mays</article-title><source>Ann Bot.</source><year>2007</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcm142</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17709366?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17709366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Marcos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Muday</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide causes root apical meristem defects and growth inhibition while reducing PIN-FORMED 1 (PIN1)-dependent acropetal auxin transport</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>18506</fpage><lpage>185011</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1108644108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22021439?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22021439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapulnik</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones interact with ethylene and auxin in regulating root-hair elongation in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2011</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>2915</fpage><lpage>2924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq464</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21307387?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21307387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruyter-Spira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physiological effects of the synthetic strigolactone analog GR24 on root system architecture in Arabidopsis: another belowground role for strigolactones?</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.166645</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21119044?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21119044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koltai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones are regulators of root development</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2011.03678.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21638793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21638793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arite</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kameoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyozuka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactone positively controls crown root elongation in rice</article-title><source>J Plant Growth Regul.</source><year>2012</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00344-011-9228-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayzlish-Gati</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones are involved in root response to low phosphate conditions in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>1329</fpage><lpage>1341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.202358</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22968830?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22968830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones suppress adventitious rooting in Arabidopsis and Pea</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>1976</fpage><lpage>1987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.187104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22323776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22323776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PIF3 is involved in the primary root growth inhibition of Arabidopsis induced by nitric oxide in the light</article-title><source>Mol Plant.</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/sst142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NO homeostasis is a key regulator of early nitrate perception and root elongation in maize</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2014</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert358</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24220653?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24220653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waldie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones and the control of plant development: lessons from shoot branching</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12488</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24612082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24612082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Cuyper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>From lateral density to nodule number, the strigolactone analogue GR24 shapes the root architecture of medicago truncatula</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2015</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eru404</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25371499?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25371499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide generated by nitrate reductase increases nitrogen uptake capacity by modulating lateral root formation and inorganic nitrogen uptake rate in rice</article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2015</year><volume>66</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2449</fpage><lpage>2459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erv030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25784715?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25784715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A strigolactones signal is required for adventitious root formation in rice</article-title><source>Ann Bot.</source><year>2015</year><volume>115</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1155</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcv052</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25888593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25888593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones are required for nitric oxide to induce root elongation in response to nitrogen and phosphate deficiencies in rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>2016</year><volume>39</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1473</fpage><lpage>1484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.12709</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27194103?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27194103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of PIN genes in rice (Oryza sativa L.): tissue specificity and regulation by hormones</article-title><source>Mol Plant.</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssp023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19825657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19825657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Responses of root architecture development to low phosphorus availability: a review</article-title><source>Ann Bot.</source><year>2013</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcs285</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23267006?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23267006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ticconi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Delatorre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis pdr2 reveals a phosphate-sensitive checkpoint in root development</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2004</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02005.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14996215?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14996215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variations in the composition of gelling agents affect morphophysiological and molecular responses to deficiencies of phosphate and other nutrients</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.136184</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19386810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19386810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling Network in Sensing Phosphate Availability in Plants</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042110-103849</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21370979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21370979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Komaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Requirement of the auxin polar transport system in early stages of Arabidopsis floral bud formation</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>1991</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.3.7.677</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12324609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12324609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carraro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Forestan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Canova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Traas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Varotto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ZmPIN1a &#x00026; ZmPIN1b encode two novel putative candidates for polar auxin transport and plant architecture determination of maize</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.080119</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16844839?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16844839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Palme</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polar auxin transport-old questions and new concepts?</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1015248926412</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12036254?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12036254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactone can promote or inhibit shoot branching by triggering rapid depletion of the auxin efflux protein PIN1 from the plasma membrane</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e1001474</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001474</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23382651?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23382651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Auxin distribution is differentially affected by nitrate in roots of two rice cultivars differing in responsiveness to nitrogen nutrients</article-title><source>Ann of Bot.</source><year>2013</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>1383</fpage><lpage>1393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mct212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24095838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> nitric oxide synthase1 is targeted to mitochondria and protects against oxidative damage and dark-induced senescence</article-title><source>Plant Cell.</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>3436</fpage><lpage>3450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.037770</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16272429?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272429</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>