<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6318952</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1600</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-018-1600-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Overexpression of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> and <italic>SrKAH</italic> enhances steviol glycosides content in transgenic Stevia plants</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Junshi</given-names></name><address><email>junshi@u.nus.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><address><email>zhuangyan1986@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Hui-Zhu</given-names></name><address><email>maohz@tll.org.sg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9408-4273</contrib-id><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>In-Cheol</given-names></name><address><email>jangi@tll.org.sg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2180 6431</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4280.e</institution-id><institution>Temasek Life Sciences Laboratory, 1 Research Link, </institution><institution>National University of Singapore, </institution></institution-wrap>Singapore, 117604 Singapore </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2180 6431</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4280.e</institution-id><institution>Department of Biological Sciences, </institution><institution>National University of Singapore, </institution></institution-wrap>Singapore, 117558 Singapore </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>1</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1"><italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> produces sweet-tasting steviol glycosides (SGs) in its leaves which can be used as natural sweeteners. Metabolic engineering of Stevia would offer an alternative approach to conventional breeding for enhanced production of SGs. However, an effective protocol for Stevia transformation is lacking.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">Here, we present an efficient and reproducible method for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of Stevia. In our attempts to produce transgenic Stevia plants, we found that prolonged dark incubation is critical for increasing shoot regeneration. Etiolated shoots regenerated in the dark also facilitated subsequent visual selection of transformants by green fluorescent protein during Stevia transformation. Using this newly established transformation method, we overexpressed the Stevia <italic>1-deoxy-d-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase 1</italic> (<italic>SrDXS1</italic>) and <italic>kaurenoic acid hydroxylase</italic> (<italic>SrKAH</italic>), both of which are required for SGs biosynthesis. Compared to control plants, the total SGs content in <italic>SrDXS1-</italic> and <italic>SrKAH-</italic>overexpressing transgenic lines were enhanced by up to 42&#x02013;54% and 67&#x02013;88%, respectively, showing a positive correlation with the expression levels of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> and <italic>SrKAH</italic>. Furthermore, their overexpression did not stunt the growth and development of the transgenic Stevia plants.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">This study represents a successful case of genetic manipulation of SGs biosynthetic pathway in Stevia and also demonstrates the potential of metabolic engineering towards producing Stevia with improved SGs yield.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-018-1600-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>1-deoxy-d-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase 1</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Kaurenoic acid hydroxylase</italic></kwd><kwd>Metabolic engineering</kwd><kwd>Stevia transformation</kwd><kwd>Steviol glycosides</kwd><kwd>Transgenic Stevia</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Temasek Life Sciences Laboratory</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par35"><italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> is a perennial shrub that belongs to the Asteraceae family. It produces steviol glycosides (SGs) that range from 150 to 300 times as sweet as sucrose, making it unique among plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. SGs are mainly accumulated in the leaves of Stevia, accounting for around 4&#x02013;20% of leaf dry weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In Paraguay where Stevia is native to, people have long been using it to sweeten their teas and medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In recent times, the value of Stevia leaf extracts or specific SG, like Rebaudioside A (Reb A), as a zero calorie natural sweetener has also gained recognition beyond its native country, leading to the introduction of Stevia as a commercial crop in many other countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p><p id="Par36">SGs are a group of diterpenoids with varying levels of sweetness depending on the different number and types of sugar moieties (glucose, rhamnose, or xylose) substituted on its aglycone, steviol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Steviol is synthesized through the methylerythritol phosphate (MEP) pathway in the chloroplast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The first step in the MEP pathway involves the condensation of pyruvate and d-glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate into 1-deoxy-d-xylulose-5-phosphate (DXP) by DXP synthase (DXS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. After six more steps of conversion, the final enzyme 4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl pyrophosphate reductase converts (<italic>E</italic>)-4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl pyrophosphate into isopentenyl pyrophosphate (IPP) and dimethylallyl pyrophosphate (DMAPP), which are the basic five-carbon precursors for the formation of all terpenoids. For the production of SGs and other diterpenoids, two intermediates, IPP and DMAPP, undergo consecutive condensation to form C<sub>20</sub> geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate (GGPP). GGPP is then further cyclized to (&#x02212;)-kaurene and subsequently oxidized to kaurenoic acid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. All steps leading to the formation of kaurenoic acid are also common to gibberellic acid (GA) biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. However, the hydroxylation of kaurenoic acid at C-13 position by kaurenoic acid hydroxylase (KAH) diverts it towards SG biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Finally, UDP-glycosyltransferases (UGTs) add sugar moieties at the C-13 or C-19 position of steviol to produce a variety of SGs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par37">Many Stevia genes uncovered from the next-generation sequencing are now publicly available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, a reliable Stevia transformation technology remains to be developed for the functional genomics of Stevia and the generation of new Stevia with improved traits such as greater sweetness and resistance towards pests and diseases. Although <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of Stevia using &#x003b2;-glucuronidase (GUS) reporter gene was introduced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], no further transgenic Stevia has been reported so far, which may result from the absence of a reliable transformation method. Tobacco plants have been routinely transformed using <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> and its protocol could be conveniently adapted to plants of Solanaceae family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. However, the transformation of other important crops such as soybean and corn required further optimization of their specific regeneration strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. For Stevia, although there are a few protocols describing shoot regeneration from leaf explants, there has been a lack of consensus on the conditions used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Therefore, the development of a new and efficient method for regeneration and genetic transformation of Stevia would be required for a broad range of biotechnological applications as well as functional genomic studies of Stevia.</p><p id="Par38">Here we describe an efficient and reliable method for the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of Stevia and demonstrate that using this method, we could obtain transgenic Stevia plants expressing the green fluorescent protein (GFP) from leaf explants. As a further demonstration of the efficacy of our transformation method, we transformed <italic>SrDXS1</italic> and <italic>SrKAH</italic> into Stevia. By <italic>SrDXS1</italic> overexpression, we successfully increased the total SGs content in the transgenic lines compared to control by up to 54%. Moreover, <italic>SrKAH</italic> overexpression in Stevia resulted in an even higher increase in total SGs content of up to 88%. Despite the increase in SGs content, the normal growth and development of Stevia were not compromised for both <italic>SrDXS1</italic>- and <italic>SrKAH</italic>-overexpression lines.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Callus induction and shoot regeneration from Stevia leaf explants</title><p id="Par39">Plant transformation involves a few major steps namely, co-cultivation, callus induction, shoot regeneration and root regeneration, but all these steps require optimization to suit individual plants. To establish a standard transformation method for Stevia, we investigated the effects of different hormone combinations on callus induction and shoot regeneration by modifying existing procedures for tobacco transformation (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. We chose the second and third leaves of in vitro cultured Stevia plants as the explant source (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Cytokinin and auxin combinations tested for callus induction and shoot regeneration from Stevia leaf explants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Condition</th><th>CCM (mg/L)</th><th>CIM (mg/L)</th><th>SIM (mg/L)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>A</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA 2</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA 2</td></tr><tr><td>B</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA 0.5</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA 0.5</td></tr><tr><td>C</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 2</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 2</td></tr><tr><td>D</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 0.5</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 0.5</td></tr><tr><td>E</td><td>2,4-D 0.25</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 0.5</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 0.5</td></tr><tr><td>F</td><td>2,4-D 0.25</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 0.5</td><td>BA 2&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 0.25</td></tr><tr><td>F-light</td><td>2,4-D 0.25</td><td>BA 1&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 0.5 <sup>a</sup></td><td>BA 2&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA 0.25<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>CCM</italic> co-cultivation media, <italic>CIM</italic> callus induction media, <italic>SIM</italic> shoot induction media, <italic>BA</italic> 6-benzylaminopurine, <italic>NAA</italic> 1-naphthaleneacetic acid, <italic>IAA</italic> 3-indoleacetic acid; 2,4-D, 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid</p><p><sup>a</sup> Explants were incubated under light with 16&#x02009;h&#x02009;L/ 8&#x02009;h D photoperiod</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of Stevia using Condition F. <bold>a</bold> The red arrows indicate the second and third leaves that were used as the explant source. <bold>b</bold> Leaf explants on CCM. <bold>c</bold> Induced callus on CIM. <bold>d</bold> Transformed callus showing GFP fluorescence under a fluorescence stereomicroscope. <bold>e</bold> Shoots regenerated from calli on SIM. <bold>f</bold> Shoot regenerated from transformed calli showing GFP fluorescence under a fluorescence stereomicroscope. <bold>g</bold> Regenerated shoots on RM. <bold>h</bold> Rooting of regenerated shoots on RM. Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;cm for (<bold>a</bold>-<bold>c</bold>, <bold>e</bold>, <bold>g</bold> and <bold>h</bold>); 1&#x02009;mm for (<bold>d)</bold> and (<bold>f</bold>). CCM, co-cultivation media; CIM, callus induction media; SIM, shoot induction media; RM, rooting media</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">Plant growth regulators most frequently supplemented for shoot regeneration from Stevia leaf explants include 6-benzylaminopurine (BA) as the cytokinin and 1-naphthaleneacetic acid (NAA), or 3-indoleacetic acid (IAA) as the auxin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. When explants were placed on BA with either NAA or IAA under long day photoperiod (LD, 16&#x02009;h Light/ 8&#x02009;h Dark), calli were induced on both media but with a different appearance (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1a, b). Shoot regeneration could also be observed from the calli on the BA + IAA media after 6 weeks but its frequency would be insufficient for successful transformation (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1b). It has been shown that prolonged dark incubation promotes somatic embryogenesis from callus cultures of Stevia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Interestingly, we found drastic improvements in shoot regeneration from calli induced in the dark (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1c). Therefore, we subsequently incubated the explants under darkness during callus induction and shoot regeneration.</p><p id="Par41">To compare the efficiency of BA with IAA or NAA on callus induction and shoot regeneration, four combinations (Conditions A-D in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) with different concentrations of NAA or IAA were designed. The difference in callus induction rates on four different callus induction media (CIM; Conditions A-D in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) was not observed to be statistically significant (<italic>P-</italic>value: 0.099; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). However, calli on CIM containing NAA (Conditions A and B) appeared friable while those on media containing IAA appeared compact (Conditions C and D; Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Subsequently, calli maintained on NAA (Conditions A and B) had lower shoot regeneration rates than those on IAA (Conditions C and D; Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Furthermore, we found that a higher BA to IAA ratio (Condition D) was more efficient for promoting shoot regeneration (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Callus induction and shoot regeneration rates under the different cytokinin and auxin combinations listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Condition</th><th>Explants with callus formation (%)</th><th>Callus condition</th><th>Explants with regeneration (%)</th><th>Shoot Condition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>A</td><td>87.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.5</td><td>Friable</td><td>5.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.4</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>B</td><td>99.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.8</td><td>Friable</td><td>22.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.6</td><td>+ +</td></tr><tr><td>C</td><td>89.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.1</td><td>Compact</td><td>29.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.9</td><td>+ + + + +</td></tr><tr><td>D</td><td>98.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.8</td><td>Compact</td><td>65.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.6</td><td>+ + + +</td></tr><tr><td>E</td><td>95.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.8</td><td>Compact</td><td>53.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.1</td><td>+ + + + +</td></tr><tr><td>F</td><td>96.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.3</td><td>Compact</td><td>53.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.8</td><td>+ + + + +</td></tr><tr><td>F-light</td><td>95.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.7</td><td>Compact</td><td>29.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.7</td><td>+ + + +</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of technical triplicates with <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;40</p><p>The shoot condition was scored based on their appearance (+: Most shoots appear watery, browning or deformed, + + + + +: Most shoots appear strong and healthy)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par42">2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid (2,4-D) is commonly used for the dedifferentiation of somatic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Therefore, to further enhance regeneration rates under Condition D, we designed Condition E with an additional 3 d incubation on 0.25&#x02009;mg/L 2,4-D (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), which can also be used as the co-cultivation media (CCM) for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation. Although regeneration rates for Conditions E were similar to Condition D, the regenerated shoots were healthier (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S2a, b).</p><p id="Par43">In general, a higher cytokinin to auxin ratio promotes shoot formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. We further optimized Condition E by doubling the cytokinin concentration of the shoot induction media (SIM) to 2&#x02009;mg/L and reducing the auxin concentration from 0.5&#x02009;mg/L to 0.25&#x02009;mg/L to form Condition F (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Under Condition F, rates for callus formation and shoot regeneration as well as the shoot condition were comparable to those under Condition E (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), but the number of regenerated shoots per callus clump seemed to be higher (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S2c). Next, we tested Condition F simultaneously under LD condition after the explants were transferred onto CIM (Condition F-light; Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) to verify the enhancement of shoot regeneration in the dark. Certainly, the percentage of explants with regenerated shoots was 1.8 times higher under Condition F (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), confirming that dark incubation greatly promotes shoot regeneration. Therefore, we subsequently applied Condition F for Stevia transformation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Stevia transformation</title><p id="Par44">To investigate the feasibility of adapting condition F for transformation, we co-cultivated Stevia leaf explants on the CCM media containing acetosyringone with <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> harboring the pK7WG2D vector [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], which contains a <italic>neomycin phosphotransferase</italic> (<italic>nptII</italic>) gene and an enhanced GFP gene fused to an endoplasmic reticulum targeting signal (<italic>EgfpER</italic>) to allow concurrent selection (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> outlines the overall procedures for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of Stevia. The appearance of the calli and regenerated shoots on media are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c and e, respectively. Incubation in the dark resulted in their etiolated appearance. GFP signals from transgenic calli or regenerated shoots were monitored and selected under a fluorescence stereomicroscope (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d, f). With reduced autofluorescence from chlorophyll, GFP signals could easily be visualized. For rooting, transgenic shoots were transferred onto rooting media (RM) and exposed to light for approximately 1 month (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>g, h). Using this approach, we were able to efficiently produce transgenic Stevia plants expressing GFP.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Transformation of Stevia with SrDXS1 and SrKAH</title><p id="Par45">DXS has been reported to play a rate-limiting role in the MEP pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], while Stevia KAH acts on kaurenoic acid as the committed step to SGs biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Thus, we hypothesized that their overexpression would lead to an increase in the flux towards SGs production.</p><p id="Par46">Four Stevia <italic>DXS</italic> homologs (<italic>SrDXS1&#x02013;4</italic>) were identified from the RNA-seq data of Stevia leaves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. To investigate if all four SrDXSs were functionally active, we carried out a complementation assay using a <italic>dxs</italic>-deficient <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a shows that <italic>dxs</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup>
<italic>E. coli</italic> transformed with all <italic>SrDXSs</italic> except <italic>SrDXS3</italic> were able to grow on selection media, similar to the Arabidopsis <italic>DXS1</italic> (<italic>AtDXS1</italic>) positive control, indicating their functionality. Among the 4 <italic>SrDXS</italic> homologs, only <italic>SrDXS1</italic> was suggested to be involved in SG biosynthesis based on the correlation between its expression pattern and the site of SGs biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Transient expression of the yellow fluorescent protein (YFP)-fused SrDXS1 in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> leaves showed that it localizes to the chloroplast (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Therefore, we selected <italic>SrDXS1</italic> for Stevia transformation.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Characterization of <italic>SrDXSs</italic> and <italic>SrKAH</italic>. <bold>a</bold> Complementation assay of Stevia DXSs using <italic>E. coli</italic> DXS deficient mutant (<italic>dxs</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup>). Transformed cells were grown on LB plates containing either with 0.5&#x02009;mM mevalonate (+ MVA) or without mevalonate (&#x02212; MVA). <italic>E. coli dxs</italic><sup><italic>&#x02212;</italic></sup> with pDEST17 (empty vector) and <italic>AtDXS1</italic> served as negative and positive controls, respectively. <bold>b</bold> Subcellular localization of SrDXS1. Auto, chlorophyll autofluorescence; Light, light microscope image; Merged, merged image between Auto and YFP channels. Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. <bold>c</bold> Subcellular localization of SrKAH. Co-expression of SrKAH-YFP with CFP-HDEL in. Light, light microscope image; Merged, merged image between CFP and YFP channels. Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;20&#x02009;&#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par47">Unlike SrDXS1, the activity of SrKAH in converting kaurenoic acid to steviol has previously been demonstrated in <italic>E. coli</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Additionally, its overexpression in Arabidopsis had led to the production of steviol that was otherwise not detected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Being a cytochrome P450 enzyme, SrKAH is expected to be localized to the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) similar to that of kaurene oxidase which acts upstream of it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. We confirmed this by transiently co-expressing YFP-fused SrKAH and cyan fluorescent protein (CFP)-fused HDEL, an ER marker, in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> leaves. Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c shows the co-localization of SrKAH-YFP with CFP-HDEL, demonstrating that SrKAH indeed localizes to the ER.</p><p id="Par48">Next, we cloned the full-length open reading frame (ORFs) of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> and <italic>SrKAH</italic> into pK7WG2D under the control of the cauliflower mosaic virus (CaMV 35S) promoter for Stevia transformation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Using our transformation protocol, we produced 13 and 9 lines of transgenic Stevia plants overexpressing <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (SrDXS1-OE) and <italic>SrKAH</italic> (SrKAH-OE), respectively. Because of the GFP visual marker, we were able to efficiently select the transgenic Stevia plants emitting GFP signals from leaf and root tissues of SrDXS1-OE and SrKAH-OE lines under a fluorescence stereomicroscope and&#x000a0;a confocal laser scanning microscope (CLSM; Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b, c). GFP expressions in leaves of each transgenic Stevia lines were also confirmed by immunoblot analysis (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S3).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Identification of transgenic Stevia plants overexpressing <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (SrDXS1-OE) or <italic>SrKAH</italic> (SrKAH-OE). <bold>a</bold> Schematic maps of T-DNA region of pK7WG2D-SrDXS1 and pK7WG2D-SrKAH used for Stevia transformation. LB, left border; <italic>nptII</italic>, <italic>neomycin phosphotransferase</italic> marker gene under the terminator and promoter of nopaline synthase gene; <italic>T35S</italic> and P35S, terminator and promoter of the cauliflower mosaic virus gene respectively; <italic>attB2</italic> and <italic>attB1</italic>, gene recombination sites; <italic>SrDXS1</italic>, Stevia <italic>1-deoxy-d-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase 1</italic>; <italic>SrKAH</italic>, Stevia <italic>kaurenoic acid hydroxylase</italic> gene; <italic>EgfpER,</italic> enhanced green-fluorescent protein gene fused to endoplasmic reticulum targeting signal; ProlD, rol root loci D promoter; <italic>Xba</italic>I and <italic>Hin</italic>dIII, sites digested by <italic>Xba</italic>I and <italic>Hin</italic>dIII, respectively, for Southern blot analysis; Probe, probe used for Southern blot analysis. <bold>b</bold> Images of GFP signals from leaves and roots of representative SrDXS1-OE #6 or SrKAH-OE #4 under a fluorescence stereomicroscope. WT, wild-type. Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;mm. <bold>c</bold> Confocal images of the leaf underside and roots of WT, representative SrDXS1-OE #6 or SrKAH-OE #4. Auto, chlorophyll autofluorescence; GFP, GFP channel image; Light, light microscope image; Merged, merged image between Auto and GFP channels. Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Analysis of transgenic Stevia lines</title><p id="Par49">To verify if exogenous <italic>SrDXS1</italic> or <italic>SrKAH</italic> was integrated into the Stevia genome<italic>,</italic> genomic PCR analysis of the transgene from each transgenic line was performed. Genomic DNA amplification corresponding to the expected size of each transgene was observed for all the SrDXS1-OE or SrKAH-OE lines and the respective positive control lanes, but not for wild-type (WT; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a, b).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Genomic and expression analysis of transgenic Stevia plants overexpressing <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (SrDXS1-OE) or <italic>SrKAH</italic> (SrKAH-OE). <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold>
<italic>SrDXS1</italic> (<bold>a</bold>) or <italic>SrKAH</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) amplified from the gDNA of each transgenic Stevia lines. M1, 2-Log DNA ladder. PC, positive control amplified from the respective vector constructs. <bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold> Southern blot analysis of SrDXS1-OE (<bold>c</bold>) or SrKAH-OE lines (<bold>d</bold>). WT, wild-type. M2, DIG-labelled DNA molecular weight marker II. <bold>e</bold> and <bold>f</bold> Relative fold change in <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (<bold>e</bold>) and <italic>SrKAH</italic> (<bold>f</bold>) transcript levels among the transgenic Stevia lines overexpressing <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (SrDXS1-OE) and <italic>SrKAH</italic> (SrKAH-OE), respectively. Expression levels of both genes were normalized to that of <italic>actin</italic> and compared to that of wild-type (WT). The values are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test was used for the analysis of statistical significance (*: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par50">After confirming the existence of full-length ORFs of each transgene in transgenic Stevia plants, we performed digoxygenin (DIG)-based Southern blot analysis to determine the number of transgene integration sites for each line with <italic>nptII</italic>-specific probe (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c and d show that all SrDXS1-OE and SrKAH-OE lines contained one or more transgene (<italic>nptII</italic>) integration site, demonstrating stable transgene integration into the Stevia genome. No bands were detected in the WT lanes.</p><p id="Par51">Then, we analyzed the expression levels of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> and <italic>SrKAH</italic> in SrDXS1-OE and SrKAH-OE lines, respectively. Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>e shows up to 13-fold increase in the expression levels of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> among the transgenic lines compared to control. However, the expression levels of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> in SrDXS1-OE lines did not correlate with the number of transgene integration sites. Among the top 5 SrDXS1-OE lines, four of them had a single transgene integration site (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c, e). For further analysis, we chose three lines, SrDXS1-OE #1, #3 and #5, each having one transgene integration site but different levels of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> overexpression.</p><p id="Par52">Among SrKAH-OE lines that contained single transgene integration site, lines #1, #4 and #7 showed around 40&#x02013;60 fold higher expression of <italic>SrKAH</italic> compared to that of WT while line #2 did not show <italic>SrKAH</italic> overexpression, and line #9 only had a small increase of around 4-fold (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>f). For further analysis of the effects of <italic>SrKAH</italic> overexpression, we selected lines #1, #4, and #9 with varying expression levels, and included line #2 as an internal control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Steviol glycosides (SGs) content increased in transgenic Stevia plants</title><p id="Par53">It is known that Stevia is a self-incompatible plant and its self-pollination results in sterile seed set [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Under our environmental conditions, we were also unsuccessful in harvesting viable transgenic T1 seeds. Therefore, we propagated the in vitro transgenic lines by cutting method and monitored the GFP signals emitted. Transgenic Stevia plants showing GFP expression in whole tissues were transferred into the soil for hardening and grown in the greenhouse for 3 weeks before analysis. Using this method, we were able to maintain each transgenic line for further analysis and obtain reproducible results.</p><p id="Par54">To investigate the effect of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> or <italic>SrKAH</italic> overexpression on SGs production, we analyzed the leaf extracts of the transgenic lines. As leaf SGs content can differ according to their nodal position, leaves from the same position of each line were harvested. Each SG peak was identified by comparing their retention time with that of their authentic standards (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S4). By summing up the concentration of the top 4 most abundant SGs (stevioside, Reb A, Reb C and dulcoside A) in each of the SrDXS1-OE lines, we found an increase in SGs content in the transgenic lines as compared to the controls (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). The total SGs content was the highest in SrDXS1-OE line #3 at 5.9% (<italic>w</italic>/w dry weight, DW), followed by 5.6% (w/w DW) in line #5 and lastly 5.1% (w/w DW) in line #1 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a), in agreement with their relative <italic>SrDXS1</italic> expression levels (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>e). These total SGs content in the transgenic lines represent an increase of between 33-54% and 23&#x02013;42% compared to the 3.8% (<italic>w</italic>/w DW) and 4.1% (w/w DW) total SGs content in the vector-only control line and WT, respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). Stevioside, which is the most abundant SG in Stevia, had concentrations of between 3.7&#x02013;4.3% (w/w DW) in the overexpression lines, increasing up to 20&#x02013;47% compared to controls (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). Similar patterns of SGs increase for Reb A, Reb C and dulcoside A were found in SrDXS1-OE lines (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S5a). Furthermore, in SrDXS1-OE line #9 where <italic>SrDXS1</italic> transcript levels were comparable to controls, the stevioside and Reb A contents were also similar (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>e and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Figure S6). These results suggest that the overexpression of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> in Stevia leads to a proportional increase in each SG.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Analysis of steviol glycosides (SGs) content in transgenic Stevia plants. <bold>a-f</bold> Total SGs (<bold>a</bold> and <bold>d</bold>), stevioside (<bold>b</bold> and <bold>e</bold>) and Reb A (<bold>c</bold> and <bold>f</bold>) content in the transgenic Stevia lines overexpressing either <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (SrDXS1-OE) or <italic>SrKAH</italic> (SrKAH-OE). Data are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE. Statistical analysis was carried out using Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test relative to wild-type (WT) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5, *: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par55">In the SrKAH-OE lines, the total amount of SGs was able to reach up to 88% higher than that of WT (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). Corresponding to their expression levels, SrKAH-OE lines #1 and #4 accumulated the highest total amount of SGs at 4.5% (w/w DW) and 6% (w/w DW), respectively (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>f and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). On the other hand, SrKAH-OE #9 with only a four-fold increase in <italic>SrKAH</italic> transcript had total SGs content of 3.9% (w/w DW), indicating a moderate increase of 8&#x02013;22% from the controls (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>f and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). SrKAH-OE line #2, an internal control line that shows similar expression levels of <italic>SrKAH</italic> with WT, did not contain higher total SGs content, confirming that elevated <italic>SrKAH</italic> transcript levels resulted in higher SGs in transgenic Stevia plants (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). Taking a closer inspection at the individual SGs, stevioside was present in concentrations of up to 4% (w/w DW) among the overexpression lines, which was an increase of 57&#x02013;71% compared to controls (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e). For Reb A, a 133&#x02013;200% increase compared to controls was observed in SrKAH-OE #4 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>f). Apart from stevioside and Reb A, statistically significant increases of Reb C and dulcoside A content were also found in the two <italic>SrKAH</italic> high expressers, SrKAH-OE lines #1 and #4, with patterns of increase similar to that of the total SGs content (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S5b).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Phenotype of transgenic Stevia plants</title><p id="Par56">To determine if the overexpression of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> and <italic>SrKAH</italic> would result in other changes in the Stevia plant, we examined their phenotype. SrDXS1-OE lines did not display any morphological differences from controls. The height of the plants, size of the leaves and the internode length among the 2 month-old Stevia plants were comparable (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a, c, e). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b, d and f show that SrKAH-OE lines also did not exhibit any obvious differences in growth. The leaf size and color and internode length were indistinguishable from the controls.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Phenotypic analysis of transgenic Stevia plants. <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold> Representative transgenic Stevia plants overexpressing <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (SrDXS1-OE) (<bold>a</bold>) or <italic>SrKAH</italic> (SrKAH-OE) (<bold>b</bold>) one week after hardening in the soil. <bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold> Representative leaf harvested from third node position of SrDXS1-OE lines (<bold>c</bold>) or SrKAH-OE lines (<bold>d</bold>) one month after being transferred to the soil. <bold>e</bold> and <bold>f</bold> Average length of the third and fourth internodes in the SrDXS1-OE (<bold>e</bold>) or SrKAH-OE (<bold>f</bold>) lines one month after being transferred to the soil. Wild-type (WT) and vector-only line were included as a control. Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;cm. <bold>g-j</bold> Relative chlorophylls content and total carotenoids content in the transgenic Stevia plants overexpressing <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (SrDXS1-OE) (<bold>g</bold> and <bold>i</bold>) or <italic>SrKAH</italic> (SrKAH-OE) compared to wild-type (WT) (<bold>h</bold> and <bold>j</bold>). All measurements are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5) and statistical analysis was carried out using Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test relative to wild-type (WT) for SrKAH-OE lines (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5, *: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par57">Apart from morphology, we also determined the relative concentration of chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>, chlorophyll <italic>b</italic> and total carotenoids because these compounds are also derived from the MEP pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Figure <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>g-j shows that except for SrDXS1-OE #1, there were no significant changes in chlorophylls and carotenoids content in both SrDXS1-OE and SrKAH-OE lines when compared to WT. Furthermore, compared to Vector-only control, chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> and total carotenoid content in SrDXS1-OE #1 were also not significantly different. Additionally, we measured the concentration of a few monoterpenes that were present in the Stevia leaf tissues since monoterpenes can also be synthesized from the MEP pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Using gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis, the relative amount of linalool, &#x003b1;-pinene and &#x003b2;-pinene were determined (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Figure S7). There were no statistically significant changes to the amount of monoterpenes in the leaves of SrDXS1-OE lines compared to those of controls. Hence, our results show that both <italic>SrDXS1</italic> and <italic>SrKAH</italic> overexpression could increase SGs content in transgenic Stevia without changing the abundance of other metabolites or having any detrimental effects on their growth and development.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par58">Since the whole transcriptome of Stevia has been sequenced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], the transformation of Stevia is indispensable not only in functional genomics for elucidating crucial genes such as those involved in SGs biosynthesis and stress response, but also for metabolic engineering to fulfill commercial interests in producing SGs more efficiently. Here, we optimized conditions for shoot regeneration from Stevia leaf explants and adapted it for the Stevia transformation. Among the different regeneration conditions tested, Condition F (CCM: 0.25&#x02009;mg/L 2,4-D, CIM: 1&#x02009;mg/L BA +&#x02009;0.5&#x02009;mg/L IAA and SIM: 2&#x02009;mg/L BA +&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;mg/L IAA) with incubation in continuous darkness was the most ideal as approximately 53% of the starting explants have healthy regenerated shoots (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Even though Khan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] previously reported regeneration frequency of nearly 90%, our attempts to replicate their condition which is equivalent to the Condition A could only achieve a regeneration rate of 5% (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par59">While optimizing for shoot regeneration, we observed that a prolonged dark incubation could improve significantly the rate of shoot regeneration (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Similar findings have been reported in other plants such as rice and citrus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. It has been suggested that increased reactive oxygen species (ROS) levels during light exposure inhibit shoot regeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Thus, the low shoot regeneration rate observed in Stevia explants under light exposure might have resulted from high ROS accumulation.</p><p id="Par60">For the selection of transgenic shoots, we found that concurrent visual and antibiotic selection was most suitable for Stevia. Fifty Milligram/liter of kanamycin was insufficient to completely inhibit the regeneration of non-transgenic shoots but higher amounts of kanamycin also reduce overall regeneration rate. The use of GFP for visual selection allowed us to easily identify transgenic shoots without compromising on the regeneration rate and thus maximized transformation rate. Such concurrent antibiotic and visual selection have also been employed for efficient transformation of the rubber tree and the sweet chestnut [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p id="Par61">The stable integration of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> or <italic>SrKAH</italic> into the genome of transgenic lines was confirmed by genomic PCR and Southern blot analyses. Notably, our genomic Southern blot analysis shows the existence of transgene and its number of integration sites in transgenic Stevia genome. Among transgenic Stevia plants, 46% of the SrDXS1-OE lines and 56% of the SrKAH-OE lines had transgene integrated at a single site (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c, d).</p><p id="Par62">Generally, the overexpression of <italic>SrKAH</italic> and <italic>SrDXS1</italic> had increased total SGs content without affecting the proportion of individual SGs in the leaves. However, an exception was observed in SrKAH-OE #4 where its Reb A content was drastically increased by 133&#x02013;200% but its stevioside content was only increased by 57&#x02013;71%. As SrUGT76G1 is responsible for the conversion of stevioside to Reb A [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], we measured its transcript levels in the SrKAH-OE lines, but no significant differences were seen amongst them (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: Figure S8). Thus, we postulate that SrUGT76G1 in SrKAH-OE #4 could have been affected at the protein level, possibly by enhanced enzymatic activity or greater stability.</p><p id="Par63">For the study with next generation of transgenic Stevia lines, we had difficulty in harvesting viable seeds under our environmental condition. Even though lots of pollen grains were attached to the stigma of the flowers, transgenic and WT seeds that we collected were always empty and non-viable. Nevertheless, by in vitro cutting propagation, we were able to continually obtain clones of the transgenic lines that do not show a reduction in expression levels of the transgene or SG content over time.</p><p id="Par64">Metabolic engineering to increase desirable metabolites in plants can be done through increasing flux towards the relevant pathways by overexpressing rate-limiting enzyme genes in the pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. We found that the total SGs content was increased by up to 54% in transgenic lines overexpressing <italic>SrDXS1</italic> when compared to vector-only control. In Arabidopsis, upregulation of <italic>DXS</italic> elevated chlorophylls and carotenoids concentration together with GA and abscisic acid content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. We also expected that an increase in precursor supply from the MEP pathway in SrDXS1-OE lines might affect the biosynthesis of other downstream metabolites along with SGs. However, the overexpression of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> did not affect levels of chlorophylls, carotenoids and monoterpenes tested. This finding is not unique to Stevia as the overexpression of Arabidopsis <italic>DXS</italic> in spike lavender also led to the higher amount of essential oil but no changes in the chlorophylls and carotenoids levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The difference in response to elevated <italic>DXS</italic> levels seemed to imply that in plants producing specialized secondary metabolites, excess precursors from the MEP pathway would be diverted to their biosynthesis instead of the biosynthesis of primary metabolites such as the phytohormones and chlorophylls that could have adverse effects on the growth and development of the transgenic plants.</p><p id="Par65">Other common targets for metabolic engineering include the cytochrome P450s as they tend to catalyze rate-limiting and irreversible steps in pathways with high specificity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. By overexpressing <italic>SrKAH</italic>, we generated transgenic lines that were up to 88% more abundant in total SGs. The expression levels of <italic>SrKAH</italic> were also found to be positively correlated to the SGs contents in the SrKAH-OE lines. However, steviol but not SGs was previously detected in the leaves of Arabidopsis by heterologous expression of <italic>SrKAH</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. This was likely due to the lack of UGTs that could glycosylate steviol. In contrast, steviol remained undetectable in the leaves of the Stevia SrKAH-OE lines, possibly due to rapid glycosylation of newly synthesized steviol by downstream UGTs for sequestration into the vacuoles to avoid its potential toxicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Overexpression of <italic>SrKAH</italic> in Arabidopsis also led to dwarfism, which is characteristic of plants with reduced GA levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. This was attributed to the diversion of precursors for GA towards steviol biosynthesis. However, our transgenic Stevia plants overexpressing <italic>SrKAH</italic> did not exhibit any observable morphological differences compared to control. SrKAH is an enzyme unique to Stevia that has been evolved for SGs biosynthesis. Therefore, the allocation of precursors for GA or SGs biosynthesis is likely to be under tight control which would allow for the continual accumulation of SGs without affecting normal growth and development of Stevia in response to changes in internal or external factors. However, this mechanism of regulation remains to be investigated.</p><p id="Par66">Comparing between high expressers of SrKAH-OE and SrDXS1-OE lines, the increase in total SGs content in the former was higher than the later. This is likely due to <italic>SrKAH</italic> being situated further down in the SGs biosynthesis pathway allowing its upregulation to have a more direct effect on SGs production. Another possible explanation is that the increased precursors supply from <italic>SrDXS1</italic> upregulation might be diverted to the production of other metabolites unidentified in this study along the many steps in the pathway. There may also be other rate-limiting steps in the pathway restricting the increase in SGs production. Nevertheless, the overexpression of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> increased SGs levels without any obvious unintended effects. We postulate that SGs content could further be enhanced by the co-expression of <italic>SrKAH</italic> and <italic>SrDXS1.</italic> The elevated SrKAH activity would help divert the greater amount of precursors resulting from <italic>SrDXS1</italic> overexpression towards SGs biosynthesis more efficiently, having a push and pull effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. It is recognized that among the two most abundant SGs present in Stevia leaves, Reb A has a sweeter and more pleasant taste profile than stevioside [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Hence, it may also be desirable to target the UGTs in the future to engineer Stevia with higher Reb A to stevioside ratio.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par67">We established an effective method for Stevia transformation demonstrated by the SrDXS1-OE and SrKAH-OE lines. This will serve as an important tool for further overexpression or knockdown studies of newly identified genes from Stevia RNA-seq database. Furthermore, it will also facilitate metabolic engineering of Stevia with greatly enhanced total SGs content and more pleasant tasting SGs including the minor SGs, Reb D and Reb M.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Plant materials and growth condition</title><p id="Par68"><italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> Bertoni were propagated and maintained in vitro by cutting and transferring apicals onto fresh RM containing Murashige &#x00026; Skoog (MS) medium with 6.5&#x02009;g/L agar and 0.5&#x02009;mg/L of IAA every 3&#x02013;4&#x02009;weeks. The in vitro plants were kept in a LD (16&#x02009;h&#x02009;L/8&#x02009;h D) plant growth chamber maintained at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. After rooting, they were transferred to potting soil mixed with sand and covered for 1 week with a transparent plastic dome for hardening.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Stevia tissue culture</title><p id="Par69">The second and third leaves (cut into ~&#x02009;5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;5&#x02009;mm pieces) from sterile 2&#x02013;3&#x02009;week-old in vitro propagated plants were used as the explants source for Stevia tissue culture and transformation. Forty pieces of explants were incubated on MS media with six different combinations (Conditions A-F, Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) of plant growth regulators under continuous darkness unless otherwise specified. Explants placed on CIM for 3 weeks were assessed for calli formation rates and transferred onto SIM for another 3 weeks to evaluate the percentage of explants with regenerated shoots. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to evaluate for differences in the callus formation and regeneration rates between the Conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Functional complementation assay for <italic>SrDXSs</italic> in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> mutant</title><p id="Par70"><italic>SrDXS1</italic>, <italic>SrDXS2</italic>, <italic>SrDXS3,</italic> and <italic>SrDXS4</italic> amplified from Stevia cDNA using primers listed in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: Table S1 were cloned into the pDONR221 and followed by recombination into the pDEST17 using Gateway cloning technology (Invitrogen). The resulting pDEST17-SrDXS constructs were transformed into an <italic>E. coli dxs</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> strain defective in DXS activity. For complementation assay, the transformed cells were streaked out on Luria-Bertani (LB) agar plates with 1&#x02009;mM of mevalonate (MVA) or without MVA and incubated overnight at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. <italic>AtDXS1</italic> and pDEST17 transformed into the <italic>E. coli dxs</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> strain were used as positive and negative controls, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Subcellular localization of SrDXS1 and SrKAH</title><p id="Par71"><italic>SrDXS1</italic> and <italic>SrKAH</italic> in the pDONR221 entry clone were transferred into the destination vector pBA-DC-YFP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] using LR clonase (Invitrogen) and the resulting C-terminal YFP-tagged constructs were transformed into the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> strain GV3101. The <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> suspension was infiltrated into the leaves of 4-week-old <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> plants and incubated at 24&#x02009;&#x000b0;C under LD photoperiod for 3 days before excision and mounting on slides for observation under a CLSM (Carl Zeiss LSM 5 Exciter, Germany). Argon laser at 514&#x02009;nm and 458&#x02009;nm were used to excite YFP and CFP, respectively. The bandpass were set at 530&#x02013;600&#x02009;nm for YFP and 475&#x02013;525&#x02009;nm for CFP while the long pass was set at 650&#x02009;nm. Image processing was done on LSM Image Browser.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Vector construction for Stevia transformation</title><p id="Par72">The full-length ORFs of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (accession number: KT276229) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and <italic>SrKAH</italic> (accession number, EU722415) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] were PCR-amplified from cDNA derived from Stevia leaves using primers listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: Table S1. PCR products were cloned into pK7WG2D using Gateway technology (Invitrogen) to generate pK7WG2D-SrDXS1 and pK7WG2D-SrKAH. All clones were confirmed by sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Stevia transformation</title><p id="Par73">Vector constructs used were transformed into the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> strain AGL2. For co-cultivation, <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> at log phase was pelleted and resuspended in MS supplemented with 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;M of acetosyringone to OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.4&#x02013;0.6. The explants were incubated with the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> suspension for 30&#x02009;min with occasional gentle shaking and then placed on CCM (0.25&#x02009;mg/L 2,4-D&#x02009;+&#x02009;100&#x02009;&#x003bc;M acetosyringone) at 22&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;days in the dark. Following co-cultivation, the explants were washed twice with sterile deionized H<sub>2</sub>O and once in MS media supplemented with 300&#x02009;mg/L cefotaxime by vigorous shaking before soaking in MS media with cefotaxime for another 20&#x02009;min. The washed explants were placed on CIM (1&#x02009;mg/L BA +&#x02009;0.5&#x02009;mg/L IAA&#x02009;+&#x02009;125&#x02009;mg/L cefotaxime +&#x02009;50&#x02009;mg/L kanamycin) for the next 3&#x02013;4&#x02009;weeks at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in the dark for callus induction. The calli were screened under a fluorescence stereomicroscope Leica MZ 10F equipped with a FITC/GFP filter and illuminated by mercury metal halide lamp. Autofluorescence from chlorophyll was not filtered out. Images were captured using a Nikon DXM 1200F camera. Calli showing GFP spots were transferred to SIM (2&#x02009;mg/L BA +&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;mg/L IAA&#x02009;+&#x02009;125&#x02009;mg/L cefotaxime +&#x02009;50&#x02009;mg/L kanamycin) and subcultured every 3&#x02013;4&#x02009;weeks. Regenerated shoots from calli emitting GFP signals were transferred onto RM supplemented with 125&#x02009;mg/L of cefotaxime. Only shoots on kanamycin containing media with GFP signal present throughout the plant were selected for rooting. Transformation efficiency of this protocol was tested using <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> harboring pK7WG2D in triplicates on 200 pieces of explants. Regenerated transgenic plants with roots formed after approximately 4 weeks on RM were multiplied by cutting the terminal shoot and propagating the lateral shoots. Lines where GFP signals could be detected from leaves of all individuals would then be transferred onto soil in growing trays and covered with a transparent plastic dome for 1 week for hardening.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Verification of transgenic Stevia plants by genomic PCR and southern blot analysis</title><p id="Par74">Genomic DNA (gDNA) was extracted from approximately 600&#x02009;mg of Stevia leaves using cetyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB)-based extraction method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The final gDNA pellet was washed with ice-cold 75% ethanol and dissolved in water.</p><p id="Par75">PCR amplification was carried out from 100&#x02009;ng of gDNA extracted from each line of transgenic Stevia to check for the presence of T-DNA using forward primers specific to the CaMV 35S promoter and reverse primers specific to the 3&#x02032;-end of <italic>SrDXS1</italic> or <italic>SrKAH</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: Table S1).</p><p id="Par76">Southern blot analysis for detection of transgene integrations and number of integration sites was performed using a DIG-labelled probe specific to the full-length <italic>nptII</italic> (Roche)<italic>.</italic> The purity of the synthesized probes was checked by electrophoresis on a 1% agarose gel. gDNAs extracted from the SrDXS1-OE and SrKAH-OE lines were digested with <italic>Hin</italic>dIII and <italic>Xba</italic>I, respectively. After digestion, the fragments were resolved on a 0.8% agarose gel together with DIG-labelled DNA molecular weight marker II (Roche). The agarose gel was treated with 0.2&#x02009;M HCl followed by denaturation solution (0.5&#x02009;M NaOH, 1.5&#x02009;M NaCl) and neutralization solution (1&#x02009;M Tris-Cl pH&#x02009;7.4, 1.5&#x02009;M NaCl) and transferred to a positively charged nylon membrane (Hybond-N+, GE healthcare life sciences) in 20x SSC (3.0&#x02009;M NaCl, 0.3&#x02009;M sodium citrate, pH&#x02009;7.0). After the transfer, UV-crosslinking was carried out using Stratalinker 2400 (Stratagene, USA). Then, DIG-based Southern blot hybridization was performed according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (Roche). Chemiluminescence from the membrane was acquired with the ChemiDoc Touch Imaging System (Bio-Rad, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Expression analysis by quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR)</title><p id="Par77">Total RNA was extracted from homogenized Stevia leaves using the TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen) and then treated with deoxyribonuclease I (DNase I; Roche, USA) to avoid possible genomic DNA contamination. Total RNA concentration was measured using a Nanodrop spectrophotometer, ND-1000 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA). One &#x003bc;g of total RNA was used for cDNA synthesis with M-MLV Superscript II (Promega, USA).</p><p id="Par78">qRT-PCR was performed using SYBR <italic>Premix Ex Taq</italic> II (Takara, Japan) on the synthesized cDNA. The gene-specific primers are listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: Table S1. The expression levels were quantified on Applied Biosystems (USA) 7900HT fast real-time PCR system. Stevia <italic>actin</italic> gene was used as an internal control for normalization. Specificity of the amplified PCR products was verified by regular PCR analysis and melting curve analysis on the qRT-PCR system. Biological and technical triplicates were carried out for each experiment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Steviol glycosides content analysis by high performance liquid chromatography</title><p id="Par79">To analyze SGs content in the transgenic lines, leaves on the 6th node were harvested from plants grown in the greenhouse for 3 weeks and dried overnight in a 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C oven. Sterile water was added at 1&#x02009;mL per 10&#x02009;mg of powdered sample and extraction was carried out twice by sonication in a 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C water bath for 20&#x02009;min. The extracts were clarified by centrifugation at 3000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 15&#x02009;min and pooled. After filtering through a 0.45&#x02009;&#x003bc;m filter, 1&#x02009;mL of the sample was applied to a solid phase extraction (SPE) column C2 (Agilent, USA) and eluted in 1&#x02009;mL of methanol:acetonitrile (50,50, <italic>v</italic>/v). Eluted samples were analyzed on Shidmadzu Nexera X2 ultra-high performance liquid chromatography (UHPLC) system as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Chlorophylls and total carotenoids analysis</title><p id="Par80">To analyze the chlorophylls and total carotenoids content in the transgenic lines, 200&#x02009;mg of leaves homogenized in liquid nitrogen was extracted twice with 2&#x02009;ml of 100% methanol. Extraction was carried out at room temperature for 1&#x02009;h in the dark with constant shaking. Methanol fraction from both extracts was pooled and diluted 5 folds before their absorbance values at wavelengths 666&#x02009;nm, 653&#x02009;nm and 470&#x02009;nm were determined using an Infinite M2000 microplate reader (Tecan, Switzerland). The relative amount of chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>, chlorophyll <italic>b</italic> and total carotenoids were calculated from their absorbance values using previously reported formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Monoterpene content analysis by GC-MS</title><p id="Par81">Leaves harvested from the 4th and 5th nodes of Stevia plants grown in the greenhouse for&#x000a0;3 weeks were homogenized in liquid nitrogen. Three hundred fifty milligrams of leaf powder was extracted with 350&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of ethyl acetate containing 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL of camphor (Sigma-Aldrich) as an internal standard. After 3&#x02009;h incubation at room temperature with constant shaking, the ethyl acetate fraction was transferred into a new tube and treated with anhydrous Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. The treated extracts were then filtered through a 0.45&#x02009;&#x003bc;m nylon centrifuge tube (Corning, USA). The GC-MS analysis was performed on Agilent 7890A GC (Agilent Technologies, USA) system as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec23"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> Representative phenotypes of callus on callus induction media. <bold>a</bold> Calli induced on media containing 1&#x02009;mg/L BA and 1&#x02009;mg/L NAA after 6&#x02009;weeks. <bold>b</bold> Calli and shoot regenerated on media containing 1&#x02009;mg/L BA and 1&#x02009;mg/L IAA after 6&#x02009;weeks. <bold>c</bold> Leaf explants placed for 1 month on media with 1&#x02009;mg/L BA and 1&#x02009;mg/L IAA either under 16&#x02009;h&#x02009;L/8&#x02009;h D photoperiod (upper panel) or under continuous darkness (lower panel). Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;cm. (PDF 214 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S2.</bold> Representative phenotypes of the regenerated shoots. <bold>a</bold> Unhealthy looking regenerated shoots with watery and translucent appearance and slight browning. <bold>b and c</bold> Healthy looking callus with few shoots typical of regenerated shoots under Condition E (<bold>b</bold>) and many regenerated shoots typical of Condition F (<bold>c</bold>). Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.5&#x02009;cm. (PDF 157 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S3.</bold> Immunoblot analyses showing GFP expression in transgenic lines. Total leaf protein was extracted from, SrDXS1-OE, SrKAH-OE and WT lines and probed with &#x003b1;-GFP antibody. Lower panel shows blot after staining with coomassie blue. Extra panel below coomassie blue stained blot shows GFP expression in the SrDXS1-OE lines #7&#x02013;13 with increased amount of sample loaded and longer exposure time. (PDF 639 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S4.</bold> Representative chromatograms from UHPLC analysis of steviol glycosides. <bold>a</bold> Chromatogram of leaf extract from SrDXS-OE #5 compared to that of the Wild type (WT) and standard sample mixture (Standard) of nine steviol glycosides (Rebaudioside D, Rebaudioside A, Stevioside, Rebaudioside F, Rebaudioside C, Dulcoside A, Rubusoside, Rebaudioside B, Steviolbioside) as indicated on the diagram. <bold>b</bold> Chromatogram of leaf extract from SrKAH-OE #1 aligned with that of WT and Standard. (PDF 172 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S5.</bold> Relative content of Reb C and dulcoside A detected from the dried leaves of transgenic Stevia. <bold>a</bold> Amount of Reb C and Dulcoside A relative to wild type (WT) control line in the <italic>SrDXS1</italic> overexpressing lines (SrDXS1-OE). <bold>b</bold> Relative abundance of Reb C and Dulcoside A in the <italic>SrKAH</italic> overexpression lines (SrKAH-OE) relative to the wild type (WT) control line. All SGs were detected using HPLC at wavelength of 210&#x02009;nm. Statistical analysis were carried out using Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test relative to wild-type (WT) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5, * <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, ** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). Data are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE. (PDF 183 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_MOESM6_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S6.</bold> Total content of stevioside and Reb A in SrDXS1-OE line #9. Measurements were made on fresh leaves pooled from five individuals. (PDF 176 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_MOESM7_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 7:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S7.</bold> Monoterpenes extracted from Stevia plants overexpressing <italic>SrDXS1</italic> (SrDXS1-OE). <bold>a-c</bold> &#x003b1;-pinene (<bold>a</bold>), &#x003b2;-pinene (<bold>b</bold>), and linalool (<bold>c</bold>), extracted from the leaves. All measurements are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE and statistical analysis was carried out using Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5). (PDF 254 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_MOESM8_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 8:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S8.</bold> Transcript levels of <italic>SrUGT76G1</italic> in SrKAH-overexpression lines (SrKAH-OE). The values are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test was used for the analysis of statistical significance. (PDF 175 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1600_MOESM9_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 9:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> List of primers used in study. (PDF 182 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>BA</term><def><p id="Par4">6-benzylaminopurine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CaMV</term><def><p id="Par5">Cauliflower mosaic virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCM</term><def><p id="Par6">Co-cultivation media</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFP</term><def><p id="Par7">Cyan fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CIM</term><def><p id="Par8">Callus induction media</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CLSM</term><def><p id="Par9">Confocal laser scanning microscope</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DIG</term><def><p id="Par10">Digoxygenin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMAPP</term><def><p id="Par11">Dimethylallyl pyrophosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DXP</term><def><p id="Par12">1-deoxy-d-xylulose-5-phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ER</term><def><p id="Par13">Endoplasmic reticulum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GC-MS</term><def><p id="Par14">Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GFP</term><def><p id="Par15">Green fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GGPP</term><def><p id="Par16">Geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GUS</term><def><p id="Par17">&#x003b2;-glucuronidase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPP</term><def><p id="Par18">Isopentenyl pyrophosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LD</term><def><p id="Par19">Long day</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MEP</term><def><p id="Par20">Methylerythritol phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MS</term><def><p id="Par21">Murashige &#x00026; Skoog</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MVA</term><def><p id="Par22">Mevalonate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NAA</term><def><p id="Par23">1-naphthaleneacetic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>nptII</term><def><p id="Par24">Neomycin phosphotransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ORF</term><def><p id="Par25">Open reading frame</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Reb A</term><def><p id="Par26">Rebaudioside A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RM</term><def><p id="Par27">Rooting media</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROS</term><def><p id="Par28">Reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SGs</term><def><p id="Par29">Steviol glycosides</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SIM</term><def><p id="Par30">Shoot induction media</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SrDXS1</term><def><p id="Par31">Stevia 1-deoxy-d-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SrKAH</term><def><p id="Par32">Stevia kaurenoic acid hydroxylase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UGT</term><def><p id="Par33">UDP glycosyltransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YFP</term><def><p id="Par34">Yellow fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr. Michael A. Phillips (Centre for Research in Agricultural Genomics, Barcelona, Spain) for providing us with the <italic>E.coli</italic> strain, <italic>dxs-</italic> and Dr. Rajani Sarojam and Mr. Nadimuthu Kumar for their help in plant tissue culture.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par82">This work was supported by Temasek Life Sciences Laboratory. The funding body has no role in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par83">All data used during current study are included in this article and its additional files or are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>ICJ conceived and supervised the project. JZ, YZ, and HZM contributed to the Stevia transformation. JZ performed SrDXSs characterization and molecular analyses of transgenic Stevia. JZ and ICJ designed the experiments, interpreted data and wrote the article. All authors read and edited the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Stevia seeds were provided by Wilmar Research &#x00026; Development Center. Collection of plant materials complied with the institutional, national or international guidelines. No specific permits were required.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ceunen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Geuns</surname><given-names>JMC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steviol glycosides: chemical diversity, metabolism, and function</article-title><source>J Nat Prod</source><year>2013</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/np400203b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23713723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemus-Mondaca</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vega-G&#x000e1;lvez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zura-Bravo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ah-Hen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni, source of a high-potency natural sweetener: a comprehensive review on the biochemical, nutritional and functional aspects</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>1121</fpage><lpage>1132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.11.140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29243591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kinghorn AD. Overview. In: Stevia: the genus Stevia. London: CRC Press; 2003. p. 1&#x02013;17.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvement of taste of natural sweeteners</article-title><source>Pure Appl Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1351/pac199769040675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tott&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Charon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Compernolle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baboeuf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Geuns</surname><given-names>JMC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of the diterpenoid steviol, an <italic>ent</italic>-kaurene derivative from <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> Bertoni, via the methylerythritol phosphate pathway</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>6407</fpage><lpage>6410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0040-4039(00)01094-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elucidation of the methylerythritol phosphate pathway for isoprenoid biosynthesis in bacteria and plastids. A metabolic milestone achieved through genomics</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.007138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12427975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gijzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Starratt</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandle</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diterpene synthesis in <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic>: recruitment and up-regulation of key enzymes from the gibberellin biosynthetic pathway</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1999.00531.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10504563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Menassa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandle</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial organisation of four enzymes from <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> that are involved in steviol glycoside synthesis</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-005-5966-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16786291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandle</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Telmer</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steviol glycoside biosynthesis</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2007</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1855</fpage><lpage>1863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2007.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17397883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McGarvey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional genomics uncovers three glucosyltransferases involved in the synthesis of the major sweet glucosides of <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic></article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2005</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02275.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15610349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA-Seq for gene identification and transcript profiling of three <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> genotypes</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>571</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25001368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative transcriptomics unravel biochemical specialization of leaf tissues of stevia for diterpenoid production</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>2462</fpage><lpage>2480</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26438788?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26438788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ur Rahman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic>-mediated transgenic plant and somaclone production through direct and indirect regeneration from leaves in <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> with their glycoside profile</article-title><source>Protoplasma</source><year>2014</year><volume>251</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00709-014-0610-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24154495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Flavell</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chilton</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A chimaeric antibiotic resistance gene as a selectable marker for plant cell transformation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1983</year><volume>304</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/304184a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horsch</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichholtz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraley</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple and general method for transferring genes into plants</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1985</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>1231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.227.4691.1229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17757866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Meer</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Loyola-Vargas</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e1;zquez-Flota</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of petunia leaf discs</article-title><source>Plant Cell Culture Protocols</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Totowa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>272</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-expression of peppermint geranyl diphosphate synthase small subunit enhances monoterpene production in transgenic tobacco plants</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2017</year><volume>213</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28079933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganeshan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Caswell</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kartha</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chibbar</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Khachatourians</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Scorza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nip</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shoot regeneration and proliferation</article-title><source>Transgenic plants and crops</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Marcel Dekker, Inc</publisher-name><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regeneration of Stevia plant through callus culture</article-title><source>Indian J Pharm Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0250-474X.51954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20177455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced development of embryogenic callus in <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> Bert. By additive and amino acids</article-title><source>Biotechnol</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/biotech.2010.368.372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient regeneration for enhanced steviol glycosides production in <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> (Bertoni)</article-title><source>C R Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crvi.2013.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24246890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bespalhok-Filho</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Embryogenic callus formation and histological studies from <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> (Bert.) Bertoni floret explants</article-title><source>Rev Bras Fisiol Veg</source><year>1997</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>188</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorst</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Atwell</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriedemann</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>CGN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differentiation and gene expression</article-title><source>Plants in action: adaptation in nature, performance in cultivation. Macmillan education AU</source><year>1999</year><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>349</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Auxin&#x02013;cytokinin interaction regulates meristem development</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssr007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21357646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Inz&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Depicker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GATEWAY&#x02122; vectors for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated plant transformation</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(02)02251-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11992820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lois</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Concepcion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carotenoid biosynthesis during tomato fruit development: regulatory role of 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2000</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.2000.00764.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10886770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Est&#x000e9;vez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reindl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>1-Deoxy-d-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase, a limiting enzyme for plastidic isoprenoid biosynthesis in plants</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>22901</fpage><lpage>22909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M100854200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cordoba</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unravelling the regulatory mechanisms that modulate the MEP pathway in higher plants</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2933</fpage><lpage>2943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19584121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathway mining-based integration of critical enzyme parts for <italic>de novo</italic> biosynthesis of steviol glycosides sweetener in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2015.111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26358188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guleria</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Masand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversion of carbon flux from gibberellin to steviol biosynthesis by over-expressing <italic>SrKA13H</italic> induced dwarfism and abnormality in pollen germination and seed set behaviour of transgenic Arabidopsis</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2015</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>3907</fpage><lpage>3916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erv198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25954046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies to improve poor seed germination in <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic>, a low calorie sweetener</article-title><source>J Med Plants Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1793</fpage><lpage>1799</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duran-Vila</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogorcena</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphogenesis and tissue culture of sweet orange (<italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> (L.) Osb.): effect of temperature and photosynthetic radiation</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult</source><year>1992</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00036140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marutani-Hert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCollum</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirkov</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Evens</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Niedz</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A dark incubation period is important for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of mature internode explants of sweet orange, grapefruit, citron, and a citrange rootstock</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e47426</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23082165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nameth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinka</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatfield</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>English</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Oro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Raizada</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The shoot regeneration capacity of excised Arabidopsis cotyledons is established during the initial hours after injury and is modulated by a complex genetic network of light signalling</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ</source><year>2013</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2012.02554.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22681544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwase</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant regeneration: cellular origins and molecular mechanisms</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2016</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>1442</fpage><lpage>1451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.134668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27143753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leclercq</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lardet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapuset</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Montoro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The green fluorescent protein as an efficient selection marker for <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic>-mediated transformation in <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic> (M&#x000fc;ll. Arg)</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-010-0840-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20306052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corredoira</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Valladares</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allona</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Aragoncillo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieitez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballester</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic transformation of European chestnut somatic embryos with a native thaumatin-like protein (CsTL1) gene isolated from <italic>Castanea sativa</italic> seeds</article-title><source>Tree Physiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1389</fpage><lpage>1402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/treephys/tps098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23086811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kirakosyan A, Cseke LJ, Kaufman PB.The use of plant cell biotechnology for the production of phytochemicals. In: Kirakosyan A, Kaufman PB, editors. Recent advances in plant biotechnology. Boston: Springer; 2009. p. 15&#x02013;33.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz-Bertomeu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrillaga</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ros</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Up-regulation of 1-Deoxy-d-Xylulose-5-phosphate synthase enhances production of essential oils in transgenic spike lavender</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.086355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16980564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassard</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Werck-Reichhart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytochrome P450-mediated metabolic engineering: current progress and future challenges</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2014.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24709279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephanopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engineering the push and pull of lipid biosynthesis in oleaginous yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> for biofuel production</article-title><source>Metab Eng</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymben.2012.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23026119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baidoo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>LJG</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Petzold</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Keasling</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic engineering for the high-yield production of isoprenoid-based C5 alcohols in <italic>E. coli</italic></article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>11128</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep11128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26052683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hellfritsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockhoff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000e4;hler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerhof</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human psychometric and taste receptor responses to steviol glycosides</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>060</volume><fpage>6782</fpage><lpage>6793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf301297n</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pareek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sopory</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singla-Pareek</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An improved protocol for efficient transformation and regeneration of diverse indica rice cultivars</article-title><source>Plant Methods</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4811-7-49</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22206592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendich</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gelvin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilperoort</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>DPS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extraction of DNA from plant tissues</article-title><source>Plant molecular biology manual</source><year>1989</year><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>83</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenthaler</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellburn</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinations of total carotenoids and chlorophylls <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> of leaf extracts in different solvents</article-title><source>Biochem Soc Trans</source><year>1983</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/bst0110591</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>