<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5794852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20420</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-20420-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>VOC emissions influence intra- and interspecific interactions among stored-product Coleoptera in paddy rice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Giunti</surname><given-names>Giulia</given-names></name><address><email>giulia.giunti@unirc.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palmeri</surname><given-names>Vincenzo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Algeri</surname><given-names>Giuseppe Massimo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campolo</surname><given-names>Orlando</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">Department of Agriculture, University &#x0201c;Mediterranea&#x0201d; of Reggio Calabria, Loc. Feo di Vito, 89122 Reggio, Calabria Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>2052</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Olfaction is a pivotal sense for insects and granivorous pests may exploit grain volatiles for food selection. <italic>Tribolium confusum</italic>, is a secondary pest of stored cereals that benefits from primary pests&#x02019; infestation, as other secondary feeders, triggering competition. This study aimed to evaluate the preferences of <italic>T. confusum</italic> females toward different-infested paddy rice, highlighting the impact of intra- and interspecific competition. <italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> showed positive chemotaxis toward rice infested by larvae of a primary pest (<italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic>), but not for grain attacked by adults alone. Furthermore, kernels concurrently infested by a primary (<italic>S. zeamais</italic>) and a secondary pest (<italic>T. confusum</italic> or <italic>Cryptolestes ferrugineus</italic>) were evaluated in Y-tube bioassays, highlighting that both food-sources were innately attractive for <italic>T. confusum</italic> females. Moreover, females positively oriented toward rice infested by conspecifics, while they avoided grain infested by <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic>, averting an extremely competitive habitat. Behavioural responses of <italic>T. confusum</italic> females and volatile emissions of different-infested rice highlighted the occurrence of plant-mediated interactions among insects from the same trophic guild. Seventy volatiles were identified and significant differences among the tested food-sources were recorded, emphasizing the presence of 6 putative attractants and 6 repellents, which may be useful biocontrol tools.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Stored product protection is a key issue in the food production and processing contexts. Worldwide annual post-harvest losses attributable to granivorous pests have been estimated at 10% of the total cereal grain yield, determining also severe weight losses (i.e. dry matter loss)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Chemical control approaches are generally preferred by food producers since they are cheapest and cost-effective<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, although also prevention procedures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> and physical control methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> are commonly employed. However, since chemical control is becoming even more strict-regulated and restrictive, researches have started to focus on the development of innovative and sustainable strategies, involving also natural enemies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> and plant-borne molecules<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Granivorous insects attacking stored cereals can be divided into internal and external feeders consistent with their feeding habits, which are also known as primary and secondary pests, respectively, according to typical infestation order. <italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic> (Motschulsky) (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) is one of the most common and destructive insects of stored cereals worldwide. The adult weevils can attack whole grains and the females lay eggs inside the kernels, in which the larvae feed and develop<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Feeding activity of a primary pest is essential to boost external feeders&#x02019; survival, since these pests preferentially forage on damaged or previous infested kernels. The confused flour beetle, <italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> J. du Val (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae), and the rusty grain beetle, <italic>Cryptolestes ferrugineus</italic> (Stephens) (Coleoptera: Cucujidae), are two economically important beetle species that typically are unable to feed on undamaged grain. Co-occurrence of <italic>Tribolium</italic> spp. and <italic>Cryptolestes</italic> spp. infestation is frequent and the magnitude of competition on the respective life-history traits has already been investigated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, highlighting that competitive dominance mainly depends on population density and abiotic factors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Olfaction is a key sense routing interspecific communication in insect communities and the role of infochemicals steering interactions among insects belonging to different trophic levels has been extensively investigated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, the impact of olfactory cues shaping the relationships among insects from the same guild, competing for shared resources, is far less explored. For instance, signals left by close related species, as oviposition and host-marking pheromones, may be exploited by herbivores and natural enemies to detect competitor activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Plant-borne volatiles play a role in food and host location, routing insect orientation and searching behaviour. Herbivore-induced plant volatiles (HIPVs), produced by the plant in response to phytophagous feeding activity, are known to be pivotal for parasitoid host location<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Overall, HIPVs are acknowledged to affect community dynamics by influencing the performances of various members<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Compared to field conditions, granivorous insects attacking foodstuff rely on foraging-environments presenting simplified community structure. Although many foodstuff insects are originally polyphagous, when foraging in anthropized habitats, they can rely on few different food resources and the association between pest species is common<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Therefore, infochemicals are pivotal to detect suitable food sources<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> and can improve pest searching efficiency, by shaping trophic interactions and competitive coexistence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Interspecific competition, either occurring as exploitation (i.e. without behavioural interactions) or interference (i.e. through aggressive behaviours), is widespread among granivorous insects and can lead to severe consequences for the involved species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In this scenario, the prompt recognition of unsuitable or harmful habitats is a key cue to enhance pest survival and fitness, and thus semiochemicals emitted by infested kernels could be exploited to overcome competition establishment.</p><p id="Par4">Here, we focused on the olfactory responses of the external feeder <italic>T. confusum</italic> toward rice sources with different infestation status, to highlight the impact of intra- and interspecific interactions and the effect of primary and secondary pest infestations. Firstly, we evaluated the na&#x000ef;ve attractiveness of intact and insect-damaged rice, testing the incidence of <italic>S. zeamais</italic> larvae and/or adults, as well as the co-occurrence of a secondary larval-infestation by <italic>T. confusum</italic> or <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic>. Then, the comparative preferences of <italic>T. confusum</italic> females for intact and <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested grains were tested in two-choice assays, in order to highlight the impact of infestation by a primary feeder on confused flour beetles&#x02019; chemotaxis. Furthermore, to assess the effect of competition among insects belonging to the same trophic guild, we evaluated the attractiveness of kernels concurrently infested by a primary (i.e. <italic>S. zeamais</italic>) and a secondary pest (i.e. <italic>T. confusum or C. ferrugineus</italic>) by comparing them to rice damaged by <italic>S. zeamais</italic> alone. Lastly, to determine the release of semiochemicals that can route insect orientation, and to identify Volatile Organic Compounds (VOCs) acting as attractants or repellents, the emissions of different-infested rice were sampled by Head-Space Solid Phase Micro-Extraction (HS-SPME) and analysed through Gas-chromatography/Mass spectrometry (GC/MS) techniques.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Behavioural responses of Tribolium confusum females toward different rice-sources</title><p id="Par5">Results highlighted that all the tested olfactory sources were innately appealing for <italic>T. confusum</italic> females (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Indeed, females positively oriented toward both intact and <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested rice. Furthermore, the presence of <italic>S. zeamais</italic> adults did not alter <italic>T. confusum</italic> orientation. However, when compared in two-choice Y-tube assays, <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested rice was preferred over intact rice alone, as well as over intact rice infested just with <italic>S. zeamais</italic> adults (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The presence of adults of <italic>S. zeamais</italic> in the odorous sources did not affected behavioural responses of <italic>T. confusum</italic> females, since tested specimens did not even discriminate between intact rice and rice with adult maize weevils (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). No significant differences in latent periods were recorded (Suplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Innate attractiveness of intact and insect-damaged rice kernels toward <italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> females. Choice bioassays were conducted in Y-tube olfactometer comparing every odour source (5&#x02009;g) vs blank. Thirty responsive beetles were tested for every comparison. For each comparison, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> and <italic>P</italic> value are provided. Subscripts reported for &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> represent the degrees of freedom. SZ&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic>, TC&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Tribolium confusum</italic>, CF&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Cryptolestes ferrugineus</italic>; NC&#x02009;=&#x02009;Number of beetle females who performed no choice between the two given cues.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20420_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e449"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Y-tube choice-tests evaluating the olfactory preferences of <italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> females for rice kernels (5&#x02009;g) with different infestation status. Thirty responsive beetles were tested for every comparison. For each comparison, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> and <italic>P</italic> value are provided when a significant difference (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) in the number of choosing beetle is recorded. Subscripts reported for &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> represent the degrees of freedom. ns&#x02009;=&#x02009;no significant difference; SZ&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic>, TC&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Tribolium confusum</italic>, CF&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Cryptolestes ferrugineus</italic>; NC&#x02009;=&#x02009;Number of beetle females who performed no choice between the two given cues.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20420_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e480"/></fig></p><p id="Par6"><italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> females displayed different responses toward double-infested rice, although both were innately attractive (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and were preferred to intact rice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref><bold>)</bold>. Furthermore, the sole presence of either <italic>T. confusum</italic> or <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic> adults in <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested rice did not alter the chemotaxis of tested specimens, which did not discriminate the olfactory stimuli of these sources from those of <italic>S. zeamais</italic>-infested rice. Nevertheless, when each double-infested rice (containing larvae of both primary and secondary pests) was evaluated against rice infested by <italic>S. zeamais</italic> larvae alone in two-choice bioassays, <italic>T. confusum</italic> females&#x02019; responses were dissimilar. <italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> females showed to recognize self-infestation by choosing rice infested by larvae of <italic>T. confusum</italic> and <italic>S. zeamais</italic> over the single <italic>S. zeamais</italic>-infested rice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In contrast, in presence of a hetero-specific double infestation, <italic>T. confusum</italic> females preferred <italic>S. zeamais</italic>-infested rice over rice infested by <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic> and <italic>S. zeamais</italic> larvae (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). No significant differences in latent periods were recorded (Suplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Identification of VOCs from rice-sources</title><p id="Par7">GC/MS analyses allowed to identify 70 different molecules (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). VOC emissions qualitatively varied according to infestation status of rice, highlighting the presence of only 21 compounds commonly produced by all the tested sources. Pest feeding-activity affected the complexity of VOC emission either by directly producing the volatiles (e.g. faeces and pheromones) or by inducing their ex-novo production from plant material. Intact rice kernels emitted a lower number of volatiles (28 VOCs) compared to <italic>S. zeamais</italic>-infested rice (45 VOCs). Furthermore, also the presence of a secondary feeder enriched the volatile bouquet of rice kernels, highlighting 54 and 56 VOCs emitted by <italic>T. confusum</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>S. zeamais</italic>-infested and <italic>C. ferrugines</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>S. zeamais</italic>-infested rice respectively. Overall, the tested rice sources showed characteristic volatile profiles and several VOCs were exclusive of a given infestation status (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Intact rice emitted 7 volatiles which disappeared following pest infestation, while in <italic>S. zeamais</italic>-infested rice were recorded 21 VOCs associated to <italic>S. zeamais</italic> infestation and a single VOC (i.e. hexadecanoic acid) exclusively emitted by this olfactory source. When a double infestation occurred, the production of 6 novel molecules, which can be related to the presence of whatever external feeder, were noted (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). However, the feeding activity of each secondary pest could be recognized according to the different volatile emissions. Rice bulks infested simultaneously by <italic>S. zeamais</italic> and <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic> emitted 56 identified VOCs, 6 of which were exclusive of this olfactory source. Similarly, rice double infested by <italic>S. zeamais</italic> and <italic>T. confusum</italic> emitted 6 peculiar VOCs out of a total of 54 volatiles, while 2 molecules were negatively correlated to <italic>T. confusum</italic> feeding-activity (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>VOCs exclusively produced by tested rice sources according to different infestation status. SZ&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic>, TC&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Tribolium confusum</italic>, CF&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Cryptolestes ferrugineus</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20420_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e619"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">PCA followed by multi-factorial analysis (MFA) highlighted differences among volatile emissions from different-infested rice. The Kaiser coefficient was around 1.00, since no correlations among the majorities of the compounds occurred and the variables could be considered independent. Three principal components, explaining 91.70% of variance, were selected (i.e. corresponding to the flex point of the scree plot obtained by PCA) and analysed (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Results from PCA are presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref> and a score plot shows the main sources of variation considering the selected principal components (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). The eigenvectors of principal components (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>) and of rotated factors (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>) were calculated for any single identified VOCs. The rotated factors with an eigenvector of at least&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 were considered for the following analyses, to label each factor according with the involved source of variability (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Based on the results of MFA, the 3 evaluated factors were labelled as: Factor1 &#x0201c;<italic>Sitophylus zeamais</italic>&#x0201d; (explained variance&#x02009;=&#x02009;54.25%), Factor2 &#x0201c;<italic>Cryptolestes ferrugineus</italic>&#x0201d; (explained variance&#x02009;=&#x02009;19.66%) and Factor3 &#x0201c;<italic>Tribolium confusum</italic>&#x0201d; (explained variance&#x02009;=&#x02009;17.88%). Indeed, for every selected factor, pest presence was associated to peculiar VOCs (i.e. those with positive eigenvectors), whereas volatiles showing negative eigenvectors were negatively correlated to infestation. In detail, Factor 1 showed strong correlation with 45 VOCs, while Factor 2 and Factor 3 with 16 VOCs each (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Principal Component Analysis (PCA) of volatile profiles from differentially infested rice. (<bold>A</bold>) PCA loading plot, showing volatile correlations with the first and second principal component; (<bold>B</bold>) PCA score plot, highlighting cluster of volatiles attributable to different infestation status (ellipses&#x02009;=&#x02009;95% of confidence). <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20420_Figa_HTML.gif" id="d29e667"/> Intact Rice; <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20420_Figb_HTML.gif" id="d29e670"/>
<italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic>-infested rice; <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20420_Figc_HTML.gif" id="d29e677"/>
<italic>Tribolium confusum</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic>-infested rice; <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20420_Figd_HTML.gif" id="d29e686"/>
<italic>Cryptolestes ferrugineus</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic>-infested rice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20420_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e695"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par9">Pest infestation strongly modifies volatile profiles emitted by rice kernels and alters behavioural responses of <italic>T. confusum</italic> females. According to Ehrlich and Raven<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, secondary plant substances play a key role in the evolutionary interactions between insects and plants, since their main objective is to attract or repel insects. Our results empathize that the feeding activity of tested species affects the whole volatile profiles of rice grains, promoting or reducing the emission of peculiar VOCs which can be strongly correlated to every pest species. This kind of VOCs have been already acknowledged to act as kairomones toward natural enemies of stored product pests, including several parasitoid species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. For instance, differences among volatile profiles attributable to diverse ongoing infestations may be exploited by either generalist and specialist parassitoids to discriminate and locate their hosts. Here, we identified 1-pentadecene, a component of <italic>T. confusum</italic> larval faeces, which serve as attractant for the parasitoid <italic>Holepyris sylvanidis</italic> (Br&#x000e8;thes) (Hymenoptera: Bethylidae)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Although this molecule is recognised to be directly produced by <italic>T. confusum</italic> larvae, here we highlighted that it is a common VOC recurrent in <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested sources. However, emission of 1-pentadecene reached the highest level in rice co-infested by <italic>T. confusum</italic> and <italic>S. zeamais</italic> larvae. Since <italic>S. zeamais</italic> performances may be impaired by hetero-specific larvae feeding on grain external surface, its fitness may profit from the recruitment of <italic>T. confusum</italic> natural enemies, which can benefit from an early host-habitat location.</p><p id="Par10">To date, the effect of distinctive herbivore-induced grain volatiles (HIGVs) on other community members belonging to the same trophic level is still uncertain and poorly investigated. Our results demonstrate that olfactory cues route searching behaviour of <italic>T. confusum</italic> females, allowing them to distinguish host grains with different suitability values by detecting peculiar HIGVs. However, all the tested host-food sources are innately attractive for <italic>T. confusum</italic> and confused beetle females revealed na&#x000ef;ve attraction also for intact rice kernels, which may be considered a less suitable resource. The presence of a primary pest has been already proved to increase positive orientation and fitness of various secondary feeders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. According to previous investigation on a close related species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, here <italic>T. confusum</italic> females prefer <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested rice over intact rice, irrespectively to the presence of adult maize weevils. Early infestation (i.e. the presence of adult <italic>S. zeamais</italic> alone) does not affect behavioural responses of <italic>T. confusum</italic>, which is incapable to detect precocious infestations and is unaffected by olfactory cues directly correlated to adult feeding activity. In contrast, the feeding activity of <italic>S. zeamais</italic> larvae induces the emission of 22 VOCs, which can either ex-novo produced by the grain, as indirect defence, as well as directly excreted by the larvae inside the kernels. Among the identified VOCs, only hexadecanoic acid is exclusively correlated to <italic>S. zeamais</italic> infestation, since this molecule disappears when a double infestation occurs. Moreover, hexadecanoic acid has been already recorded as aggregation cue for the females of khapra beetle, <italic>Trogoderma granarium</italic> Everts (Coleottera: Dermestidae), one of the most destructive pests of stored grains and seeds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">Furthermore, the incidence of primary infestation on foodstuff usually promotes the outbreak of fungal infections, which can either change the environmental conditions as well as affect the volatile emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Indeed, fungi are able to release a number of VOCs including aliphatic eight-carbon compounds derived from the degradation of unsaturated fatty acids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Several fungi-related VOCs are emitted by <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested rice, highlighting that the insurgence of mold infection is favoured when kernels are damaged by an internal feeder. The presence of an external feeder generally reduces the emission of fungal volatiles, since secondary pests consume also fungal mycelia when feeding on kernels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Indeed, as a primary pest of stored grain, <italic>S. zeamais</italic> can contribute to the dispersal of fungal spores and provide through feeding damages entry points for fungal infections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Furthermore, those fungal-related molecules may also impact the other components of trophic contexts, as natural enemies. For instance, the parasitoid <italic>Lariophagus distinguendus</italic> F&#x000f6;rster (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae) use fungi-related volatiles for host-habitat assessment to avoid moldy grains which can be less profitable for the survival of the parasitized larvae<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par12">Population-based competition implies the concept of resource-limitation, which can even occur among conspecifics as scramble (i.e. without behavioural interferences) and contest (i.e. <italic>via</italic> aggressive behaviours) competition. Indeed, individuals of the same species have the same resource requirements, while different species could just present some resource overlaps, thus generally classifying the interspecific competition as less effective than the intraspecific one. Nevertheless, <italic>T. confusum</italic> females show to be innately attractive by rice co-infested by <italic>T. confusum</italic> and <italic>S. zeamais</italic> and even to prefer rice infested by conspecific over singly <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested kernels. This behavioural response cannot be attribute to pheromone release by other <italic>T. confusum</italic> adults, since tested females are not able to discern and identify the presence of adult conspecifics within the kernels in choice bioassays. However, <italic>T. confusum</italic> larval infestation cause the emission of 6 characteristic HIGVs, which can act as attractant for conspecific adults. Among these exclusive volatiles, three terpenes have been identified: two monoterpenes, <italic>&#x003b1;-</italic>pinene and <italic>&#x003b3;</italic>-terpinene, and a sesquiterpene oxygenated, nerolidol, which have been already recorded as attractant for a number of Coleopteran species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Definitely, terpenes are the largest class of natural molecules and are generally devoted to mediate the interactions between organisms, whether toward conspecifics and beneficial species, or as defence response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Remarkably, (<italic>E</italic>)-anethole, a recurrent component of essential oils, has been identified in <italic>T. confusum-</italic>infested rice, although its insecticidal activity has been already investigated against a number of stored product pests<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. The responses recorded for <italic>T. confusum</italic> in behavioural assays could seem in contrast with the fundamental concept of competition and a kind of maladaptive behaviour. However, as already demonstrated for other stored-product pests<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, these results can highlight the occurrence of an adaptive behaviour that may help <italic>T. confusum</italic> females to readily detect a host-grain source previously colonized by conspecifics and thus certainly suitable for oviposition and larval development. Indeed, the ecological consequence of intraspecific interactions need to be carefully evaluated by each individual<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>, since competitive outcomes depend on the availability of resources, population density, developmental requirements and life-history traits of every species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Thus, when competing for local resources, individuals of the same species develop adaptive responses just to overcome extremely harmful situations, which can lead to serious negative fitness consequences<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par13">According to niche theory, interspecific competition is mainly attributable to the overlap of the resources exploited by the involved species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. However, the coexistence of two species sharing the same trophic niche can take place and hetero-specific interactions can lead to different competitive results, according to population density and colonization order<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Furthermore, to avoid interference with aggressive species, many insects evolved conflict-avoidance behaviours to recognize chemically marked resources, which have been already exploited and colonized<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. Avoidance of direct conflict is favourable for both dominant and minor species, since interference competition involving aggressive behaviours is energetically expensive and can cause severe mortality also for the predominant species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Plant-mediated interactions are frequent among contending species, and can involve the induction of chemical responses in the host-plant or grain to deter competitor feeding activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Indirect plant-mediated competition is consistent with the behavioural responses of <italic>T. confusum</italic> females toward rice co-infested by <italic>S. zeamais</italic> and <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic> larvae. It has been already investigated the negative impact of <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic> on the development and survival of other stored-product Coleoptera, including <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> Herbst (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae), a close related species of <italic>T. confusum</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Consistently with previously described results, confused beetle females are not able to detect <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic> early infestation, whereas the presence of larval stages of rusty grain beetles evokes negative chemotaxis. Feeding activity of hetero-specific larvae induce the emission of 6 peculiar HIGVs, which may affect the orientation of <italic>T. confusum</italic> females and serve as repellents. In detail, nonanoic acid and &#x003b3;-nonanolide are recognized allelochemicals among Coleoptera, while 9,12-Tetradecadien-1-ol is a pheromonal component of many pyralid moths, including the foodstuff pests <italic>Ephestia kuehniella</italic> Zeller<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup> and <italic>Plodia interpunctella</italic> H&#x000fc;bner (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par14">Our results clearly reveal that olfactory stimuli can route interactions between members of the same guild and thus play a role on the coexistence and the competition establishing among stored-product pests. Furthermore, the feeding activity of tested species impacts the whole volatile profiles of rice grains, promoting or reducing the emission of specific VOCs which can be strongly correlated to every pest species infestation. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first time that the occurrence of indirect plant-mediated competition has been demonstrated for granivorous insects. Overall, deep knowledge of the mechanisms underlying interspecific interactions and associations among stored-product pests is pivotal to develop and design new and effective pest-control strategies. Therefore, the identified putative attractants and repellents specific for <italic>T. confusum</italic> could represent an innovative tool to enhance Integrated Pest Management (IPM) against stored-product pests.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Grain and insect materials</title><p id="Par15">Paddy rice kernels (var. Ribe, supplied by a local producer and organic certified) were used as rearing medium for all the insects involved in the experimental set up. Prior to use rice grain as rearing medium, the presence and the insurgence of previous infestations was checked for 30 days, to avoid possible kernel contaminations from other insect pests. Insect species were individually reared on rice medium for at least three generations. <italic>Sithopilus zeamais</italic> was reared using intact rice kernels, while <italic>T. confusum</italic> and <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic> were fed with mechanically crushed grains. Insect rearing were placed in a climatic chamber and maintained under controlled conditions [25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% RU and 12:12 (light:dark) photoperiod]. Adult insects (<italic>S. zeamais</italic>, <italic>T. confusum</italic> and <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic>) from these rearing media were used to infest the rice employed for the bioassays or the volatile collection.</p><p id="Par16">Four different rice-based sources were then set up: (<italic>i</italic>) intact rice, (<italic>ii</italic>) <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested rice (SZ-infested rice), (<italic>iii</italic>) <italic>T. confusum</italic> and <italic>S. zeamais</italic> double-infested rice (TC&#x02009;+&#x02009;SZ-infested rice), (<italic>iv</italic>) <italic>C. ferruginues</italic> and <italic>S. zeamais</italic> and double-infested rice (CF&#x02009;+&#x02009;SZ infested rice). To obtain <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested rice, 50 unsexed adult maize weevils (15&#x02013;30 days old) were placed in a glass vessel (1&#x02009;L volume) containing 500&#x02009;g of intact rice to allow feeding and oviposition for 5 days. Then, <italic>S. zeamais</italic> adults were removed and infested rice was stored at controlled conditions for 23&#x02013;25 days, to allow larval growth inside the kernels, before been tested. Double-infested rice was similarly obtained inserting 50 adults <italic>S. zeamais</italic> (15&#x02013;30 days old) in an analogous glass vessel with 500&#x02009;g of intact rice. After 5 days <italic>S. zeamais</italic> adults were removed and the infested rice was kept for 7 days without adult insects. Then, 50 unsexed <italic>T. confusum</italic> or <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic> (15&#x02013;30 days old) were introduced in the medium and allowed to infest the grains for 5 days, before being removed. Lastly, the obtained double-infested rice-media were stored for 12&#x02013;14 days at controlled conditions, prior to be used in the experimental set up. Intact rice (500&#x02009;g) was also placed in a 1L-glass vial and maintained at the same conditions of infested rice-bulks for 25&#x02013;30 days Before been employed for the behavioural assays or the volatile collection, all the tested rice-based sources were maintained at the above mentioned controlled conditions for the entire duration of trials.</p><p id="Par17">To avoid previous experience, and thus conditioning to volatiles emitted by rice kernels, <italic>T. confusum</italic> females, which were tested in the bioassays, fed on a different rearing medium (i.e. wheat flour) for at least three generations. Insect rearing were placed in a climatic chamber and maintained under controlled conditions during the entire experimental duration [25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% RU and 12:12 (light:dark) photoperiod].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Olfactometry</title><p id="Par18">All experiments were conducted at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (45&#x02013;55% R.H.); to avoid visual cues, all the trials were carried out in a dark plastic box (1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.7&#x02009;m) illuminated with red fluorescent tubes (20&#x02009;W). The bioassays were conducted in a Y-tube olfactometer connected with an air delivery system which blown the air at 0.5&#x02009;L&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> constant flow. The inflow was purified by passing through an activated charcoal filter. The Y-tube system was a horizontal glass unit consisting of a central tube (100&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;30&#x02009;mm diam) and two lateral arms (90&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;30&#x02009;mm diam) ending with a spherical chamber (50&#x02009;mm diam). Two Drechsel bottles (250&#x02009;mL), containing odorous sources, were connected to the lateral arms with Teflon connections. Equally, previously humidified and purified air was blown into the Drechsel bottles through Teflon connections.</p><p id="Par19"><italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> females were tested at 14&#x02013;21 days of age and were used only once. To exclude the presence of visual cues affecting insect orientation, preliminary trials were performed using no odorant sources (blank vs blank), showing no positional effect. However, replicates of every treatment were conducted over several days (to allow for a daily variability in responsiveness) and the olfactometer arms were reversed after every test to control for any other positional effect. The olfactometer was washed with warm water (35&#x02013;40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) and mild soap every 5 replicates, and then rinsed with hot water, followed by distilled water. A total of 30 responsive <italic>T. confusum</italic> females were tested for each comparison, with every specimen gently introduced into the central arm of the Y-tube from a glass vial and observed for 6&#x02009;min. Individuals that remained unresponsive for 5&#x02009;min were discarded and labelled as no-choice. For insects that started searching within 5&#x02009;min, a choice was recorded when the female remained in one of the Y-tube arms for at least 20&#x02009;seconds. For each replicate, we recorded the latent period (i.e. time spent inside the choice arena before entering an arm) and the choice (i.e. the odor source selected).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Behavioural responses of Tribolium confusum females toward different rice-sources</title><p id="Par20">The following bioassays were set up to investigate: (<italic>i</italic>) the attractiveness toward <italic>T. confusum</italic> females of intact rice and rice infested by primary and/or secondary pests, (<italic>ii</italic>) the na&#x000ef;ve preferences for intact and <italic>S. zeamais-</italic>infested grain and (<italic>iii</italic>) the alteration of those preferences attributable to the occurrence of a secondary infestation (<italic>T. confusum</italic> or <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic>).<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p id="Par21">To assess the na&#x000ef;ve attractiveness of grain with different infestation status, the following treatments were tested against blank in Y-tube bioassays: a) intact rice; b) intact rice plus 10 adult <italic>S. zeamais</italic>; c) SZ<italic>-</italic>infested rice; d) SZ<italic>-</italic>infested rice plus 10 adult <italic>S. zeamais;</italic> e) TC&#x02009;+&#x02009;SZ-infested rice; f) CF&#x02009;+&#x02009;SZ-infested rice. Treatments b) and d) were obtained placing 10 adult maize weevils in 5&#x02009;g of intact and SZ<italic>-</italic>infested rice respectively 24&#x02009;h before being used for olfactometer trials. This incubation time (24&#x02009;h) was selected to allow insect feeding activity, odour contamination (also from faeces) and possibly oviposition activity, while preventing the presence of newly-born larvae, which could alter the emission by feeding on the kernels. Five grams of every odour source were tested for each comparison.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p id="Par22">To assess the impact of a primary infestation on <italic>T. confusum</italic> preferences, two-choice Y-tube bioassays were performed by pair-comparing the following treatment: a) intact rice; b) intact rice plus 10 adult <italic>S. zeamais</italic>; c) SZ<italic>-</italic>infested rice; d) SZ<italic>-</italic>infested rice plus 10 adult <italic>S. zeamais</italic>. All possible binary combinations were carried out. The experiment aimed to explore the effect of S<italic>. zeamais</italic> presence (both as adult and/or larvae) on the appeal of food-sources. Five grams of every odour source were tested for each comparison.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p id="Par23">The effect of larval infestation by a secondary pest was evaluated in two choice bioassays against intact and SZ<italic>-</italic>infested rice. To evaluate the effect of an early infestation of either secondary pests (<italic>T. confusum</italic> or <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic>), the chemotaxis of confused beetle females toward SZ<italic>-</italic>infested rice plus secondary pest adults (i.e. 10 adult <italic>T. confusum</italic> or <italic>C. ferrugineus</italic> added in 5&#x02009;g SZ<italic>-</italic>infested rice 24&#x02009;h prior to test) was evaluated against SZ-infested rice and double-infested rice in two-choice bioassays. This incubation time (24&#x02009;h) was selected to allow insect feeding activity, odour contamination (also from faeces) and possibly oviposition activity, while preventing the presence of newly-born larvae, which can alter the emission by feeding on the kernels.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par24">For every described comparison, binary choice data were analyzed by &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> likelihood test with Yates&#x02019; correction (&#x003b1;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05); latent periods were analyzed in JMP 11<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> using a generalized linear model with &#x02018;treatment&#x02019; as a fixed factor, after verifying normality distribution and variance homoscedasticity by Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk and Levene&#x02019;s test respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>VOC collection and identification</title><p id="Par25">Head-space samplings of the paddy rice were performed using a Supelco<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (Bellefonte, PA, USA) SPME device coated with polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS, 100 &#x003bc;m), which can selectively extract the majority of secondary metabolites, acting as infochemicals for insects. Equilibration and SPME sampling was achieved using the same new fiber, preconditioned according to the manufacturer instructions. For all treatments, 5&#x02009;g of intact or infested rice were inserted into a 20-mL hermetic glass vial, and allowed to equilibrate for 30&#x02009;min. After the equilibration time, the fiber was inserted in the vial and exposed to the headspace for 30&#x02009;min. Samplings were accomplished in a thermostatic chamber (25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) to guarantee the stable temperature. Once samplings were completed, the fiber was withdrawn into the needle and transferred to the injection port of the GC/MS system. According to the results of behavioural assays, the following treatment were evaluated: a) intact rice; b) SZ-infested rice; c) TC&#x02009;+&#x02009;SZ-infested rice and d) CF&#x02009;+&#x02009;SZ-infested rice. Four replicates (i.e. each containing 5&#x02009;g of rice) for every treatment were performed. All the SPME sampling and desorption conditions were identical for all the samples and replicates. Blanks were performed before first SPME extraction and repeated randomly during each series. Relative-quantitative comparisons of peak areas were provided for the same identified chemical in different samples, after verifying that the intensity of the chromatograms was equivalent.</p><p id="Par26">GC/MS analyses were performed with a Thermo Fisher TRACE 1300 gas chromatograph equipped with a MEGA-5 capillary column (30&#x02009;m x 0.25&#x02009;mm; coating thickness&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.25 &#x003bc;m) and a Thermo Fisher ISQ LT ion trap mass detector (emission current: 10 microamps; count threshold: 1 count; multiplier offset: 0 volts; scan time: 1.00&#x02009;second; prescan ionization time: 100 microseconds; scan mass range: 30&#x02013;300&#x02009;m/z; ionization mode: EI). The following analytical conditions were employed: injector and transfer line temperature at 250 and 240&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, respectively; oven temperature programmed from 60 to 240&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at 3&#x02009;&#x000b0;C min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; carrier gas, helium at 1&#x02009;mL&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; splitless injection. Identification of chemicals was based on the comparison of retention times (RT) and their linear retention indices (LRI), relative to the series of n-hydrocarbons, with those of pure chemicals, and on computer matching against the commercial libraries (NIST 98 and ADAMS) and compared to a homemade library built from pure substances, components and the MS literature data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. LRI was calculated by comparing the retention times of the compounds to those of a standard mixture of alkanes (C7-C30 saturated alkanes standard mixture, Supelco<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Bellefonte, PA, USA), which were sampled with the same fiber and the same procedure described for rice, as well as was analysed by GC/MS set at the identical conditions of biological samples.</p><p id="Par27">To compare relative volatile emissions among different-infested rice, the variance between peak areas was analysed using JMP 11<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> for each compound emitted by two or more tested treatments. Before statistical analysis, the area integration report of every identified compound was transformed into Log values. Normality distribution and variance homoscedasticity were verified by the Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk and Levene&#x02019;s test respectively. Differences in volatile emissions among different treatments were analysed using a general linear model with a normal error structure and one fixed factor: y&#x02009;=&#x02009;X&#x000df;&#x02009;+&#x02009;&#x003b5; where y is the vector of the observations, X is the incidence matrix, &#x000df; is the vector of fixed effect (i.e. treatment), and &#x003b5; is the vector of the random residual effects. We used the False Discovery Rate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup> to control for the experiment-wide error rate inherent in large numbers of comparisons. Principal Component Analysis (PCA), followed by Multi-Factorial Analysis (MFA), was performed on transformed values of each VOCs using JMP 11<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> software. MFA was achieved using a principal component procedure and a VARIMAX orthogonal rotation technique, and the scores of common factors were calculated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Data availability</title><p id="Par28">The datasets generated and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec12"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_20420_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Files</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-20420-2.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Dr. F. Araniti for his technical assistance. G. Giunti is funded by AGRIFOODTECH PON03 PE_00090_2 Modelli sostenibili e nuove tecnologie per la valorizzazione delle olive e dell&#x02019;olio extravergine di oliva prodotto in Calabria (Grant ID: 14/2016/AGRARIA). Funders had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>G.G., V.P., G.M.A. and O.C. equally contributed to conceive and conduct the experiments, analyse the data, interpret the results and prepare the manuscript. All authors approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par29">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajendran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of insect infestation in stored foods</article-title><source>Adv. Food Nutr. Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1043-4526(05)49005-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15797346?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15797346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zettler</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical control of stored product insects with fumigants and residual treatments</article-title><source>Crop Prot.</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0261-2194(00)00075-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barreca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardinali</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fichera</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamberto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Modica</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety performance assessment of food industry facilities using a fuzzy approach</article-title><source>J. Agric. Eng.</source><year>2013</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>291</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barreca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardinali</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgese</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of the roughness of floor tiles on the cleanability from wheat flour residues in agri-food buildings</article-title><source>J. Food, Agric. Environ.</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of an anti-insect sachet using a polyvinyl alcohol&#x02212;cinnamon oil polymer strip against <italic>Plodia interpunctella</italic></article-title><source>J. Food Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>E1713</fpage><lpage>E1720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.12268</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24245888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24245888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campolo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Response of four stored products insects to a structural heat treatment in a flour mill</article-title><source>J. Stored Prod. Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jspr.2013.05.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Prozell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Kirshi</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichmuth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards biological control as a major component of integrated pest management in stored product protection</article-title><source>J. Stored Prod. Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-474X(96)00048-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajendran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sriranjini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant products as fumigants for stored-product insect control</article-title><source>J. Stored Prod. Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jspr.2007.08.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campolo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of inert dusts applied alone and in combination with sweet orange essential oil against <italic>Rhyzopertha dominica</italic> (Coleoptera: Bostrichidae) and wheat microbial population</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2014</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2014.07.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campolo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fumigant bioactivity of five <italic>Citrus</italic> essential oils against <italic>Tribolium confusum</italic></article-title><source>Phytoparasitica</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12600-013-0355-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Athanassiou</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavallieratos</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Trematerra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responses of <italic>Sitophilus oryzae</italic> (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) and <italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae) to traps baited with pheromones and food volatiles</article-title><source>Eur. J. Entomol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14411/eje.2006.050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insect populations in wheat, corn, and oats stored on the farm</article-title><source>J. Econ. Entomol.</source><year>1983</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/76.6.1323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulasare</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality resulting from interactions between the red flour beetle and the rusty grain beetle</article-title><source>Proc. Entomol. Soc. Manitoba</source><year>2001</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hulasare</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>NDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayas</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of suboptimal temperatures and sublethal CO<sub>2</sub> levels on multiplication of <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae), alone or competing with <italic>Cryptolestes ferrugineus</italic> (Coleoptera: Cucujidae)</article-title><source>J. Stored Prod. Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jspr.2004.02.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hulasare</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>NDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayas</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Demianyk</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intra- and interspecific interactions among <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> and <italic>Cryptolestes ferrugineus</italic> in stored wheat at different insect densities</article-title><source>Phytoprotection</source><year>2003</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7202/007441ar</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Futuyma</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insect-Plant Interactions: The Evolution of Component Communities</article-title><source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci.</source><year>1996</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>1361</fpage><lpage>1366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.1996.0119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Giunti, G. <italic>et al</italic>. VOCs-mediated location of olive fly larvae by the braconid parasitoid <italic>Psyttalia concolor</italic>: a multivariate comparison among VOC bouquets from three olive cultivars. <italic>Biomed Res. Int</italic>. <bold>2016</bold>, (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trematerra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Athanassiou</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavallieratos</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kernel-kernel interactions and behavioral responses of <italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic> Motschulsky (Coleoptera: Curculionidae)</article-title><source>Appl. Entomol. Zool.</source><year>2007</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1303/aez.2007.129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nufio</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Papaj</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host marking behavior in phytophagous insects and parasitoids</article-title><source>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</source><year>2001</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1570-7458.2001.00827.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ukeh</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodcock</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Birkett</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of host kairomones from maize, <italic>Zea mays</italic>, for the maize weevil, <italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic></article-title><source>J. Chem. Ecol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1402</fpage><lpage>1409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-012-0191-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23053917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23053917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steidle</surname><given-names>JLM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gantert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do grains whisper for help? Evidence for herbivore-induced synomones in wheat grains</article-title><source>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</source><year>2005</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1570-7458.2005.00295.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolutionary context for herbivore-induced plant volatiles: beyond the &#x02018;cry for help&#x02019;</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2009.12.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20047849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20047849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Giunti, G., Benelli, G., Flamini, G., Michaud, J. P. &#x00026; Canale, A. Innate and learned responses of the tephritid parasitoid <italic>Psyttalia concolor</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) to olive volatiles induced by <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) infestation. <italic>J. Econ. Entomol</italic>. (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Halitschke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specificity and complexity: the impact of herbivore-induced plant responses on arthropod community structure</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2007.06.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17652009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17652009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Flinn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagstrum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Toews</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Meikle</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interspecific associations among stored-grain beetles</article-title><source>J. Stored Prod. Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jspr.2009.04.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the insect community in a stored-maize facility</article-title><source>Ecol. Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1703.2003.00624.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ukeh</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Behavioural responses of the maize weevil, <italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic>, to host (stored-grain) and non-host plant volatiles</article-title><source>Pest Manag. Sci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ps.1828</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19760598?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19760598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wenda-Piesik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Piesik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wawrzyniak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> responses to blends of cereal kernels and plant volatiles</article-title><source>J. Appl. Entomol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>558</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jen.12284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trematerra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ianiro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Athanassiou</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavallieratos</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral responses of <italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic> Motschulsky adults to conditioned grain kernels</article-title><source>J. Stored Prod. Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jspr.2013.02.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodale</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Magrath</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieh</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruxton</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interspecific information transfer influences animal community structure</article-title><source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2010.01.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20153073?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20153073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Athanassiou, C. G., Kavallieratos, N. G., Throne, J. E. &#x00026; Nakas, C. T. Competition among species of stored-product psocids (Psocoptera) in stored grain. <italic>PLoS One</italic><bold>9</bold>, (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wearing</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sait</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two-species asymmetric competition: effects of age structure on intra- and interspecific interactions</article-title><source>J. Anim. Ecol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2656.2006.01185.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17184356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17184356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Butterflies and plants: a study of coevolution</article-title><source>Evolution (N. Y).</source><year>1964</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>608</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Germinara</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>De Cristofaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotundo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrophysiological and behavioral responses of <italic>Theocolax elegans</italic> (Westwood) (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae) to cereal grain volatiles</article-title><source>Biomed Res. Int.</source><year>2016</year><volume>2016</volume><fpage>5460819</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/5460819</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26904680?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26904680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sitophilus zeamais -induced rice grain volatiles: attractiveness towards the generalist parasitoid wasp</article-title><source>Theocolax elegans. Pakistan J. Zool</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1817</fpage><lpage>1824</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collatz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steidle</surname><given-names>JLM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hunting for moving hosts: <italic>Cephalonomia tarsalis</italic>, a parasitoid of free-living grain beetles</article-title><source>Basic Appl. Ecol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.baae.2007.04.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>F&#x000fc;rstenau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host Habitat Volatiles Enhance the Olfactory Response of the Larval Parasitoid <italic>Holepyris sylvanidis</italic> to Specifically Host-Associated Cues</article-title><source>Chem. Senses</source><year>2016</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>bjw065</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/chemse/bjw065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trematerra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sciarreta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamasi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioural responses of <italic>Oryzaephilus surinamensis</italic>, <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> and <italic>Tribolium confusum</italic> to naturally and artificially damaged durum wheat kernels</article-title><source>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</source><year>2000</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1570-7458.2000.00619.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trematerra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ianiro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Athanassiou</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavallieratos</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral interactions between <italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic> and <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic>: the first colonizer matters</article-title><source>J. Pest Sci. (2004).</source><year>2015</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10340-014-0633-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response of the females of <italic>Trogoderma granarium</italic> (Coleoptera, Dermestidae) to cuticular free fatty acids</article-title><source>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</source><year>1971</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1570-7458.1971.tb00169.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;rjesson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000f6;llman</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Schn&#x000fc;rer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile metabolites produced by six fungal species compared with other indicators of fungal growth on cereal grains</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>1992</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>2599</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1514807?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1514807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaminski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stawicki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasowicz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile Flavor Compounds Produced by Molds of <italic>Aspergillus</italic>, <italic>Penicillium</italic>, and Fungi imperfecti</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol.</source><year>1974</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1001</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16349989?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16349989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of fungal colonization of wheat grains with <italic>Fusarium</italic> spp. on food choice, weight rain and mortality of meal beetle larvae (<italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic>)</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e100112</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24932485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24932485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamboni</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Propagation of mycotoxigenic fungi in maize stores by post-harvest insects</article-title><source>Int. J. Trop. Insect Sci.</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1742758409391511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Steidle</surname><given-names>JLM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruther</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host habitat assessment by a parasitoid using fungal volatiles</article-title><source>Front. Zool.</source><year>2007</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-9994-4-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17284315?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17284315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">El-Sayed, A. M. The pherobase: database of pheromones and semiochemicals. (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The function of terpene natural products in the natural world</article-title><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.2007.5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17576428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17576428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaspar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Haubruge</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of grain quantity on the biology of <italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic> Motschulsky (Coleoptera: Curculionidae): oviposition, distribution of eggs, adult emergence, body weight and sex ratio</article-title><source>J. Stored Prod. Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-474X(01)00027-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Danho, M. &#x00026; Haubruge, E. Optimal clutch size and oviposition strategy for the maize weevil, <italic>Sitophilus zeamais</italic>. in <italic>Advances in stored product protection. Proceedings of the 8th International Working Conference on Stored Product Protection</italic> 271&#x02013;275 (2003).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>NMP</given-names></name><name><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>RNC</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Throne</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contest behaviour of maize weevil larvae when competing within seeds</article-title><source>Anim. Behav.</source><year>2010</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anbehav.2009.10.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Smith, R. H. &#x00026; Lessells, C. M. in B<italic>eha</italic>vioural <italic>Ec</italic>ology<italic>: Ecological Consequences of Adaptative Behaviour</italic> (eds Sibly, R. M. &#x00026; Smith, R. H.) 423&#x02013;448 (Blackwell Scientific, 1985).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life-cycles and competition-avoiding strategies of seed-eating weevil species on broom species (Coleoptera: Curculionidae/Leguminosae: Genisteae)</article-title><source>Entomol. Gen.</source><year>1999</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1127/entom.gen/24/2000/237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves-Costa</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Knogge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larval competition in weevils <italic>Revena rubiginosa</italic> (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) preying on seeds of the palm <italic>Syagrus romanzoffiana</italic> (Arecaceae)</article-title><source>Naturwissenschaften</source><year>2005</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00114-005-0620-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15871001?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15871001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denno</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interspecific interactions in phytophagous insects: competition reexamined and resurrected</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Entomol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.en.40.010195.001501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Community assembly: when should history matter?</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2003</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-003-1311-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12836009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12836009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schowalter, T. D. <italic>Insect ecology: an ecosystem approach</italic>. (Academic Press, 2000).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Allen</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudolf</surname><given-names>VHW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Habitat-mediated carry-over effects lead to context-dependent outcomes of species interactions</article-title><source>J. Anim. Ecol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1646</fpage><lpage>1656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2656.12408</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26060938?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26060938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kant</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms and ecological consequences of plant defence induction and suppression in herbivore communities</article-title><source>Ann. Bot.</source><year>2015</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>1051</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcv054</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26019168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26019168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunan</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>THQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for plant-mediated competition between defoliating and gall-forming specialists attacking <italic>Solidago altissima</italic></article-title><source>Am. Midl. Nat.</source><year>2015</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1674/amid-173-02-208-217.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuwahara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Casida</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative Analysis of the Sex Pheromone of Several Phycitid Moths by Electron-capture Gas Chromatography</article-title><source>Agric. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1973</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00021369.1973.10860730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Unelius</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Valeur</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofstedt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reidentification of the female sex pheromone of the Indian meal moth, <italic>Plodia interpunctella</italic>: evidence for a four-component pheromone blend</article-title><source>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</source><year>1999</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1570-7458.1999.00533.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teal</surname><given-names>PEA</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dueben</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffelt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vick</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production and release of (Z,E)-9,12-tetradecadienal by sex pheromone glands of females of <italic>Plodia interpunctella</italic> (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae)</article-title><source>J. Chem. Ecol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02033461</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24234318?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24234318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stenhagen, E., Abrahamsson, S. &#x00026; McLafferty, F. W. <italic>Registry of mass spectral data</italic>. (Wiley New York, 1974).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Masada, Y. <italic>Analysis of essential oils by gas chromatography and mass spectrometry</italic>. (Wiley New York, 1976).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Adams, R. P. <italic>Identification of essential oil components by gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</italic>. (Allured Publishing Corporation, 1995).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title><source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society B</source><year>1995</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macciotta</surname><given-names>NPP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicario</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Mauro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappio-Borlino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A multivariate approach to modeling shapes of individual lactation curves in cattle</article-title><source>J. Dairy Sci.</source><year>2004</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1092</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(04)73255-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15259245?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15259245</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>