<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6343584</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5877</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Agricultural Science</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Mycology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Soil Science</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Food, Water and Energy Nexus</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling treatment with System of Rice Intensification management and with conventional management of transplanted rice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Khadka</surname><given-names>Ram B.</given-names></name><email>khadka.13@osu.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>Norman</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Regional Agricultural Research Station, Nepal Agricultural Research Council</institution>, <city>Khajura</city>, <state>Banke</state>, <country>Nepal</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Plant Pathology, The Ohio State University</institution>, <city>Wooster</city>, <state>OH</state>, <country>United States of America</country></aff><aff id="aff-3"><label>3</label><institution>SRI-Rice, International Programs (IP/CALS), Cornell University</institution>, <city>Ithaca</city>, <state>NY</state>, <country>United States of America</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Landa</surname><given-names>Blanca</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2019-01-11"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e5877</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-06-07"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-10-05"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2019 Khadka and Uphoff</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khadka and Uphoff</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/5877"/><abstract><p>Many benefits of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation for improving crop production have been documented, including growth and yield enhancement and the alleviation of biotic and abiotic stresses. However, because rice is usually cultivated under continuous flooding that creates anaerobic soil conditions, this limits the benefits of these beneficial fungi. Cultivating rice with the methods of the System of Rice Intensification (SRI) provides rice plants with a more favorable environment for their colonization by beneficial microbes in the soil because the soil is more aerobic under SRI management and contains more organic matter. This study evaluated the effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation of rice plants under SRI management compared with transplanted and flooded rice plants, considering also the effects of different means of fertilization and different varieties in rice. Experiments were conducted in 2015 and 2016 under the tropical climate of Nepal&#x02019;s western terai (plains) during both the rainy season (July to November) and the dry season (March to July). The results indicated significantly better performance (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.01) associated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation for both seasons and for both systems of crop management in terms of grain yield and other growth-contributing factors, compared to non-inoculated rice cropping. Relatively higher effects on grain yield were recorded also with organic compared to inorganic fertilization; for unimproved (heirloom) varieties compared with improved varieties; and from SRI vs. conventional flooded crop management. The yield increase with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> treatments across all trials was 31% higher than in untreated plots (4.9 vs 4.5 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). With <italic>Trichoderma</italic> treatment, yields compared with non-treated plots were 24% higher with organic SRI (6.38 vs 5.13 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and 52% higher with non-organic SRI (6.38 vs 3.53 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). With regard to varietal differences, under SRI management <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation of the improved variety Sukhadhan-3 led to 26% higher yield (6.35 vs 5.04 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), and with the heirloom variety Tilkidhan, yield was 41% higher (6.29 vs 4.45 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Economic analysis indicated that expanding the organic cultivation of local landraces under SRI management should be profitable for farmers where such rice has a good market price due to its premium quality and high demand and when SRI enhances yield. These varieties&#x02019; present low yields can be significantly increased by integrating <italic>Trichoderma</italic> bio-inoculation with SRI cultural methods. Other recent research has shown that such inoculation can be managed profitably by farmers themselves.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Beneficial Microbes</kwd><kwd>Premium Rice Land-races</kwd><kwd>Organic Farming</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Nepal Agricultural Research Council</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was financially supported by the Nepal Agricultural Research Council. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Microorganisms are a vital but unseen constituent of farming systems. Many free-living microorganisms establish beneficial biological relationships with crop plants by living in the rhizosphere around the roots and by colonizing plants&#x02019; roots, an effect not limited to leguminous crops. Some microorganisms also inhabit tissues and cells within plants&#x02019; above-ground organs as well as in their roots, living inside the plants as symbiotic endophytes (<xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Uphoff et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>While many microorganisms are predatory or parasitic, the majority live harmoniously and even beneficially with their plant hosts (<xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Parmar &#x00026; Dadarwal, 1999</xref>). They have capability to influence plants&#x02019; physiological processes, enhance their growth and development, and make plants more tolerant of biotic and abiotic stresses (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Dardanelli et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Berendsen, Pieterse &#x00026; Bakker, 2012</xref>).</p><p>The concept of <italic>microbiota</italic>, which refers to the ensemble of diverse microbes, particularly bacterial and fungal, that reside around, on, and inside plants (the latter as endophytes), has been gaining currency in the literature (<xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000fc;ller et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Hacquard, 2016</xref>). So has the concept of <italic>holobionts</italic>, which refers to the composite entities where microbiota are living symbiotically with their host plants (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Margulis &#x00026; Fester, 1991</xref>).</p><p>To date, most attention has been given to free-living endophytic bacteria such as plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria (PGPR) (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Glick, Karaturov&#x000ed;c &#x00026; Newell , 1995</xref>). But free-living beneficial fungi known as plant growth-promoting fungi (PGPF) may be as significant. Much research has already been done on mycorrhizal fungi, which are resident in plants&#x02019; roots and acquire significant amounts of water and nutrients (especially P) through their hyphal filaments which extend from the root system into the surrounding soil. These symbionts share the water and nutrients with their plant cell hosts and in turn receive carbohydrates and other compounds that have been synthesized by the plant (<xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Hirsch et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Sarma, Oehrle &#x00026; Emerich, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Parniske, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Lanfranco, Fiorilli &#x00026; Gutjahr, 2018</xref>).</p><p>The study of mycorrhizal fungi extends back well over 150&#x000a0;years (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Frank, 2005</xref>). In more recent years, increasing attention has been given to other fungi that have symbiotic, mutually-beneficial relationships with plants. These fungi can enhance crops&#x02019; growth and yield through the production of phytohormones, through phosphate solubilization, through cellulose degradation, and siderophore production (<xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Smith &#x00026; Read, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Balestrini et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Doni et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>These fungal microbes change the physiochemical properties of the rhizosphere, among other things producing exopolysaccharides and forming biofilms. They also induce osmoprotectants and heat-shock proteins in cells, thereby making the plant better able to resist abiotic stresses such as salinity, drought, cold, and high temperature (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Redman et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Redman et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Grover et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>). Furthermore, plant-fungi associations can change the growing environment, making it more congenial for plants&#x02019; growth and development (<xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Schenk, Carvalhais &#x00026; Kazan, 2012</xref>). Thus, free-living PGPF play a vital although unobserved role in terrestrial ecosystems (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Cox, Eaton &#x00026; Scott, 2010</xref>). Here we focus on a less-studied fungal genus that can have similar beneficial effects.</p><p><italic>Trichoderma</italic> (teleomorph <italic>Hypocrea</italic>) is a ubiquitously-distributed genus of fungi that can be symbiotically associated with plant roots (<xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Vargas, Mandawe &#x00026; Kenerley, 2009</xref>). These fungal species provide major benefits in farming systems such as the mitigation of biotic and abiotic stresses (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Harman, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">De Souza et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Harman et al., 2010</xref>); the enhancement of plant growth regulators (<xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Yedidia et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Harman &#x00026; Shoresh, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Shoresh, Harman &#x00026; Mastouri, 2010</xref>); bioremediation and detoxification of harmful chemicals such as DDT, dieldrin, endosulfan, pentachloronitrobenzene, and pentachlorophenol (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Katayama &#x00026; Matsumura, 1993</xref>); suppression of phytopathogens; nutrient mobilization in the rhizosphere; and enhancement of plants&#x02019; defense mechanisms (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Bae et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Higher biomass production, better seedling vigor, and lower impact of biotic and abiotic stresses have been observed in a variety of crops when their seeds were treated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Chang, 1986</xref>; <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Mastouri, Bj&#x000f6;rkman &#x00026; Harman, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Rego et al., 2014</xref>)<italic>.</italic> However, because rice, the staple food for over half the world&#x02019;s population, is grown in inundated fields wherever there is sufficient water available, this flooding creates a soil environment that is inhospitable for <italic>Trichoderma</italic> and other fungi because these aerobic organisms cannot grow well under hypoxic flooded conditions.</p><p>A rice culture methodology that is gaining attention and acceptance, known as the System of Rice Intensification (SRI), relies on alternate wetting and drying (AWD) of rice paddies rather than on their continuous inundation. AWD enhances water use efficiency in rice production along with increased land and water productivity (<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Carrijo, Lundy &#x00026; Linquist, 2017</xref>). This change in standard water management methods for growing rice creates a hospitable environment for aerobic soil microbes, both bacteria and fungi. SRI methods enhance the soil environment for microbes by favoring the use of organic materials for soil fertilization in preference to inorganic means. Further, the use of a simple mechanical rotary weeder to control weeds breaks up and aerates the top layers of soil at the same time that it eliminates weeds, burying them as green manure, which also enhances the environment for soil microbial populations (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Anas et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>SRI achieves higher productivity by improving the growing environment for rice rather than by relying on making changes in crop genetic potential and applying agrochemical inputs. While there are some benefits from continuous flooding of the soil as done in conventional rice production, it has deleterious effects for rice root systems, such as deforming their cortex to create air pockets (aerenchyma) in the roots (<xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Kirk &#x00026; Bouldin, 1991</xref>), inhibiting root respiration, and causing degeneration of roots due to hypoxia (<xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Kar et al., 1974</xref>). Continuous flooding can slow down root metabolism, ion transport, and root and canopy growth (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Barison &#x00026; Uphoff, 2011</xref>) at the same time that it suppresses beneficial soil microbes which thrive under aerobic conditions.</p><p>By rapidly depleting the oxygen level in bulk soil (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Liesack, Schnell &#x00026; Revsbech, 2000</xref>), flooding promotes the growth of anaerobic microorganisms such as fermentative bacteria and methanogenic archaea so that these become dominant rather than PGPR and PGPF. The practices of SRI create a different and more productive environment for growing rice. They combine a number of changes in the standard methods of rice production: plant density is optimally low; very young seedlings are transplanted with minimum &#x02018;shock&#x02019;; paddy soils are alternately wetted and dried, not flooded; active soil aeration is part of weeding operations; and soil organic matter is enhanced (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Thakur, Uphoff &#x00026; Antony, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Barison &#x00026; Uphoff, 2011</xref>).</p><p>These practices suggest that SRI should be compatible with, and its benefits could be further amplified by, the incorporation of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> into this rice cropping system. One feature of SRI methodology is the transplanting of young seedlings, for better crop establishment, before the start of their 4th phyllochron of growth, so as to maintain more of the plants&#x02019; inherent potential for tillering and root growth (<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Nemoto, Morita &#x00026; Baba, 1995</xref>). Transplanting rice seedlings from a nursery into the field, however, is an operation in which seedlings are vulnerable to injury, disease, and abiotic stresses. The treatment of seedlings with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> during transplanting operations could help young rice plants buffer these stresses, with a positive impact on eventual yield.</p><p>Research is needed on the possible role of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spp. in enhancing rice crop phenology and yield, to assess the potentials of these fungi to act as plant growth regulators/promoters and as disease suppressors. This present study was designed to evaluate the effects that native <italic>Trichoderma</italic> isolates, taken from local soils in Nepal, might have on the growth and performance of rice plants grown under SRI management vs. conventional methods (transplanting of older seedlings, closely spaced, and flooded) and also to assess the effects of organic vs. inorganic fertilization as well as of using improved vs. local varieties under the agroecosystem conditions of western Nepal.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>Experiments were conducted in two consecutive seasons: a rainy season (July to November 2015), and a dry season (March to July 2016). Both experiments were conducted in a tropical environment, 181&#x000a0;m above sea level, at the Regional Agricultural Research Station (RARS) in Khajura, Banke district, Nepal. This is located at 81&#x000b0;37&#x02033;E longitude and 28&#x000b0;06&#x02033;N latitude. The soil of the experimental plot was sandy loam (68% sand, 22% silt, and 10% clay), poor in organic matter (1.97%) and available potassium (97.7&#x000a0;kg ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), and medium in available nitrogen (0.16%) and phosphorus (51.4&#x000a0;kg ha-1). The soil pH was neutral to slightly alkaline (7.2).</p><p>The first experiment was conducted with a split-plot design where the main plot evaluated the methods of SRI with either organic or inorganic fertilization. Two different varieties were planted in the subplots. A popular local unimproved variety known as Tilki (formally designated as Tilkidhan #8) was evaluated. Its seeds were obtained from a community seed bank in Beluwa, Bardia, which is managed by a non-governmental organization, Local Initiatives for Biodiversity, Research, and Development (LI-BIRD), based in Pokhara, Nepal. This &#x02018;heirloom&#x02019; landrace which has a crop cycle of 145&#x02013;150 days is considered to have medicinal properties and to be tolerant of flooding. Its market price is high because of its unique aroma and texture (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Maharjan, Gurung &#x00026; Sthapit, 2013</xref>). The improved variety used in the first trials was a drought-tolerant variety, Sukha-3 (Sukhadhan-3), which has medium-length grain and a relatively short cycle, 125 days. This recently-released, photoperiod-insensitive variety was originally introduced from the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) in the Philippines.</p><p>For the SRI trials, 10-day-old seedlings were transplanted individually at spacing of 25&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;25&#x000a0;cm in a grid square pattern. Alternate drying and wetting was maintained as much as possible up to 60&#x02013;70 days after transplanting (DAT). A rotary weeder was used at 25 and 45 DAT to remove weeds and create some aeration of the rhizosphere. In the inorganic treatments, soil fertilization was done with 100&#x000a0;kg of nitrogen, 30&#x000a0;kg of phosphorus, and 30&#x000a0;kg of potassium per hectare, provided respectively through urea, diammonium phosphate, and potassium chloride, along with 10 tonnes per ha of farmyard manure (FYM). In the organic treatments, 20 tonnes of farm yard manure (FYM) per ha were applied, without any amendments of inorganic fertilizer. With both methods of cultivation, the FYM was incorporated one week before transplanting. For the inorganic fertilization, 50% of the N and all of the P and K were applied at the final stage of land preparation (puddling), with the remaining 50% of N applied in split treatments at 30 and 60 days after transplanting.</p><p>The second experiment was conducted with a similar factorial design where the main factor was seedling treatment, either with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> (bio-inoculated) or no treatment (no inoculation), with then three variants of management as the sub-factors: organic SRI (org SRI), inorganic SRI (inorg SRI), and conventional transplanting (CT). In this experiment, a short-duration (125-day) variety (Chaite-2) was used, recommended for dry-season cultivation in the terai (southern plain) and inner terai (plain region between Churiya hills and Mahabharat mountain range) regions of Nepal. All of the agronomic practices in SRI method were applied as mentioned earlier; however, the age of seedling was 18 days (at 3-leaf stage) because of the slower seedling growth associated with lower night temperatures in that season. In the conventional management trials, seedlings were transplanted at the 5&#x02013;6 leaf stage, with 15&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;15&#x000a0;cm spacing and three seedlings per hill. This made the respective plant densities 133 plants per m<sup>2</sup> for CT and 16 plants per m<sup>2</sup> in the SRI trials. The researchers tried to keep the CT plots continuously flooded during the crop&#x02019;s entire life cycle, except from 15&#x02013;20 days before harvesting.</p><p>In both sets of experiments, the individual plot sizes were 15 m<sup>2</sup>, and each treatment was replicated three times. For the bio-inoculation treatments, the seedlings were dipped in a <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spore suspension for 10 to 20&#x000a0;min before transplanting. The <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strain used was one reported to be a native isolate of Nepal, <italic>Trichoderma viride</italic> which is commercially produced and distributed by Agri-Care Nepal Pvt. Ltd. based in Bharatpur, Chitwan. The final concentration of the suspension used for seedling treatment was about 10<sup>6</sup> spores per ml. In the non-inoculation treatments, seedlings were transplanted without such treatment. For weed control in the SRI trials, a rotary weeder was used two times at 20 and 40 days after transplanting, to also give aeration to the rhizosphere; in the CT trials, hand weeding was done at 30 days after transplanting.</p><p>Data were collected on grain yield, grain weight (thousand-grain weight in g), panicle length, number of panicles hill<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, plant height, and number of grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. All these parameters were recorded during harvesting. Panicle length, number of panicles hill<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, and number of grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were recorded from the central area of the plot to avoid any border effect. Grain moisture was measured with a moisture meter (WILE Twister Grain Moisture Meter), and both grain weight and grain yield were adjusted to a 14% grain moisture level.</p><p>The normality of the data was tested by the Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test. Normally-distributed data were subjected to analysis of variance (ANOVA) testing using RStudio (R-3.2.5) (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">RStudio Support, 2018</xref>). When there was a significant difference between the treatment means, Fisher tests of least significant difference (LSD) were applied. Data that were not normally distributed were transformed to log before proceeding for ANOVA and the value of back transformed were presented. Multiple Factor Analysis was also done in RStudio using packages FactoMineR and factoextra (<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Le, Josse &#x00026; Husson, 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Effect of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling treatment with different rice cultivation methods</title><p>Measures of grain yield, grain test weight, and number of panicles hill<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> averaged across the three different methods of crop establishment showed significantly better crop performance with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling treatment. The values of these three parameters comparing bio-inoculated vs. non-inoculated plants in their respective plots were, respectively, 5.9 vs. 4.7 tonnes ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for yield; 20.6 vs. 19.5 grams for 1000-grain weight; and 11.8 vs. 10.7 for panicles hill<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The yield increases recorded with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> treatment thus averaged 26% across the three methods of crop establishment compared to non-treated samples. Grain weight with inoculation was 5% higher, and panicles hill<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were 9% more.</p><p>Similarly, there was significantly higher yield, grain weight, plant height, and more panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> in organic SRI that had been treated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic>. The average yield with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation and conventional cultivation methods was 12.5% higher compared to untreated plots. In comparison with results from non-treated rice plants using the respective methods in the dry season 2016, average yields from the <italic>Trichoderma</italic>-treated plants under organic SRI management were 24% higher, and they were 52% higher with inorganic SRI methods. We also observed significantly higher grain yield (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.01; 6.1 vs. 4.8 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), greater grain weight (21.9 vs 19.8 gm), and taller plant height (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.02; 88.0 vs 85.2&#x000a0;cm) in the organic SRI compared to the inorganic SRI, as seen in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Growth and yield attributes affected by <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling inoculation and methods of crop establishment in dry season, 2016,</title><p>Each data point indicates the average of three replications. The error bar indicates the standard error.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Growth and yield attributes affected by <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling inoculation and methods of crop establishment in dry season, 2016.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-g005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatments</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grain yield (mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Days to maturity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant height (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of tillers per hill</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test weight (gm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Inoculation</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-inoculation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.8a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.9 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179.9 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;24.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No inoculation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180.8 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;29.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Method of cultivation</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organic SRI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.14a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.04 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.0a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;24.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.74ab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.8+1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.2 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.4b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.0b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">163.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;25.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.5b</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inorganic SRI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.2 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.2ab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.3a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">191.4 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;24.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.2ab</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1" fn-type="other"><p>Means followed by same letter(s) do not differ significantly at 5% level of probability, <italic>P</italic>, Probability value, LSD, Least significant difference. CT, Conventional transplanting with chemical fertilizer: 100:30:30&#x000a0;kg NPK and 10 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of farmyard manure (FYM), Org SRI, Organic SRI with 20 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of FYM and no chemical fertilizer applied; in the case of SRI chemical fertilizer treatments, only 100:30:30&#x000a0;kg NPK were applied. Bio-inoc: Rice seedling treated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spore suspension before transplanting, Non-inoc: No inoculation with <italic>Trichoderma</italic>. The values behind &#x000b1;&#x000a0;indicates standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling treatment in heirloom vs. improved varieties with either organic vs. inorganic versions of SRI management</title><p>An experiment was conducted in the main rice-growing season 2015 at RARS in Khajura where two varieties of rice were planted with SRI methods&#x02014;Tilki, an aromatic heirloom variety, and Sukhadhan-3, an improved, drought-tolerant variety&#x02014;having either <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling treatment or no treatment. Different parameters were considered to understand the effects of variety, bio-inoculation, and fertilization, and their interaction, under SRI management.</p><p>Analysis of variance for various crop phenological parameters showed significant differences among the treatments with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation or no inoculation, organic or inorganic fertilization, local or improved varieties, and their interactions. Significant effect on grain yield was observed across all the trials between organic and inorganic fertilization (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.02). Furthermore, SRI management with organic fertilization, the values for number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, number of filled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and panicle length were all higher compared to inorganic fertilization under SRI management (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). Under SRI management, there was significantly higher grain yield (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001) on average across all trials in the <italic>Trichoderma</italic>-inoculated plots compared to non-inoculated rice plots.</p><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling treatment on yield and different growth attributes under SRI management in main season, 2015.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-g006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatments</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grain yield (mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<sup>z</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panicle length (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of filled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of unfilled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thousand- grain weight (gm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Variety</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sukhadhan-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.5 (0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;20.2b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.4b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;31.7b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.6a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tilkidhan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.5 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.5a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;30.2a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.0a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">194.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;17.5a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.54b</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Method of fertilization</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inorganic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.8 (0.6b)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;46.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.0 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;39.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.09 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9 (0.7a)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;45.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178.0 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;22.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.01 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Inoculation</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-inoculation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.8 (0.8a)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.7 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">187.9 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;48.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;11.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.9 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.01 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No inoculation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.6 (0.6b)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;43.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.26 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177.25 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;30.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.08 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1" fn-type="other"><p>Means followed by same letter(s) do not differ significantly at 5% level of probability, ns = non-significant at 5% level of probability. Bio-inoculation is seedling treated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spore suspension before transplanting, the values behind &#x000b1; indicates standard deviation, <sup>z</sup> values inside the parenthesis indicates the log transformed values.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling treatment on yield and different growth attributes under SRI management in main season 2015.</title><p>Each data point indicates the average of three replications. The error bar indicates the standard error. Means followed by same letter(s) do not differ significantly at 5% level of probability.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-g002"/></fig><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> seedling treatment on yield and different growth attributes, average for two varieties, under SRI management in the main season, 2015.</title><p>Each data point indicates the average of three replications. Means followed by same letter (s) do not differ significantly at 5% level of probability. The error bar indicate standard error.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-g003"/></fig><p>Interaction effects of fertilization and bio-inoculation were found to be significant in grain yield, while other parameters were statistically at par in bio-inoculated and non-inoculated plots with organic and inorganic fertilization. The effect of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation on grain yield was significantly higher with organic compared to inorganic fertilization (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). Further, the heirloom variety was found to be more responsive to bio-inoculation with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> than was the improved variety.</p><p>The heirloom variety Tilki had significantly longer panicle length and a higher number of filled grains than the improved variety Sukhadhan-3. However, no significant effect of bio-inoculation and fertilization was recorded in panicle length and number of filled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The number of filled grains and number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> were higher in the bio-inoculated treatments than in the non-inoculated treatments (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Interaction effects of bio-inoculation, method of cultivation, and varieties on yield and yield-contributing parameters under SRI management</title><p>Significant effects of treatment interaction on grain yield were observed in both experiments. With SRI as the method of cultivation, the highest grain yield among all the treatment interactions was with Sukha-3 + bio-inoculation + organic fertilization (6.5 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). This was, however, not much higher than the Tilki + bio-inoculation + inorganic fertilization treatment (6.3 mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The lowest yield was with Tilki + non-inoculation + inorganic fertilizer, which showed that this landrace did not respond very favorably to chemical fertilizer and <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation under SRI management in main rice season 2015.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-g007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatments</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grain yield (mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<sup>z</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panicle length (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (no.)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unfilled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (no.)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panicle m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (no.)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test grain weight (gm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sukha-3 + bio-inoc + inorg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2 (0.7ab)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.7 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;17.8bc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.5abc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;36.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.50a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sukha-3 + bio-inoc + org</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.5 (0.8a)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158.8 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.6bc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.6c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">154.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;15.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.31a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sukha-3 + no inoc + inorg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1 (0.6c)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.2 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;26.8bc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.9bc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160.0 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;57.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.7 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.68a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sukha-3 + no inoc + org</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.8 (0.7ab)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.9 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;24.7c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.8c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;11.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.85a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tilki + bio-inoc + inorg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2 (0.7ab)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246.8 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.0a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.1a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;24.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.00b</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tilki + bio-inoc + org</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1 (0.8a)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;49.9abc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.5abc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.94 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.62b</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tilki + no inoc + inorg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.5 (0.4c)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;22.9abc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.7ab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">195.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.28b</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tilki + no inoc + org</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.6 (0.75ab)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.4 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.5ab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.4a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181.3 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;23.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08b</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-3fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-3fn1" fn-type="other"><p>Means followed by same letter(s) do not differ significantly at 5% level of probability, <italic>P</italic>, Probability value, LSD, least significant difference; Bio-inoc, Rice seedling treated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spore suspension before transplanting, Non-inoc, <italic>Trichoderma</italic> not inoculated, the values behind &#x000b1;&#x000a0;indicates standard deviation. <sup>z</sup> values inside the parenthesis indicates the log transformed values.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> was similarly and significantly affected by the different treatments. The highest number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>was observed in Tilki + bio-inoculation + organic fertilization (201), followed closely by the other treatments, except for Sukhadhan-3 + bio-inoculation + inorganic fertilization treatment, which had the lowest number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (147).</p><p>The numbers of filled grains and unfilled grains were also found to be significantly affected by the treatments, as shown in <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Among all of the interacting treatment, the highest number of unfilled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was recorded with Tilki + no inoculation + organic fertilization (43.6), which was statistically at par with Tilki + bio-inoculation + inorganic fertilization (42.7); Tilki + no inoculation + inorganic (40.6); and Tilki + bio-inoculation + organic (35.3). The lowest number was recorded with Sukhadhan-3 + no-inoculation + organic fertilization (17.3), a large drop-off.</p><p>Similarly, the number of filled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was found to be highest also in Tilki + bio-inoculation + inorganic (246), and lowest with Sukhadhan-3 + no-inoculation + organic (135). The longest panicle length was found with Tilki + no inoculation + organic (31.7); but this was not significantly longer than with the other treatments. The lowest value for this parameter was with Sukhadhan-3 + no inoculation + inorganic (25.6) (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>).</p><p>These results are further analyzed and discussed in the section which follows, trying to parse and explain what patterning can be discerned by doing some rank-ordering of the treatments with regard to the respective parameters. From the comparisons made here, however, we already see indications of there being combined effects of organic fertilization and <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation in SRI. That the highest grain yields with both varieties were obtained with <italic>Trichoderma-</italic> treatment and organic fertilization indicated the significant role that <italic>Trichoderma</italic> can play in increasing grain yield with organic SRI methods of cultivation.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion of Results through Rank-Ordering and Multiple Factor Analysis</title><p>As with any multi-factorial evaluation, presenting results and relationships can be complicated. To gain some perspective on the above findings, we rank-ordered the results reported in <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and conducted Multiple Factor Analysis to calculate an average ranking for the eight different treatments according to the five positive parameters (grain yield, grain weight, panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, filled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and panicle length). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref> and <xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>, these numbers are shown with the treatments listed according to their average rank, the highest number representing the highest performance.</p><fig id="fig-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Multiple Factor Analysis of the interaction effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation under SRI management in main rice season 2015.</title><p>Multiple Factor Analysis results for variable group: 1. coord, Coordinates, 2. cos2, quality of representation of interactions (treatments), 3. contrib, Contributions, 4. correlation, Correlation between groups and principal dimensions</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="table-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/table-4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Rank-ordering of the effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation under SRI management in main rice season 2015.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-g008"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatments</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grain yield (mt ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panicle length</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tiller m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test grain weight (gm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average rank</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tilki + bio-inoc + org</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1st</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 (1st)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tilki + bio-inoc + inorg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3rd<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1st</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7th<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (2nd)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tilki + no inoc + org</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1st</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (3rd)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tilki + no inoc + inorg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3rd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3rd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3rd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7th<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 (4th)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sukha-3 + bio-inoc + org</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1st</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 (4th)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sukha-3 + no inoc + org</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3rd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (6th)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sukha-3 + no inoc + inorg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1st</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 (7th)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sukha-3 + bio-inoc + inorg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3rd<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8th</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 (8th)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-4fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-4fn1" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl1"><def-item><term> Bio-inoc</term><def><p>Rice seedling treated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spore suspension before transplanting</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Non-inoc</term><def><p>No <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn><fn id="table-4fn2"><label>a</label><p>Tied in rank.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figure 4</xref> Multiple Factor Analysis of the interaction effects of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation under SRI management in main rice season 2015 (Multiple Factor Analysis results for variable group: 1. coord = Coordinates, 2. cos2 = quality of representation of interactions (treatments), 3. contrib = Contributions, 4. correlation = Correlation between groups and principal dimensions) The number ranked according to the ranking of the treatments (1 is best, 7 is worst) analyzed based on five positive parameters (grain yield, grain weight, panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, filled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and panicle length).</p><p>What is seen from <xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref> is that the combination of Tilki with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation and either organic or inorganic fertilization ranks fairly consistently at the top among the treatments. Then, fairly closely ranked in the middle range come Tilki + no inoculation + organic fertilization and Sukha-3 with either no inoculation + organic fertilization or with no inoculation and inorganic fertilization. Sukha-3 under SRI management responds roughly similarly to either combination of no <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation plus NPK, or <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation plus FYM. These three treatments on average are pretty similar in their results.</p><p>Interesting results were obtained from the multiple factor analysis of the interaction effects of the different treatments. Five variable groups were considered&#x02014;coordinates, quality of representation of interaction of the treatments, contributions of the treatments, correlation between groups, and principal dimensions of the five positive parameters (grain yield, grain weight, panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, filled grains panicle<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and panicle length). Each parameter represented different groups in the analysis.</p><p>We found four distinct clustering of the treatments where non-inoculated and inorganic fertilizations made for two separate clusters for different varieties at the bottom of the graph. However, treatments with both bio-inoculation and organic fertilization appeared at the top with a higher cos2 value. We observed a clear effect of bio-inoculation and organic fertilization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref>). Thus it is easy to explain the positive effect of either organic fertilization or bio-inoculation or a combination of these in both varieties. However, ranking showed greater effect of these treatments in Tilki where Tilki + bio inoculation + organic appeared frequently in the number one ranking (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><p>Then come the other three treatments that lag fairly clearly behind the others: Sukha-3 with inoculation and inorganic fertilizer, or with no inoculation but with organic fertilization, as well as Tilki that received inorganic fertilizer and no inoculation. The HYV having been bred to be responsive to inorganic fertilizer showed no response to inoculation; fertilizing it with NPK but no inoculation gave a higher ranking (3rd) than with biofertilization (6th), an interesting finding. Overall, perhaps the most important finding was that both the modern variety and the traditional one gave their best performance when receiving both inoculation and organic fertilization.</p><p>The number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> was similarly and significantly affected by the different treatments. We observed that the highest number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> was in Tilki + bio-inoculation + organic fertilization (201), followed closely by the other treatments, except for Sukhadhan-3 + bio-inoculation + inorganic fertilization treatment, which had the lowest number of panicles m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> (147).</p><p>These results are consistent with the observation of <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Rubio et al. (2017)</xref> who when studying tomato production found higher yield and growth parameters when <italic>T.&#x000a0;harzianum</italic> (T34) was applied with inorganic NPK. On the other hand, the HYV plants when inoculated with <italic>T. harzianum</italic> and grown with chemical fertilization gave the fewest panicles per m<sup>2</sup>.</p><p>These researchers concluded that NPK-fertilized tomato plants were more sensitive to salt stress than were unfertilized ones. However, it appeared that there was some synergistic effect of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation when combined with NPK that helped the plants to combat salt stress. When unfertilized, the tomato plants were seen to have higher growth and better tolerance of salinity when inoculated with <italic>T. harzianum</italic>.</p><p>The authors proposed that NPK in T34-treated plants triggered accelerated plant growth which caused some down-regulation of phytohormone networking that made plants less able to tolerate environmental stresses. The effect could be somewhat different in HYVs, however. As we noted already, Sukhadhan 3 is a drought-tolerant variety developed by IRRI with drought-tolerance QTLs (<xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Vikram et al., 2015</xref>) that could be affected by ecosystem and environmental factors.</p><p>We saw that <italic>Trichoderma</italic> combined with NPK fertilization created a super-favorable environment for rice growth under SRI management, but with the genetic make-up of the drought-tolerant HYV, it could have some inherent limitations. There may be different QTLs in the traditional Tilki variety that do not inhibit utilization of nutrients, so the addition of nutrients from chemical fertilizer would augment the boost that <italic>Trichoderma</italic> gives rice plants under favorable conditions, resulting in higher yield from Tilki under either organic or inorganic fertilization with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation<italic>.</italic></p><sec><title>General discussion of treatment effects</title><p>SRI is a strategy for modified and careful management of plants, soil, water and nutrients to provide the rice plants with the optimum growing environment. Through its alternative wetting and drying of paddy soils and by enhancing the exchange of gases in rhizosphere regions through frequent soil disturbance by a rotary weeder, SRI can be understood as improving the conditions for growth of beneficial soil microbes. Increased levels of organic matter in the soil amplify the effects of this soil and water management. Evaluations done in India and Indonesia have found that beneficial microbial populations in the rhizosphere are generally higher under SRI management (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Anas et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p><italic>Trichoderma</italic> is one of the fungal genera in agriculture best known for growth promotion and for biological control of plant diseases (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Ben&#x000ed;tez et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Savazzini, Longa &#x00026; Pertot, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Di&#x000e1;nez Mart&#x000ed;nez et al., 2016</xref>). This genus colonizes roots and provides signaling to the plants to trigger the production of growth regulators and to induce systemic resistance to pathogens. In our study, we observed better plant architecture, higher panicle number, longer panicle length, and increased plant height in <italic>Trichoderma</italic>-inoculated SRI rice plants compared to plants inoculated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> but grown with conventional practices. This indicated that the SRI methods of cultivation produced a more hospitable environment for <italic>Trichoderma</italic> than conventional rice cultivation, as has been reported also by <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Doni et al. (2017)</xref> from their evaluations of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation of rice grown with either SRI or conventional (flooded) management.</p><p>Significant increases in grain weight and yield indicated the potential for commercial application of these techniques. The better performance of rice plants inoculated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> and having organic soil fertilization indicated the potency of these techniques for cultivating organically a rice crop and variety which has high market value and strong consumer demand.</p><p>Researchers have previously found higher grain yield, disease-resistance, and better plant architecture associated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic>-inoculated rice plants compared to non-inoculated ones. In their greenhouse experiments, (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Doni et al., 2014</xref>) found plant height, leaf number, root length, root fresh weight, and tiller number to be enhanced in <italic>Trichoderma</italic> sp. SL2-inoculated treatments compared to non-inoculated treatment. Further, it has been seen that <italic>Trichoderma</italic> altered physiological processes which enabled plants to utilize resources such as water, light and nutrients more efficiently (<xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Shoresh &#x00026; Harman, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Doni et al., 2014</xref>). <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Doni et al. (2014)</xref> have demonstrated higher photosynthetic rates, greater root length, and more water use efficiency in <italic>Trichoderma</italic>-inoculated plants. Further, our results are consistent with the recent work of <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Zaidi et al. (2017)</xref>, who found in field and village-level trials in Bihar, India, that rice plants inoculated with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strain S2 had higher grain yield compared to uninoculated treatments from the drought-tolerant rice variety <italic>Sabhagi dhan</italic>. This was found with both farmers&#x02019; practices and IRRI-recommended improved cultivation practices, with the latter giving better results.</p><p>In other reporting, <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Doni et al. (2015)</xref> have showed that <italic>Trichoderma asperellum</italic> SL2 inoculation in combination with SRI practices led to remarkably higher plant growth, germination rate, vigour index, and chlorophyll content, also prompting better plant architecture from the same genotypic potential. They concluded that SRI field management creates a more congenial environment for <italic>Trichoderma</italic> to contribute to plants&#x02019; growth and development traits, to more supportive soil conditions and nutrient uptake, and ultimately to the rice plants&#x02019; productivity, whereas conventional cultivation practices were seen to have detrimental effects. <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Doni et al. (2018)</xref> have shown further that farmers can produce and inoculate their SRI seedlings with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> on a cost-effective basis.</p><p>SRI has great promise to enhance yield of rice compared to conventional cultivation practice because it provides rice plants with a better growing environment regardless the variety used. In our second study, we observed no significant difference in yield between the improved dwarf variety Sukhadhan-3 and the heirloom, photoperiod-insensitive variety Tilkidhan. This result is consistent with a previous evaluation (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Khadka, Acharya &#x00026; Uphoff, 2014</xref>) in which, under SRI management, a two-fold increase in yield was observed from a locally-adopted rice variety known as Hansaraj Basmati in Bajang district of Nepal in the foothills of the Himalayas. Similarly, <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed, Dutta &#x00026; Ray (2015)</xref> also found the traditional variety <italic>Koiya Boro</italic> under SRI management giving a 16% higher yield compared to that from currently recommended practices, and a 33% increase compared to traditional cultivation practices.</p><p>However, higher yield response is often reported for hybrid varieties under SRI management than results obtained from traditional or improved (inbred) varieties. <xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Senthil et al. (2013)</xref> reported increased yield, reduced lodging, and faster multiplication of seed of indigenous rice varieties in Tamil Nadu state of India under system of rice intensification. They concluded that SRI methodology would be an important tool to conserve the indigenous rice varieties that are under threat of extinction as these can be produced commercially and organically under SRI management to make rice-growing more profitable and viable for farmers.</p><p>The mechanisms behind higher yield and better plant architecture as a result of inoculation with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> has been described by a number of researchers for various crops. <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Baker (1984)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Chang (1986)</xref> have described how <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation led to growth promotion in crops such as radish, pepper, cucumber and tomato. Similarly, <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Harman (2000)</xref> demonstrated that <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation leads to a proliferation of secondary roots and to increases in root length, leaf area, and seedling fresh weight. Further, <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Altomare et al. (1999)</xref> demonstrated a higher percentage of P and Fe in inoculated cucumber plants, with a significant increase in plant fresh weight and leaf area due to colonization of <italic>T. asperellum</italic> in the roots. Similarly, <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Borges Chagas et al. (2015)</xref> demonstrated highest rice biomass with most phosphate-solubilization efficiency in rice that had been inoculated with <italic>T. asperelloides</italic> and <italic>T. harzianum</italic>. They proposed that <italic>Trichoderma</italic> can enhance the availability of plant nutrients through P solubilization. Studies have also shown that <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spp produce growth-regulating phytohormones like auxin that stimulate plant growth and development (<xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Contreras-Cornejo et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>This study also evaluated the performance of two different and contrasting rice varieties under organic SRI management. We observed no significant difference in their grain yield and other parameters under either organic or inorganic fertilization when grown under SRI management. This indicated that SRI methods can match the higher-cost methods of input-dependent &#x02018;modern&#x02019; agriculture through organic farming practices that are both less expensive and more environmentally-friendly.</p><p>Further, the very positive and productive response of an &#x02018;unimproved&#x02019; heirloom variety when grown with organic SRI methods showed that this could even be superior to &#x02018;improved&#x02019; varieties under optimizing crop management in terms of economic profitability. Similar results have been reported also by <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Debbarma et al. (2015)</xref> who observed higher grain yield and other parameters in Japonica rice under SRI management compared to conventional transplanting in organic production. We observed better grain yield when <italic>Trichoderma</italic> was bio-inoculated in organically-fertilized rice compared to inorganic fertilization. Plant-growth-promoting fungi such as <italic>Trichoderma</italic> are supported by having more access to organic matter in the soil, while inorganic fertilization can have a detrimental effect on these soil microbes, e.g., by altering the soil pH. <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al. (2017)</xref> recently recorded elevated microbial counts (fungal, bacterial and actinomycetes) with organic SRI compared to both inorganic SRI and conventional transplanting methods.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study has shown the significant potential of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> for increasing both rice grain yield and quality, especially in combination with SRI management practices. More effect was seen with the landrace Tilki than with the HYV Sukha-5. The analysis here found the efficiency of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> to be greater with organic than with inorganic methods of cultivation. This effect in organic systems would be due to the more hospitable environment for <italic>Trichoderma</italic> build-up.</p><p>The use of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation as a seedling treatment can help to enhance rice production and productivity in Nepal, especially in conjunction with SRI methods and even more so with organic fertilization, which in this integrated system of rice cultivation can reduce the use and cost of chemical fertilizer. In such a system under the prevailing soil and climatic conditions, an indigenous heirloom rice variety was able to outperform in both agronomic and economic terms the more modern improved variety.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title> Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Raw data</title><p>Dry season experiment</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-s001.csv"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5877/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>Raw data</title><p>Main season experiment</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-5877-s002.csv"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Ram B. Khadka</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft, submission of article.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Norman Uphoff</xref> prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft, got review from non-author.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The raw data are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplemental-information">Supplemental Files</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Ahmed, Dutta &#x00026; Ray (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Response of some rice varieties to different crop management practices towards morphological and yield parameters</article-title><source>International Journal of Scientific and Research Publications</source><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Altomare et al. (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altomare</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Norvell</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solubilization of phosphates and micronutrients by the plant-growth-promoting and biocontrol fungus <italic>Trichoderma harzianum</italic> Rifai 1295-22</article-title><source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>2926</fpage><lpage>2933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10388685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Anas et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupela</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiyagarajan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>A review of studies on SRI effects on beneficial organisms in rice soil rhizospheres</article-title><source>Paddy and Water Environment</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10333-011-0260-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Bae et&#x000a0;al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sicher</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Strem</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Melnick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The beneficial endophyte <italic>Trichoderma</italic> hamatum isolate DIS 219b promotes growth and delays the onset of the drought response in Theobroma cacao</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>3279</fpage><lpage>3295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Baker (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><article-title>The controlled experiment in the scientific method with special emphasis on biological control</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>1021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/Phyto-74-1019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Balestrini et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balestrini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;ther</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfante</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Tullio</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Ascorbate oxidase: the unexpected involvement of a wasteful enzyme in the symbioses with nitrogen-fixing bacteria and arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi</article-title><source>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2012.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22863656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Barison &#x00026; Uphoff (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barison</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Rice yield and its relation to root growth and nutrient-use efficiency under SRI and conventional cultivation: an evaluation in Madagascar</article-title><source>Paddy and Water Environment</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10333-010-0229-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Ben&#x000ed;tez et&#x000a0;al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ben&#x000ed;tez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinc&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cod&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Biocontrol mechanisms of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strains</article-title><source>International Microbiology</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15666245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Berendsen, Pieterse &#x00026; Bakker (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berendsen</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>CMJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>PAHM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>The rhizosphere microbiome and plant health</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2012.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22564542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Borges&#x000a0;Chagas et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borges&#x000a0;Chagas</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chagas&#x000a0;Jr</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues&#x000a0;de Carvalho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Oliveira&#x000a0;Miller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Orozco&#x000a0;Colonia</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Evaluation of the phosphate solubilization potential of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strains (Trichoplus JCO) and effects on rice biomass</article-title><source>Journal of Soil Science and Plant Nutrition</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>794</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4067/S0718-95162015005000054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Carrijo, Lundy &#x00026; Linquist (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrijo</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundy</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Linquist</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Rice yields and water use under alternate wetting and drying irrigation: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>203</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2016.12.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Chang (1986)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year><article-title>Increased growth of plants in the presence of the biological control agent <italic>Trichoderma</italic> harzianum</article-title><source>Plant Disease</source><volume>70</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PD-70-145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>RStudio&#x000a0;Support (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Citing RStudio&#x02014;RStudio&#x000a0;Support</collab></person-group><year>2018</year><uri xlink:href="https://support.rstudio.com/hc/en-us/articles/206212048-Citing-Rstudio?mobile_site=true">https://support.rstudio.com/hc/en-us/articles/206212048-Citing-Rstudio?mobile_site=true</uri><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2018-08-28">28 August 2018</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Contreras-Cornejo et&#x000a0;al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Contreras-Cornejo</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mac&#x000ed;as-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cort&#x000e9;s-Penagos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Bucio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title><italic>Trichoderma</italic> virens, a plant beneficial fungus, enhances biomass production and promotes lateral root growth through an auxin-dependent mechanism in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>149</volume><fpage>1579</fpage><lpage>1592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.130369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19176721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Cox, Eaton &#x00026; Scott (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Exploring molecular signaling in plant-fungal symbioses using high throughput RNA sequencing</article-title><source>Plant Signaling and Behavior</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>1353</fpage><lpage>1358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.5.11.12950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21045557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Dardanelli et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dardanelli</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Manyani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Barroso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Carvajal</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil-Serrano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Espuny</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Baena</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellog&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meg&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ollero</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Effect of the presence of the plant growth promoting rhizobacterium (PGPR) Chryseobacterium balustinum Aur9 and salt stress in the pattern of flavonoids exuded by soybean roots</article-title><source>Plant and Soil</source><volume>328</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-009-0127-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>De&#x000a0;Souza et&#x000a0;al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Souza</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomella</surname><given-names>AWV</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbe</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebbar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Colonization of cacao seedlings by <italic>Trichoderma</italic> stromaticum, a mycoparasite of the witches&#x02019; broom pathogen, and its influence on plant growth and resistance</article-title><source>Biological Control</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2008.01.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Debbarma et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debbarma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Debbarma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Debbarma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Influence of different planting methods and organic nutrients on growth and yield of rice [Oryza sativa (l.) sub sp. japonica]</article-title><source>The Ecoscan</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1044</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Di&#x000e1;nez&#x000a0;Mart&#x000ed;nez et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di&#x000e1;nez&#x000a0;Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carretero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mar&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title><italic>Trichoderma</italic> saturnisporum, a new biological control agent</article-title><source>Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>1934</fpage><lpage>1944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.7301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26059112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Doni et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Isahak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zain</surname><given-names>CRCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulaiman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fathurrahman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>NSM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zain</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadhimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alhasnawi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusoff</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Increasing fitness of rice plants by microbes</article-title><conf-name>Proceeding of international conference in advancement in science and technology, 10&#x02013;12th August, 2012, Malaysia</conf-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Doni et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Isahak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zain</surname><given-names>CRCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusoff</surname><given-names>WMW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Physiological and growth response of rice plants (Oryza sativa L.) to <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spp. inoculants</article-title><source>AMB Express</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2191-0855-4-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24383578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Doni et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zain</surname><given-names>CRCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Isahak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fathurrahman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Anhar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamad</surname><given-names>WNM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusoff</surname><given-names> WMW</given-names></name><name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple, efficient, and farmer-friendly Trichoderma-based biofertilizer evaluated with the SRI Rice Management System</article-title><source>Organic Agriculture</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13165-017-0185-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Doni et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zain</surname><given-names>CRCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Isahak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fathurrahman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulaiman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusoff</surname><given-names>WMW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Relationships observed between <italic>Trichoderma</italic> inoculation and characteristics of rice grown under System of Rice Intensification (SRI) vs. conventional methods of cultivation</article-title><source>Symbiosis</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13199-016-0438-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Frank (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the nutritional dependence of certain trees on root symbiosis with belowground fungi (an English translation of A.B. Frank&#x02019;s classic paper of 1885)</article-title><source>Mycorrhiza</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00572-004-0329-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15549482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Glick, Karaturov&#x000ed;c &#x00026; Newell (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glick</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Karaturov&#x000ed;c</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>A novel procedure for rapid isolation of plant growth promoting pseudomonads</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Microbiology</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/m95-070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Grover et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandhya</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkateswarlu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Role of microorganisms in adaptation of agriculture crops to abiotic stresses</article-title><source>World Journal of Microbiology and Biotechnology</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-010-0572-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Hacquard (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hacquard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Disentangling the factors shaping microbiota composition across the plant holobiont</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><volume>209</volume><fpage>454</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26763678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Harman (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Myths and dogmas of biocontrol changes in perceptions derived from research on <italic>Trichoderma</italic> harzinum T-22</article-title><source>Plant Disease</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS.2000.84.4.377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Harman et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Obreg&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Changing models for commercialization and implementation of biocontrol in the developing and the developed world</article-title><source>Plant Disease</source><volume>94</volume><fpage>928</fpage><lpage>939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-94-8-0928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Harman &#x00026; Shoresh (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoresh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The mechanisms and applications of symbiotic opportunistic plant symbionts</article-title><series>NATO security through science series</series><source>Novel biotechnologies for biocontrol agent enhancement and management</source><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>155</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Hirsch et&#x000a0;al. (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullimore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Molecular signals and receptors: controlling rhizosphere interactions between plants and other organisms</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>858</fpage><lpage>868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/0012-9658(2003)084[0858:MSARCR]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Kar et al. (1974)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Varade</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanyam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghildyal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nature and growth pattern of rice root system under submerged and unsaturated conditions</article-title><source>Il Riso</source><year>1974</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>179</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Katayama &#x00026; Matsumura (1993)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Degradation of organochlorine pesticides, particularly endosulfan, by <italic>Trichoderma</italic> harzianum</article-title><source>Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/etc.5620120612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Khadka, Acharya &#x00026; Uphoff (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khadka</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Performance of landrace and improved rice varieties under the system of rice intensification management in Bajhang district of Nepal</article-title><source>Journal of Agriculture and Environment</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3126/aej.v15i0.19809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Kirk &#x00026; Bouldin (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouldin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Speculations on the operation of the rice root system in relation to nutrient uptake</article-title><source>Simulation and systems</source><publisher-name>Pudoc</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Wageningen</publisher-loc><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>203</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Lanfranco, Fiorilli &#x00026; Gutjahr (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanfranco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiorilli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutjahr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Partner communication and role of nutrients in the arbuscular mycorrhizal symbiosis</article-title><source>The New Phytologist</source><volume>220</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.15230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29806959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Le, Josse &#x00026; Husson (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Josse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Husson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>FactoMineR: an R package for multivariate Analysis</article-title><source>Journal of Statistical Software</source><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>Liesack, Schnell &#x00026; Revsbech (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liesack</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Revsbech</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Microbiology of flooded rice paddies</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiology Reviews</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2000.tb00563.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11077155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Maharjan, Gurung &#x00026; Sthapit (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maharjan</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurung</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sthapit</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Enhancing on-farm conservation of agro-biodiversity through community seed bank: an experience Of Western Nepal</article-title><source>Journal of Agriculture and Environment</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>139</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Margulis &#x00026; Fester (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margulis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fester</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><source>Symbiosis as a source of evolutionary innovation</source><publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Mastouri, Bj&#x000f6;rkman &#x00026; Harman (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mastouri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Seed treatment with <italic>Trichoderma</italic> harzianum alleviates biotic, abiotic, and physiological stresses in germinating seeds and seedlings</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-03-10-0091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20649416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>M&#x000fc;ller et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vorholt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>The plant microbiota: systems-level insights and perspectives</article-title><source>Annual Review of Genetics</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-genet-120215-034952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Nemoto, Morita &#x00026; Baba (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nemoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shoot and root development in rice related to the phyllochron</article-title><source>Crop Science</source><year>1995</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1995.0011183X003500010005x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Parmar &#x00026; Dadarwal (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dadarwal</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Stimulation of nitrogen fixation and induction of flavonoid-like compounds by rhizobacteria</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Microbiology</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.1999.00634.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Parniske (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parniske</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Arbuscular mycorrhiza: the mother of plant root endosymbioses</article-title><source>Nature Reviews. Microbiology</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18794914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Redman et al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>CJDA</given-names></name><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Espino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Doty</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased fitness of rice plants to abiotic stress via habitat adapted symbiosis: a strategy for mitigating impacts of climate change</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e14823</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21750695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Redman et al. (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Roossinck</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Field performance of cucurbit and tomato plants infected with a nonpathogenic mutant of Colletotrichum magna (teleomorph: Glomerella magna; Jekins and Winstead)</article-title><source>Symbiosis</source><year>2002</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Rego et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rego</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Go</surname><given-names>MCF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilkiu-Borges</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippi</surname><given-names>MCC&#x000a0;de</given-names></name><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Morphoanatomical and biochemical changes in the roots of rice plants induced by plant growth-promoting microorganisms</article-title><source>Journal of Botany</source><volume>2014</volume><comment>Article 818797</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/818797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Rodriguez et al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>McArthur</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Symbiotic regulation of plant growth, development and reproduction</article-title><source>Communicative &#x00026; Integrative Biology</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19704912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Rubio et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermosa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Acosta</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morcuende</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Monte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettiol</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The combination of Trichoderma harzianum and chemical fertilization leads to the deregulation of phytohormone networking, preventing the adaptive responses of tomato plants to salt stress</article-title><source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>294</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28303151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Sarma, Oehrle &#x00026; Emerich (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oehrle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Emerich</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Metabolic intricacies of the symbiotic association between soybean and <italic>Bradyrhizobium japonicum</italic>: a proteomic outlook</article-title><source>Plant proteomics</source><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>325</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Savazzini, Longa &#x00026; Pertot (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savazzini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Longa</surname><given-names>CMO</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertot</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Impact of the biocontrol agent <italic>Trichoderma</italic> atroviride SC1 on soil microbial communities of a vineyard in northern Italy</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>1457</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2009.03.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Schenk, Carvalhais &#x00026; Kazan (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalhais</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Unraveling plant-microbe interactions: can multi-species transcriptomics help?</article-title><source>Trends in Biotechnology</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2011.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22209623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Senthil et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senthil</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Subhashini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abarna</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayalakshmi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>System of rice intensification as a tool for indigenous seed conservation and organic seed production</article-title><source>Seed production&#x02014;experiences from the field</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Vijayalakshmi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Centre for Indian Knowledge Systems</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Chennai</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>Sharma et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kachroo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardev&#x000a0;Ram</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pooja Gupta&#x000a0;Soni</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Malu Ram&#x000a0;Yadav</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Impact of different transplanting dates and nutrient sources on soil microbial population and grain yield of basmati rice (Oryza sativa L.) grown under SRI</article-title><source>International Journal of Current Microbiology and Applied Sciences</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>778</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20546/ijcmas.2017.603.090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>Shoresh &#x00026; Harman (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shoresh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Differential expression of maize chitinases in the presence or absence of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> harzianum strain T22 and indications of a novel exo- endo-heterodimeric chitinase activity</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biology</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>136</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-10-136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20594307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-57"><label>Shoresh, Harman &#x00026; Mastouri (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shoresh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastouri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Induced systemic resistance and plant responses to fungal biocontrol agents</article-title><source>Annual Review of Phytopathology</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-phyto-073009-114450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-58"><label>Smith &#x00026; Read (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><source>Mycorrhizal symbiosis</source><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-59"><label>Thakur, Uphoff &#x00026; Antony (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Antony</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>An assessment of physiological effects of system of rice intensification (SRI) practices compared to recommended rice cultivation practices in India</article-title><source>Experimental Agriculture</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0014479709990548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-60"><label>Uphoff et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uphoff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dazzo</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil fertility as a contingent rather than inherent characteristic: considering the contributions of crop-symbiotic soil biota</article-title><source>Principles of sustainable soil management in agroecosystems</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>166</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-61"><label>Vargas, Mandawe &#x00026; Kenerley (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandawe</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenerley</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Plant-derived sucrose is a key element in the symbiotic association between <italic>Trichoderma</italic> virens and maize plants</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>151</volume><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.141291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19675155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-62"><label>Vikram et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vikram</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Swamy</surname><given-names>BPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Miro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drought susceptibility of modern rice varieties: an effect of linkage of drought tolerance with undesirable traits</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>14799</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep14799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26458744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-63"><label>Yedidia et&#x000a0;al. (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yedidia</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastva</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapulnik</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chet</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Effect of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> harzianum on microelement concentrations and increased growth of cucumber plants</article-title><source>Plant and Soil</source><volume>235</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1011990013955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-64"><label>Zaidi et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaidi</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangle</surname><given-names>UR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nityanand&#x000a0;Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachitanand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Singha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Waza</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title><italic>Trichoderma</italic> harzianum improves the performance of stress-tolerant rice varieties in rainfed ecologies of Bihar, India</article-title><source>Field Crops Research</source><volume>220</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2017.05.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>