<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6173924</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-018-1443-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of the plant-specific PLATZ proteins in maize and identification of their general role in interaction with RNA polymerase III complex</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jiechen</given-names></name><address><email>jcwang@sibs.ac.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Chen</given-names></name><address><email>jichen@sibs.ac.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name><address><email>liqi01@sibs.ac.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Yong</given-names></name><address><email>zhouyong@sippe.ac.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Yongrui</given-names></name><address><phone>+86-21-54924340</phone><email>yrwu@sibs.ac.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000119573309</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9227.e</institution-id><institution>National Key Laboratory of Plant Molecular Genetics, CAS Center for Excellence in Molecular Plant Sciences, Institute of Plant Physiology &#x00026; Ecology, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, </institution><institution>Chinese Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>300 Fenglin Road, 200032 Shanghai, People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1797 8419</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410726.6</institution-id><institution>University of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 100049 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>221</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">PLATZ proteins are a novel class of plant-specific zinc-dependent DNA-binding proteins that are classified as transcription factors (TFs). However, their common biochemical features and functions are poorly understood.</p></sec><sec><title>Result</title><p id="Par2">Here, we identified and cloned 17 <italic>PLATZ</italic> genes in the maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) genome. All ZmPLATZs were located in nuclei, consistent with their predicted role as TFs. However, none of ZmPLATZs was found to have intrinsic activation properties in yeast. Our recent work shows that FL3 (ZmPLATZ12) interacts with RPC53 and TFC1, two critical factors in the RNA polymerase III (RNAPIII) transcription complex. Using the yeast two-hybrid assay, we determined that seven other PLATZs interacted with both RPC53 and TFC1, whereas three had no protein-protein interaction with these two factors. The other six PLATZs interacted with either RPC53 or TFC1. These findings indicate that ZmPLATZ proteins are generally involved in the modulation of RNAPIII-mediated small non-coding RNA transcription. We also identified all of the PLATZ members in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and constructed a Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree for ZmPLATZs. The resulting tree included 44 members and 5 subfamilies.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">This study provides insight into understanding of the phylogenetic relationship, protein structure, expression pattern and cellular localization of PLATZs in maize. We identified nine and thirteen ZmPLATZs that have protein-protein interaction with RPC53 and TFC1 in the current study, respectively. Overall, the characterization and functional analysis of the PLATZ family in maize will pave the way to understanding RNAPIII-mediated regulation in plant development.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-018-1443-x) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Maize</kwd><kwd>Transcription factor</kwd><kwd>PLATZ</kwd><kwd>RNA polymerase III</kwd><kwd>RPC53</kwd><kwd>TFC1</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>91635303</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Yongrui</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution></funding-source><award-id>XDPB0401</award-id><award-id>XDA08020107</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Yongrui</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Ministry of Science and Technology of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016YFD0100500</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Yongrui</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par11">In plants, 84 putatively TF families and other transcriptional regulators (TRs) have been identified from 19 species whose genomes have been completely sequenced and annotated (Plant Transcription Factor Database, PlantTFDB3.0) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. TFs are proteins that bind to cis-elements in their target promoters in a sequence-specific manner, whereas TRs exert their regulatory function through protein&#x02013;protein interactions or chromatin remodelling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par12">Plants and animals or yeast do not show a good corresponding relationship in the evolution of the TF families. Approximately 50% of TFs in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and 45% in maize are plant-specific, indicating that these TFs play important roles in processes specific to plants, including secondary metabolism, responses to plant hormones, and the identity of specific cell types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Additionally, several TF families such as MYB superfamily, bHLH, and bZIP are large families in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], but their numbers are remarkably fewer in animals and yeast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">The PLATZ TF family is a novel class of plant-specific zinc-dependent DNA-binding proteins. The first reported member was PLATZ1, which was isolated from pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and shown to bind nonspecifically to A/T-rich sequences and repress transcription. However, the mutants and biological functions of any member in this family were not identified until the maize <italic>Fl3</italic> gene was cloned from a classic endosperm semi-dominant mutant. <italic>Fl3</italic> encodes a PLATZ protein that interacts with the RNAPIII subunits RPC53 and TFC1 through which it regulates the transcription of many transfer RNAs (tRNAs) and 5S ribosomal RNA (5S rRNA), and as a consequence, maize endosperm development and filling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">RNAPIII is the largest enzyme complex among RNA polymerases, which is composed of 17 subunits and is responsible for the synthesis of a range of short noncoding RNAs (ncRNAs), including 5S rRNA, U6 small nuclear RNA (U6 snRNA), and different tRNAs, many of which have functions related to ribosome and protein synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The high energetic cost of synthesizing these ncRNAs by RNAPIII is thought to underlie an accurate and coordinated regulation to balance cell survival and reproduction.</p><p id="Par15">In yeast, the RNAPIII transcription complex requires three transcription factors in addition to Pol III: two general transcription factors, TFIIIB and TFIIIC, and a specific transcription factor, TFIIIA, which is only required for the synthesis of 5S rRNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Maf1 is a master regulator in the RNAPIII transcription system in yeast, which is essential for modulating transcription under changing nutritional, environmental and cellular stress conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Nhp6 is another small but powerful effector of chromatin structure in yeast, with a function involved in promoting RNAPIII transcription at a high temperature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">Despite these findings in yeast, the components and mechanisms that modulate RNAPIII transcription in plants are little understood. CsMAF1 from <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> was the first characterized RNAPIII-interacting protein in plants, which can interact with the human RNAPIII and repress tRNA<sup>His</sup> synthesis in yeast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], indicating that the functions of MAF1 proteins are evolutionally conserved across different kingdoms. Another example is UBL1, a putative RNA exonuclease belonging to the 2H phosphodiesterase superfamily, which possesses RNA exonuclease activity in vitro and is involved in biogenesis of snRNA U6. The structure and function of UBL1 is conserved in plants, human and yeast, although the plant UBL1 is only 25.8% and 20.6% identical to its human and yeast counterpart, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">Grain filling in maize and other grasses is a high energy-cost process for the synthesis and accumulation of starch and storage proteins, which require an accurate and coordinated regulation of ribosome and protein synthesis. FL3 (ZmPLATZ12) is specifically expressed in maize endosperm starchy cells and functions as a modulator of the RNAPIII transcription complex consistent with the highly abundant synthesis of tRNAs and 5S rRNA in the maize endosperm. Genome-wide identification and characterization of PLATZs and analysis of their interaction with RNAPIII in maize will provide an avenue for understanding the common and specific features of each PLATZ member in plant development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant growth conditions</title><p id="Par18">The maize inbred line A619 seeds were originally obtained from the Maize Genetics Cooperation Stock Center (accession number 3405&#x02013;001) and planted at our institute farm in Shanghai in the summer of 2017. Tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>) plants were grown in a growth chamber under a day/night regime of 16/8&#x000a0;h at a temperature of 20&#x02013;25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Database search and sequence retrieval</title><p id="Par19">First, the maize PLATZ proteins were used to search against the PlantTFDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plntfdb.bio.uni-potsdam.de/">http://plntfdb.bio.uni-potsdam.de/</ext-link>) and GrassTFDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.grassius.org/grasstfdb.php">http://www.grassius.org/grasstfdb.php</ext-link>) databases. Second, the FL3 (ZmPLATZ12) protein sequence was used as a query to search against National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) using the BLASTP program in the maize B73 genome version 4 (E-value &#x02264; e-05). The unique sequences from the three databases were used for this study. Third, the FL3 (ZmPLATZ12) protein sequence was used as a query to search against NCBI using the BLASTP program in <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (japonica cultivar-group, taxid: 39947) (E-value &#x02264;8e-18) and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (taxid: 3702) (E-value &#x02264;2e-05) reference protein databases. Fourth, the identified rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> PLATZ proteins (OsPLATZs and AtPLATZs, respectively) from the above were used to search against the PlantTFDB database. The unique sequences from the two databases were used for this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>RNA preparation, reverse transcription-PCR (RT-PCR) and cloning of PLATZ genes</title><p id="Par20">Tissues (root, stem, the third leaf and SAM) were collected from at least three healthy plants at 32&#x000a0;days after sowing. The tassel 1, tassel 5 and ear were sampled as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Developing kernels were harvested at 1, 3, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 18, 24, and 30&#x000a0;days after pollination. Total RNA from fresh tissues was extracted using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, USA) and then purified with an RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, Germany). The first-strand cDNAs were synthesized using SuperScript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen, USA) following manual instructions. The full open-reading frame of each <italic>ZmPLATZ</italic> gene was amplified with a specific primer pair. All primers used for RT-PCR are listed in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1. The maize GRMZM2G105019 was used as the reference [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Fifteen <italic>ZmPLATZ</italic> cDNAs were amplified from the leaf, stem, tassel, endosperm or embryo tissue, with the exceptions <italic>ZmPLATZ1</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ8</italic>. The coding sequences of <italic>PLATZ1</italic> and <italic>8</italic> were synthesized at Sangon Biotech (Shanghai, China) Co., Ltd., based on the gene annotation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Expression patterns of <italic>PLATZ</italic> genes in B73</title><p id="Par21">Expression patterns of fifteen maize <italic>PLATZ</italic> genes were summarized based on the maize reference genome B73 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: File S1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Hierarchical clustering of fifteen genes and heat map of 53 different seed samples were carried out by using normalized gene expression values with log2 (RPKM +&#x02009;1) in R package &#x02018;pheatmap&#x02019;. Fifty-three samples represent different tissues and different developmental stages of the whole seed, endosperm and embryo.The sample IDs were used as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Structure and phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="Par22">The amino acid sequences translated from the ZmPLATZ CDSs were used to predict conserved domains using the Pfam database of Hidden Markov Model with an i-value threshold at 1.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk/search">http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk/search</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] and SMART database of default parameters (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de">http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de</ext-link>/) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The complete amino acid sequences of ZmPLATZs, were submitted to the Clustal W program using the default settings (pairwise alignment options: gap opening penalty 10, gap extension penalty 0.1; multiple alignment options: gap opening penalty 10, gap extension penalty 0.2, gap distance 4, no end gaps and protein weight matrix using Gonnet) for for multiple protein alignment. Based on the aligned protein sequences, the ZmPLATZ phylogenetic tree was constructed using the MEGA7.0 program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.megasoftware.net">http://www.megasoftware.net</ext-link>/) and the maximum likelihood method with Jones-Taylor-Thornton (JTT) Model, and the bootstrap test was conducted with 1000 replicates. The amino acid sequences of ZmPLATZs, OsPLATZs and AtPLATZs were submitted to the Clustal W program using the default settings for multiple protein alignment. Based on the aligned protein sequences, sequences with &#x0003e;&#x02009;30% gap was removed. Then, a maximum likelihood tree about ZmPLATZs, OsPLATZs and AtPLATZs was constructed using the default settings based on Jones-Taylor-Thornton (JTT) Model with partial deletion and 70% Site Coverage Cut off, and the bootstrap test was conducted with 1000 replicates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Subcellular localization of PLATZ proteins</title><p id="Par23">The amino acid sequences translated from the ZmPLATZ CDSs were used to predict nuclear localization signal (NLS) using the wolf-psort (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://psort.hgc.jp/">https://psort.hgc.jp/</ext-link>) or PredictNLS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://rostlab.org/owiki/index.php/%20PredictNLS">https://rostlab.org/owiki/index.php/ PredictNLS</ext-link>) online tool. The C-terminal of each <italic>ZmPLATZ</italic> CDS was fused to a reporter gene encoding the enhanced GFP (eGFP), which was then cloned into pCAMBIA1301 plasmid driven by the 35S promoter. <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> (strain GV3101) harbouring this construct was infiltrated into 3-week-old <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves using a needle-less syringe. At least three replicates were performed. The eGFP signal was observed and imaged using a confocal microscope (FV1000, Olympus, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Yeast two-hybrid assay</title><p id="Par24">Full-length coding sequences of <italic>PLATZs</italic> were cloned into the pGBKT7 plasmid (BD) and transformed into yeast strain Y2HGold to test for auto-activation. Yeast on SD/&#x02212;Trp agar plates were grown at 28&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2 days and on SD/&#x02212;Trp -Ade -His for 3 days. For the protein-protein interaction assay, TFC1 and RPC53 were ligated to the pGADT7 plasmid (AD). pGADT7-TFC1 or pGADT7-RPC53 with pGBKT7-PLATZs were co-transformed into Y2HGold. The yeast cells were plated on SD/&#x02212;Trp -Leu at 28&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2 days and on SD/&#x02212;Trp -Leu -Ade -His for 3 days.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Identification of ZmPLATZs in the maize genome</title><p id="Par25">To characterize the number of members in this new family, we searched the maize PLATZ proteins in the PlantTFDB and GrassTFDB databases, which were both based on the B73 genome version 3. This search resulted in the identification of 21 and 15 members from the two databases. Although 26 completely unique protein sequences were characterized, only 15 <italic>PLATZs</italic> were confirmed as expressed genes by the public maize RNA-seq data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Because the B73 genome version 4 is available now [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], BLASTP searches were performed using the FL3 (ZmPLATZ12) protein sequence with E-value &#x02264; e-05. Fourteen ZmPLATZs from version 3 were re-identified in the version 4 genome, with PLATZ2 exception, whereas two new <italic>PLATZ</italic> genes (Zm00001d046688 and Zm00001d046958) missing in version 3 were annotated in version 4. Collectively, 17 ZmPLATZ members including the previously reported FL3 (ZmPLATZ12) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] were analysed in the current study (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The protein nomenclature was in accordance with that of the GrassTFDB ID (ZmPLATZ1&#x02013;15), and the two new PLATZs annotated from version 4 were designated ZmPLATZ16 and ZmPLATZ17 (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The 17 <italic>ZmPLATZ</italic> genes are unevenly distributed on 7 chromosomes, with chromosomes 1, 5 and 9 each bearing 4 members.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>17 ZmPLATZs identified from the completed maize genome sequence</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Family members</th><th rowspan="2">Model V3</th><th rowspan="2">Model V4</th><th rowspan="2">Chromosome No.<sup>a</sup></th><th>Chromosome</th><th>Position<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="2">Chromosome Strand<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th>From</th><th>To</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>ZmPLATZ1</td><td>GRMZM2G408887</td><td>Zm00001d028594</td><td>1</td><td>40221978</td><td>40223031</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ2</td><td>GRMZM2G311656</td><td>Zm00001d029437</td><td>1</td><td>70442356</td><td>70448204</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ3</td><td>GRMZM2G094168</td><td>Zm00001d030032</td><td>1</td><td>101087719</td><td>101089688</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ4</td><td>GRMZM2G171934</td><td>Zm00001d031925</td><td>1</td><td>206932526</td><td>206934498</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ5</td><td>GRMZM2G131280</td><td>Zm00001d002489</td><td>2</td><td>13850163</td><td>13852195</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ6</td><td>GRMZM2G342691</td><td>Zm00001d051376</td><td>4</td><td>156414419</td><td>156415562</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ7</td><td>GRMZM2G091044</td><td>Zm00001d051511</td><td>4</td><td>160984327</td><td>160986154</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ8</td><td>GRMZM2G017882</td><td>Zm00001d015394</td><td>5</td><td>88146164</td><td>88150303</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ9</td><td>GRMZM2G070295</td><td>Zm00001d015560</td><td>5</td><td>97682870</td><td>97684322</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ10</td><td>GRMZM2G323553</td><td>Zm00001d015868</td><td>5</td><td>127438923</td><td>127439977</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ11</td><td>GRMZM2G004548</td><td>Zm00001d017682</td><td>5</td><td>204120837</td><td>204122561</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ12 (Fl3)</td><td>GRMZM2G006585</td><td>Zm00001d009292</td><td>8</td><td>52707946</td><td>52709109</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ13</td><td>GRMZM2G093270</td><td>Zm00001d047025</td><td>9</td><td>115708968</td><td>115711076</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ14</td><td>GRMZM2G077495</td><td>Zm00001d047250</td><td>9</td><td>124047961</td><td>124049024</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ15</td><td>GRMZM2G086403</td><td>Zm00001d026047</td><td>10</td><td>136891569</td><td>136893726</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ16</td><td/><td>Zm00001d046688</td><td>9</td><td>102440929</td><td>102445873</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ17</td><td/><td>Zm00001d046958</td><td>9</td><td>113035703</td><td>113040261</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>The gene position in chromosome was according <italic>Zea mays</italic> B73 genome sequence Vision4</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Cloning and domain prediction of ZmPLATZs</title><p id="Par26">RT-PCR was employed to amplify the intact CDS of each <italic>ZmPLATZ</italic> gene. PLATZ2, 5, 7, 11, 12, and 13 were cloned from the 12-DAP endosperm, and PLATZ3, 16, and 17 were cloned from the root. PLATZ4, 6, 9, 10, 11, 14, and 15 were cloned from the 18-DAP endosperm, tassel, 20-DAP embryo, 6-DAP endosperm, 12-DAP endosperm, 3-DAP seed, and 36-DAP endosperm, respectively. The expression of PLATZ1 and 8 was not detected in any tissue used in this study. (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: File S1). The cDNA sequences of <italic>ZmPLATZ2</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ3</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ5</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ7</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ10</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ13</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ15</italic> were identical to the predicted CDSs from the B73 genome version 3, whereas those of <italic>ZmPLATZ4</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ9</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ11</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ14</italic> had several mismatches compared with the predicted CDSs (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S1). The version 3 predicted <italic>ZmPLATZ6</italic> CDS was different from that of version 4 at the C-terminal. We sequenced the amplified <italic>ZmPLATZ6</italic> cDNA, which was nearly identical to the version 4 CDS except for 9 SNPs (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S2). The cloned cDNA sequences of <italic>ZmPLATZ16</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ17</italic> were the same as the predicted CDSs of version 4 except for a 3-bp insertion in the <italic>ZmPLATZ17</italic> cDNA.</p><p id="Par27">PLATZ proteins were classified as TFs containing a conserved PLATZ domain, although the components of other domains have not been recognized. The protein sequences of 15 cloned and 2 predicted (<italic>ZmPLATZ1</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ8</italic>) <italic>ZmPLATZ</italic> genes were subject to conserved domains prediction using the Pfam [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] and SMART [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] databases. It was predicted that all ZmPLATZ members contained a PLATZ domain (Pfam family PLATZ: PF04640, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pfam.xfam.org/family/PLATZ">http://pfam.xfam.org/family/PLATZ</ext-link>). Additionally, many members were predicted to bear a BBOX(B-Box-type zinc finger, SMART accession number: SM00336, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/smart/do_annotation.pl?ACC=SM000336&#x00026;BLAST=DUMMY">http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/smart/do_annotation.pl?ACC=SM000336&#x00026;BLAST=DUMMY</ext-link>)domain, which is located before the PLATZ domain. The PLATZ domain is highly conserved between ZmPLATZs which could be identified though all the database and the BBOX domain is not very conserved with highly E-value. ZmPLATZ8 was an exception, with the BBOX positioned in the rear of the PLATZ domain with an overlap (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: File S2). Only ZmPLATZ2 has a CC (coiled coil) domain, and ZmPLATZ4 and ZmPLATZ12 have a signal peptide domain.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of ZmPLATZs. The putative domains or motifs were identified using the Pfam and SMART databases with the default parameters. PLATZ, PLATZ domain; BBOX, B-Box-type zinc finger; SP, signal peptide; CC, coiled coil. Bar, 100 aa</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Identification protein domains of 17 PLATZs by Pfam and SMART databases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Family members</th><th>Model V4</th><th>CDS Length</th><th>Signal Peptide</th><th>PLATZ Domain</th><th>BBOX Domain</th><th>Coiled-Coil</th><th>Low Comlexity Region</th><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>ZmPLATZ1</td><td>Zm00001d028594</td><td>231</td><td/><td>170&#x02013;199</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">129&#x02013;169</td><td/><td>36&#x02013;53</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ2</td><td>Zm00001d029437</td><td>309</td><td/><td>155&#x02013;229</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">111&#x02013;154</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">68&#x02013;89</td><td>269&#x02013;291</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ3</td><td>Zm00001d030032</td><td>254</td><td/><td>109&#x02013;185</td><td/><td/><td>21&#x02013;34,79-97,205&#x02013;216</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ4</td><td>Zm00001d031925</td><td>212</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">1&#x02013;31</td><td>74&#x02013;152</td><td/><td/><td>160&#x02013;178</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ5</td><td>Zm00001d002489</td><td>256</td><td/><td>87&#x02013;158</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">46&#x02013;86</td><td/><td>14&#x02013;27,192-216,220&#x02013;234</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ6</td><td>Zm00001d051376</td><td>198</td><td/><td>64&#x02013;134</td><td/><td/><td>168&#x02013;181</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ7</td><td>Zm00001d051511</td><td>251</td><td/><td>89&#x02013;160</td><td/><td/><td>15&#x02013;28,63-78,170-182,197&#x02013;230</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ8</td><td>Zm00001d015394</td><td>214</td><td/><td>13&#x02013;84</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">59&#x02013;97</td><td/><td>102&#x02013;110,173&#x02013;185</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ9</td><td>Zm00001d015560</td><td>237</td><td/><td>62&#x02013;134</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">19&#x02013;62</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ10</td><td>Zm00001d015868</td><td>220</td><td/><td>80&#x02013;152</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">27&#x02013;79</td><td/><td>173&#x02013;188</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ11</td><td>Zm00001d017682</td><td>251</td><td/><td>88&#x02013;159</td><td/><td/><td>8&#x02013;27,169-183,194&#x02013;230</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ12 (Fl3)</td><td>Zm00001d009292</td><td>214</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">1&#x02013;24</td><td>65&#x02013;144</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">25&#x02013;64</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ13</td><td>Zm00001d047025</td><td>261</td><td/><td>112&#x02013;192</td><td/><td/><td>21&#x02013;36,82-92,232&#x02013;242</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ14</td><td>Zm00001d047250</td><td>299</td><td/><td>143&#x02013;217</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">99&#x02013;142</td><td/><td>5&#x02013;10,19-43,57-70,73-88,244-256,268&#x02013;277</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ15</td><td>Zm00001d026047</td><td>253</td><td/><td>88&#x02013;159</td><td/><td/><td>15&#x02013;26,170-189,195&#x02013;213</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ16</td><td>Zm00001d046688</td><td>259</td><td/><td>92&#x02013;163</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">46&#x02013;91</td><td/><td>183&#x02013;195</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ZmPLATZ17</td><td>Zm00001d046958</td><td>250</td><td/><td>59&#x02013;129</td><td/><td/><td>188&#x02013;203</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Phylogenetic analysis of ZmPLATZs</title><p id="Par28">To characterize the phylogenetic relationships among ZmPLATZ proteins, we constructed a phylogenetic tree of the 17 ZmPLATZs (15 cloned and 2 predicted (<italic>ZmPLATZ1</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ8</italic>)) using Clustal W and MEGA 7.0. The maximum likelihood method was used to construct the phylogenetic tree (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Figure S3). The ZmPLATZs were grouped into three branches. Clade 1 contained ZmPLATZ5, ZmPLATZ15, ZmPLATZ1, ZmPLATZ7, ZmPLATZ11, ZmPLATZ3, andZmPLATZ13. Clade 1 ZmPLATZ members contained a conserved domain (MAID-x<sub>4&#x02013;8</sub>-L-x<sub>4</sub>-R-x<sub>4&#x02013;5</sub>-GGG) in N-terminal (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Figure S3). Clade 2 contained ZmPLATZ16, ZmPLATZ4, ZmPLATZ12, and ZmPLATZ10. Clade 3 contained ZmPLATZ6, ZmPLATZ2, ZmPLATZ14, ZmPLATZ9, ZmPLATZ8, and ZmPLATZ17.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of ZmPLATZs. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree summarizes the evolutionary relationships among ZmPLATZs. The numbers under the branches refer to the bootstrap value of the maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree. The length of the branches is proportional to the amino acid variation rates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Spatial and temporal expression patterns of <italic>ZmPLATZs</italic></title><p id="Par29">The temporal and spatial expression patterns of the <italic>PLATZ</italic> genes in maize were investigated by analysing the transcripts using the public RNA-seq data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) and RT-PCR (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Expression patterns of the ZmPLATZ genes analysed by the public RNA-seq data. The genes are located on the right, and the tissues are indicated at the bottom of each column. The colour bar represents the expression values. S0-S38: developing seed from 0 to 38 DAP (day after pollination); Em10-Em38: developing embryo from 10 to 38 DAP; En6-En38: developing endosperm from 6 to 38 DAP</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Expression patterns of <italic>ZmPLATZ</italic> genes by RT-PCR. The gene names are placed on the left, and the examined tissues are indicated on the top of each column. The phylogenetic tree was based on the RNA-seq data (B73 genome version 3). Since <italic>ZmPLATZ16</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ17</italic> were not annotated in B73 genome version 3, they were not included in the tree. Each <italic>ZmPLATZ</italic> gene was amplified with a specific primer pair for 32&#x000a0;cycles. The genomic DNA bands of <italic>ZmPLATZ4</italic> and <italic>17</italic> were not shown, due to their sizes being much larger than those of the cDNA bands. The GRMZM105019 gene was used as control. S1-S6: developing seed from 1 to 6 DAP; En8-En30: developing endosperm from 8 to 30 DAP; Em12-Em24: developing embryo from 12 to 24 DAP</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par30">Three <italic>PLATZs</italic>, namely <italic>11, 7</italic> and <italic>15</italic>, were exhibited high and ubiquitous expression in all tissues except the developing endosperm. <italic>PLATZ5</italic> was expressed at varying levels in all tested tissues as shown by RT-PCR. but not in the public RNA-seq data. <italic>PLATZ3</italic> and <italic>PLATZ13</italic> exhibited similar expression patterns in root, stem, leaf, SAM and early seed, but <italic>PLATZ3</italic> had a higher expression level. The <italic>PLATZ6</italic> gene was specifically expressed in tassel, indicating that the function of this gene is involved in tassel development, The <italic>PLATZ9</italic> transcripts were only detected in root and stem. Transcript levels of <italic>PLATZ4</italic> were much higher in the developing endosperm than those in other tissues. However, <italic>PLATZ4</italic> was more ubiquitously expressed than <italic>Fl3 (PLATZ12)</italic> which expression was only detected at a high level in endosperm and at a weak level in the embryo (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Two other <italic>PLATZs</italic>, <italic>2</italic> and <italic>14</italic>, were expressed between 8 and 10 DAP in the endosperm, coincident with initiation of the endosperm filling. <italic>PLATZ10</italic> was weakly but specifically expressed in endosperm at 8 DAP. These four PLATZs might all be involved in maize endosperm development and storage reserve synthesis. We failed to clone <italic>ZmPLATZ1</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ8</italic> cDNAs from any tissue, most likely because they are only expressed in a highly differentiated tissue that was not investigated in the current study or under a special condition.</p><p id="Par31">According to their expression levels and patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], maize <italic>PLATZ</italic> genes could be clustered into two categories and <italic>Fl3 (PLATZ12)</italic> appeared as an out-group branch for its highest and specific expression in endosperm. The first category was composed of five genes (<italic>PLATZ4</italic>, <italic>PLATZ5</italic>, <italic>PLATZ11, PLATZ7</italic> and <italic>PLATZ15</italic>) with high and more ubiquitous expression levels, suggesting comprehensive roles in plant growth and development. The second category included other <italic>PLATZs</italic> of which the expression levels were relatively low and specific. ZmPLATZ16 and ZmPLATZ17 have not been included in either of the two clusters due to being missing in the B73 genome version 3.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Subcellular localization of ZmPLATZs</title><p id="Par32">The nuclear localization signal (NLS) could be predicted using wolf-psort (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://psort.hgc.jp/">https://psort.hgc.jp/</ext-link>) or PredictNLS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://rostlab.org/owiki/index.php/PredictNLS">https://rostlab.org/owiki/index.php/PredictNLS</ext-link>). A NLS was not identified in the FL3 (ZmPLATZ12) protein by online software, although the FL3-GFP fused protein is localized in nuclei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. To determine the subcellular localization of other members, each PLATZ protein was fused to green fluorescent protein (GFP). Because of the failure to amplify <italic>ZmPLATZ1</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ8</italic> cDNAs in any investigated tissue, their coding sequences were artificially synthesized (See methods). The free GFP was used as the control. The constitutive 35S promoter drove all gene cassettes. We transiently expressed the resulting constructs in tobacco leaves. All signals of the fused proteins including those of <italic>35S::PLATZ1:GFP</italic> and <italic>35S::PLATZ8:GFP</italic> were localized in nuclei, consistent with their predicted function as TFs, whereas the control <italic>35S:GFP</italic> was detected both in nuclei and the cytoplasm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Subcellular localization of ZmPLATZs. The <italic>GFP</italic> gene was fused to the C-terminal of each ZmPLATZ. The constructs were transiently expressed in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves via <italic>Agrobacteria</italic> infiltration. Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>The protein-protein interaction of ZmPLATZs and RNAPIII</title><p id="Par33">Previously, FL3 (ZmPLATZ12) was shown to have protein-protein interaction with RNAPIII subunits RPC53 and TFC1, but this protein was not found to have no intrinsic activation properties by using the yeast transactivation assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. We then investigate other fused BD-ZmPLATZ proteins whether they were able bind to GAL4 upstream activating sequences (GALUAS) and activate transcription of the lacZ reporter gene. In contrast to the Opaque 2 (O2) control, an endosperm-specific bZIP TF for regulation of the storage-protein zein gene expression, none of PLATZs showed intrinsic activation properties (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Therefore, ZmPLATZs could be used to verify protein-protein interaction with yeast two-hybrid. We also tested whether other PLATZs could interact with RPC53 and TFC1. ZmPLATZ1 only interacted with RPC53, and ZmPLATZ4, ZmPLATZ5, ZmPLATZ7, ZmPLATZ13 and ZmPLATZ15 only interacted with TFC1. Similar to FL3 (ZmPLATZ12), ZmPLATZ3, ZmPLATZ9, ZmPLATZ10, ZmPLATZ11, ZmPLATZ14, ZmPLATZ16 and ZmPLATZ17 interacted with both. However, PLATZ2, PLATZ6 and PLATZ8 did not have a protein-protein interaction with RPC53 or TFC1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Collectively, these results indicate that PLATZ proteins are generally involved in modulation of RNAPIII-mediated transcription in different tissues.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Auto-activation assay of ZmPLATZs in yeast Each ZmPLATZ and the endosperm-specific transcription factor O2 as the positive control were fused to the C-terminal of GAL4-BD. The resulting constructs pBD-PLATZs and pBD-O2 were transformed into Y2HGold and selected on the medium plates (SD/&#x02212;Trp). Then, the transformed yeast colonies were grown on the selection medium plates (SD/&#x02212;Trp/-His/&#x02212;Ade)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>The protein-protein interaction assay of ZmPLATZs and RPC53/TFC1 by yeast two-hybrid assay. Constructs of pAD-RPC53/TFC1 and pBD-PLATZs were transformed into Y2HGold and selected on the medium plates (SD/&#x02212;Trp/&#x02212;Leu). Then, the transformed yeast colonies were grown on the selection medium plates (SD/&#x02212;Trp/&#x02212;Leu/-His/&#x02212;Ade)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Phylogenetic analysis of PLATZ proteins in maize, rice and Arabidopsis</title><p id="Par34">We identified 17 ZmPLATZs from the maize genome. To explore the evolutionary conservation of PLATZ proteins in other species, we used the FL3 (ZmPLATZ12) protein sequence to blast against the rice (japonica cultivar-group, taxid: 39947, E-value &#x02264;8e-18) and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (taxid: 3702, E-value &#x02264;2e-05) reference protein databases. A total of 15 and 12 unique protein sequences were identified in rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> databases, respectively (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: File S3). To investigate the phylogenetic relationships among PLATZ proteins, we constructed a phylogenetic tree of the 17 ZmPLATZs, 15 OsPLATZs and 12 AtPLATZs. The maximum likelihood method was used to construct the phylogenetic tree using Clustal W and MEGA 7.0 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: Figure S4).<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of ZmPLATZs, OsPLATZs and AtPLATZs. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree summarizes the evolutionary relationships among PLATZs. The numbers under the branches refer to the bootstrap values of the maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree. The length of the branches is proportional to the amino acid variation rates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p><p id="Par35">We divided the 44 PLATZ proteins into 5 subfamilies, designated I, II, III, IV and V based on the primary amino acid sequence. We noted that each subfamily included maize, rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> members. Subfamily I was corresponding to clade1 of the phylogenetic tree of ZmPLATZs and contained a conserve domain (MAID-x<sub>4&#x02013;8</sub>-L-x<sub>4</sub>-R-x<sub>4&#x02013;5</sub>-GGG) in N-terminal (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: Figure S4). Some ZmPLATZ members had OsPLATZ homologues with high bootstrap support (&#x0003e;&#x02009;90%), such as ZmPLATZ9 and LOC Os02g09070, ZmPLATZ16 and LOC Os06g41930, and ZmPLATZ6 and LOC Os02g44260, indicating that these members are evolutionarily conserved in the grass family. Some ZmPLATZ members had two OsPLATZ homologues, such as LOC Os01g33350 and LOC Os01g33370 with ZmPLATZ12 and LOC Os08g44620 and LOC Os11g24130 with ZmPLATZ4. The close genome locations and similar expression patterns of LOC Os01g33350 and LOC Os01g33370 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/cgi-bin/ORF_infopage.cgi">http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/cgi-bin/ORF_infopage.cgi</ext-link>) indicated the two <italic>OsPLATZ</italic> genes resulted from gene duplication after the split with speciation of maize and rice<italic>.</italic></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec19"><title>PLATZ proteins belong to a novel TF family interacting with RNAPIII</title><p id="Par36">In a genome-wide screen of PLATZ proteins in the maize B73 genome version 3 and 4, we identified 17 complete members that all harboured the conserved PLATZ domain. Among the members, the expression of 15 <italic>ZmPLATZs</italic> was confirmed in variant tissues. The coding sequences of <italic>ZmPLATZ1</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ8</italic> were artificially synthesized for the following research. All ZmPLATZ proteins located to nuclei. Based on the random binding site selection (RBSS) experiment, A/T-rich sequences were recognized by FL3 (ZmPLATZ12). All members, except for ZmPLATZ2, ZmPLATZ6 and ZmPLATZ8, had a protein-protein interaction with either RPC53 or TFC1 or both (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). This finding indicates that ZmPLATZ proteins are generally involved in modulation of RNAPIII transcription.</p><p id="Par37">Although the gain-of-function mutant <italic>fl3</italic> shows severe defects in endosperm development and storage reserve filling, the knockout and knockdown mutations of this gene do not cause an apparent floury phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In addition to <italic>FL3 (ZmPLATZ12)</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ2</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ4</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ10</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ14</italic> were also expressed in the developing endosperm (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). ZmPLATZ4 interacted with TFC1, and ZmPLATZ10/14 interacted with RPC53 and TFC1. One could envision that the three RNAPIII-interacting ZmPLATZs have redundant function with FL3 in the maize endosperm. Thus, creation of a series of double, triple and quadruple mutants of <italic>ZmPLATZ4</italic>, <italic>ZmPLATZ10</italic>, <italic>Fl3</italic> (<italic>ZmPLATZ12)</italic> and <italic>ZmPLATZ14</italic> will be an effective approach to overcome the functional redundancy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Classification and phylogenetic analysis of the plant-specific PLATZ family</title><p id="Par38">A comparable number of <italic>PLATZ</italic> genes were identified in rice (15) and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (12), although the maize genome size (2300&#x000a0;Mb) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] is ~&#x02009;5.3- and ~&#x02009;18.4-fold larger than that of rice (430&#x000a0;Mb) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (125&#x000a0;Mb) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. This huge discrepancy could be explained by a much higher percentage of transposons in the maize genome. The number of <italic>PLATZ</italic> genes is apparently conserved across different plant genomes.</p><p id="Par39">The phylogenetic comparison of the PLATZ proteins was conducted in maize, rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, and their evolutionary relationships within and among the different species were investigated for the first time. Because of low identity between ZmPLATZs and AtPLATZs (the lowest at only 27%), the bootstrap values of some outer nodes were low; nevertheless, the internal nodes had more credible bootstrap values. The 44 PLATZ members from maize, rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> were divided into 5 subfamilies (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). The ML phylogenetic tree constructed by the 17 ZmPLATZ proteins could be divided into three branches (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Subfamily I of the total ML tree corresponding to clade1 of the phylogenetic tree of ZmPLATZs, contained a conserved domain (MAID-x<sub>4&#x02013;8</sub>-L-x<sub>4</sub>-R-x<sub>4&#x02013;5</sub>-GGG) in N-terminal. Meanwhile, the internal nodes between the two trees were comparable. For example, the branch of ZmPLATZ12 (FL3) and ZmPLATZ4 in the maize ML tree was also included in subfamily III in the total ML tree, and the branch of ZmPLATZ2 and ZmPLATZ14 in the maize ML tree was included in subfamily V in the total ML tree. Moreover, the subfamily III included LOC Os01g33350, LOC Os01g33370 and ZmPLATZ12, which display a similar expression pattern during rice and maize endosperm development, indicating a conserved function of the three orthologous PLATZ members in grass.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par40">In conclusion, we identified and cloned 17 <italic>PLATZ</italic> genes in the maize genome and found that seven PLATZs interacted with both RPC53 and TFC1. Our findings indicate that ZmPLATZ proteins are generally involved in the modulation of RNAPIII-mediated small non-coding RNA transcription.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec22"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> Primer list. (XLSX 14 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_MOESM2_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>File S1.</bold> cDNA sequences of 17 ZmPLATZs. (TXT 12 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> ZmPLATZ4&#x00026;9&#x00026;11&#x00026;14&#x00026;17 cDNA sequence alignment. Sequence alignment of <italic>ZmPLATZ4&#x00026;9&#x00026;11&#x00026;14&#x00026;17</italic> CDS from cloned and predicted. (PDF 191 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S2.</bold> The PLATZ6 cDNA sequence alignment. Sequence alignment of <italic>ZmPLATZ6</italic> CDS from cloned and predicted. (PDF 518 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_MOESM5_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><bold>File S2.</bold> Protein sequences of 17 ZmPLATZs. (TXT 4 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_MOESM6_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S3.</bold> The amino acid sequence alignment of ZmPLATZs. Amino Acid Sequence Alignment of ZmPLATZs Black shaded amino acids represent identical amino acid residues and gray ones indicate the similar amino acid residues. (PDF 1843 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_MOESM7_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 7:</label><caption><p><bold>File S3.</bold> Protein sequences of AtPLATZs and OsPLATZs. (TXT 4 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1443_MOESM8_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 8:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S4.</bold> The amino acid sequence alignment of AtPLATZs, OsPLATZs and ZmPLATZs. Amino Acid Sequence Alignment of ZmPLATZs, AtPLATZs and OsPLATZs. Black shaded amino acids represent identical amino acid residues and gray ones indicate the similar amino acid residues. (PDF 5870 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>DAP</term><def><p id="Par4">Day after pollination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NLS</term><def><p id="Par5">Nuclear localization signal</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PLATZ</term><def><p id="Par6">Plant AT-rich sequence and zinc-binding protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RBSS</term><def><p id="Par7">the random binding site selection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNAPIII</term><def><p id="Par8">RNA polymerase III</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPC53</term><def><p id="Par9">RNA polymerase III subunit 53</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TFC1</term><def><p id="Par10">Transcription factor class C 1</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><p>We are grateful to Mr. Xiaoyan Gao, Mr. Zhiping Zhang, Miss. Jiqin Li, Miss. Yunxiao He and Mrs. Qiong Wang (Institute of Plant Physiology and Ecology, SIBS, CAS) for their technical support.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par41">This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (91635303 to Y. W., 31871626 to J. C and 31671703 to Z. Z.), Chinese Academy of Sciences (XDPB0401 and XDA08020107 to Y. W.), the Ministry of Science and Technology of China (2016YFD0100500) and a Chinese Thousand Talents Program Grant (to Y. W.).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par42">The datasets supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the article and its Additional files. The A619 seeds are available from the Maize Genetics Cooperation Stock Center (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://maizecoop.cropsci.uiuc.edu/request/">https://maizecoop.cropsci.uiuc.edu/request/</ext-link>).</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>JW, CJ and YW designed the research, analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. JW, CJ, QL and YZ performed the research. All authors have read and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Riano-Pachon</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rensing</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kersten</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller-Roeber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PlnTFDB: updated content and new features of the plant transcription factor database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D822</fpage><lpage>D827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19858103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The VQ motif-containing protein family of plant-specific transcriptional regulators</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>169</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.00788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26220951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riechmann</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Heard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Keddie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Samaha</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis transcription factors: genome-wide comparative analysis among eukaryotes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>290</volume><issue>5499</issue><fpage>2105</fpage><lpage>2110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.290.5499.2105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11118137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide transcription factor gene prediction and their expressional tissue-specificities in maize</article-title><source>J Integr Plant Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>54</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2012.01149.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22862992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carretero-Paulet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Galstyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roig-Villanova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Garcia</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilbao-Castro</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide classification and evolutionary analysis of the bHLH family of transcription factors in Arabidopsis, poplar, rice, moss, and algae</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>153</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1398</fpage><lpage>1412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.153593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20472752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katiyar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenka</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajwanshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinnusamy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide classification and expression analysis of MYB transcription factor families in rice and Arabidopsis</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>544</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-13-544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23050870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nijhawan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic survey and gene expression analysis of the basic leucine zipper transcription factor family in rice</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>146</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.107.112821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18065552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yandell</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabor Miklos</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hariharan</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortini</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of the eukaryotes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>287</volume><issue>5461</issue><fpage>2204</fpage><lpage>2215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.287.5461.2204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anantharaman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of transcription factors and chromatin proteins in parasitic protists and other eukaryotes</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2008</year><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2007.07.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17949725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuhashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel class of plant-specific zinc-dependent DNA-binding protein that binds to a/T-rich DNA sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>4097</fpage><lpage>4105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/29.20.4097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11600698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The maize imprinted gene Floury3 encodes a PLATZ protein required for tRNA and 5S rRNA transcription through interaction with RNA polymerase III</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>29</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2661</fpage><lpage>2675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.17.00576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28874509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcription by RNA polymerase III: more complex than we thought</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg3001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21540878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moir</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling to and from the RNA polymerase III transcription and processing machinery</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>2018</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-biochem-062917-012624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29328783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast RNA polymerase III transcription factors and effectors</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2013</year><volume>1829</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2012.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23063749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pluta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Smagowicz</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanford</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sentenac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boguta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maf1p, a negative effector of RNA polymerase III in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>5031</fpage><lpage>5040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.21.15.5031-5040.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Upadhya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maf1 is an essential mediator of diverse signals that repress RNA polymerase III transcription</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1489</fpage><lpage>1494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1097-2765(02)00787-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12504022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nhp6: a small but powerful effector of chromatin structure in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2010</year><volume>1799</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2009.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20123079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soprano</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name><name><surname>Smetana</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Citrus MAF1, a repressor of RNA polymerase III, binds the Xanthomonas citri canker elicitor PthA4 and suppresses citrus canker development</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>163</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.224642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23898043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soprano</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuseppe</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimo</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>FAH</given-names></name><name><surname>Righetto</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>JGC</given-names></name><name><surname>Granato</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>AFZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gozzo</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure and regulation of the Citrus pol III repressor MAF1 by auxin and phosphorylation</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>2017</year><volume>25</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1360</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.str.2017.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28781084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The U6 biogenesis-like 1 plays an important role in maize kernel and seedling development by affecting the 3&#x02032; end processing of U6 snRNA</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2016.10.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27825944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic transcriptome landscape of maize embryo and endosperm development</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>166</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.240689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25037214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification of housekeeping genes in maize</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>86</volume><issue>4&#x02013;5</issue><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-014-0246-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25209110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coggill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberhardt</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mistry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Punta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Qureshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangrador-Vegas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Pfam protein families database: towards a more sustainable future</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D279</fpage><lpage>D285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26673716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letunic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>20 years of the SMART protein domain annotation resource</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D493</fpage><lpage>D496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29040681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitzer</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improved maize reference genome with single-molecule technologies</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>546</volume><issue>7659</issue><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28605751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28605751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saegusa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Japanese plan speeds up rice genome sequencing</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>401</volume><issue>6749</issue><fpage>102</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/43503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10490009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Arabidopsis Genome I</collab></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the genome sequence of the flowering plant Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>408</volume><issue>6814</issue><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35048692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130711</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>