<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hortic Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Horticulture Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2052-7276</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6355865</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">88</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41438-018-0088-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genetic control of compound leaf development in the mungbean (<italic>Vigna radiata</italic> L.)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Keyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3052-8426</contrib-id><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name><address><email>lixin@njau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1953-0242</contrib-id><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Shihao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Wuxiu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Yafang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Yining</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Zhubing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Zhenguo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Da</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 3548</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.258164.c</institution-id><institution>Institute of Traditional Chinese Medicine and Natural Products, College of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Jinan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9750 7019</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27871.3b</institution-id><institution>College of Life Sciences, Laboratory Center of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Nanjing Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Nanjing, China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2360 039X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12981.33</institution-id><institution>Guangdong Key Laboratory of Plant Resources, School of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Sun Yat-Sen University, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou, China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9139 560X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256922.8</institution-id><institution>Institute of Plant Stress Biology, State Key Laboratory of Cotton Biology, Department of Biology, </institution><institution>Henan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kaifeng, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>23</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Many studies suggest that there are distinct regulatory processes controlling compound leaf development in different clades of legumes. Loss of function of the <italic>LEAFY</italic> (<italic>LFY</italic>) orthologs results in a reduction of leaf complexity to different degrees in inverted repeat-lacking clade (IRLC) and non-IRLC species. To further understand the role of <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs and the molecular mechanism in compound leaf development in non-IRLC plants, we studied leaf development in <italic>unifoliate leaf</italic> (<italic>un</italic>) mutant, a classical mutant of mungbean (<italic>Vigna radiata</italic> L.), which showed a complete conversion of compound leaves into simple leaves. Our analysis revealed that <italic>UN</italic> encoded the mungbean LFY ortholog (VrLFY) and played a significant role in leaf development. In situ RNA hybridization results showed that <italic>STM</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes were expressed in compound leaf primordia in mungbean. Furthermore, increased leaflet number in <italic>heptafoliate leaflets1</italic> (<italic>hel1</italic>) mutants was demonstrated to depend on the function of <italic>VrLFY</italic> and <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in mungbean. Our results suggested that <italic>HEL1</italic> is a key factor coordinating distinct processes in the control of compound leaf development in mungbean and its related non-IRLC legumes.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="LongSummary"><title>Genetics: Leaf architecture gene evolved early in legume plants</title><p id="Par2">A legume gene involved in determining the spatial pattern of leaflets seems to have evolved this function earlier than previously thought. Xin Li from Nanjing Agricultural University, China, and coworkers studied a mutant variety of mungbean in which the plant&#x02019;s leaves display a simple architecture instead of the usual compound arrangement, with several leaflets joined to a single stem. They discovered a mutation in the mungbean version of a gene called <italic>LEAFY</italic>. This gene, together with others, proved pivotal in compound leaf development in mungbeans. The results run counter to prior data showing that, outside of a small group of related legume species, <italic>LEAFY</italic> plays only to play a minor role in compound leaf development in these agriculturally important plants. The findings could thus inform breeding efforts in legumes generally.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China (National Science Foundation of China)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31700186</award-id><award-id>31700186</award-id><award-id>31700186</award-id><award-id>31700186</award-id><award-id>31700186</award-id><award-id>31700186</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Keyuan</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Shihao</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Wuxiu</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Da</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Plant leaves are the primary photosynthetic organs that are initiated on the flanks of the shoot apical meristem (SAM). The class I <italic>KNOTTED1</italic>-like homeobox (<italic>KNOXI</italic>) genes are involved in the maintenance of the meristem activity of SAM, while the initiation of leaves requires downregulation of <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes at the incipient site<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. In simple-leafed species such as <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, downregulation of <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in leaf primordia is permanent, whereas in most compound-leafed eudicot species, including the tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) and <italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic>, <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes are reactivated in leaf primordia after initiation of leaf development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. In <italic>C. hirsuta</italic>, the leaflet number is reduced in mutants of the <italic>KNOXI</italic> gene <italic>SHOOTMERISTEMLESS</italic> (<italic>ChSTM</italic>) or <italic>BREVIPEDICELLUS</italic> (<italic>ChBP</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. In <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, ectopic expression of the <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes <italic>Tomato KNOTTED1</italic> (<italic>Tkn1</italic>) or <italic>Tkn2</italic> (orthologs of <italic>STM</italic> and <italic>BP</italic> in tomato, respectively) in transgenic lines, or upregulated expression of <italic>Tkn1</italic> or <italic>Tkn2</italic> in related mutants, results in ramification for compound leaves suggesting that regulatory processes mediated by <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes, especially <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes, play pivotal roles in compound leaf development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">However, in the inverted repeat-lacking clade (IRLC) of legumes, which includes <italic>Pisum sativum</italic> and <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic>, the expression of <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes is excluded from leaf primordia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Genetic analysis shows that single mutants, double mutants and triple mutants of 3 <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes, namely, <italic>MtKNOX1</italic>, <italic>MtKNOX2</italic>, and <italic>MtKNOX6</italic>, in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> do not show obvious defects in compound leaves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Thus, <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes may not be involved in compound leaf development in IRLC legume plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Instead, another type of transcription factor, UNIFOLIATA (UNI) in <italic>P. sativum</italic> and SINGLE LEAFLET1 (SGL1) in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, orthologs of LEAFY (LFY) from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, functions in controlling compound leaf development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. The <italic>uni</italic> mutants in pea and <italic>sgl1</italic> mutants in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> exhibit single leaflet phenotypes, and inflorescence and floral defects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Hence, the LFY orthologs appear to play a significant role in compound leaf development in IRLC legumes. Furthermore, it has been shown that the UNI cofactor UNUSUAL FLORAL ORGANS (UFO) in pea, and PALM1, an upstream transcription factor of <italic>SGL1</italic> in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, are involved in the control of leaf complexity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Recent studies show that the adaxial&#x02013;abaxial regulators PHANTASTICA (PHAN), ARGONAUTE7 (AGO7), and AUXIN RESPONSIVE FACTOR 3 (ARF3) regulate the expression level of <italic>PALM1</italic> and therefore control compound leaf development in <italic>M. truncatula</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The function of the <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs during compound leaf development has also been investigated in non-IRLC legumes, including soybean and <italic>L. japonicus</italic> in which KNOXI proteins are expressed in leaves, and are likely associated with compound leaf development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. In <italic>L. japonicus</italic>, a mutant of the <italic>LFY</italic> ortholog <italic>Proliferating Floral Meristem</italic> (<italic>PFM</italic>) exhibits one or two reduced basal leaflets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. In soybean <italic>LFY</italic>-RNAi-silenced lines, only the leaflet number of the compound leaves produced at the second node is reduced<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. This would indicate that there is a minor role in compound leaf development for <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs in non-IRLC legume species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">In this study, we described the compound leaf developmental processes in a non-IRLC legume species, mungbean (<italic>Vigna radiata</italic> L.), a fast-growing (60&#x02013;90 days) warm-season grain legume, and characterized the <italic>unifoliate leaf</italic> (<italic>un</italic>) mutants that showed a complete conversion of compound leaves into simple leaves. Four alleles of <italic>un</italic> carried mutations in the <italic>LFY</italic> ortholog, indicating that the <italic>LFY</italic> ortholog in mungbean played a significant, rather than a minor role in compound leaf development. Phylogenetic analysis of the KNOX gene family in legumes was conducted, and the expression of four <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes was characterized in mungbean using in situ RNA hybridization. Furthermore, genetic interaction and gene expression analysis showed that increased leaflet number in <italic>heptafoliate leaflets1</italic> (<italic>hel1</italic>) mutants involved regulatory processes mediated by <italic>VrLFY</italic> and <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in mungbean. This study showed that the LFY ortholog might play a more significant role in the control of compound leaf development earlier than the time estimated by Champagne et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant material and growth conditions</title><p id="Par7">All the mutants were isolated from the M<sub>2</sub> population of a mutagenized mungbean cultivar, Sulu, generated in Nanjing, China. The gamma irradiator was calibrated to irradiate the seed lots with 400&#x02009;Gy of gamma rays. The M<sub>1</sub> seeds were sown in the field, and the M<sub>2</sub> seeds were individually harvested from the population. Approximately 36 seeds of each M<sub>2</sub> line were planted in individual rows in the field, with a distance of 0.3&#x02009;m between rows. The mutant plants were then individually harvested and sown for further observation in the greenhouse at 26&#x02013;30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with a 16-h light/8-h dark photoperiod at 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The allelic nature of genes was confirmed by crosses among <italic>un1-1</italic>, <italic>un1-2</italic>, <italic>un1-3</italic>, and <italic>un1-4</italic>, using heterozygote parents because the mutants were sterile (the mutant plants were found in F<sub>1</sub> plants of the crosses). The <italic>L. japonicus</italic> ecotype Gifu B-129 was grown at 20&#x02013;22&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with a 16-h light/8-h dark photoperiod at 150&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the greenhouse.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Scanning electron microscopy</title><p id="Par8">Mungbean shoot apices at different developmental stages were fixed in FAA solution containing 3.7% (v/v) formaldehyde, 50% (v/v) ethanol, and 5% (v/v) acetic acid. Before vacuum freeze drying, fixed samples were dehydrated in an ethanol/tert-butanol series. The materials were transferred to a vacuum freeze dryer overnight. The preparation of shoot apices for scanning electron microscopy (SEM) analysis was as described by Chen et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Samples were examined in a JEOL JSM-6360LV (JEOL) SEM at 10&#x02013;15&#x02009;kV of acceleration voltage.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Molecular cloning of the full-length <italic>LFY</italic> gene (<italic>VrLFY</italic>) from mungbean</title><p id="Par9">To clone the full-length mungbean <italic>LFY</italic> gene, we first searched the genome sequence database of mungbean (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plantgenomics.snu.ac.kr">http://plantgenomics.snu.ac.kr</ext-link>) using sequences for <italic>UNI</italic> and <italic>SGL1</italic>. Finally, sequence alignment with <italic>UNI/SGL1/LFY/FLO</italic> coding sequences allowed the open reading frame of <italic>VrLFY</italic> to be defined. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was carried out using the primers in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">3</xref>. PCR products were cloned into the pGEM-T easy vector (Promega), and inserts were characterized by nucleotide sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>In situ hybridization</title><p id="Par10">For in situ probes, gene-specific regions of <italic>VrLFY</italic>, <italic>VrKNOXI</italic>, and <italic>LjKNOXI</italic> genes were generated by PCR with primer sets (see Supplemental Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">4</xref>) and cloned into a pGEM-T vector (Promega, A1360). In situ probes were synthesized from these clones by in vitro transcription using the Digoxigenin RNA Labeling Kit (Roche) from either the T7 or SP6 promoter flanking the insert, generating either sense or anti-sense probes. Mungbean shoot apices were fixed overnight in 4 % (wt/vol) paraformaldehyde, pH 7.0, and then embedded in Paraplast (Sigma). RNase-free slices of the shoot apices were hybridized to digoxigenin-labeled probes and used for subsequent immunological detection as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Expression analysis by quantitative reverse transcription PCR</title><p id="Par11">Shoot apices from 2-week-old mutant and wild-type plants were collected in RNase-free tubes and stored in a &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C freezer. Samples were taken in triplicate as biological replicates. Total RNA was extracted using the Plant RNA Kit (Omega) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Samples were then treated with RNase-free DNase I (Promega) for 30&#x02009;min.</p><p id="Par12">For quantitative reverse transcription PCR (qRT-PCR), first-strand cDNA was synthesized from total RNA using the First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Fermentas). Real-time RT-PCR analysis was performed as three technical replicates in 384-well plates using SYBR&#x000ae; Premix ExTaq&#x02122; (Takara), on an ABI StepOnePlus machine, according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol (Applied Biosystems). The relative expression level of genes was determined by the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;CT</sup> method. Amplification of <italic>VrTUB</italic> (<italic>Vradi05g13910</italic>), a constitutively expressed gene, was used as an internal control to normalize all data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Shoot apices from a single genotype were represented by nine samples; independent total RNA isolations were generated from the three biological replicates, and three technical qRT-PCR replicates were performed on each of the total RNA preparations. The primers used for qRT-PCR are given in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">5</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Transcript profiling by deep-sequencing</title><p id="Par13">For Illumina sequencing, mRNA was purified from shoot apices of 2-week-old seedlings of <italic>un1-1</italic> mutant and wild-type plants and then fragmented into small pieces. Random hexamer primers and reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen) were used to carry out first-strand cDNA synthesis. Second-strand cDNA synthesis was performed with DNA polymerase I (New England BioLabs) after RNase H (Invitrogen) treatment. Four cDNA libraries were constructed, and cDNA sequencing was conducted using the Illumina HiSeq X Ten system according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol, with read lengths of 150&#x02009;bp. The raw data were submitted to the NCBI Short Read Archive (SRP110723). The number of reads per kilobase of exon region in a gene per million mapped reads (RPKM) was used to normalize the gene expression data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Differentially expressed genes were determined between the wild type and mutants according to statistical analysis of the frequency of each transcript, and their corresponding P-values were calculated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. The significance threshold of <italic>P</italic>-values in multiple tests was set by the false discovery rate (FDR). We used a FDR&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 and an absolute value of |log<sub>2</sub> ratio|&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1 as the threshold to judge the significance of gene expression differences.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="Par14">The phylogenetic tree was constructed using the Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis software (MEGA; version 6.0) by the neighbor-joining method (JFF Matrix model) with 1000 bootstrap replications.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="Par15">Sequence data from this article can be found in the GenBank data libraries under the following accession numbers: XP_014491863.1 (VrLFY); XP_017441945.1 (VaLFY); XP_007137848.1 (PhvLFY); XP_003526918.2 (GmLFY1); XP_014630701.1 (GmLFY2); AAX13294.1 (PFM); AAC49782.1 (UNI); XP_003602745.1 (SGL1); XP_002284664.1 (VFL); AF197934_1 (FALSIFLORA); AAM27941.1 (LEAFY); AAA62574.1 (FLORICAULA); AQQ16908.1 (ChLFY); XP_015635355.1 (RFL); and O04407.1 (NEEDLY).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Compound leaf development in mungbean</title><p id="Par16">Similar to <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, <italic>L. japonicus</italic>, and other compound leaf-producing species, leaf development in mungbean was heteroblastic. The first pair of juvenile leaves with simple leaf morphologies emerged in opposite phyllotaxy on the first node of a developing mungbean plant and was succeeded by adult trifoliate leaves in alternate phyllotaxy (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a&#x02013;c</xref>). The wild-type trifoliate leaves of mungbean consisted of a pair of stipules, a petiole, 2 lateral leaflets, a rachis, and a single terminal leaflet (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). To facilitate the characterization of leaf mutants in mungbean, we investigated leaf developmental processes by scanning electron microscopy (SEM). The morphological changes during compound leaf development in mungbean can be divided into seven distinct stages. At Stage 0 (S0), cells along the periphery of SAM were recruited as founder cells and became an incipient leaf primordium (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). At S1, a common leaf primordium formed as a strip of cells grew out along the periphery of SAM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). At the subsequent S2, a pair of stipule primordia emerged at the proximal end of the common leaf primordium (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>), enlarged, and then separated away from the common leaf primordium so that boundaries were established between the two stipules and the common leaf primordium at S3 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>). At S4, a pair of lateral leaflet primordia emerged between the stipule and the common leaf primordium; and then the common leaf primordium differentiated into a terminal leaflet primordium (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1g</xref>). Subsequently, at S5, the lateral leaflet primordia were separated away from a terminal leaflet primordium so that a boundary was established, and trichomes initiated from the abaxial surface of the terminal leaflet primordium (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref>). Following S5, the lateral leaflets and terminal leaflet primordium became folded (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1i</xref>), and the region between the stipule and lateral leaflet primordia expanded to become a petiole as a result of cell division and cell expansion at the S6 stage.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>The ontogeny of compound leaf development in wild-type mungbean.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Whole plant morphology of mungbean. The arrow indicates the opposite juvenile leaves at the first node. <bold>b</bold> A pair of juvenile leaves of mungbean. <bold>c</bold> Adult compound leaf of mungbean. <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>i</bold> SEM analysis of compound leaf development. <bold>d</bold> Sites of the incipient leaf primordia were specified at the periphery of the SAM at S0. At S1, a common leaf primordium was initiated as a strip of cells outgrowing along the periphery of SAM. <bold>e</bold> A pair of stipule primordia (ST) was initiated from the proximal end of the common leaf primordium at S2. <bold>f</bold> At S3, the boundaries (arrows) between the stipule and lateral leaflet primordia were formed. <bold>g</bold> At S4, a pair of lateral leaflet primordia (LL) emerged between the stipule and common leaf primordium. <bold>h</bold> At S5, the common leaf primordium differentiated into a terminal leaflet primordium (TL) as indicated by development of trichomes from the abaxial surface. Boundaries (arrows) were formed between the lateral and terminal leaflet primordia. <bold>i</bold> At S6, the leaflet primordia folded as a result of outgrowth of the abaxial surface, and the region between the stipule and lateral leaflet primordia expanded to form a petiole (P). Trichomes developed from the abaxial surface of both the stipule and lateral leaflet primordia. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;1&#x02009;cm; <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>i</bold> Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x02009;&#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_88_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e982"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Isolation and characterization of <italic>un</italic> mutants in mungbean</title><p id="Par17">Four similar leaf mutants (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">1</xref>), which mimicked the phenotype of the classical mutant <italic>un</italic>, were isolated from a mutant population of mungbean generated by gamma irradiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Genetic analyses demonstrated that they were allelic (Materials and Methods section). In these mutants, all adult leaves consisted of a short petiole bearing a single terminal leaflet (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref>). Compared with the terminal leaflet of the wild type, the single terminal leaflet of the mungbean <italic>un</italic> mutant was larger (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). We found that the heteroblastic progression was also delayed in <italic>un</italic> mutants such that two simple leaves were produced at the first and second nodes in opposite phyllotaxis. Flowers that developed in <italic>un</italic> mutants were abnormal and infertile. <italic>un</italic> mutants produced sepal-like proliferating structures that lacked petals and stamens, and the number of whorls of organs within the flowers was increased (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Because of their infertility, <italic>un</italic> mutants were maintained as heterozygotes. Progeny from self-pollination of heterozygous lines segregated in a 3:1 ratio (33 wild-type plants and 9 mutant plants, <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.28&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup><sub>0.05</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.99), suggesting that the mutant phenotype was controlled by a single-recessive gene.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Phenotypes of mungbean <italic>unifoliate</italic> (un) mutants.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Wild-type mungbean (left) and <italic>un1-1</italic> mutant (right) exhibiting compound and simple leaf forms, respectively. Arrows indicate the opposite juvenile leaves at the first node in the wild type and at the first and second nodes in the <italic>un1-1</italic> mutant. <bold>b</bold> Close-up views of the adult leaves of the wild type (left) and <italic>un1-1</italic> mutant (right). <bold>c</bold> Morphology of a mature <italic>un1-1</italic> mutant (right), exhibiting simple leaf and floral homeotic phenotypes compared to the wild type (left). The inset has a close-up view of the inflorescence of the <italic>un1-1</italic> mutant. <bold>d</bold>, <bold>f</bold> Leaf development of wild type at S4 and S6. <bold>e</bold>, <bold>h</bold> Leaf development of <italic>un1-1</italic> at S4 and S6. The lateral leaflet primordia did not form at the proximal end of the common leaf primordium. LL lateral leaflet, TL terminal leaflet, SL single leaflet. <bold>b</bold>&#x02013;<bold>c</bold> Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;10&#x02009;cm; <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;m indicated</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_88_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1104"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">To characterize leaf development defects in mungbean <italic>un</italic> mutants, SEM analysis of leaf development was conducted. This analysis indicated that in <italic>un</italic> mutants, leaf development was initially normal until S4, at which point, the pair of lateral leaflet primordia failed to initiate between the stipule and the common leaf primordium (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d, e</xref>). All four alleles of the mungbean <italic>un</italic> mutants exhibited this identical defect. The defect in the initiation of the lateral leaflet primordia was persistent throughout subsequent developmental stages, resulting in the formation of simple adult leaves in the <italic>un</italic> mutants of mungbean (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f, g</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Molecular cloning of <italic>VrLFY</italic> in mungbean</title><p id="Par19">The floral homeotic defects and single-leaf phenotype of the <italic>un</italic> mutants resembled that of the <italic>uni</italic> mutant in pea and the <italic>sgl1</italic> mutant in <italic>M. truncatula</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. The full-length DNA sequence of the <italic>LFY</italic> ortholog (<italic>VrLFY</italic>) in mungbean was obtained from the mungbean genomic database; the genomic sequence of <italic>VrLFY</italic> was 2155&#x02009;bp in length. Alignment of the genomic sequence of <italic>VrLFY</italic> with its cDNA sequence showed the existence of two introns (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a</xref>). PCR amplification of mungbean genomic <italic>LFY</italic> from the <italic>un</italic> mutants and from the wild-type plants indicated that three <italic>un</italic> alleles (<italic>un1-1</italic>, <italic>un1-2</italic>, and <italic>un1-3</italic>) carried deletions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). Nucleotide sequencing showed that another allele, the <italic>un1-4</italic> mutant, had only a single base-pair substitution from the wild type gene (GAA to GGA, Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a</xref>). This resulted in an amino acid change (E112G, where the acidic amino acid Glu was replaced by a neutral amino acid Gly) in the N terminal domain of the protein (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1b</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Molecular cloning of the VrLFY gene from mungbean.</title><p><bold>a</bold> PCR amplification of the <italic>VrLFY</italic> gene from wild-type mungbean and <italic>un</italic> mutants (WT, <italic>un1-1</italic>, <italic>un1-2</italic>, <italic>un1-3</italic>, and <italic>un1-4</italic>). Deletions were detected as no product on attempted amplification of the <italic>VrLFY</italic> gene from three mutant alleles. <bold>b</bold> Phylogenetic analysis of VrLFY and its putative orthologs: VaLFY of <italic>V. angularis</italic>, PvLFY of <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>, GmLFY1 and GmLFY2 of soybean, PFM of <italic>L. japonicas</italic>, UNI of pea, SGL1 of <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, VFL of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>, FALSIFLORA of tomato, FLORICAULA of snapdragon, LEAFY of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, ChLFY of <italic>C. hirsute</italic>, RFL of rice and NEEDLY of <italic>Pinus radiata</italic>. Bootstrap supports above 50 % from 1000 replicates are shown. <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>
<italic>VrLFY</italic> gene expression was detected in SAM and developing leaf primordia. <bold>e</bold> The <italic>VrLFY</italic> sense probes were used as a negative control, and no hybridization signal was detected in SAM and leaf primordia. Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_88_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1278"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Segregation analysis of an F<sub>2</sub> population of the <italic>un1-1</italic> allele indicated that 50 out of a total of 208 individuals were homozygous for the deletion and exhibited both simple leaf and floral homeotic defects, suggesting that the deletion in the corresponding <italic>VrLFY</italic> gene cosegregated with the mutant phenotype. Thus, the locus of <italic>un</italic> in mungbean was allelic to <italic>VrLFY</italic>, which encoded a putative plant-specific transcription factor closely related to UNI in pea and SGL1 in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>). In situ RNA hybridization data revealed that the <italic>VrLFY</italic> gene was expressed in the SAM and in the emerging leaf primordia (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>) and showed relatively high expression in the distal portion of leaf primordia (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Characterization and expression analysis of <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in mungbean</title><p id="Par21">To characterize the <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in mungbean, we conducted a BLAST search of its genome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plantgenomics.snu.ac.kr">http://plantgenomics.snu.ac.kr</ext-link>), verifying candidate genes with the public transcriptome dataset<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Sixteen KNOX proteins were identified from mungbean and these were divided into three classes (class I, class II, and class M) based on phylogenetic analysis (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Nine proteins were classified as STM-like KNOXI proteins (Vradi07g26830, Vradi10g07810 and Vradi06g03570), BP-like KNOXI protein (Vradi06g14320) and KNAT2/6-like KNOXI proteins (Vradi08g11380, Vradi03g07470, Vradi05g04350, Vradi11g09640, and Vradi0322S00070). Five KNOXII proteins were classified as KNAT3/4/5-like proteins (Vradi05g1039, Vradi05g03240, and Vradi07g21010) and KNAT7-like proteins (Vradi11g02470 and Vradi07g13210). In addition, there were two members of class M KNOX proteins found in our mungbean sequence search (Vradi01g05360 and Vradi11g11780).</p><p id="Par22">It has been reported that <italic>STM</italic>/<italic>BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in tomato and <italic>C. hirsuta</italic> are expressed in the compound leaf and are involved in the control of lateral leaflet development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. However, <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes are not associated with compound leaf development in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> and pea<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Previously, accumulation of KNOXI proteins in compound leaf primordia of non-IRLC legumes was detected by polyclonal KNOXI-specific antibodies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. To compare the expression patterns of <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in mungbean with those of IRLC-legume and model plant species, in situ RNA hybridization of four <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes (<italic>Vradi07g26830</italic>, <italic>Vradi10g07810</italic>, <italic>Vradi06g03570</italic>, and <italic>Vradi06g14320</italic>) was carried out on sections of apices from 2-week-old mungbean seedlings (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The results showed that there were different expression patterns among the four <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like genes in mungbean (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a&#x02013;d</xref>). The expression of the two <italic>STM</italic>-like genes <italic>Vradi10g07810</italic> and <italic>Vradi06g03570</italic> was strongly detected in the shoot apical meristem, and transcripts were also observed in the leaf primordia (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b, c</xref>). However, expression of the <italic>STM</italic>-like gene <italic>Vradi07g26830</italic> and the <italic>BP</italic>-like gene <italic>Vradi06g14320</italic> was detected in the SAM but not in the leaf primordia (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, d</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>RNA in situ hybridization analysis of STM/BP-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> gene expression in mungbean.</title><p>RNA in situ hybridization analysis of <bold>a</bold>
<italic>Vradi07g26830</italic>, <bold>b</bold>
<italic>Vradi10g07810</italic>, <bold>c</bold>
<italic>Vradi06g03570</italic>, and <bold>d</bold>
<italic>Vradi06g14320</italic> in the vegetative apices of mungbean. No expression was detected using the control sense probes of <bold>e</bold>
<italic>Vradi07g26830</italic>, <bold>f</bold>
<italic>Vradi10g07810</italic>, <bold>g</bold>
<italic>Vradi06g03570</italic>, and <bold>h</bold>
<italic>Vradi06g14320</italic>. Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_88_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1511"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">Therefore, our data showed that the expression patterns of 2 <italic>STM</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes from mungbean differed from pea and <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, as in those species, no <italic>STM</italic>-like genes have been shown to be expressed in any stage of the compound leaf primordia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Moreover, <italic>BP</italic>-like genes were not expressed in the compound leaf primordia of mungbean, <italic>L. japonicus</italic>, pea and <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, which is a different situation from the expression of these genes in <italic>C. hirsuta</italic> and tomato<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Transcript profiling of VrLFY downstream targets</title><p id="Par24">To address the molecular function of <italic>VrLFY</italic> during leaf development, the transcriptome of shoot apices of 2-week-old seedlings from <italic>un1-1</italic> mutant and wild-type plants was studied using RNA-Seq. A total of 538 differentially expressed genes (300 downregulated and 238 upregulated) were identified between the mutant and wild-type plants (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">2</xref>). The results revealed a significant representation of genes associated with circadian rhythm and plant hormone signal transduction (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">2</xref>). In the <italic>un1</italic> mutants, the genes encoding proteins with high similarity to GIGANTEA 3 (GI3), GIGANTEA-like, Phytochrome A (PHYA), TIME OF CAB EXPRESSION 1 (TOC1), CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED 1 (CCA1), EARLY FLOWERING 3 (ELF3), and Adagio protein 3 (ADO3) were significantly downregulated, while those with high similarity to LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL (LHY) were significantly upregulated. It has been reported that these are key factors in the regulation of the circadian clock and regulate important developmental transitions such as flowering, which was consistent with the involvement of LFY and its orthologs in controlling flowering time and phase transition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">Previous studies have reported that plant hormones, including auxin and gibberellins (GA), play critical roles in leaflet initiation and compound leaf development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. In our expression studies, auxin, GA, ethylene and cytokinin-related genes were significantly differentially expressed in mutants compared to wild-type plants (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">2</xref>). In addition, a number of receptor-like protein kinases were differentially expressed, which might imply that several signaling cascades involved in cell proliferation and differentiation play a significant role in the control of compound leaf development in mungbean.</p><p id="Par26">The transcripts of the <italic>KNOX</italic> family genes showed no obvious differential expression (data not shown), with the exception that one of the class M <italic>KNOX</italic> genes, <italic>Vradi11g11780</italic>, was decreased by approximately eightfold in vegetative shoot apices of the <italic>un1-1</italic> mutant compared with the wild-type plant (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">2</xref>), and this was confirmed by qRT-PCR (data not shown). It has been reported that increasing the expression of class M <italic>KNOX</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and tomato results in serrated leaves and a larger number of leaflets, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Genetic interactions affecting compound leaf development in mungbean mutants</title><p id="Par27">Other mutants that showed an increase in the number of leaflets were identified, including <italic>heptafoliate leaflets1</italic> (<italic>hel1</italic>) and <italic>small-pentafoliate leaflets1</italic> (<italic>smp1</italic>), with 2 and 3 alleles, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a&#x02013;c</xref>; Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The juvenile leaves of the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant showed an extreme dissection and leaflet-like structures, sometimes associated with stipules, which developed in the proximal part of the blade (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). The juvenile leaves of the <italic>smp1</italic> mutant were normal, but the adult leaves exhibited five leaflets of small size (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). We made crosses between <italic>hel1</italic> and <italic>smp1</italic> to examine genetic interactions. In the resulting F<sub>2</sub> population, there were four classes of leaflet size and number: trifoliate, heptafoliate, small-heptafoliate, and small-pentafoliate. The numbers of plants in the different leaflet classes approximated a 9:3:3:1 ratio of the respective phenotypes (data not shown), suggesting that there were 2 unlinked genes controlling the multiple leaflet trait in mungbean. Further genetic analysis showed that the small-heptafoliate plants were <italic>hel1 smp1</italic> double mutants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>), indicating that there was no additive phenotype of the double mutation in terms of leaflet number and that <italic>HEL1</italic> interacted genetically with <italic>SMP1</italic> in the control of leaflet number in mungbean compound leaf development.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Genetic interactions among leaf mutants in mungbean.</title><p>Compound leaf phenotype of the wild type and mutants. <bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> Mature compound leaves of <bold>a</bold> WT, <bold>b</bold>
<italic>hel1-1</italic>, <bold>c</bold>
<italic>smp1-1</italic>, <bold>d</bold>
<italic>hel1-1 smp1-1</italic>, <bold>e</bold>
<italic>un1-1</italic>, and <bold>f</bold>
<italic>hel1-1 un1-1</italic> mutants (all in the Sulu ecotype). Leaves of the <italic>hel1-1 un1-1</italic> double mutants exhibited three leaflets with short petioles. The <italic>hel1-1 smp1-1</italic> double mutants were heptafoliate leaves of small size, indicating an epistatic interaction between <italic>hel1</italic> and <italic>smp1</italic> in the control of leaflet number. Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;10&#x02009;cm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_88_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1755"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">To genetically test the involvement of <italic>un</italic> in the proliferation of lateral leaflet primordia in the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant, we generated <italic>hel1-1 un1-1</italic> double mutants. Juvenile plants of the double mutant were similar to that of a <italic>hel1</italic> single mutant. However, all adult leaves in the <italic>hel1-1 un1-1</italic> double mutants consisted of a short petiole bearing two lateral leaflets and one terminal leaflet (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5f</xref>), indicating the requirement for the <italic>VrLFY</italic> gene in the proliferation of lateral leaflet primordia in the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant. In addition to the alterations in leaflet number, the <italic>hel1</italic> and <italic>un</italic> mutants also exhibited alterations in the proximal-distal axis of compound leaves. Compared with wild-type leaves, the petiole length of mature leaves in the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant was increased by approximately 10%, while the mature leaves of the <italic>un</italic> mutant exhibited short petioles (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b, e</xref>). Interestingly, the petiole length of mature leaves of <italic>hel1-1 un1-1</italic> double mutants was short (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5f</xref>), resembling those of the <italic>un</italic> single mutant, suggesting that <italic>un</italic> is genetically epistatic to <italic>hel1</italic> in leaf petiole development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>HEL1 regulates the expression of <italic>VrLFY</italic> and <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes</title><p id="Par29">The genetic analysis described above indicated that <italic>HEL1</italic> controls trifoliate development via 2 distinct pathways, either dependent or independent of LFY. We first examined the expression of <italic>VrLFY</italic> and its putative upstream transcription factor <italic>PALM1</italic> (<italic>VrPALM1</italic>) and cofactor <italic>UFO</italic> (<italic>VrUFO</italic>) in the wild type and <italic>hel1</italic> mutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. qRT-PCR data revealed that in vegetative shoot apices of the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant compared with wild-type plants, <italic>VrLFY</italic> and <italic>VrUFO</italic> transcript levels were increased by threefold and fourfold, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). However, <italic>VrPALM1</italic> transcript levels showed no obvious change in the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant compared with wild-type plants. Because some <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes expressed in the compound leaf were likely associated with compound leaf development in mungbean, we further examined the expression of <italic>KNOX</italic> genes in the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant and wild-type plants. The results showed that the expression of the 4 <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes was significantly upregulated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>), while other <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes were not upregulated (data not shown). Interestingly, a <italic>KNOXM</italic> gene, <italic>Vradi11g11780</italic> (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>), was also upregulated by fourfold in the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). Taken together, these data suggest that HEL1 regulates the expression of <italic>LFY</italic> and <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes to determine the leaflet number in mungbean.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>qRT-PCR analysis of key genes expressed in <italic>hel</italic> mutants.</title><p>qRT-PCR analysis of gene expression relative to that of the mungbean <italic>TUB</italic> gene. The level of transcripts was examined in the shoot apices of mutants compared with wild-type plants 2 weeks after seed germination. Bars represent means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEs (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). <italic>Vradi07g26830</italic> is a KNOXM gene. <italic>Vradi07g26830</italic>, <italic>Vradi10g07810</italic>, <italic>Vradi06g03570</italic>, and <italic>Vradi06g14320</italic> are <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41438_2018_88_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1962"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec20"><title>The role of the <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs in compound leaf development in legumes</title><p id="Par30">In most compound-leafed species, activation of <italic>KNOXI</italic> gene expression in the leaf primordia is correlated with the development of compound leaves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. However, in IRLC legume species with compound leaves such as pea and <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, the <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes are excluded from the leaf primordia, and their expression is not correlated with compound leaf development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. In these plants, the <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs appear to function in place of the <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in controlling compound leaf development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. The pea <italic>uni</italic> mutants and <italic>M. truncatula sgl1</italic> mutants exhibit compound leaf defects, with all adult leaves changed to simple leaves, indicating that the <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs play a significant role in compound leaf development in IRLC legumes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par31">The available information on the role of <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs in compound leaf development in non-IRLC legumes comes from phenotypic analysis of <italic>L. japonicus pfm</italic> mutants and soybean <italic>LFY</italic> transgenic lines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. In the <italic>pfm</italic> mutants, compound leaves lack 1 or 2 basal leaflets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. In transgenic soybean lines in which the endogenous <italic>LFY</italic> genes are downregulated, only the leaflet number of the compound leaves produced at the second node is reduced<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. In tomato, the mutant of the <italic>LFY</italic> ortholog, <italic>fa</italic>, has a reduced number of small leaflets present on the compound leaf<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Recently, it has been reported that the <italic>lfy</italic> mutant in <italic>C. hirsuta</italic> shows a lower number of leaflets than the wild type<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Therefore, it seems that the single leaflet phenotype caused by mutations of the <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs is only exhibited in IRLC legumes. It is thought that the <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs acquired a more significant role no earlier than the divergence of the Hologalegina clade from the other legumes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par32">However, our results showed that the <italic>un</italic> mutants in mungbean, with a complete conversion of compound leaves into simple leaves, were loss-of-function mutations of <italic>VrLFY</italic>. This finding indicated that <italic>VrLFY</italic> could play a significant rather than a minor role in compound leaf development in mungbean, a member of the non-IRLC legumes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a&#x02013;c</xref>). Interestingly, mutants exhibiting simple leaves and malformed flowers have also been reported in other non-IRLC legumes, including adzuki bean and cowpea<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. While unproven, one could speculate that some of these mutant phenotypes in adzuki bean and cowpea, with similarities to the <italic>un</italic> mutants in mungbean, could also be caused by mutations of <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs. If so, <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs could play a significant role in compound leaf development in other non-IRLC legumes, not just in mungbean. In addition, the question of when in evolution <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs acquired a significant role in compound leaf development might need to be re-addressed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Further investigation of the function of <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs in leaf development of different clades of non-IRLC legumes would be helpful in answering this question.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Expression pattern of <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in legumes</title><p id="Par33">Phylogenetic analysis showed that there were duplications of <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in legumes (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). There was 1 <italic>STM</italic> gene and 1 <italic>BP</italic> gene in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, tomato and <italic>C. hirsuta</italic>. However, in IRLC legumes such as <italic>M. truncatula</italic> and pea, there were 2 <italic>STM</italic>-like genes and 1 <italic>BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> gene. In non-IRLC legumes such as mungbean and <italic>L. japonicus</italic>, there were 3 <italic>STM</italic>-like genes and 1 <italic>BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> gene. <italic>In situ</italic> RNA hybridization showed that the 2 <italic>STM</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in mungbean were expressed at the compound leaf primordia (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), which was different from that of pea and <italic>M. truncatula</italic> in which none of the <italic>STM</italic>-like genes were expressed in any stage of the compound leaf primordia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. <italic>BP</italic>-like genes were not expressed in the compound leaf primordia of mungbean (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) and <italic>L. japonicus</italic> or in pea and <italic>M. truncatula</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. This result was in contrast to findings of <italic>BP</italic> orthologs from <italic>C. hirsuta</italic> and tomato, which were expressed in the compound leaf primordia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. It has been shown that differences in expression patterns between <italic>BP</italic> from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and <italic>ChBP</italic> from <italic>C. hirsuta</italic> are attributable to their cis-regulatory regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. When <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes are overexpressed in <italic>M. truncatula</italic> and <italic>Alfalfa</italic>, there is an increase in leaflet number<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The loss of the role for <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in compound leaf development of IRLC legumes also likely occurred due to a loss of expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. However, this loss of expression of the <italic>STM</italic>-like and <italic>BP</italic>-like genes in compound leaf primordia in IRLC legumes could have occurred at different times in evolution because <italic>BP</italic>-like genes were also not expressed in compound leaf primordia in non-IRLC legumes, such as mungbean and <italic>L. japonicus</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>VrLFY could interact with KNOXI in mungbean to regulate compound leaf development</title><p id="Par34">In simple-leafed species, <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs play a key role in phase transition and floral development. Many downstream targets and DNA binding motifs of LFY have been identified at the genomic level in the model plant <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Despite its key role in compound leaf development in species such as pea and <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, how the LFY orthologs regulate downstream genes to affect lateral organ development, especially that of compound leaf development, remains elusive. In this study, transcriptomic analysis uncovered a total of 538 differentially expressed genes between mutants and the wild type. Several types of key factors, such as <italic>CCA1</italic> and <italic>ELF3</italic>, involved in flowering time and phase transition were among the significantly differentially expressed genes (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">2</xref>), which was consistent with the conserved function of LFY orthologs in plants.</p><p id="Par35">LFY has been reported to regulate the expression of some <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes such as <italic>BP</italic> and <italic>KNAT2</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> during pedicel and flower development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. However, the transcription levels of the <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes showed no obvious change in the <italic>un</italic> mutant compared with the wild-type plant (data not shown), suggesting that <italic>VrLFY</italic> does not regulate the expression of <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes at the transcriptional level in mungbean. Nevertheless, 1 class M <italic>KNOX</italic> gene, <italic>Vradi11g11780</italic>, with high similarity to <italic>PETROSELIUM</italic> (<italic>PTS</italic>) in tomato and <italic>FUSED COMPOUND LEAF</italic> (<italic>FCL2</italic>) in <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, was downregulated 3.5-fold in the <italic>un1-1</italic> mutant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. It has been shown that the class M KNOX proteins in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and tomato could form heterodimers with BEL1-like homeodomain (BELL) proteins and interfere with the regulatory networks of KNOXI-BELL complexes during leaf development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> lines overexpressing <italic>KNATM-B</italic> exhibit serrated leaves, and a mutant with upregulated expression of the <italic>PTS</italic> gene in tomato exhibits a proliferation of compound leaves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. In <italic>M. truncatula</italic>, the class M <italic>KNOX</italic> gene <italic>FCL1</italic> has been shown to control boundary establishment and petiole length of compound leaves and is required for the development of extra leaflet primordia in a <italic>palm1</italic> mutant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Therefore, our results indicated that <italic>VrLFY</italic> might modulate KNOXI regulatory networks by regulating the expression of a class M <italic>KNOX</italic> gene (<italic>Vradi11g11780</italic>) to control compound leaf development. Mutant databases for model legume plants such as <italic>M</italic>. <italic>truncatula</italic> and <italic>L</italic>. <italic>japonicus</italic> and legume crops such as soybean are available<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. It would be worth identifying mutants of <italic>Vradi11g11780/FCL2</italic> orthologs and dissecting their roles in compound leaf development in different legumes. Furthermore, it will also be necessary to identify mutations of the <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes in mungbean and other non-IRLC legumes to investigate gene and protein interactions between <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes and the <italic>LFY</italic> orthologs during compound leaf development in non-IRLC plants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>HEL1 could orchestrate <italic>VrLFY</italic> and <italic>KNOXI</italic> to control compound leaf development in mungbean</title><p id="Par36">Our results suggested that there were 2 distinct regulatory processes mediated by the LFY ortholog and KNOXI proteins during compound leaf development in mungbean. It also raised the question of how the two processes were coordinated during compound leaf development in mungbean. The <italic>HEL1</italic> gene was a key locus of mungbean in the control of leaflet number, whose mutation resulted in dissected juvenile leaves and heptafoliate adult leaves (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref> and Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). Double mutant analysis showed that <italic>hel1</italic> genetically interacted with <italic>un</italic> and <italic>smp1</italic> to control the leaflet number of the compound leaves, indicating that lateral leaflet formation in the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant was dependent not only on <italic>LFY</italic> but also on other regulators in the control of compound leaf development. Consistently, gene expression analysis showed that the <italic>STM/BP</italic>-like <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes and a <italic>KNOXM</italic> gene, <italic>VrLFY</italic>, as well as its putative cofactor <italic>VrUFO</italic>, were significantly upregulated in the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant compared to the wild type (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Therefore, these results suggested that HEL1 could coordinate the regulatory processes mediated by VrLFY and KNOXI to control compound leaf development in mungbean.</p><p id="Par37">Interestingly, <italic>heptafoliate-leaf</italic>-<italic>like</italic> mutants similar to the <italic>hel1</italic> mutant in mungbean were also identified and characterized in other legumes, including soybean and cowpea<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. In soybean, the seven-leaflet character is a single recessive trait conditioned by the <italic>lf2</italic> locus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Preliminary mapping results in mungbean revealed that the <italic>HEL1</italic> gene was located to a region of chromosome 11, which showed synteny with the <italic>lf2</italic> locus in soybean (data not shown)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Future work to clone the <italic>HEL1</italic> gene and its ortholog in soybean and related legumes could provide new insights into the molecular mechanisms orchestrating the two regulatory processes mediated by the <italic>LFY</italic> ortholog and <italic>KNOXI</italic> genes during compound leaf development in mungbean and other legumes.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec24"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41438_2018_88_MOESM1_ESM.jpg"><caption><p>Supplementary Figure 1. LFY gene structure and alignment of protein sequences</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41438_2018_88_MOESM2_ESM.jpg"><caption><p>Supplementary Figure 2. Phylogenetic analysis of members of KNOX gene family in mungbean, L. japonicus, M. truncatula, pea, and Arabidopsis</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41438_2018_88_MOESM3_ESM.jpg"><caption><p>Figure S3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41438_2018_88_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Table 1 The information of wild type and mutant lines</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="41438_2018_88_MOESM5_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Table 2 The list of the differentiated expressed genes in un1-1 mutant compared with wild type</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="41438_2018_88_MOESM6_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Table 3 The list of primers for PCR detection in un mutants</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="41438_2018_88_MOESM7_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Table 4 The list of primers for in in situ hybridization</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="41438_2018_88_MOESM8_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Table 5 The list of primers for qRT-PCR</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>These authors have contributed equally: Keyuan Jiao, Xin Li and Shihao Su</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at (10.1038/s41438-018-0088-0).</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 31700186) and the Ministry of Agriculture of China for Transgenic Research (Grant No. 2014ZX0800943B).</p></ack><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moan</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Medford</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A member of the KNOTTED class of homeodomain proteins encoded by the STM gene of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>379</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/379066a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8538741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of the maize homeo box gene, KNOTTED-1, causes a switch from determinate to indeterminate cell fates</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>1993</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>795</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.7.5.787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7684007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Veit</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of maize KNOTTED 1 related homeobox genes in the shoot apical meristem predicts patterns of morphogenesis in the vegetative shoot</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1994</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>413</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hareven</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutfinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lifschitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The making of a compound leaf: genetic manipulation of leaf architecture in tomato</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81051-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8625411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A gene fusion at a homeobox locus: alterations in leaf shape and implications for morphological evolution</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1289</fpage><lpage>1304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.9.8.1289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9286107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharathan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Homologies in leaf form inferred from KNOXI gene expression during development</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>296</volume><fpage>1858</fpage><lpage>1860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1070343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12052958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsiantis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genetic basis for differences in leaf form between <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and its wild relative <italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic></article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2006</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>942</fpage><lpage>947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16823378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rast-Somssich</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alternate wiring of a KNOXI genetic network underlies differences in leaf development of <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and <italic>C. hirsuta</italic></article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2015</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>2391</fpage><lpage>2404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.269050.115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26588991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parnis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The dominant developmental mutants of tomato, Mouse-ear and Curl, are associated with distinct modes of abnormal transcriptional regulation of a Knotted gene</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2143</fpage><lpage>2158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.9.12.2143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9437860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stage-specific regulation of <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> leaf maturation by class 1 KNOTTED1-LIKE HOMEOBOX proteins</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3078</fpage><lpage>3092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.068148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19820191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourlay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of a class 1 knotted1-like homeobox gene is down-regulated in pea compound leaf primordia</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1010739812836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11352458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Compound leaf development and evolution in the legumes</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3369</fpage><lpage>3378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.107.052886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17993625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STM/BP-like KNOXI is uncoupled from ARP in the regulation of compound leaf development in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1464</fpage><lpage>1479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.123885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24781113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LEAFY controls floral meristem identity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>859</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(92)90295-N</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1350515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UNIFOLIATA regulates leaf and flower morphogenesis in pea</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(06)00257-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9259553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of compound leaf development by FLORICAULA/LEAFY ortholog SINGLE LEAFLET1 in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>1759</fpage><lpage>1772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.117044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18287485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Murfet</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stamina pistilloida, the Pea ortholog of Fim and UFO, is required for normal development of flowers, inflorescences, and leaves</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.13.1.31</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of dissected leaf morphology by a Cys(2)His(2) zinc finger transcription factor in the model legume <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>10754</fpage><lpage>10759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1003954107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20498057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>(2014). PHANTASTICA regulates leaf polarity and petiole identity in Medicago truncatula</article-title><source>Plant Signal. Behav.</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e28121</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.28121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The transacting short interfering RNA3 pathway and no apical meristem antagonistically regulate leaf margin development and lateral organ separation, as revealed by analysis of an argonaute7/lobed leaflet1 mutant in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>4845</fpage><lpage>4862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.113.117788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24368797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berbel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Madue&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR3 regulates compound leaf patterning by directly repressing PALMATE-LIKE PENTAFOLIATA1 expression in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1630</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.01630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28979286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiple components are integrated to determine leaf complexity in <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic></article-title><source>J. Integr. Plant Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jipb.12034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23331609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of compound leaf development</article-title><source>Plants</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/plants3010001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27135488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LEUNIG has multiple functions in gynoecium development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Genesis</source><year>2002</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1526-968X(200001)26:1&#x0003c;42::AID-GENE7&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-J</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Different expression patterns of duplicated PHANTASTICA-like genes in <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic> suggest their divergent functions during compound leaf development</article-title><source>Cell Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.cr.7290336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16117856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sairam</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dharmar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinnusamy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Meena</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water logging-induced increase in sugar mobilization, fermentation, and related gene expression in the roots of mung bean (<italic>Vigna radiata</italic>)</article-title><source>J. Plant. Physiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2008.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18947901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Audic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Claverie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The significance of digital gene expression profiles</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>986</fpage><lpage>995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.7.10.986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9331369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sangsiri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorajjapinun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivesc</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gamma radiation induced mutations in mungbean</article-title><source>ScienceAsia</source><year>2005</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2306/scienceasia1513-1874.2005.31.251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence of mungbean and insights into evolution within <italic>Vigna</italic> species</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>5451</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian clock and photoperiodic flowering in Arabidopsis, CONSTANS is a hub for signal integration</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.16.01327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27688622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molinero-Rosales</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FALSIFLORA, the tomato orthologue of FLORICAULA and LEAFY, controls flowering time and floral meristem identity</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>1999</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1999.00641.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10652140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monniaux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conservation vs divergence in LEAFY and APETALA1 functions between <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic></article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>216</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28098947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The gibberellin pathway mediates KNOTTED1-type homeobox function in plants with different body plans</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1557</fpage><lpage>1565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(02)01125-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12372247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barkoulas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kougioumoutzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsiantis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A developmental framework for dissected leaf formation in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> relative <italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic></article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1136</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19165928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magnani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KNOX lost the OX, The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> KNATM gene defines a novel class of KNOX transcriptional regulators missing the homeodomain</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.108.058495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18398054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoong</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural variation in leaf morphology results from mutation of a novel KNOX gene</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2008.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18424140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blakeslee</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A unifoliolate mutation in adzuki bean</article-title><source>J. Hered.</source><year>1919</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a101904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawal</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Franckowiak</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fawole</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachie</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unifoliolate leaf, A mutant in cowpeas</article-title><source>J. Hered.</source><year>1976</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a108707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moyroud</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prediction of regulatory interactions from genome sequences using a biophysical model for the Arabidopsis LEAFY transcription factor</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>1306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.083329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21515819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LEAFY target genes reveal floral regulatory logic, cis motifs, and a link to biotic stimulus response</article-title><source>Dev. Cell.</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2011.03.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21497757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Komeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LEAFY controls <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> pedicel length and orientation by affecting adaxial-abaxial cell fate</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2012</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>844</fpage><lpage>856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04836.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22050454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Giacomo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>KNAT3/4/5-like class 2 KNOX transcription factors are involved in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> symbiotic nodule organ development</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27582377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of compound leaf development in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> by fused compoundleaf1, a class M KNOX gene</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>3929</fpage><lpage>3943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.089128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22080596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Large scale insertional mutagenesis using Tnt1 retrotransposon in the model legume <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2008.03418.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18208518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma&#x00142;olepszy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The LORE1 insertion mutant resource</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2016</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27322352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and utilization of a new chemically-induced soybean library with a high mutation density</article-title><source>J. Integr. Plant Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jipb.12505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27774740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic control of leaflet number in soybeans</article-title><source>Crop Sci.</source><year>1972</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1972.0011183X001200020023x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fawole</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic control of leaflet number and shape in cowpea, <italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> (L) Walp</article-title><source>Niger. J. Sci.</source><year>2000</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>80</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seversike</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shultz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soybean molecular linkage group B1 corresponds to classical linkage group 16 based on map location of the lf (2) gene</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2008</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-008-0759-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18392801</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>