<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2045-7758</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECE3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Ecology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-7758</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6093152</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ECE32483</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Higher efficiency of <styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content> markers over plastid <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region in resolving taxonomical status of genus <italic>Ocimum</italic> L.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="ece32483-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Amit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32483-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece32483-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>Priyanka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32483-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece32483-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baskaran</surname><given-names>Kuppusamy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32483-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece32483-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>Ashutosh K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32483-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece32483-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shasany</surname><given-names>Ajit K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32483-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece32483-cr-0006" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Sundaresan</surname><given-names>Velusamy</given-names></name><address><email>vsundaresan@cimap.res.in</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32483-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="ece32483-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Plant Biology and Systematics</named-content>
<institution>CSIR &#x02013; Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants, Research Centre</institution>
<named-content content-type="city">Bengaluru</named-content>
<country country="IN">India</country>
</aff><aff id="ece32483-aff-0002">
<label><sup>2</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Biotechnology Division</named-content>
<institution>CSIR &#x02013; Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants</institution>
<named-content content-type="city">Lucknow</named-content>
<country country="IN">India</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Velusamy Sundaresan, Department of Plant Biology and Systematics, CSIR &#x02013; Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants, Research Centre, Bengaluru, India.<break/>
Email: <email>vsundaresan@cimap.res.in</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>21</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2016.6.issue-21</issue-id><fpage>7671</fpage><lpage>7682</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2016 Published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd. <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2016 The Authors. <italic>Ecology and Evolution</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:ECE3-6-7671.pdf"/><abstract id="ece32483-abs-0001"><title>Abstract</title><p>High level of morphological as well as chemical variability exists within the genus <italic>Ocimum</italic>, and its taxonomy and phylogenetic relationships are still doubtful. For evaluating interspecific genetic relationships among the <italic>Ocimum</italic> species, genotyping with intersimple sequence repeat (<styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content>) markers and sequence analyses of noncoding <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> intergenic region belonging to chloroplast <styled-content style="fixed-case">DNA</styled-content> were carried out. Although <styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content> markers are highly efficient and reproducible, they have not been used extensively in phylogenetic studies. The use of the plastidial barcode candidate was expected to provide more variable and informative insight into evolutionary rates, and was thus employed as a phylogenetic marker to assess interspecific relationships. This study revealed that the <styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content> markers were more efficient than <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> sequences in resolving the current status of <italic>Ocimum</italic> L. genus. Distance&#x02010; and character&#x02010;based methodological approaches applied on the molecular data with biparental and maternal inheritance were used for deducing the phylogenetic relationships among <italic>Ocimum</italic> species. Average polymorphic information content (0.344) and resolving power (6.285) depicted through <styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content> markers proved to be efficient in discriminating the studied species of <italic>Ocimum</italic>. The primers used in this study revealed 99.585% polymorphism across the species demonstrating the polymorphic nature of <styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content> markers.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="ece32483-kwd-0001"><styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content></kwd><kwd id="ece32483-kwd-0002">Lamiaceae</kwd><kwd id="ece32483-kwd-0003"><italic>Ocimum</italic> spp.</kwd><kwd id="ece32483-kwd-0004">Phylogeny</kwd><kwd id="ece32483-kwd-0005"><italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Council of Scientific and Industrial Research</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>XIIth FYP project ChemBio</funding-source><award-id>BSC&#x02010;0203</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="8621"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>ece32483</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>November 2016</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:version=5.4.3 mode:remove_FC converted:18.07.2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-1001">
<string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mishra</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Baskaran</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shukla</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shasany</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<surname>Sundaresan</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>), <article-title>Higher efficiency of <styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content> markers over plastid <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region in resolving taxonomical status of genus <italic>Ocimum</italic> L.</article-title>
<source xml:lang="en">Ecology and Evolution</source>, <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>7671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7682</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2483</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</p><fn-group id="ece32483-ntgp-0001"><fn fn-type="funding" id="ece32483-note-1101"><p>
<bold>Funding Information</bold>
</p><p>Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), New Delhi, XIIth FYP project ChemBio (BSC&#x02010; 0203).</p></fn><fn id="ece32483-note-1001"><p>CIMAP Communication No.: CIMAP/PUB/2016/13.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec id="ece32483-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>The genus <italic>Ocimum</italic> L., belonging to family Lamiaceae (sixth largest family), collectively called as basil is an important economic and medicinal herb, widely distributed in tropical, subtropical, and warm temperate regions of the world (Paton, Harley, &#x00026; Harley, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>). Due to substantial taxonomical complexity caused by polyploidy and possibility of inter&#x02010; and intraspecific hybridization within the genus <italic>Ocimum</italic>, estimates of the number of species vary from 30 (Paton, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>) to 160 (Pushpangadan &#x00026; Bradu, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>). To add further to this complexity, there are varieties having similar chemical compositions within the species that do not differ significantly in morphology (Verma et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko et al. (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) reported that basic chromosome number in <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. is <italic>x</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12. <italic>O. basilicum</italic> and <italic>O. americanum</italic> are reported to be tetraploid (2<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4<italic>x</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;48) and hexaploid (2<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6<italic>x</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;72), respectively. <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> is a perennial shrub with a basic chromosome number of <italic>x</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9, while <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> has a basic chromosome number <italic>x</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10. <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> L., <italic>O. basilicum</italic> L., <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> L., <italic>O. kilimandscharicum</italic> Gurke, <italic>O. americanum</italic> L., and <italic>O. africanum</italic> Lour. are important species belonging to the genus <italic>Ocimum</italic> that grow in different parts of the world and are known for their diverse medicinal properties and as sources of important essential oils (Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Prakash &#x00026; Gupta, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). In India, nine species are found, of which three are exotic (Balyan &#x00026; Pushpangadan, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">1988</xref>). <italic>O. adscendens</italic> is a lesser known species with few studies carried out on it (Asthana, Tripathi, &#x00026; Dixit, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">1986</xref>; Verma et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>).</p><p>
<italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. have been used in folk medicine due to their diverse biological activities, such as mosquito repellency, antimicrobial, insecticidal, antiseptic, carminative, stimulant, antispasmodic, antioxidant, and antipyretic properties (Padalia, Verma, Chauhan, &#x00026; Chanotiya, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> has been well documented in Ayurveda for its therapeutic potential as a <italic>Kapha</italic>&#x02010;balancing plant (Shukla et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) and possesses antioxidant and antimicrobial activities due to its phenolic and aromatic compounds (Verma, Padalia, Chauhan, &#x00026; Thul, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). The oil components of <italic>Ocimum</italic> have been found to be produced by two different biochemical pathways, viz. shikimic acid pathway (phenylpropanoids) and mevalonic acid pathway (terpenes). Essential oil consisting of monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and phenylpropanoids reported from <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. includes linalool, linalyl acetate, geraniol, citral, camphor, eugenol, methyl eugenol, methyl chavicol, methyl cinnamate, thymol, safrole, which are of immense value and have been used principally in the food and cosmetic industries (Balyan &#x00026; Pushpangadan, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">1988</xref>; Vina &#x00026; Murillo, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>).</p><p>The genus <italic>Ocimum</italic> is very variable and possesses a wide range of intra&#x02010; and interspecific genetic diversity. According to previous reports on <italic>Ocimum</italic>, the genus is grouped into three sections: <italic>Ocimum</italic> (<italic>Ocymodon</italic> Benth.), <italic>Hierocymum</italic> Benth., and <italic>Gymnocymum</italic> Benth. Section <italic>Ocimum</italic> was again divided into subsections: <italic>Ocimum</italic>,<italic> Gratissima</italic>, and <italic>Hiantia</italic> Benth (Paton et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>). Further, Pushpangadan divided the whole taxa into two groups: the Basilicum group, containing herbaceous annuals/perennials with black, ellipsoid, strongly mucilaginous seeds, and the Sanctum group, consisting of perennial shrubs with brown, globose, nonmucilaginous, or weakly mucilaginous seeds. According to Pushpangadan's classification, the Basilicum group contains only section <italic>Ocimum</italic> subsection <italic>Ocimum</italic> (Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). However, Pushpangadan's infrageneric classification does not act in accordance with the <italic>International Code of Botanical Nomenclature</italic>. Several studies throughout worldwide related to cytotaxonomical studies, taxonomical status and geographic distribution, classification and relationships, genetic diversity and phylogenetic study, and chemical characterization (Balyan &#x00026; Pushpangadan, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">1988</xref>; Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Paton et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>; Sobti &#x00026; Pushpangadan, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">1979</xref>; Verma et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Vieira &#x00026; Simon, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>) reported ample extent of genetic variability within the genus <italic>Ocimum,</italic> making it taxonomically and phylogenetically convoluted.</p><p>Inter simple sequence repeat (ISSR) markers (Zietkiewicz, Rafalski, &#x00026; Labuda, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>) are dominant genetic markers generated through polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification of genomic DNA using a single primer that amplifies the regions between adjacent, inversely oriented simple sequence repeats, provided the primer binding sites are located within an amplifiable range. The evolutionary rate of change within microsatellites is considerably higher as compared to most other types of DNA, which increases the likelihood of polymorphism in these sequences. However, ISSR markers are present in both nuclear and organellar genomes and are responsible for the generation of highly polymorphic loci. ISSR markers have frequently been used in the characterization of germplasm collections and in the screening of genetic diversity within species (Kumar, Mishra, Singh, &#x00026; Sundaresan, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Mishra et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), cultivar identification (Chowdhury, Vandenberg, &#x00026; Warkentin, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>), molecular mapping, genomic instability assessment, but they are rarely used for phylogeny reconstruction at the species level. The ISSR technique is less expensive comparatively to RFLPs and AFLPs, giving higher reproducibility than RAPDs. Individuals of the same species usually show a few to no difference between their ISSR patterns, whereas closely related taxa, that is, subspecies and species, give a specific banding profile that can be used for deducing phylogenetic relationship.</p><p>Chloroplast DNA (cpDNA) is the smallest as compared to mitochondria and nuclear genome, and during the course of evolution, it is assumed to be conserved in terms of nucleotide substitution with very little rearrangements, which makes the molecule best suited to be used in resolving phylogenetic relationships especially at higher levels of evolution (Zurawski &#x00026; Clegg, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>). cpDNA sequences, particularly the noncoding regions, were in demand as source of markers because they are evolving faster as they have fewer functional constraints than gene&#x02010;coding regions in terms of nucleotide substitution rates (Kimura, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">1983</xref>). Also, this allows comparisons between seed gene flow and pollen gene flow as well as the identification of hybridization events when compared to nuclear, biparentally inherited DNA, demonstrating genealogical structure (Dong et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Thus, noncoding cpDNA sequences are expected to provide more variable and informative characters for phylogenetic studies of evolutionary rates. The <italic>psbA&#x02013;trnH</italic> intergenic spacer, an evolutionarily plastid region, is employed as a phylogenetic marker to assess interspecific relationships.</p><p>
<italic>Ocimum</italic> species are similar in apparent vegetative morphology and often debated upon with regard to their nomenclature and taxonomical positioning. The nomenclature of <italic>Ocimum</italic> species and varieties is complicated and often confusing. Besides, different physicochemical properties have been observed in the oils extracted from morphologically identical plants (single phenotype) (Singh et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). This study on <italic>Ocimum</italic> species from India was carried out with the following objectives: (1) comparative phylogenetic analysis using ISSR markers and plastid DNA (<italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic>) sequences and (2) evaluation of the efficiency of ISSR markers vis&#x02010;&#x000e0;&#x02010;vis chloroplast noncoding <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region in elucidating the phylogenetic relationship among medicinally/agro&#x02010;economically important species of <italic>Ocimum</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="ece32483-sec-0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Plant material</title><p>Seeds from seven different species of <italic>Ocimum</italic> (few of them represented by different varieties) were collected from different parts of India (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Seeds were grown in the ChemBio genebank at CSIR&#x02010;CIMAP Research Centre, Bengaluru, India. The different <italic>Ocimum</italic> species included were <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> L.<italic>, O. basilicum</italic> L.<italic>, O. africanum</italic> Lour, <italic>O. americanum</italic> L.<italic>, O. kilimandscharicum</italic> Gurke<italic>, O. gratissimum</italic> L.<italic>, O. viride</italic> Willd., and <italic>O. adscendens</italic> Willd. Along with the <italic>Ocimum</italic> species, an outgroup taxon <italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic> L. was chosen because of its known distant relationship. According to the plant list, <italic>O. viride</italic> is synonymous to <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theplantlist.org/">http://www.theplantlist.org/</ext-link>), but looks morphologically different. All the voucher specimens of the plant accessions used were deposited in the herbarium at CSIR&#x02010;Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants, Research Centre, Bengaluru, India, located at 12&#x000b0;58&#x02032;N latitude and 77&#x000b0;35&#x02032;E longitude for future reference.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32483-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Different <italic>Ocimum</italic> species from India. (A) <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic>, (B) <italic>Ocimum americanum</italic>, (C) <italic>Ocimum kilimandscharicum</italic>, (D) <italic>Ocimum africanum</italic>, (E) <italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. Ram tulsi, (F) <italic>Ocimum adscendens</italic>, (G) <italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. Krishna tulsi, (H) <italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic>, (I) <italic>Ocimum viride</italic>
</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-6-7671-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="ece32483-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Geographic location of <italic>Ocimum</italic> seed collections</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S. no.</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Code</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Place of collection</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">State</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latitude</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitude</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. Ram tulsi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venkateswarapuram</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tamil Nadu</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N08&#x000b0;55&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E77&#x000b0;34&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. Krishna tulsi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rasipuram</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tamil Nadu</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N11&#x000b0;28&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E78&#x000b0;09&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hilsa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bihar</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N25&#x000b0;20&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E85&#x000b0;17&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum africanum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kanyakumari</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tamil Nadu</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N08&#x000b0;04&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E77&#x000b0;32&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> var. purpurascens</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vasudevanallur</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tamil Nadu</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N09&#x000b0;14&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E77&#x000b0;24&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum americanum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vellur</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tamil Nadu</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N11&#x000b0;06&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E78&#x000b0;00&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum kilimandscharicum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yercaud</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tamil Nadu</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N11&#x000b0;46&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E78&#x000b0;12&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yercaud</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tamil Nadu</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N11&#x000b0;46&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E78&#x000b0;12&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum adscendens</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rajapalayam</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tamil Nadu</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N09&#x000b0;28&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E77&#x000b0;33&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum viride</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jammu Tawi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jammu &#x00026; Kashmir</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N32&#x000b0;43&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E74&#x000b0;50&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bangalore</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karnataka</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N12&#x000b0;58&#x02032;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E77&#x000b0;35&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. CIM&#x02010;Ayu</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lucknow</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uttar Pradesh</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N26&#x000b0;53&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E80&#x000b0;58&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. CIM&#x02010;Angana</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lucknow</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uttar Pradesh</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N26&#x000b0;53&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E80&#x000b0;58&#x02032;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> var. CIM&#x02010;Saumya</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lucknow</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uttar Pradesh</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">N26&#x000b0;53&#x02032;</td><td align="char" char=" " rowspan="1" colspan="1">E80&#x000b0;58&#x02032;</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0004"><label>2.2</label><title>DNA isolation</title><p>Fresh plant leaves were collected, and genomic DNA was isolated using the protocol described by Khanuja, Shasany, Darokar, and Kumar (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>). The purity and concentration of isolated genomic DNA were quantified spectrophotometrically (NanoDrop ND&#x02010;1000, Nanodrop Technologies, Wilmington, Delaware, USA) by measuring absorbance at 260&#x000a0;nm and 280&#x000a0;nm for the OD<sub>260</sub>/OD<sub>280</sub> ratio. Its integrity was checked by visualizing it under UV light after electrophoresis on 0.8% agarose gel. Stock DNA was diluted to make a required working solution of 25&#x000a0;ng/&#x003bc;l.</p></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0005"><label>2.3</label><title>ISSR&#x02010;PCR amplification</title><p>Twenty ISSR primers were procured from the University of British Columbia (UBC set No. 9). PCR reaction was prepared in a total volume of 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l and contained 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0; Taq DNA polymerase buffer (with MgCl<sub>2</sub>) (GeNei&#x02122;), 50&#x000a0;ng genomic DNA, 1 unit of Taq DNA polymerase (GeNei&#x02122;), 200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol/l of each dNTP (dATP: dTTP: dCTP: dGTP in 1:1:1:1 parts) (GeNei&#x02122;), and 0.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol/l primer. Amplifications were carried out using a thermal cycler (iCycler&#x02122; Thermal Cycler, Bio&#x02010;Rad, USA) using the following parameters: initial denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min; 45 cycles of denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min, annealing at 48&#x02013;60&#x000b0;C (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>) for 1&#x000a0;min, extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;min; final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 7&#x000a0;min. Amplicons were electrophoresed on 1.2% agarose gel alongside a 2&#x02010;Log DNA ladder (New England Biolabs Inc.). Gel photographs were taken by means of Bio&#x02010;Rad Universal Hood II gel documentation system (Bio&#x02010;Rad laboratories Inc.).</p><table-wrap id="ece32483-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Marker parameters calculated for each ISSR primer used with <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S. No.</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence (5&#x02032;&#x02013;3&#x02032;)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC%</th><th align="char" char=" " valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>T</italic> [&#x000b0;C]</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PB</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPB (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PIC</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 807</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(AG)<sub>8</sub>T</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.374</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.571</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 809</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(AG)<sub>8</sub>G</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.333</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.571</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 810</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(GA)<sub>8</sub>T</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.325</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.857</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 823</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(TC)<sub>8</sub>C</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.341</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.142</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 825</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(AC)<sub>8</sub>T</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.428</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 826</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(AC)<sub>8</sub>C</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.857</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 828</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(TG)<sub>8</sub>A</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.363</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.285</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 834</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(AG)<sub>8</sub>YT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.714</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 835</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(AG)<sub>8</sub>YC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.365</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.142</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 841</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(GA)<sub>8</sub>YC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.395</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.857</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 843</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(CT)<sub>8</sub>RA</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.299</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.571</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 844</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(CT)<sub>8</sub>RC</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.357</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 845</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(CT)<sub>8</sub>RG</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.342</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.571</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 848</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(CA)<sub>8</sub>RG</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.368</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.142</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 855</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(AC)<sub>8</sub>YT</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.376</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.428</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 856</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(AC)<sub>8</sub>YA</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.343</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 862</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(AGC)<sub>6</sub>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.30</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.328</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.285</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 866</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(CTC)<sub>6</sub>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.338</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.142</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 876</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(GATA)<sub>2</sub>(GACA)<sub>2</sub>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.397</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.285</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBC 881</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(GGGTG)<sub>3</sub>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.327</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.857</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>241</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>240</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avg./Primer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12.05</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12.00</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>99.585</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.344</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6.285</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ece32483-note-0002"><p>
<italic>T</italic> [&#x000b0;C], annealing temperature; R, (A, G); Y, (C, T); TB, total band; PB, polymorphic band; PPB (%), percentage polymorphic band (%); PIC, polymorphic information content; RP, resolving power of primer.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0006"><label>2.4</label><title>PCR amplification and sequencing of <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> (cpDNA)</title><p>Noncoding <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region of cpDNA was amplified using universal primers fwd&#x02010;PA: 5&#x02032;&#x02010;GTT ATG CAT GAA CGT AAT GCT C&#x02010;3&#x02032; and rev&#x02010;TH: 5&#x02032;&#x02010;CGC GCA TGG TGG ATT CAC AAT CC&#x02010;3&#x02032; (Newmaster &#x00026; Ragupathy, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Zheng, Jiang, Wu, Wang, &#x00026; Huang, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). PCR was run in a manner similar to that of ISSR&#x02010;PCR with the following cycling parameters: an initial denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min; 30 cycles of denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min, annealing at 55&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min, extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 90&#x000a0;s; final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 7&#x000a0;min. PCR products were visualized on a 1.2% agarose gel and purified using QIAquick PCR purification kit (QIAGEN) prior to sequencing in both directions on an ABI 3130XL automated sequencer (Applied Biosystems) using both the primers. Sequences generated were deposited at the GenBank (NCBI) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="ece32483-tbl-0003" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Characteristics of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. sequences (of noncoding <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region) deposited in GenBank (NCBI)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S. no.</th><th align="left" colspan="2" valign="top" rowspan="1">Species</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank accession no.</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. Ram tulsi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338799.1">KT338799.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">328</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KU666421.1">KU666421.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">372</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. Krishna tulsi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338800.1">KT338800.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">328</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KU666422.1">KU666422.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338801.1">KT338801.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">323</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KU666423.1">KU666423.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum africanum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338802.1">KT338802.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">338</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KU707910.1">KU707910.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> var. purpurascens</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338803.1">KT338803.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">323</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX096039.1">KX096039.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum americanum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338804.1">KT338804.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">343</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KU707911.1">KU707911.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">284</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum kilimandscharicum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338805.1">KT338805.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">324</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KU707912.1">KU707912.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">292</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338806.1">KT338806.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX013103.1">KX013103.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum adscendens</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338807.1">KT338807.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">328</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX013104.1">KX013104.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">373</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum viride</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338808.1">KT338808.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX013105.1">KX013105.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">358</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338809.1">KT338809.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX013106.1">KX013106.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">271</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. CIM&#x02010;Ayu</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338810.1">KT338810.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">328</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX096040.1">KX096040.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">373</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic> var. CIM&#x02010;Angana</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338811.1">KT338811.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">328</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX096041.1">KX096041.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">372</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> var. CIM&#x02010;Saumya</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT338812.1">KT338812.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">343</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX096042.1">KX096042.1</ext-link>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">344</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.19</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0007"><label>2.5</label><title>Data analysis</title><p>Amplified ISSR products were manually scored for band presence (1) or absence (0) for each accession, and a binary data matrix was constructed. Primer banding characteristics such as the number of total bands (TB), the number of polymorphic bands (PB), and the percentage of polymorphic bands (PPB) were obtained. Polymorphic information content (PIC) analysis is useful for selection of the most appropriate marker for genetic mapping and phylogenetic analysis. It provides an estimate of the discriminating power of the marker based on the number of noticeable alleles and their distribution (Mishra et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Powell et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>). Resolving power (RP) of a marker is yet another parameter for checking the efficiency of discrimination potential of any marker system (Kumar et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Prevost &#x00026; Wilkinson, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>).</p><p>To check the genetic relatedness among the <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp., data matrix of ISSR markers was converted into genetic similarity matrix using Jaccard coefficient (Jaccard, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">1908</xref>) in SPSS 17.0 (SPSS Inc.) and NTSYS&#x02010;PC 2.02j (Rohlf, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">1998</xref>). Bootstrap analysis (Felsenstein, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">1985</xref>) using Nei's (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>) genetic distance search with 1,000 replicates was performed to obtain the confidence of the neighbor&#x02010;joining tree using the software TREECON (Van De Peer &#x00026; Wachter, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>). Further, to highlight the resolving power of the ordination, principal component analysis (PCA) was performed based on similarity coefficient of data realized from ISSR average similarity indices using SPSS statistics 17.0 software (SPSS Inc.).</p></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0008"><label>2.6</label><title>Sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis</title><p>Forward and reverse electropherograms were superimposed, visually checked, and edited using the BioEdit software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mbio.ncsu.edu/BioEdit/bioedit.html">http://www.mbio.ncsu.edu/BioEdit/bioedit.html</ext-link>). Sequence identity was confirmed by comparison with sequences deposited in public databases, using the BlastN search algorithm (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BlastN">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BlastN</ext-link>). Multiple sequence alignment of <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region sequences was performed using clustalW.</p><p>Neighbor&#x02010;joining (NJ) phylogenetic trees were constructed using Kimura 2&#x02010;parameter (K2P) model, and reliability of the trees was tested with the 1000 replicates of nonparametric bootstrap (Felsenstein, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">1985</xref>) for estimating evolutionary distances using software TREECON (Van De Peer &#x00026; Wachter, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>). Molecular phylogeny trees were reconstructed for character support using maximum parsimony (MP) and maximum likelihood (ML) through phylogeny program PAUP*4.0b10 (Swofford, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). For MP, all character transformations were weighted equally, and gaps were treated as missing data. Tree Bisection and Reconnection (TBR) branch swapping option, addition sequence option &#x0201c;random,&#x0201d; and MAXTREES&#x000a0;set to auto increase, and 100 heuristic searches per replicate were applied. For ML, best&#x02010;fit nucleotide substitution model was tested to facilitate comparisons between 56 alternative models in PAUP*4.0b10. Heuristic search was conducted under the general time&#x02010;reversible (GTR) and gamma distributed with invariant sites (G&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;I) model with TBR branch swapping algorithm on a starting tree built under the parsimony criterion and bootstrapped with 1,000 replicates. Estimated substitution rate matrix: AC&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.4792878; AG&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.155157; AT&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.54992304; CG&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.2440845; CT&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.0431192; GT&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.000000. Gamma shape parameter&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.678. Assumed proportion of invariable sites&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.2897. MP and ML trees were visualized and saved using FigTree 1.4.2 (Rambaut, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0009"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="ece32483-sec-0010"><label>3.1</label><title>Performance of ISSR markers</title><p>The GC percentages of the primers used in this study were within the range 38%&#x02013;80% (with eight primers having 47% GC content and another eight having 53% GC content). Eleven of the primers were 18&#x000a0;bp long, seven were 17&#x000a0;bp long, and one each was 16 and 15&#x000a0;bp long. All the used dinucleotide primers were anchored at their 3&#x02032;&#x02010;end with one or two degenerate nucleotide(s), to increase the specificity and polymorphism. Twenty ISSR primers used in this study yielded 241 loci ranging from 0.2 to 1.5&#x000a0;kb, out of which 240 loci were polymorphic in nature representing 99.585% polymorphism. The number of loci reproduced by these arbitrary primers was found to range from 6 to 16 of different sizes with an average frequency of 12.05 loci per ISSR primer. The primers UBC 810 and UBC 856 that gave the maximum number of amplicons (16) were the most informative, while the primers UBC 826 and UBC 843 that gave the minimum number of products (6) were least informative. A total of 1,040 clear DNA fragments were scored from all <italic>Ocimum</italic> species and its varieties including outgroup taxa <italic>P. cablin</italic>. Two hundred and forty variable loci showed fragment frequency range of 0.071&#x02013;0.928. Of these, 113 loci (47.08%) showed a frequency __0.25, whereas 99 (41.25%) of the loci showed a frequency range of &#x02265;0.25 to &#x02264;0.5, and 28 (11.67%) showed a frequency &#x0003e;0.5. The ISSR loci were 100% polymorphic at species level for each primer except UBC 862 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In this study, the highest PIC value of 0.397 was observed for primer UBC 876, and the lowest PIC value of 0.229 was observed for primer UBC 826, with an overall average PIC value of 0.344 per primer. The highest RP value was observed with the primer UBC 834 (8.714) and the lowest with the primer UBC 826 (1.857) with an average RP of 6.285 per primer.</p></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0011"><label>3.2</label><title>
<italic>Cluster analysis based on the ISSR</italic>&#x02010;<italic>derived genotyping</italic>
</title><p>Fingerprinting dataset composed of 241 ISSR loci with 1040 DNA fragments was selected for banding pattern similarity analysis based on Jaccard coefficient. The pairwise genetic distance based on the similarity matrix ranged from 0.098 (<italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> var. Ram tulsi and <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> var. CIM&#x02010;Ayu) to 0.888 (<italic>O. kilimandscharicum</italic> and <italic>O. gratissimum</italic>) with an average pairwise genetic distance of 0.493. Genetic relationships were determined by neighbor&#x02010;joining tree based on the Nei's genetic distance obtained from the ISSR profiles and showed two major clusters with 51% bootstrap value, one of &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; group and other of &#x0201c;Sanctum&#x0201d; group, while <italic>P. cablin</italic> was placed as an outgroup as expected. &#x0201c;Gratissimum&#x0201d; group was bifurcated from &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Sanctum&#x0201d; groups with 100% bootstrap value. &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; group consisted of <italic>O. americanum</italic>,<italic> O. kilimandscharicum</italic>,<italic> O. africanum</italic>, and <italic>O. basilicum</italic> with its varieties. &#x0201c;Sanctum&#x0201d; group consisted of <italic>O. adscendens</italic> and <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> with its varieties. The phylogram depicted in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref> clearly shows that <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> and <italic>O. viride</italic> diverge earlier than the &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Sanctum&#x0201d; groups. Principal component analysis (PCA) derived on the basis of ISSR data is illustrated in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. The first two principal component axes accounted for 43.01% and 22.12% data variance, respectively, representing 65.17% of data variance cumulatively, which is sufficient to resolve the taxa into distinct groups. The third (9.13%) and fourth (6.72%) axes of the data variance did not significantly improve the resolution of the taxa. Groupings with the PCA analysis are in agreement with the NJ tree as revealed by the TREECON software.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32483-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Neighbor&#x02010;joining bootstrap tree resulting from <styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content> dataset. Bootstrap value less than 50% is omitted</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-6-7671-g002"/></fig><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32483-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Principal component analysis (<styled-content style="fixed-case">PCA</styled-content>) of <italic>Ocimum</italic>
<styled-content style="fixed-case">ISSR</styled-content> data. These cumulatively account for 65.17% (43.05% and 22.12%, respectively) of the data variance, the third axis (not shown) representing 9.13%; V1&#x02013;V14 represent different plant genotypes as listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>
</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="ECE3-6-7671-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0012"><label>3.3</label><title>
<italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> sequence data analysis</title><p>Chloroplast <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> intergenic spacers were successfully amplified in all <italic>Ocimum</italic> species and <italic>P. cablin</italic>. Forward sequences of <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region were observed in the range of 320 to 343&#x000a0;bp for <italic>Ocimum</italic> species and 187&#x000a0;bp for <italic>P. cablin</italic>. The average GC content in the sequences was low (28.49%). The aligned sequence length of <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> was 357&#x000a0;bp, harbored 310 (86.83%) characters constant, 29 (8.12%) variable sites but parsimony&#x02010;uninformative and 18 (5.04%) parsimony&#x02010;informative sites. Nucleotidic divergence (p&#x02010;distance), including the outgroup, ranged between 0.00 and 0.155, with an average of 0.025. For <italic>Ocimum</italic> species, the maximum pairwise p&#x02010;distance of 0.039 was observed with <italic>O. adscendens</italic> and <italic>O. basilicum</italic> and with <italic>O. adscendens</italic> and <italic>O. basilicum</italic> var. purpurascens.</p><p>Dataset of <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> sequences was used to reconstruct NJ, MP, and ML trees for 14 genotypes comprising of eight <italic>Ocimum</italic> species (few of them represented by different varieties) and also including an outgroup <italic>P. cablin</italic>. The topology of all the NJ (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), MP (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), and ML (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32483-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) trees is almost congruent and is supported by bootstrap value of more than 50%. Topology of MP and ML tree constructed through the program PAUP*4.0b10 is similar with different bootstrap value. In the MP analysis, after bootstrapping the single most parsimonious tree was retained with a tree length of 54, a consistency index (CI) of 0.926, a retention index (RI) of 0.934, and a rescaled consistency index (RC) of 0.865. A single best tree with likelihood &#x02013;ln L&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;736.44021 was found in ML analyses. The trees show that &#x0201c;Gratissimum&#x0201d; group is sister to &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; group with support value of NJ &#x0003c;50%, MP 74%, and ML 54%.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32483-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Neighbor&#x02010;joining bootstrap tree using Kimura 2&#x02010;parameter algorithm. Phylogram resulting from <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> nucleotide sequence data</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="ECE3-6-7671-g004"/></fig><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32483-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Equally weighted parsimony tree of <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> sequence data for <italic>Ocimum</italic> species. Single consensus parsimonious trees (tree length&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;54, <styled-content style="fixed-case">CI</styled-content>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.926, <styled-content style="fixed-case">RI</styled-content>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.934); values above branches are bootstrap value of 1,000 replicates; branch colors represent the support (violet&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;maximum; red&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;minimum)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="ECE3-6-7671-g005"/></fig><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32483-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Reconstruction of a phylogenetic tree from <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> sequence dataset by maximum likelihood using <styled-content style="fixed-case">GTR</styled-content>&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;G&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;I model of substitution. Bootstrap support values of 1,000 replicates are given above the branches. Branch colors represent the support (violet&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;maximum; red&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;minimum)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="ECE3-6-7671-g006"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0013"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>Several groups have been working worldwide on <italic>Ocimum</italic> species targeting different aspects and using distinct tools. Some of these are as follows: taxonomical status and geographic distribution (Balyan &#x00026; Pushpangadan, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">1988</xref>); cytotaxonomical studies (Sobti &#x00026; Pushpangadan, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">1979</xref>); classification and relationships (Paton et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>); genetic diversity and phylogenetic study using different molecular markers (Lal, Mistry, Thaker, Shah, &#x00026; Vaidya, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Patel, Fougat, Kumar, Mistry, &#x00026; Kumar, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Singh et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>); chemical characterization (Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Verma et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Vieira &#x00026; Simon, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>); compositional diversity in essential oils (Verma et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>); genetic relations based on molecular markers, nuclear DNA content, and chromosome number (Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>); taxonomical distribution, medicinal properties, and drug development potentiality (Nahak, Mishra, &#x00026; Sahu, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>); nucleotide&#x02010;based validation by evaluating three candidate barcodes of the chloroplast region (Christina &#x00026; Annamalai, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). However, no report is found on comparative phylogenetic study in <italic>Ocimum</italic> using PCR (ISSR)&#x02010;based and sequence (cpDNA)&#x02010;based analyses. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on the comparative phylogenetic study of <italic>Ocimum</italic> species through ISSR markers and plastid DNA region. The phylogenetic relationships of <italic>Ocimum</italic> species were inferred using distance (NJ)&#x02010;based approach applied on ISSR genomic data as well as both distance&#x02010; and character&#x02010;based (MP and ML) methodological approaches applied on <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region sequence data.</p><p>In the present study, 14 genotypes belonging to seven species of <italic>Ocimum</italic> (few of them represented by different varieties) and also including one outgroup <italic>P. cablin</italic> were studied using ISSR markers. The selection of ISSR markers was based on their relative technical simplicity, higher level of polymorphism detected, robustness, cost effectiveness (less time consuming and less expensive), easily adaptability to any plant species, and capability to target sequences that are abundant throughout the eukaryotic genome. The polymorphism level of 99.585% observed through ISSR analysis in the present study was in line with the earlier studies carried out by Patel et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), whereby ISSR analysis of five <italic>Ocimum</italic> species showed 98.17% polymorphism. Chen et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) found 97% polymorphism in four <italic>Ocimum</italic> species, and Lal et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>) found 100% polymorphism in six species of <italic>Ocimum</italic>. High polymorphism of ISSR over other marker systems was also reported in many previous studies, such as in <italic>Ocimum</italic> (Chen et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Lal et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>), <italic>Allium</italic> (Mukherjee et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), and <italic>Arachis</italic> (Raina et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). The average PIC value of 0.344 was observed in this study, which was closer to 0.5, the maximum value of PIC for any dominant marker (Nagy et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Although ISSR amplifies the regions between two microsatellites, the average PIC of ISSR marker systems was reasonably higher. The high PIC value obtained for the ISSRs reflects the efficiency of the marker to simultaneously analyze a large number of bands, rather than the level of polymorphism detected (Powell et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>). High levels of polymorphism and PIC found in the present work showed that ISSR markers are suitable for differentiating the genus <italic>Ocimum</italic> and its closely related varieties. Prevost and Wilkinson (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>) reported that resolving power (RP) of a primer correlates strongly with its ability to distinguish between genotypes. In other words, RP provides quantitative data allowing comparisons between primers, including those that are able to distinguish all genotypes under examination. It can also be used to predict the performance of groups of primers. In the present study, average RP value of 6.285 proved the efficiency of ISSR markers to discriminate among the <italic>Ocimum</italic> species.</p><p>ISSR analyses based on the distance&#x02010;based (NJ) method grouped the <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. in three groups: &#x0201c;Basilicum,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Sanctum,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Gratissimum&#x0201d; groups. This grouping is explained by the earlier studies carried out by Paton et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>) based on morphological characters, which grouped <italic>Ocimum</italic> into sections and subsections. Sect. &#x0201c;<italic>Ocimum</italic>&#x0201d; subsect. &#x0201c;<italic>Ocimum</italic>&#x0201d; comprised of &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; group, and sect. &#x0201c;<italic>Ocimum</italic>&#x0201d; subsect. &#x0201c;<italic>Gratissima</italic>&#x0201d; comprised of &#x0201c;Gratissimum&#x0201d; group, while <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> is placed in section &#x0201c;<italic>Hierocymum</italic>&#x0201d; subsect. &#x0201c;<italic>Foliosa</italic>.&#x0201d; Moreover, <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;40) and <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;36) have a smaller number of chromosomes compared to <italic>O. basilicum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;48) and <italic>O. americanum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;72) (Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) also reported the same type of grouping based on molecular markers, nuclear DNA content, and chromosome number. Our studies clearly demonstrated that morphologically dissimilar species <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> and <italic>O. viride</italic> form a single group. &#x0201c;Gratissimum&#x0201d; group is bifurcated earlier with 100% support value from &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Sanctum&#x0201d; group in ISSR&#x02013;NJ tree, which is supported by the study carried out by Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). According to the results presented, <italic>O. kilimandscharicum</italic> grouped together with <italic>O. basilicum</italic>,<italic> O. africanum</italic>, and <italic>O. americanum</italic>, which is again in agreement with the study done by Khosla (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>). Paton (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>) placed <italic>O. kilimandscharicum, O. basilicum</italic>, and <italic>O. americanum</italic> in section &#x0201c;<italic>Ocimum</italic>&#x0201d; subsection &#x0201c;<italic>Ocimum</italic>,&#x0201d; which also backed the same grouping pattern. <italic>O. kilimandscharicum</italic> was found to group with <italic>O. basilicum</italic> in an earlier rapid amplification of polymorphic DNA (RAPD)&#x02010;based study also (Shasany, Shukla, &#x00026; Khanuja, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>).</p><p>Multivariate approach was used to complement the information retrieved from the cluster analysis methods because it is more informative regarding distances among major groups (Taran, Zhang, Warkentin, Tullu, &#x00026; Vanderberg, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). PCA analysis used in the present study provides complementary information to the cluster analysis, as it allows a graphical presentation of <italic>Ocimum</italic> species in a scatter plot. The PCA of <italic>Ocimum</italic> species and an outgroup <italic>P. cablin</italic> explained 74.3% of total variation by the first three principal components. Grouping in PCA based on ISSR marker dataset corresponded well to the ISSR&#x02013;NJ phylogenetic tree.</p><p>On the other hand, distance&#x02010;based (NJ) and character&#x02010;based (MP and ML) trees depicted through <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> sequence dataset grouped the <italic>Ocimum</italic> species into two major clades. Clade I indicated that the &#x0201c;Gratissimum&#x0201d; group was sister to &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; group with reliable bootstrap values (NJ &#x0003c;50%, MP 74%, ML 54%). Clade II was comprised of <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> with its varieties and <italic>O. adscendens</italic>. The CI (0.926) and RI (0.934) of the <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> consensus maximum&#x02010;parsimony tree are high, suggesting that the phylogenetic reconstruction is fairly reliable. Unlike the present grouping, many workers reported grouping of &#x0201c;Gratissimum&#x0201d; group with &#x0201c;Sanctum&#x0201d; group on the basis of morphological, cytological, and oil characters (Khosla, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>; Sobti &#x00026; Pushpangadan, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">1979</xref>) or genetic similarity defined through RAPD (Singh et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). On the basis of pollen morphology, Harley, Paton, Harley, and Cade (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>) placed <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> and <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> in same group, while <italic>O. basilicum</italic>,<italic> O. americanum</italic>, and <italic>O. kilimandscharicum</italic> together in another group. On the other hand, <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> outgrouped in the <italic>O. basilicum</italic> cluster in a RAPD&#x02010;based analysis carried out by Shasany et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>).</p><p>By contrast, in all the phylogenetic trees, grouping of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. based on ISSR and <italic>psbA&#x02013;trnH</italic> sequence dataset differs largely. Neighbor&#x02010;joining analyses based on the ISSRs dataset placed &#x0201c;Gratissimum&#x0201d; group away from both &#x0201c;Sanctum&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; groups, while the distance&#x02010; and character&#x02010;based analyses on the <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> sequence dataset placed &#x0201c;Gratissimum&#x0201d; group with &#x0201c;Basilicum&#x0201d; group. The best explanation for this grouping is that the ISSRs (biparentally inherited) amplified from both nuclear and organellar regions, while <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region amplified from cpDNA region (maternally inherited). The size of the nucleome in comparison with the plastome and the chondriome is large. Hence, the origin of the ISSR bands is likely to be nuclear and can serve as control for the groups found with the plastid region. Due to haploid and uniparental inheritance, cpDNA reveals only half of the parentage of plants with hybridization/introgression or polyploidy and may incorrectly categorize plants into a clade of one of the two parents. Therefore, phylogenetic trees based on cpDNA may be discordant (Treutlein, Smith, van Wyk, &#x00026; Wink, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). The present report indicated the high efficiency of ISSRs markers in resolving the taxonomy of <italic>Ocimum</italic>. Interestingly, the earlier study by Christina and Annamalai (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) proved that <italic>psbA&#x02013;trnH</italic> region was a more suitable barcode as compared to the other tested cpDNA regions (<italic>matK</italic>,<italic> rbcL</italic>) for <italic>Ocimum</italic> species identification, but not for differentiating their varieties. They also indicated that the study of deletions in the sequences could prove helpful in species identification. Moreover, study carried out by Bhamra, Heinrich, Howard, Johnson, and Slater (<xref rid="ece32483-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) in <italic>Ocimum</italic> illustrated <italic>psbA&#x02010;trnH</italic> region to be more efficient in species identification than nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacer (<italic>ITS</italic>).</p><p>ISSR technique is a PCR&#x02010;based method with advantages of high sensitivity to low levels of genetic variation, low&#x02010;cost, and high efficiency as compared with other DNA genotyping techniques, thus making it a very useful molecular tool for studying population genetics on a wide range of plant species, as well as for identifying species, or cultivars (Wang, Feng, Lu, Shi, &#x00026; Liu, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). The present phylogeny study on <italic>Ocimum</italic> based on ISSR markers strongly supported genetic divergence and also correlated to some extent with the morphological level.</p><p>To date, various molecular marker techniques have been developed and are used in phylogenetic investigations. Although ISSR markers are highly efficient and reproducible, yet they have not been used extensively in phylogenetic studies. Many phylogeny studies carried out through ISSRs as in case of <italic>Vigna</italic> (Ajibade, Weeden, &#x00026; Chite, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>), Asian&#x02010;cultivated rice <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (Joshi, Gupta, Aggarwal, Ranjekar, &#x00026; Brar, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>), wheat (Nagaoka &#x00026; Ogihara, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>), and finger millet (Salimath, Oliveira, Godwin, &#x00026; Bennetzen, <xref rid="ece32483-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>) have been found to be very effective. This study provided valuable information for the potential application of ISSR markers in phylogenetic investigation, and there is boundless scope to use this powerful technique in resolving intra&#x02010; or interspecific status in many genera or in deciding the uniqueness of different genera within a family. Along with the vast applications of ISSR markers, unique alleles produced in the present study for <italic>Ocimum</italic> can be converted in codominant sequence characterized amplified regions (SCARs) to develop species&#x02010;specific diagnostic markers for a fast and effective diagnosis of this important medicinal material.</p></sec><sec id="ece32483-sec-0015"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="ece32483-sec-0014"><label>5</label><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors wish to express their sincere thanks to Director, CSIR&#x02010;CIMAP, Lucknow, for providing the laboratory facilities required to carry out this research. The financial support from the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), New Delhi, through the XIIth FYP project ChemBio (BSC&#x02010;0203) is gratefully acknowledged.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="ece32483-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="ece32483-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Ajibade</surname>, <given-names>S. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weeden</surname>, <given-names>N. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Chite</surname>, <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Inter&#x02010;simple sequence repeat analysis of genetic relationships in the genus <italic>Vigna</italic>
</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Euphytica</source>, <volume>111</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Asthana</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tripathi</surname>, <given-names>N. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Dixit</surname>, <given-names>S. N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Fungitoxic and phytotoxic studies with essential oil of <italic>Ocimum adscendens</italic>
</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Phytopathology</source>, <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Balyan</surname>, <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Pushpangadan</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>A study on the taxonomical status and geographic distribution of genus <italic>Ocimum</italic>
</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Perfumes and Flavours Association of India journal</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="ece32483-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Bhamra</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Heinrich</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Howard</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Slater</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>DNA authentication of tulsi (<italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic>) using the nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacer (<italic>ITS</italic>) and the chloroplast intergenic spacer <italic>trnH&#x02010;psbA</italic>
</article-title>. In: (Proceedings) 63rd International Congress and Annual Meeting of the Society for Medicinal Plant and Natural Product Research (GA) (pp. 1498). Georg Thieme Verlag KG.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liber</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Besendorfer</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Javornik</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bohanec</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kolak</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Satovic</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Genetic relations among basil taxa (<italic>Ocimum</italic> L.) based on molecular markers, nuclear DNA content, and chromosome number</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Plant Systematics and Evolution</source>, <volume>285</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Carvoic&#x02010;Stanko</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liber</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Politeo</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Strikic</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kolak</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Milos</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Satovic</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Molecular and chemical characterization of the most widespread <italic>Ocimum</italic> species</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Plant Systematics and Evolution</source>, <volume>294</volume>, <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>S. Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dai</surname>, <given-names>T. X.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chang</surname>, <given-names>Y. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ou</surname>, <given-names>S. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chuang</surname>, <given-names>W. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Ku</surname>, <given-names>H. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Genetic diversity among <italic>Ocimum</italic> species based on ISSR, RAPD and SRAP markers</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Australian Journal of Crop Science</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1471</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Chowdhury</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vandenberg</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Warkentin</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Cultivar identification and genetic relationship among selected breeding lines and cultivars in chickpea (<italic>Cicer arietinum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Euphytica</source>, <volume>127</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>325</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Christina</surname>, <given-names>V. L. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Annamalai</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Nucleotide based validation of <italic>Ocimum</italic> species by evaluating three candidate barcodes of the chloroplast region</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Molecular Ecology Resources</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24164957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Dong</surname>, <given-names>Z. Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fan</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sha</surname>, <given-names>L. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zeng</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>, <given-names>Y. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Phylogeny and molecular evolution of the <italic>rbcL</italic> gene of St genome in <italic>Elymus sensu</italic> lato (Poaceae: Triticeae)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Biochemical Systematics and Ecology</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>322</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>330</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Felsenstein</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies: An approach using the bootstrap</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Evolution</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>791</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28561359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Harley</surname>, <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Paton</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Harley</surname>, <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Cade</surname>, <given-names>P. G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Pollen morphological studies in tribe Ocimeae (Nepetoideae: Labiatae): I. <italic>Ocimum</italic> L. <italic>Grana</italic>
</article-title>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Jaccard</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1908</year>). <article-title>Nouvelle recherches sur La distribution florale</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Bulletin de la Soci&#x000e9;t&#x000e9; vaudoise des sciences naturelles</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Joshi</surname>, <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gupta</surname>, <given-names>V. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aggarwal</surname>, <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ranjekar</surname>, <given-names>P. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Brar</surname>, <given-names>D. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Genetic diversity and phylogenetic relationship as revealed by inter&#x02010;simple sequence repeat (ISSR) polymorphism in the genus <italic>Oryza</italic>
</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>1311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1320</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Khanuja</surname>, <given-names>S. P. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shasany</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Darokar</surname>, <given-names>M. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Rapid isolation of DNA from dry and fresh samples of plants producing large amounts of secondary metabolites and essential oils</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Plant Molecular Biology Reporter</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Khosla</surname>, <given-names>M. K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Study of inter&#x02010;relationship, phylogeny and evolutionary tendencies in genus <italic>Ocimum</italic>
</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">The Indian Journal of Genetics and Plant Breeding</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32483-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Kimura</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1983</year>). <source xml:lang="en">The neutral theory of molecular evolution</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mishra</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Singh</surname>, <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sundaresan</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Efficiency of ISSR and RAPD markers in genetic divergence analysis and conservation management of <italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic> L., a medicinal plant</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Plant Systematics and Evolution</source>, <volume>300</volume>, <fpage>1409</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1420</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Lal</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mistry</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Thaker</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shah</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Vaidya</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Genetic diversity assessment in six medicinally important species of <italic>Ocimum</italic> from central Gujarat (India) utilizing RAPD, ISSR and SSR markers</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Journal of Advanced Biological and Biomedical Research</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Mishra</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>L. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gokul</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ravikumar</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shukla</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sundaresan</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Population dynamics and conservation implications of <italic>Decalepis arayalpathra</italic> (J. Joseph and V. Chandras.) Venter., a steno endemic species of Western Ghats, India</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Applied Biochemistry and Biotechnology</source>, <volume>176</volume>, <fpage>1413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1430</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25969156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Mukherjee</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sikdar</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ghosh</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Banerjee</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ghosh</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bhattacharya</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Roy</surname>, <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>RAPD and ISSR analysis of some economically important species, varieties, and cultivars of the genus <italic>Allium</italic> (Alliaceae)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Turkish Journal of Botany</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>618</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Nagaoka</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ogihara</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Applicability of inter&#x02010;simple sequence repeat polymorphisms in wheat for use as DNA markers in comparison to RFLP and RAPD markers</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>, <volume>94</volume>, <fpage>597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>602</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Nagy</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Poczai</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cernak</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gorji</surname>, <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hegedus</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Taller</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>PICcalc: An online program to calculate polymorphic information content for molecular genetic studies</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Biochemical Genetics</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>670</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>672</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22573137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Nahak</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mishra</surname>, <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sahu</surname>, <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Taxonomic distribution, medicinal properties and drug development potentiality of <italic>Ocimum</italic> (Tulsi)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Drug Invention Today</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Nei</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>Analysis of gene diversity in subdivided populations</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>3321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3323</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Newmaster</surname>, <given-names>S. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ragupathy</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Testing plant barcoding in a sister species complex of pantropical <italic>Acacia</italic> (Mimosoideae, Fabaceae)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Molecular Ecology Resources</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>180</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21564976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Padalia</surname>, <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Verma</surname>, <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chauhan</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Chanotiya</surname>, <given-names>C. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Changes in aroma profiles of 11 Indian <italic>Ocimum</italic> taxa during plant ontogeny</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Acta Physiologiae Plantarum</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>2567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2587</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Patel</surname>, <given-names>H. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fougat</surname>, <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mistry</surname>, <given-names>J. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Detection of genetic variation in <italic>Ocimum</italic> species using RAPD and ISSR markers</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">3 Biotech</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>707</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Paton</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>A synopsis of <italic>Ocimum</italic> L. (Labiatae) in Africa</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Kew Bulletin</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>437</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32483-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Paton</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Harley</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Harley</surname>, <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1999</year>). <chapter-title><italic>Ocimum</italic>: An overview of classification and relationships</chapter-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hiltunen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, &#x00026; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (Eds.), <source xml:lang="en">Basil: The genus Ocimum</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harwood</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Powell</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Morgante</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Andre</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hanafey</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vogel</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tingey</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Rafalski</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A comparison of RFLP, RAPD, AFLP and SSR markers for germplasm analysis</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Molecular Breeding</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>Prakash</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Gupta</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Therapeutic uses of <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> Linn. (Tulsi) with a note on eugenol and its pharmacological actions: A short review</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Indian Journal of Physiology and Pharmacology</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16170979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Prevost</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Wilkinson</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A new system of comparing PCR primers applied to ISSR fingerprinting of potato cultivars</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32483-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<surname>Pushpangadan</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Bradu</surname>, <given-names>B. L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1995</year>). <chapter-title>Medicinal and aromatic plants</chapter-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Chadha</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, &#x00026; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (Eds.), <source xml:lang="en">Advances in horticulture</source>, Vol. <volume>11</volume> (pp. <fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>657</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Malhotra Publishing House</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<surname>Raina</surname>, <given-names>S. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rani</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kojima</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ogihara</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Singh</surname>, <given-names>K. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Devarumath</surname>, <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>RAPD and ISSR fingerprints as useful genetic markers for analysis of genetic diversity, varietal identification, and phylogenetic relationships in peanut (<italic>Arachis hypogaea</italic>) cultivars and wild species</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Genome</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>763</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>777</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11681599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32483-cit-0037">
<string-name>
<surname>Rambaut</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <source xml:lang="en">FigTree</source>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institute of Evolutionary Biology, Univ Edinburgh</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32483-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<surname>Rohlf</surname>, <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1998</year>). <source xml:lang="en">NTSYS&#x02010;PC: Numerical taxonomy and multivariate analysis system. Version 2.02</source>. <publisher-loc>Setauket, New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Exeter software</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0040">
<string-name>
<surname>Salimath</surname>, <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Oliveira</surname>, <given-names>A. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Godwin</surname>, <given-names>I. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Bennetzen</surname>, <given-names>J. L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Assessment of genome origins and genetic diversity in the genus <italic>Eleusine</italic> with DNA markers</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Genome</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>757</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>763</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7672607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32483-cit-0041">
<string-name>
<surname>Shasany</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shukla</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Khanuja</surname>, <given-names>S. P. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <chapter-title>Medicinal and aromatic plants</chapter-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kole</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (Ed.), <source xml:lang="en">Genome mapping and molecular breeding in plants</source>, Vol. <volume>6</volume> (pp. <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>)., <series>Technical Crops</series>
<publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer&#x02010;Verlag</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0042">
<string-name>
<surname>Shukla</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mall</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rai</surname>, <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Singh</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nair</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Parashar</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Khanuja</surname>, <given-names>S. P. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A transcriptomic approach for exploring the molecular basis for <italic>dosha</italic>&#x02010;balancing property&#x02010;based classification of plants in Ayurveda</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Molecular Biology Reports</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>3255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3262</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23322031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0043">
<string-name>
<surname>Singh</surname>, <given-names>A. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dwivedi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bharti</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Srivastava</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Singh</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Khanuja</surname>, <given-names>S. P. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships as in <italic>Ocimum</italic> revealed by RAPD markers</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Euphytica</source>, <volume>136</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32483-cit-0044">
<string-name>
<surname>Sobti</surname>, <given-names>S. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Pushpangadan</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1979</year>). <chapter-title>Cytotaxonomical studies in the genus <italic>Ocimum</italic></chapter-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bir</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (Ed.), <source xml:lang="en">Taxonomy, cytogenetics and cytotaxonomy of plants</source> (pp. <fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>377</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kalyani</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32483-cit-0045">
<string-name>
<surname>Swofford</surname>, <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2002</year>). <source xml:lang="en">PAUP&#x02014;phylogenetic analysis using parsimony</source>. <publisher-loc>Sunderland, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sinauer Associates</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0046">
<string-name>
<surname>Taran</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Warkentin</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tullu</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Vanderberg</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Genetic diversity among varieties and wild species accessions of pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.) based on molecular markers, and morphological and physiological characters</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Genome</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15838548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0047">
<string-name>
<surname>Treutlein</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>G. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>van Wyk</surname>, <given-names>B. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Wink</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships in Asphodelaceae (subfamily Alooideae) inferred from chloroplast DNA sequences (<italic>rbcL</italic>,&#x000a0;<italic>matK</italic>) and from genomic fingerprinting (ISSR)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Taxon</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0048">
<string-name>
<surname>Van De Peer</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Wachter</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>TREECON for windows: A software package for the construction and drawing of evolutionary trees for the Microsoft Windows environment</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Computer Applications in the Biosciences</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>569</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>570</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7828077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0049">
<string-name>
<surname>Verma</surname>, <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mishra</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Baskaran</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Padalia</surname>, <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sundaresan</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Essential oil composition of four <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. from the Peninsular India</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Essential Oil Research</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0050">
<string-name>
<surname>Verma</surname>, <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Padalia</surname>, <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chauhan</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Thul</surname>, <given-names>S. T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Exploring compositional diversity in the essential oils of 34 <italic>Ocimum</italic> taxa from Indian flora</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Industrial Crops and Products</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0051">
<string-name>
<surname>Vieira</surname>, <given-names>R. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Simon</surname>, <given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Chemical characterization of basil (<italic>Ocimum</italic> spp.) found in the markets and used in traditional medicine in Brazil</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Economic Botany</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0052">
<string-name>
<surname>Vina</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Murillo</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Essential oil composition from twelve varieties of basil (<italic>Ocimum</italic> spp.) grown in Colombia</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of the Brazilian Chemical Society</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>744</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>749</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0053">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>H. Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Feng</surname>, <given-names>S. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lu</surname>, <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shi</surname>, <given-names>N. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic study and molecular identification of 31 <italic>Dendrobium</italic> species using inter&#x02010;simple sequence repeat (ISSR) markers</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Scientia Horticulturae</source>, <volume>122</volume>, <fpage>440</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>447</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0054">
<string-name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wu</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Chemical and genetic discrimination of <italic>Cistanches Herba</italic> based on UPLC&#x02010;QTOF/MS and DNA barcoding</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">PLoS ONE</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e98061</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24854031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0055">
<string-name>
<surname>Zietkiewicz</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rafalski</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Labuda</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Genome fingerprinting by simple sequence repeat (SSR)&#x02010;anchored polymerase chain reaction amplification</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Genomics</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8020964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32483-bib-0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32483-cit-0056">
<string-name>
<surname>Zurawski</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Clegg</surname>, <given-names>M. T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Evolution of higher plant chloroplast DNA encoded genes: Implications for structure&#x02013;function and phylogenetic studies</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Annual Review of Plant Physiology</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>