<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Physiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Physiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-042X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6300573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2018.01809</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Changes in Running Economy During a 65-km Ultramarathon</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scheer</surname><given-names>Volker</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/585613/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vieluf</surname><given-names>Solveig</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/50199/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>Leoni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jakobsmeyer</surname><given-names>Rasmus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heitkamp</surname><given-names>Hans-Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Ultra Sports Science Foundation</institution>, <addr-line>Pierre-B&#x000e9;nite</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Exercise and Health, Institute of Sports Medicine, Paderborn University</institution>, <addr-line>Paderborn</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Francis Degache, University of Applied Sciences and Arts of Western Switzerland, Switzerland</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Beat Knechtle, University Hospital Zurich, Switzerland; Chuanye Huang, Shandong Sport University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Volker Scheer, <email>volkerscheer@yahoo.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Exercise Physiology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Physiology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1809</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Scheer, Vieluf, Cramer, Jakobsmeyer and Heitkamp.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Scheer, Vieluf, Cramer, Jakobsmeyer and Heitkamp</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><bold>Purpose:</bold> Running economy (RE), expressed as oxygen cost (O<sub>2</sub> cost) and energy cost of running (Cr) is important in ultramarathon (UM) running as it can help predict race performance. Controversy remains if RE increases, decreases, or remains stable in UM running. We examined RE before, during, and after a 65-km UM.</p><p><bold>Methods:</bold> 15 male UM runners (mean age 45 &#x000b1; 5.7 years) completed a standard exercise test (mean VO<sub>2</sub>max 48.8 &#x000b1; 3.4 ml&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;min<sup>-1</sup>) for determination of the individual testing speed (60% VO<sub>2</sub>max: mean speed 9.4 &#x000b1; 0.7 km/h). This was followed by a 65-km UM (elevation &#x000b1; 1093 m) consisting of three laps (each 21.7 km). Pre and post indirect calorimetry measurements at individual running speed on the treadmill at UM-specific slopes (average percentage of positive and negative elevation) at -3, +3%, and level grade were performed in randomized order on a motorized treadmill in the laboratory for calculation of RE. Additionally after each lap, testing at +3% took place.</p><p><bold>Results:</bold> The O<sub>2</sub> cost, Cr, and RER increased significantly pre to post UM (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). During the uphill running, a main effect of distance indicated a gradual, linear increase in O<sub>2</sub> cost, <italic>F</italic>(2,28) = 5.81, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0.29, and Cr, <italic>F</italic>(2,28) = 5.96, <italic>p</italic> = 0.01, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0.30.</p><p><bold>Conclusion:</bold> O<sub>2</sub> cost and Cr increased significantly pre to post UM in all testing conditions as well as during the uphill testing throughout the UM. This is the first study to demonstrate a consistent increase in O<sub>2</sub> cost and Cr among a range of different slopes, at individual running speeds and race-specific slopes giving further evidence that these measures of RE increase in UM running.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>oxygen consumption</kwd><kwd>physiology</kwd><kwd>endurance</kwd><kwd>energy cost of running</kwd><kwd>oxygen cost of running</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="37"/><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Popularity in ultramarathon (UM) running has increased over the years and includes race distances in excess of the traditional marathon distance of 42.195 km (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Scheer, 2018</xref>). They are often held in challenging environmental conditions, testing the limits of human endurance (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Scheer et al., 2015</xref>). Considerable research has focused on the medical and physiological aspects of UMs (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Millet et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2011a</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Scheer and Murray, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Millet and Millet, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Costa et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Hoffman et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Scheer et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017a</xref>), but up to now, controversy remains on the role of running economy (RE) in UM running (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>). RE is important as it is classically used in conjunction with VO<sub>2</sub>max and percentage of VO<sub>2</sub>max to predict race performance (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Barnes and Kilding, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Scheer et al., 2018a</xref>). RE is a multifactorial concept that combines the function of the metabolic, cardiopulmonary, biomechanical, and neuromuscular system (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Barnes and Kilding, 2015</xref>) and can either be expressed as oxygen consumption (in ml&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;min<sup>-1</sup>), oxygen consumption to cover a given distance [oxygen cost (O<sub>2</sub> cost), e.g., in ml O<sub>2</sub>&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;km<sup>-1</sup>] or as the energy cost of running (Cr) expressed in units of energy (J&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;m<sup>-1</sup>) (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Fletcher et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Barnes and Kilding, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2017a</xref>). Cr is of particular interest in UM as it reflects the energy demand in prolonged exercise where a shift from carbohydrate to fat substrate utilization can be observed (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2017a</xref>). Cr typically increases up to marathon distances (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Brueckner et al., 1991</xref>), but in UM, there is debate if Cr really increases after an UM (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>) as some studies suggest (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gimenez et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2015</xref>), remains stable (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Balducci et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Savoldelli et al., 2017</xref>), or decrease post UM (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Data pertaining the O<sub>2</sub> cost of running are more uniform, with the majority of studies demonstrating an increase (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Lazzer et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>) or no change post UM (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Millet et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Fusi et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Lazzer et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Balducci et al., 2017</xref>). Most studies have investigated RE changes pre to post UM (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Lazzer et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Balducci et al., 2017</xref>) but only one study to date (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>) investigated RE during a 60-km UM in field conditions that found no significant changes in Cr. Some of those discrepancies observed may be due to methodological differences in study designs (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>). It has recently been suggested that future studies should take into consideration the specific UM race characteristics and profile and use individual testing speeds and race-specific gradients for RE testing on the treadmill after sufficient familiarization with testing conditions (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>).</p><p>The purpose of our study was to investigate RE (Cr and O<sub>2</sub> cost) before, during, and after a 65-km UM, addressing some of those methodological concerns raised and examining runners at individual running speeds and different specific gradient slopes (level, uphill, and downhill) on the treadmill according to the specific UM profile. Our hypothesis was that Cr and O<sub>2</sub> cost would increase with increasing running distance and among different gradients.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>Fifteen experienced male UM runners (age 44.9 &#x000b1; 5.7 years, height 178.3 &#x000b1; 4.9 cm, weight 78.4 &#x000b1; 8.4 kg, BMI 24.6 &#x000b1; 2.2 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, running experience 12.2 &#x000b1; 8.6 years, previous UM experience 5 &#x000b1; 4.2 races, training kilometers per week 75 &#x000b1; 19.3 km) volunteered to participate in the study. Only healthy male athletes, between the ages of 18 and 60 years, who previously participated in at least one UM of more than 60 km, were allowed to participate. Runners who had sustained a recent injury (less than 3 months before the event) were excluded. They were recruited through announcements at local running clubs and local Internet groups for runners. All participants were informed of the protocol prior to the first test and provided written, informed consent. The internal review board of the local medical council (&#x000c4;rztekammer Westfalen-Lippe) and the University of M&#x000fc;nster, Germany, approved all procedures (approval number 2017-465-f-S), and research was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec><title>Study Design</title><p>The study design consisted of two test days. Participants were instructed to abstain from consuming alcohol or caffeine and refrain from strenuous and exhaustive exercise 24 h prior to each test day. On test day 1, participants received a medical checkup, consisting of medical history and examination of the musculoskeletal and cardiovascular system, resting blood pressure (Adult 11, durable blood pressure cuff, Welch Allyn, Skaneateles, NY, United States) and resting ECG (Cardio 100 BT, Custo, Ottobrunn, Germany) by the attending physician to exclude any significant underlying pathologies. All participants were attested to be in good health and able to participate in the study. Participants were familiar with treadmill running and were further familiarized with the specific running protocol on the treadmill (h/p/cosmos Pulsar 3p; Traunstein, Germany). This was followed by a standard graded exercise test (starting at 6.0 km/h, step duration 3 min, increased by 2.0 km/h, and inclination 1.0%) until task failure with continuous breath by breath measurements for ventilatory parameters (Metalyzer 3B, Cortex Biophysik, Leipzig, Germany) (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Scheer et al., 2018b</xref>). To determine individual running speed for treadmill tests on test day 2, the speed at 60% VO<sub>2</sub>max was extrapolated from the VO<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;work rate relationship. This intensity was selected as it corresponds to intensities observed during 6-h events (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Davies and Thompson, 1979</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Ultramarathon</title><p>Test day 2 included four running tests on the treadmill, two venous blood samples, and a 65-km UM. Test day 2 was conducted on three separate occasions due to limitations of equipment and staff capacity, to ensure smooth testing procedures with little to no waiting times (maximum number of six participants per day). For the same reason, RE measurements during the UM could only be conducted at +3% incline. Tests took place in January and February 2018 with comparable outdoor conditions (average temperature + 6&#x000b0;C) for the UM. The UM was designed as a loop course (a total of three laps) starting and finishing at our university department. Each lap measured 21.7 km with a cumulative ascent of 364.4 m and cumulative descent of 364.4 m (Garmin Forerunner 735XT), equating to a total distance of 65 km (&#x000b1;1093 m). The terrain consisted predominately of forest tracks, gravel, and tarmac paths. It contained several uphill and downhill running sections and the average slope measured 3% (positive and negative elevation), which was used as the incline/decline for further tests (uphill/downhill) on the treadmill as outlined below. Participants were allowed to select their own individual running speed during the UM and were allowed to drink and eat <italic>ad libitum</italic>. During the course, runners were self-sufficient but after each lab food and drink was provided to them at the university.</p></sec><sec><title>Running Economy</title><p>Treadmill tests (A&#x02013;D) were standardized and included continuous measurements of ventilatory parameters including oxygen uptake (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>), carbon dioxide output (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>CO<sub>2</sub>), and respiratory exchange ratio (RER) after calibration before each test (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Scheer et al., 2018b</xref>). Heart rate values were obtained <italic>via</italic> Bluetooth (Polar T31 sensor) and participants were asked to provide rate of perceived exertion (RPE) on the 6- to 20-point Borg scale immediately prior and at the end of each test (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Borg, 1985</xref>). Test A (just before the start of the UM) and test D (immediately after the finish of the UM) were conducted in the same fashion and consisted of three 5-min running intervals on the treadmill at 60% VO<sub>2</sub>max of the individual running speed in randomized order at level grade, +3% incline, and -3% decline, with a one minute rest period between intervals. Test B (after one lap of running) and Test C (after two laps of running) where conducted in the same fashion but only at +3% incline of the treadmill. To calculate RE, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>O2, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>CO<sub>2</sub>, and RER were obtained from the last minute of treadmill running during steady state conditions and were filtered into 5-s blocks for data analyses as described by <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al. (2015)</xref>. Net VO<sub>2</sub> values were obtained from calculating the difference of VO<sub>2</sub> at steady state minus <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>O<sub>2</sub> at rest and for determination of the caloric equivalent of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>O<sub>2</sub> values were converted depending on RER values (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">P&#x000e9;ronnet and Massicotte, 1991</xref>). RE was expressed as both net O<sub>2</sub> cost of running (O<sub>2</sub>&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;km<sup>-1</sup>) and net Cr of running (Cr in J&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;m<sup>-1</sup>) (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Blood Sampling</title><p>Venous blood samples were obtained immediately prior and post UM in resting supine position from the antecubital vein by the attending physician. Blood parameters obtained included creatine kinase (CK), C-reactive protein (CRP), and leucocyte count.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>Statistical analyses were conducted in SPSS for Windows version 20.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, United States). The relative change [relative change = (post - pre)/pre &#x000d7; 100] was expressed as the difference between pre and post measure in relation to pretest values in per cent and was calculated for RER, O<sub>2</sub> cost and Cr. Rate of change was tested with one-sample tests. Standard significance level was set to <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 and corrected for multiple comparisons by Bonferroni correction (&#x003b1;&#x02032;= 0.05/5 = 0.01). To test for differences between tests, repeated measure ANOVA with three tests (downhill, level, and uphill) was calculated for the relative change of RER, O<sub>2</sub> cost, and Cr. To analyze changes continuously during the uphill test, RER, O<sub>2</sub> cost, and Cr changes in relation to pretest measures were analyzed with a repeated measure ANOVA with the factor three distance (21.7, 43.4, and 65 km). Greenhouse&#x02013;Geisser adjustment was reported in case the sphericity assumption was violated. Effect sizes were reported as partial eta squares (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). <italic>Post hoc</italic> tests were corrected with Bonferroni. <italic>p</italic>-Values were corrected by SPSS. Based on violation of normal distribution, we calculated Spearman correlations between the relative changes of RER, O<sub>2</sub> cost, Cr and the blood parameters as well as the numerical values of the RPE.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The values from the initial exercise test, pre and post UM blood parameters, and values of the RPE with their relative change and correlation to O<sub>2</sub> cost and Cr are shown in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. All blood markers and the RPE increased significantly pre to post UM, but their relative changes did neither correlate with O<sub>2</sub> cost nor Cr apart from RPE values. Absolute mean values (&#x000b1;SD) were the following for RER, O<sub>2</sub> cost, and Cr pre vs. post for level (0.95 &#x000b1; 0.02 vs. 0.88 &#x000b1; 0.04, 180.60 &#x000b1; 24.75 vs. 199.47 &#x000b1; 28.43 O<sub>2</sub>&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;km<sup>-1</sup>, and 3.88 &#x000b1; 0.52 vs. 4.22 &#x000b1; 0.59 J&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;m<sup>-1</sup>) and downhill running (0.94 &#x000b1; 0.03 vs. 0.86 &#x000b1; 0.04, 166.60 &#x000b1; 24.25 vs. 182.40 &#x000b1; 26.58 O<sub>2</sub>&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;km<sup>-1</sup>, and 3.57 &#x000b1; 0.52 vs. 3.85 &#x000b1; 0.55 J&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;m<sup>-1</sup>). During the four different time points in uphill running RER, O<sub>2</sub> cost, and Cr were as follows: 0.96 &#x000b1; 0.03 vs. 0.89 &#x000b1; 0.03 vs. 0.89 &#x000b1; 0.03 vs. 0.89 &#x000b1; 0.03, 218.87 &#x000b1; 28.29 vs. 227.93 &#x000b1; 30.45 vs. 234.93 &#x000b1; 30.63 vs. 239.93 &#x000b1; 29.17 O<sub>2</sub>&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;km<sup>-1</sup>, and 4.71 &#x000b1; 0.59 vs. 4.83 &#x000b1; 0.54 vs. 4.98 &#x000b1; 0.63 vs. 5.08 &#x000b1; 0.60 J&#x022c5;kg<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;m<sup>-1</sup>. Graphical presentation of the mean values and data of each individual runner for RER, O<sub>2</sub> cost, and Cr for downhill, level, and uphill running at the different time points can be seen in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. Calculated relative changes are presented in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Relative changes for RER showed changes through all pre to post-tests during level and downhill running and all subsequent measures during uphill running. This was also observed with O<sub>2</sub> cost and Cr during level and downhill running and after 21.7 km and subsequent tests in uphill running (see Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). All protocols showed significant relative changes from pre to post test, as indicated by significant one sample <italic>t</italic>-test for the parameters RER, O<sub>2</sub>, and Cr (see Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Comparing the relative changes across protocols, repeated measure ANOVA revealed no main effect of protocol for RER, <italic>F</italic>(2,28) = 0.55, <italic>p</italic> = 0.58, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0.04, O<sub>2</sub> cost, <italic>F</italic>(2,28) = 0.11, <italic>p</italic> = 0.83, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0.01, and Cr, <italic>F</italic>(2,28) = 0.08, <italic>p</italic> = 0.86, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0.01. In addition to pre and post measures, the uphill test was conducted after 21.7 and 43.4 km, to illustrate the progression of change. Analysis revealed no main effect of distance for RER, <italic>F</italic>(2,28) = 0.20, <italic>p</italic> = 0.82, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0.01. For both measures of RE, O<sub>2</sub> cost, <italic>F</italic>(2,28) = 5.81, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0.29, and Cr, <italic>F</italic>(2,28) = 5.96, <italic>p</italic> = 0.01, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathcolor="black" mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0.30, a significant main effect of distance was revealed. Bonferroni corrected <italic>post hoc</italic> comparisons showed O<sub>2</sub> cost (<italic>p</italic> = 0.04) and Cr (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03) increased more at post-test than after 21.7 km.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Descriptive results [mean values and standard deviation (SD)] from the initial exercise test, blood parameters and RPE pre and post UM, with relative change and correlation to O<sub>2</sub> cost and Cr.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative change</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation with O<sub>2</sub> cost</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation with Cr</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VO<sub>2</sub>max (ml&#x022c5;km<sup>-1</sup>&#x022c5;min<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.80 (3.41)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vVO<sub>2</sub>max (km/h)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.22 (1.00)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60% vVO<sub>2</sub>max (km/h)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.42 (0.69)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leukocytes (10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.58 (1.62)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.75 (3.20)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174.84<sup>*</sup> (68.32)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>r</italic> (<italic>p</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.37 (0.17)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.38 (0.17)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK (U/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172.27 (71.79)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">681.53 (393.64)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311.29<sup>*</sup> (178.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>r</italic> (<italic>p</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (0.27)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (0.29)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (mg/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (0.13)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113.49 (98.61)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>r</italic> (<italic>p</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (0.26)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 (0.27)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPE (Borg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.27 (1.75)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.93 (1.83)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.18<sup>*</sup> (24.27)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>r</italic> (<italic>p</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.45 (0.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.47 (0.08)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup>&#x02217;</sup>Indicates that one-sample tests reached significance with Bonferroni correction.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Mean values of RER, O<sub>2</sub> cost, and Cr (colored marker) and individual for each UM runner (gray markers) during the different tests.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphys-09-01809-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Mean values and standard deviations (SD) as well as results of one-sample tests (<italic>df</italic> = 14 and <sup>&#x02217;</sup> indicates significance after Bonferroni correction) relative changes per group for all measures in the three different tests and distances.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RER</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O<sub>2</sub> cost</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cr</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Level</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post UM</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.40 (3.88)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.66 (8.33)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.98 (8.04)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T; <italic>p</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.37; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Downhill</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post UM</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.74 (3.55)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.86 (9.39)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.34 (9.47)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T</italic>; <italic>p</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.44; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Uphill</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7 km</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-6.81 (2.81)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56 (7.40)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90 (7.47)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T</italic>; <italic>p</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.37; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50; 0.15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4 km</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.19 (2.37)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.58 (7.40)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.98 (7.28)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T</italic>; <italic>p</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11.77; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.97; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post UM</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-6.91 (2.86)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.97 (7.45)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.34 (7.53)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T; <italic>p</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.35; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.19; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.29; &#x0003c;0.01<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Our main findings are that Cr and O<sub>2</sub> cost increased significantly pre to post UM in all testing conditions as well as during the uphill testing throughout the UM. This is in line with our hypothesis demonstrating a consistent increase in these measures of RE.</p><sec><title>O<sub>2</sub> Cost of Running</title><p>Oxygen cost of running increased by about 10% for uphill and downhill and about 11% for level grade running conditions pre to post UM. This is in line with most previous studies that showed an increase in the O<sub>2</sub> cost of running post UM (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Lazzer et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>). A new finding is that during the UM in the uphill running conditions a significant gradual linear increase was observed at the different time points.</p></sec><sec><title>RER and Energy Cost of Running</title><p>However, it is also known that the O<sub>2</sub> cost of running, especially in UM running can be overestimated and an expression of RE as Cr is a much better way of describing RE as it takes into account the caloric equivalent of VO<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">P&#x000e9;ronnet and Massicotte, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>). RER values are therefore important, and it is known that they decrease over time with exercise especially post UM (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2015</xref>), in line with our own result. In prolonged exercise, a progressive depletion of glycogen stores occur with a shift in substrate utilization from carbohydrates to fat resulting in decreased RER values (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>). Interestingly, that decrease was already observed after 21.7 km, suggesting that the shift in substrate utilization had occurred at or before this time point.</p><p>Changes in RER values will have an obvious impact in calculating Cr when for the determination of the caloric equivalent <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002d9;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>O<sub>2</sub> values are converted depending on RER values (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">P&#x000e9;ronnet and Massicotte, 1991</xref>). Cr has been shown to increase in running distances up to marathon (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Brueckner et al., 1991</xref>), but in UM, there is still some debate if Cr increases (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gimenez et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2015</xref>), decrease (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) or remains stable after an UM (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Fusi et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Balducci et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Savoldelli et al., 2017</xref>). Our results showed a significant increase in Cr across all testing conditions in downhill, level, and uphill running pre to post UM of between 8 and 9%. <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al. (2015)</xref> reported a 13.1% increase in post-race Cr in downhill running conditions only with no differences in level or uphill Cr post UM over a similar distance of 65 km but with a much steeper elevation of +4000 m and fixed treadmill testing conditions for participants regarding slope and speed (&#x000b1;5% and 10 km/h) (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2015</xref>). A new finding is that we also observed a significant gradual increase of Cr during uphill running conditions throughout the UM. To our knowledge, there is only one other study to date examining Cr changes during an UM in field conditions (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>). A non-significant, but small gradual increase of Cr was observed, during a flat 60-km UM course, with Cr measured at level grade running on a 400-m running track at self-selected speed equating to speeds of 65&#x02013;70% VO<sub>2</sub>max (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>). Another study (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gimenez et al., 2013</xref>) examined RE during a 24-h treadmill run, demonstrating an increase in oxygen consumption and concomitant decrease of RER in the first 8 h, thus remaining stable thereafter. This resulted in an increased Cr during that time period (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gimenez et al., 2013</xref>) The mechanisms behind the increase in Cr after an UM are not fully understood but changes in the neuromuscular system and biomechanical factors seem to play an important role (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Millet et al., 2011b</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Degache et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Neuromuscular Factors and Fatigue</title><p>Muscle fatigue and skeletal muscle damage can lead to changes in neural input to compensate decreasing muscle force especially during push off phase of the gait pattern (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Millet et al., 2011b</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>). Biomechanical changes can alter gait pattern and increased stride frequency, and leg and tendon stiffness have been observed leading to compensatory adjustments in the gait pattern through the gait cycle (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Millet et al., 2011b</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Degache et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>). These changes require an increasing VO<sub>2</sub> demand leading to increases in Cr. For those studies that have shown an improvement in Cr post UM (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) the underlying mechanism are not clear either. Positive neuromuscular adaptations and control of fatigued muscles may lead to improvements in movement through redistribution from motor units of fatigued to non-fatigued muscle groups (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Giandolini et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>). This may lead to a preservation of a more economical running pattern (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>) which may be of importance in extreme UM that have been investigated over a distance of 330 km and +24.000 m elevation (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2016</xref>) but this is not comparable to our current UM run.</p><p>Muscle enzyme (CK) and inflammatory markers (CRP and leukocytes) showed a significant increase from pre to post UM as described in previous studies (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Gill et al., 2015</xref>). An increase of Cr with increasing muscle damage and raised CK have been observed (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Kyr&#x000f6;l&#x000e4;inen et al., 2000</xref>); however, the correlation between muscle damage and changes in Cr are unclear (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Schena et al., 2014</xref>) In our group, this increase was not correlated to and could not explain the rising O<sub>2</sub> cost or Cr, suggesting other mechanisms to be involved. This could be further substantiated by the increase of the RPE that correlated with the rising O<sub>2</sub> cost and Cr, demonstrating that fatigue or the subjective rating of effort and fatigue may play a role as previously suggested (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Millet et al., 2011b</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gimenez et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Methodological Considerations</title><p>Methodological concerns may be an explanation of the discrepancies observed in Cr in the different studies. Race distances, race profiles, and race conditions have varied widely with races ranging from 43 to 330 km and 24,000 m elevations, to single case reports of a 8500-km expedition, making comparisons difficult (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Millet et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Lazzer et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2017a</xref>). Running speed and intensity have also varied widely ranging from speeds at 40&#x02013;80% of VO<sub>2</sub>max (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Lazzer et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>). <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al. (2017b)</xref> had therefore suggested to include specific testing conditions of the UM, assessing the consistency of the individual responses, providing adequate familiarizations sessions to participants to the specific protocol, and inserting a control group for future studies.</p></sec><sec><title>Strength</title><p>The main strength of the study is that we addressed some of the methodological considerations raised in the literature (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>). We included a preceding exercise test, to determine individual running speeds and participants received an adequate familiarization session of the testing protocol. The test protocol was designed according to specific slope conditions of the actual UM topography and tests were conducted not only pre- and post-race but also during the UM. Individual responses are presented in the results. However, we recognize that there are still some limitations and weaknesses to our study.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>Testing took place on a treadmill and outdoor running condition and surface differ; however recently, it has been shown that although subtle differences exist between overground and treadmill running, overground running can reasonably be replicated on the treadmill (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Firminger et al., 2018</xref>). Outdoor testing in the field can be done with a mobile spirometry unit as has been demonstrated (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Savoldelli et al., 2017</xref>); however, this may lead to other biases as for example testing speed and ambient conditions cannot be controlled as in laboratory conditions.</p><p>Other factors such as changes in running biomechanics can affect RE; however, we were not able to conduct kinematic analyses in this current study. Testing took place over three test days due to limitations in laboratory and staff capacity; however, ambient conditions at the three test days were comparable so this should not have had an impact on the results. The study was conducted as a simulated 65 km run and not under race conditions, so some participants may not have reached their full potential, but considering the distance covered and the time needed to complete that distance this should not have negatively impacted the results obtained.</p></sec><sec><title>Future Considerations</title><p>Examining changes in RE in the field, during different time points at varying UM distances and gradient slopes will be interesting, especially in groups of homogenous UM runners or elite UM runners. The insertion of a control group (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Vernillo et al., 2017b</xref>) may also yield new insights.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Energy cost of running and O<sub>2</sub> cost increased significantly pre to post UM in all testing conditions as well as during the uphill testing throughout the UM. This is the first study to demonstrate a consistent increase in these measures of RE among a range of different slopes, at individual running speeds and race-specific slopes giving further evidence that Cr and O<sub>2</sub> cost indeed increase in UM running.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>VS and H-CH contributed substantially to the conception and design of this study. VS and LC contributed to data collection. SV carried out the data analysis and interpretation together with VS, LC, RJ, and H-CH. VS wrote the first draft of the manuscript, and all authors were involved in revising it critically. All authors gave final approval of the version to be published and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of this work.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Jennifer Ahmann, Laura Fassbender, Tanja Janssen, and Roman Gaidai in helping to collect data during this research project. We thank all ultramarathon runners for their participation in this study.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balducci</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cl&#x000e9;men&#x000e7;on</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trama</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blache</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hautier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Performance factors in a mountain ultramarathon.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Sports Med.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>819</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>826</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0043-112342</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28799161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28799161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilding</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Running economy: measurement, norms, and determining factors.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sports Med. Open</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>:<issue>8</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40798-015-0007-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27747844?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27747844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source><italic>An Introduction to Borg&#x02019;s RPE-Scale</italic>.</source> Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://trove.nla.gov.au/version/45253441">http://trove.nla.gov.au/version/45253441</ext-link> [accessed December 1, 2017].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brueckner</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atchou</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capelli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duvallet</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrault</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jousselin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The energy cost of running increases with the distance covered.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol. Occup. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00626607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1893899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>R. J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rama</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swancott</surname><given-names>A. J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Water and sodium intake habits and status of ultra-endurance runners during a multi-stage ultra-marathon conducted in a hot ambient environment: an observational field based study.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nutr. J.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>:<issue>13</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2891-12-13</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23320854?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23320854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Aerobic performance of female marathon and male ultramarathon athletes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol. Occup. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00429740</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 499187?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">499187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degache</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guex</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourchet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomazin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Changes in running mechanics and spring-mass behaviour induced by a 5-hour hilly running bout.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sports Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2012.729136</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23051041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23051041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Firminger</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernillo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savoldelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanyshyn</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Joint kinematics and ground reaction forces in overground versus treadmill graded running.</article-title>
<source><italic>Gait Posture</italic></source>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gaitpost.2018.04.042</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29729612?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29729612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esau</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macintosh</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Economy of running: beyond the measurement of oxygen uptake.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Appl. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>1918</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1922</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00307.2009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19833811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19833811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fusi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvadego</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bresadola</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Maximal oxygen consumption and energy cost of running after a long-lasting running race: the 100 km of Sahara.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sport Sci. Health</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>:<issue>93</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11332-008-0046-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giandolini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernillo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samozino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvais</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>J.-B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Fatigue associated with prolonged graded running.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>116</volume>
<fpage>1859</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1873</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-016-3437-4</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27456477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27456477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rama</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prestes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosado</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hankey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Circulatory endotoxin concentration and cytokine profile in response to exertional-heat stress during a multi-stage ultra-marathon competition.</article-title>
<source><italic>Exerc. Immunol. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 25830597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25830597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gimenez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerherv&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messonnier</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000e9;asson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Changes in the energy cost of running during a 24-h treadmill exercise.</article-title>
<source><italic>Med. Sci. Sports Exerc.</italic></source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>1807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1813</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0b013e318292c0ec</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23524515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23524515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasternak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khodaee</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Townes</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Medical services at ultra-endurance foot races in remote environments: medical issues and consensus guidelines.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sports Med.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>1055</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1069</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-014-0189-3</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24748459?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24748459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyr&#x000f6;l&#x000e4;inen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pullinen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Candau</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avela</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huttunen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Komi</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Effects of marathon running on running economy and kinematics.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004210000219</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10958372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10958372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazzer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvadego</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rejc</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buglione</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonutto</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>di Prampero</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The energetics of ultra-endurance running.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>112</volume>
<fpage>1709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1715</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-011-2120-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21881950?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21881950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazzer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvadego</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taboga</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rejc</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovanelli</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>di Prampero</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Effects of the Etna uphill ultramarathon on energy cost and mechanics of running.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Sports Physiol. Perform.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>247</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2014-0057</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25117400?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25117400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazzer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taboga</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvadego</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rejc</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simunic</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Narici</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Factors affecting metabolic cost of transport during a multi-stage running race.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>217</volume>
<fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>795</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.091645</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24265425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24265425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepers</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lattier</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Babault</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maffiuletti</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Influence of ultra-long-term fatigue on the oxygen cost of two types of locomotion.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>376</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>380</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004210000313</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11138578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11138578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Ultramarathon is an outstanding model for the study of adaptive responses to extreme load and stress.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Med.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>77</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-10-77</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22812424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22812424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banfi</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerherve</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estrade</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011a</year>). <article-title>Physiological and biological factors associated with a 24 h treadmill ultra-marathon performance.</article-title>
<source><italic>Scand. J. Med. Sci. Sports</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0838.2009.01001.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19883385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19883385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomazin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verges</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnefoy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boisson</surname><given-names>R.-C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011b</year>). <article-title>Neuromuscular consequences of an extreme mountain ultra-marathon.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>e17059</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017059</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21364944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21364944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>J.-B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Degache</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edouard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feasson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verney</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Running from Paris to Beijing: biomechanical and physiological consequences.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>738</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-009-1194-3</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19756701?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19756701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;ronnet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Massicotte</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Table of nonprotein respiratory quotient: an update.</article-title>
<source><italic>Can. J. Sport Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1645211?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1645211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savoldelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornasiero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trabucchi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Limonta</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>La Torre</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Degache</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The energetics during the world&#x02019;s most challenging mountain ultra-marathon-a case study at the Tor des Geants<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>1003</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2017.01003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheer</surname><given-names>B. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Al Andalus ultra trail: an observation of medical interventions during a 219-km, 5-day ultramarathon stage race.</article-title>
<source><italic>Clin. J. Sport Med.</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>444</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>446</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JSM.0b013e318225b0df</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21860348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21860348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheer</surname><given-names>B. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doral</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). &#x0201c;<article-title>Ultramarathon running injuries</article-title>,&#x0201d; in <source><italic>Sports Injuries</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Doral</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>2889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2898</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-642-36569-0_216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheer</surname><given-names>B. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reljic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>R. J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The enemy of the feet: blisters in ultraendurance runners.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Am. Podiatr. Med. Assoc.</italic></source>
<volume>104</volume>
<fpage>473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>478</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7547/0003-0538-104.5.473</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25275735?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25275735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheer</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Participation trends of ultra endurance events.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sports Med. Arthrosc. Rev.</italic></source> (in press).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheer</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>T. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieluf</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitkamp</surname><given-names>H.-C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018a</year>). <article-title>Predicting trail running performance with laboratory exercise tests and field based results.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Sports Physiol. Perform.</italic></source>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2018-0390</pub-id> [Epub ahead of print]. <?supplied-pmid 29952678?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29952678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheer</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramme</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinsberger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitkamp</surname><given-names>H.-C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018b</year>). <article-title>VO2max testing in trail runners: is there a specific exercise test protocol?</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Sports Med.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>461</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-0577-4851</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29665614?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29665614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schena</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarperi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calabria</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvagno</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capelli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Running economy during a simulated 60-km trial.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Sports Physiol. Perform.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>609</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2013-0302</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24088379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24088379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernillo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giandolini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>J.-B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samozino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvais</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017a</year>). <article-title>Biomechanics and physiology of uphill and downhill running.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sports Med.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>629</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-016-0605-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27501719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27501719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernillo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017b</year>). <article-title>Does the running economy really increase after ultra-marathons?</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>783</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2017.00783</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29062284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29062284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernillo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savoldelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skafidas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zignoli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>La Torre</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>An extreme mountain ultra-marathon decreases the cost of uphill walking and running.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>530</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2016.00530</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27877137?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27877137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernillo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savoldelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zignoli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skafidas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornasiero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>La Torre</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Energy cost and kinematics of level, uphill and downhill running: fatigue-induced changes after a mountain ultramarathon.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sports Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>1998</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2005</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2015.1022870</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25751128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25751128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernillo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savoldelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zignoli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trabucchi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Influence of the world&#x02019;s most challenging mountain ultra-marathon on energy cost and running mechanics.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>929</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>939</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-014-2824-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24477570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24477570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>