<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dent Res J (Isfahan)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dent Res J (Isfahan)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DRJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Dental Research Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1735-3327</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2008-0255</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6340217</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">DRJ-16-24</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessment of antimicrobial activity of different concentrations of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> against <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>: An <italic>in vitro</italic> study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>Sankalp</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramamurthy</surname><given-names>Priyadarshini H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>Bennete</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rath</surname><given-names>Avita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sidhu</surname><given-names>Preena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Public Health Dentist, Madhur Smile Dental Clinic, Bareily, Uttar Pradesh, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Faculty of Dentistry, SEGi University, Selangor 47810, Malaysia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Priyadarshini H. Ramamurthy, Faculty of Dentistry, SEGi University, No. 9, Jalan Teknologi, PJU5, Kota Damansara, Petaling Jaya, Selangor 47810, Malaysia. E-mail: <email xlink:href="reachdocpriya@rediffmail.com">reachdocpriya@rediffmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2019 Dental Research Journal</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0"><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>The antimicrobial property of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> has been tested against a variety of microorganisms in the literature. The present study aimed to assess the antimicrobial activity of different concentrations of commercially available <italic>T. cordifolia</italic> powder against <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>An <italic>in vitro</italic> study was undertaken in which extract of <italic>T. cordifolia</italic> was obtained using 100% ethanol by maceration. Seven different concentrations were prepared and tested against <italic>S. mutans</italic> in brain&#x02013;heart infusion agar medium. Plates were incubated aerobically at 37&#x000b0;C for 48 h, and zone of inhibition was measured using Vernier caliper. 0.2% chlorhexidine and dimethylformamide were used as positive and negative controls respectively. The data were analysed by descriptive analytic tests.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>The maximum antibacterial activity of <italic>T. cordifolia</italic> was observed with a volume of 40 &#x003bc;l at 2% concentration with a zone of inhibition of 19 mm. A 30 &#x003bc;l volume of 0.2% chlorhexidine showed a zone of inhibition of 28 mm, and no zone of inhibition was observed with dimethylformamide.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p><italic>Tinospora</italic> exhibited antimicrobial activity against <italic>S. mutans</italic>. However, it needs to be confirmed further with <italic>in vivo</italic> studies.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Antimicrobial</kwd><kwd><italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Tinospora</italic></kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The use of plants for medicinal purposes is as old as human civilization itself. Medicinal plants have been used for curing diseases in different traditional systems of medicine such as Ayurveda, Siddha, European, Tibetan, and Unani.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Herbal medicine is still the mainstay of treatment in about 75%&#x02013;80% of people in many developing countries for their primary health care because of better cultural acceptability and compatibility with the human body and fewer side effects.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</p><p>One such immensely valuable plant regarding its constituents and pharmacology is <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> of the <italic>Menispermaceae</italic> family, commonly called as Guduchi in Sanskrit.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] It is a deciduous climbing shrub with small greenish flowers, having enormous medicinal value in all its parts such as leaves, stem, and also the root.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] It is a Rasayana (rejuvenator) and anti-aging medicine in Ayurveda, used to improve the immune system and the body resistance against infections.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] It has also been found that <italic>Tinospora</italic> has antispasmodic,[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] antipyretic,[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] anti-inflammatory,[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] anticomplementary,[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and immunomodulatory activities.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] In addition to it, <italic>Tinospora</italic> has been found to exhibit antidiabetic,[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] hepatoprotective,[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] anticancer,[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and antioxidant properties[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] as well. It has been listed as an insecticide, an antifungal agent, and an antibacterial agent.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] A ntimicrobial features have been found in its root, stem, and leaf extracts on pathogenic microorganisms.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] Ethanolic and aqueous extracts of <italic>T. cordifolia</italic> have been successfully tested against various bacteria such as <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis, Escherichia coli, Aspergillus niger, Candida albicans</italic>, and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] Unfortunately, no much research has been done to explore its antimicrobial properties against oral organisms. Hence, the present <italic>in vitro</italic> study was undertaken to assess the antimicrobial properties of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> against <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>, the most common organism associated with dental plaque and caries.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Study design</title><p>An <italic>in vitro</italic> study was designed to assess the antimicrobial activity of different concentrations of commercially available <italic>Tinospora</italic> powder against <italic>S. mutans</italic>. The study was approved by the Institutional Ethical Committee (SRDCHRC/146/11).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Preparation of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> extract</title><p><italic>Tinospora</italic> powder was first sieved to obtain uniform sized particles. 300 g of finely sieved powder of <italic>T. cordifolia</italic> was macerated with 1 L of 100% ethanol. It was then subjected to filtration with Whatman filter paper (No. 1) to obtain a clear filtrate. This filtrate was reduced at 80&#x000b0;C temperature in a water bath for 48 h to get a solid residue of <italic>T. cordifolia</italic> extract. From 300 g of <italic>Tinospora</italic> powder dissolved in 1 L of ethanol, 1.6 g of residue (extract) was obtained.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Preparation of seven different concentrations of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> extract</title><p>One gram of extract was dissolved in 10 ml of dimethylformamide to obtain a 10% concentration of extract. One milliliter of the extract was transferred to a sterilized test tube and labeled as 10%. The remaining 9 ml of the extract was diluted further with dimethylformamide to obtain seven different concentrations (2%, 3%, 4%, 5%, 6%, 7%, and 8%). In this study, 0.2% chlorhexidine was used as positive control, and dimethylformamide was used as negative control. The method for obtaining different concentrations was adopted from a study by Agarwal <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</p><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Bacterial sample</title><p>Pure strains of <italic>S. mutans</italic> (MTCC 890) obtained from Microbial Type Culture Collection and Gene Bank, Chandigarh, were used in the present study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Culture media and methods</title><p>Glass petri dishes and brain&#x02013;heart infusion agar were used for culture and to determine the zones of inhibition. 20 ml of freshly prepared, autoclaved, brain&#x02013;heart infusion agar media was transferred to each petri dish. Four circular wells to accommodate four different volumes (10 &#x003bc;l, 20 &#x003bc;l, 30 &#x003bc;l, and 40 &#x003bc;l) of the <italic>T. cordifolia</italic> extract were cut in the agar plates. Nine such petri dishes were prepared and labeled, seven of the seven different concentrations of <italic>Tinospora</italic> extract, one for the positive control (chlorhexidine), and one for the negative control (dimethylformamide). The sterile environment around the Petri dishes was maintained using split lamps. <italic>S. mutans</italic> (MTCC 890) strains were mixed with saline and swabbed to each agar plate using sterile wooden tongue blades. The plates were then incubated aerobically at 37&#x000b0;C for 48 h. After 48 h, the zone of inhibition was measured using a Vernier caliper. Data were tabulated and expressed as descriptive as this observational study did not require any inferential analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>A total of seven different concentrations of <italic>T. cordifolia</italic> extract along with positive and negative control were assessed for antimicrobial activity against <italic>S. mutans</italic>.</p><p>At 2% concentration, a maximum zone of inhibition of 19 mm was seen with a volume of 40 &#x003bc;l followed by 9 mm with 30 &#x003bc;l. On the contrary, no inhibition zone was found with secondary volumes such as 10 &#x003bc;l and 20 &#x003bc;l. At 4% and 5% concentrations, a maximum area of inhibition of 5 mm was observed at a volume of 40 &#x003bc;l while lesser quantities failed to produce any zone of inhibition. At 7% and 8% concentrations, a maximum area of inhibition of 2 mm was observed at a volume of 40 &#x003bc;l while no zone of inhibition was seen with lesser volumes. At 3% and 6% concentrations, no area of inhibition was observed with any of the volumes [<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Zones of inhibition at different concentrations and volumes of <italic>Tinospora</italic> extract</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DRJ-16-24-g001"/></table-wrap><p>The results with 0.2% chlorhexidine which was used as a positive control showed a maximum zone of inhibition of 28 mm with 30 &#x003bc;l followed by 20 mm with a volume of 40 &#x003bc;l, 8 mm with 20 &#x003bc;l, and the least of 7 mm with 10 &#x003bc;l, respectively [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Zones of inhibition with different volumes of 0.2% chlorhexidine (positive control)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DRJ-16-24-g002"/></table-wrap><p>No zone of inhibition was seen with any of the volumes of dimethylformamide, which was used as a negative control, indicating total lack of antimicrobial activity [<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Zones of inhibition with different volumes of dimethylformamide (negative control)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DRJ-16-24-g003"/></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The enormous heritage of vast natural, time-tested medicinal resources is worth exploring the possibility of developing efficient, economically viable, and clinically acceptable antimicrobials for human application. One among them is <italic>T. cordifolia</italic>, an indispensable medicinal plant, referred to in Ayurveda as &#x0201c;Amruth&#x0201d; or the &#x0201c;Nectar of Immortality&#x0201d; in recognition of its ability to impart youthfulness, vitality, and longevity. Preclinical and clinical pharmacological studies affirm the importance of its therapeutic efficacy and hence have placed it as a novel candidate to be used as the primary drug in the treatment of different ailments.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</p><p>Previously, plants such as Tulsi (<italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic>) and <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> have been tested for their antimicrobial activity on <italic>S. mutans</italic> with positive outcomes.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] However, studies regarding antimicrobial properties of <italic>Tinospora</italic> against oral microorganisms, especially <italic>S. mutans</italic>, are lacking though studies have evaluated its antimicrobial activity against <italic>E. coli, S. aureus, Pseudomonas aeruginosa,</italic> and <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] Some studies found that the maximum antimicrobial property was exhibited against <italic>S. aureus</italic>.[<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</p><p>In the present study, out of seven different concentrations and volumes tested against <italic>S. mutans</italic>, maximum inhibition of 19 mm was found with 40 &#x003bc;l at 2% concentration of the extract. Lesser amounts of the same strength failed to elicit the same results. It was also found that the zone of inhibition decreased with the increasing concentration of the extract of <italic>Tinospora</italic>. Furthermore, a volume of &#x0003c;30 &#x003bc;l of extract in all concentrations except for 2% failed to elicit any zone of inhibition. This indicates that the antimicrobial activity of <italic>Tinospora</italic> is effective at a lower concentration and higher volume with a maximum antibacterial activity as seen with 40 &#x003bc;l at 2% concentration. However, further studies are required to confirm the same. A study by Vermani <italic>et al</italic>. on antimicrobial properties of crude <italic>Tinospora</italic> extract against five dental pathogens showed similar results. The zone of inhibition against <italic>S. mutans</italic> was 10 mm, 11 mm, 19 mm, and 18 mm with ether, chloroform, methanol, and aqueous extracts of <italic>Tinospora</italic>, respectively.[<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</p><p>The antimicrobial property of <italic>Tinospora</italic> against <italic>Streptococcus mutants</italic> could be attributed to the secondary metabolites and the phytochemicals present in it such as quinones, polyphenols, alkaloids, flavonoids, tannins, coumarins, terpenoids, lectins, and polypeptides.[<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] While quinones and flavonoids bind to adhesins form complexes with cell wall and inactivate bacterial enzymes, terpenoids, polyphenols, and tannins cause membrane disruption and form metal ion complexes, thus inactivating the bacteria.[<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</p><p>In the present study, chlorhexidine was found to be more effective and exhibited better antimicrobial properties against <italic>S. mutans</italic> with a zone of inhibition of 28 mm, as compared to <italic>T. cordifolia</italic> extract. However, the well-known side effect of chlorhexidine, i.e., staining of teeth and restorations, alteration of taste sensation, and development of resistant microorganisms, may limit the long-term use of chlorhexidine.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] On the contrary, <italic>Tinospora</italic> is abundantly available, easily accessible, economically feasible, and culturally acceptable and may possess minimal side-effects. Hence, it can be recommended for long-term use to prevent plaque formation by <italic>S. mutans</italic> and in turn decrease the risk of caries and periodontal disease as plaque is a common etiological factor for both.</p><p>In the present study, dimethylformamide was resistant to <italic>S. mutans</italic>. This could be attributed to its property of being an inert solvent. It was used in the present study to dilute the <italic>Tinospora</italic> extract and to neutralize the effect of alcohol so that the results could be solely attributed to <italic>Tinospora</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>According to the present study, <italic>Tinospora</italic> exhibited antimicrobial properties against <italic>S. mutans</italic> with the maximum activity at 2% concentration. It could be formulated as mouthwash and used to prevent plaque in patients at high risk for caries and gingivitis. However, more research is required to test its antimicrobial properties in the oral environment through <italic>in vivo</italic> studies and also the adverse effects if any on oral mucosal cells and teeth.</p><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Nil.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6" sec-type="COI-satement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>The authors of this manuscript declare that they have no conflicts of interest, real or perceived, financial or non-financial in this article.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spandana</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nirmala</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Santhi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic></article-title><source>Int J Curr Pharm Rev Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagesh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Murlikrishnan</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the antimicrobial activity of various concentrations of tulsi (<italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic>) extract against <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>: An <italic>in vitro</italic> study</article-title><source>Indian J Dent Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20930344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neeraja</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Margaret</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amruthavalli (<italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic>) multipurpose rejuvenator</article-title><source>Int J Curr Pharm Rev Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chikara</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tinospora cardifolia &#x02013; A climbing shrub in health care management</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Biol Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kavya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramarao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkateshwarlu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tinospora cardifolia (WILLD.) Meirs &#x02013; Nutritional, ethnomedical and therapeutic utility</article-title><source>Int J Res Ayurveda Pharm</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gaduchi-the best ayurvedic herb</article-title><source>Pharm Innov J</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gacche</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhole</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and possible anti-inflammatory potential of selected medicinal plants prescribed in the Indian traditional system of medicine</article-title><source>Pharm Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>UN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakkar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> extract modulates COX-2, iNOS, ICAM-1, pro-inflammatory cytokines and redox status in murine model of asthma</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24556222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamat</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sainis</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An immunomodulator from <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> with antioxidant activity in cell-free systems</article-title><source>J Chem Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ittiyavirah</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahees</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic>: A potential plant with immunomodulatory activity</article-title><source>Iran J Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hetal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pradeep</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antidiabetic claims of Tinospora cardifoloia (willd) Meirs; critical appraisal and role in therapy</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Biomed</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kavitha</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shruthi</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramachandra</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical analysis and hepatoprotective properties of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> against carbon tetrachloride-induced hepatic damage in rats</article-title><source>J Basic Clin Pharm</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24826014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jagetia</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the antineoplastic activity of guduchi (<italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic>) in Ehrlich ascites carcinoma bearing mice</article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2006</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>460</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16508146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Premnath</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakshmidevi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on antioxidant activity of Tinospora cardifolia (Miers.) leaves using <italic>in vitro</italic> models</article-title><source>J Am Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>736</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jigar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagruti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guduchi <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic>: Biological and medicinal properties, a review</article-title><source>Internet J Altern Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>11</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic>: One plant, many roles</article-title><source>Anc Sci Life</source><year>2012</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23661861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panchabhai</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rege</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of therapeutic claims of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic>: A review</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18167043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahesh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Satish</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of some important medicinal plant against plant and human pathogens</article-title><source>World J Agric Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vashist</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jindal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activities of medicinal plants &#x02013; Review</article-title><source>Int J Res Pharm Biomed Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cagetti</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ionescu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Campus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lingstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> comparison of the effect of <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> extracts on different caries-related variables: A randomized controlled trial pilot study</article-title><source>Caries Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24216624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Noorulla</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Asma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalaichelvi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vadivel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thangabalan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>
<italic>In vitro</italic> antibacterial activity of methanolic root extract of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> WILLD</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Res Dev</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of potential antimicrobial activity of Indian medicinal plant of different solvent extract: <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> and <italic>Hymenocallis littoralis</italic></article-title><source>Int Res J Eng Technol</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>928</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhasin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Punia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehrawat</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of antimicrobial activity and phytochemical screening of extracts of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> against some pathogenic microbes</article-title><source>J Pharm Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Archa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Navneet</surname></name><name><surname>Shiv Shankar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of antibacterial activity of Tinospora cardifolia Miers extracts against dental pathogens</article-title><source>J Pharm Toxicol</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nimri</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Meqdam</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkofalri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of Jordanian medicinal</article-title><source>Plants Pharm Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>201</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamdar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meshram</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical analysis and assessment of <italic>in vitro</italic> antibacterial activity of <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic></article-title><source>Int J Curr Microbiol Appl Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choudhry</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Azmat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatoon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> comparison of the effect: Ethnobotany, phytopharmacology, and phytochemistry aspects</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Sci Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>