<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5859436</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4535</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-4535-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Systematic analysis of the lysine malonylome in common wheat</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jiabin</given-names></name><address><email>jiabinliu@qau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Guangyuan</given-names></name><address><email>gywang@qau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name><address><email>nxxlinqi@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Wenxing</given-names></name><address><email>wliang1@qau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Zhiqiang</given-names></name><address><email>gaozhiqiang1964@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>Ping</given-names></name><address><email>muping@qau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Guiquan</given-names></name><address><email>li-gui-quan@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Limin</given-names></name><address><email>andrewhjliang@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1798 1300</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412545.3</institution-id><institution>College of Agriculture, </institution><institution>Shanxi Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Taigu, Shanxi 030801 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Mordern Agriculture Demonstration Farm, Qindao Agricultural University, Qingdao, 266109 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9526 6338</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412608.9</institution-id><institution>College of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Qingdao Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Qingdao, 266109 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9526 6338</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412608.9</institution-id><institution>College of Agronomy and Plant Protection, </institution><institution>Qingdao Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Qingdao, Shandong 266109 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>209</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Protein lysine malonylation, a newly discovered post-translational modification (PTM), plays an important role in diverse metabolic processes in both eukaryotes and prokaryotes. Common wheat is a major global cereal crop. However, the functions of lysine malonylation are relatively unknown in this crop. Here, a global analysis of lysine malonylation was performed in wheat.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">In total, 342 lysine malonylated sites were identified in 233 proteins. Bioinformatics analysis showed that the frequency of arginine (R) in position +&#x02009;1 was highest, and a modification motif, K<sup>ma</sup>R, was identified. The malonylated proteins were located in multiple subcellular compartments, especially in the cytosol (45%) and chloroplast (30%). The identified proteins were found to be involved in diverse pathways, such as carbon metabolism, the Calvin cycle, and the biosynthesis of amino acids, suggesting an important role for lysine malonylation in these processes. Protein interaction network analysis revealed eight highly interconnected clusters of malonylated proteins, and 137 malonylated proteins were mapped to the protein network database. Moreover, five proteins were simultaneously modified by lysine malonylation, acetylation and succinylation, suggesting that these three PTMs may coordinately regulate the function of many proteins in common wheat.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">Our results suggest that lysine malonylation is involved in a variety of biological processes, especially carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms. These data represent the first report of the lysine malonylome in common wheat and provide an important dataset for further exploring the physiological role of lysine malonylation in wheat and likely all plants.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12864-018-4535-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Malonylome</kwd><kwd>Lysine malonylation</kwd><kwd><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.</kwd><kwd>Calvin cycle</kwd><kwd>Post-translational modification</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the agricultural well-breed project in Shandong Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016lzgc023</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Major Key Technology Project for Independent Innovation in Shandong Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>2014GJJS0201</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Innovation Team of Wheat for Modern Agricultural Technology System in Shandong Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>SDAIT-04-021-09</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>Ping</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>31601624</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Limin</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Taishan Scholar Construction Foundation of Shandong Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>tshw20130963</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Wenxing</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par21">Post-translational modifications (PTMs) are dynamic and reversible modifications of proteins and have wide effects in broadening the range of functionality of these proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Many functional groups, such as phospho, ubiquityl, acetyl, methyl, and malonyl groups, are able to be introduced by PTMs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Among PTMs, protein malonylation is a newly discovered modification, playing an important role in modulating various cellular processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Through reversible addition of a malonyl group to lysine residues, protein malonylation regulates protein localization, enzymatic activity, protein stability and many other biochemical processes. Although Malonyl-CoA is considered to be one of the most common donors of malonyl group, the enzymes controlling the malonylation status of proteins are largely unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Sirt5, a member of the lysine deacetylases (KDACs), was found to be able to catalyze lysine demalonylation reaction in mammalian cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Therefore, it is speculated that both protein acetylation and malonylation are reversibly regulated by lysine acetyltransferases (KATs) and KDACs, which are located to diverse cell compartments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Similar to lysine acetylation, many malonylated proteins localized in the nucleus, cytoplasm, mitochondria and chloroplast have been identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], indicating that a wide variety of biological processes are potentially regulated by lysine malonylation.</p><p id="Par22">In recent years, as a result of advancements in liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS), a large number of lysine-acetylated proteins have been identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. However, compared to these acetylation profiles, only a few organisms have been studied with respect to lysine malonylation, including <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], <italic>Saccharopolyspora erythraea</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], cyanobacteria (<italic>Synechocystis</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], HeLa cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], and mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">Common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) is one of the most important cereal crops in the world. Systematic analysis of the lysine acetylated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and succinylated proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] in common wheat revealed that they were involved in a variety of signaling pathways in development and metabolism. As one PTM that occurs on a lysine residue and competes with succinylation and acetylation, protein malonylation was expected to play a very important role in multiple processes in common wheat. To test this hypothesis, we performed the first proteomics study of lysine malonylation in common wheat. In total, we identified 342 lysine malonylation sites in 233 proteins. The malonylated proteins were associated with diversified biological processes and were distributed in multiple compartments, including the cytosol, chloroplast, nucleus, mitochondria, plasma membrane, cytoskeleton, extracellular space and peroxisome. Importantly, we found that 30% of the malonylated proteins were located to the chloroplast, and further studies showed that these proteins play an important role in photosynthetic carbon fixation in common wheat. Comparative analyses of proteomic profiles among the malonylome, acetylome and succinylome suggest that these three PTMs can occur on the same lysine residues and may coordinately regulate the function of many proteins in common wheat. This systematic analysis provides a rich dataset for further exploring the physiological role of lysine malonylation in this cereal crop and likely all plants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Protein extraction from common wheat</title><p id="Par24">Qing Mai 6, a common wheat variety (<italic>T. aestivum</italic> L.) tolerant to salt stress, was used for lysine malonylome analysis in this research. The seedlings of Qing Mai 6 were grown in a greenhouse for 3 weeks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and the excised leaves were subjected to protein extraction as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In brief, the leaves were ground in liquid nitrogen followed by sonicating for three times on ice in lysis buffer containing 8&#x000a0;M urea (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA), 1% TritonX-100 (Sangon Biotech, Shanghai, China), 10&#x000a0;mM dithiothreitol (DTT) (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA), and 1% Protease inhibitor cocktail (Merck Millipore, Billerica, USA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. After centrifugation at 20,000&#x000d7;g 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x000a0;min, proteins in the supernatant were precipitated with tricarboxylic acid (TCA) (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA) at &#x02212;&#x02009;20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The precipitates were washed three times by cold acetone (Hannuo, Lanxi, China) and were then redissolved in buffer (8&#x000a0;M urea, 100&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, pH&#x000a0;8.0) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Protein concentration was determined using the standard Bradford method.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Affinity enrichment of lysine malonylated peptides</title><p id="Par25">For affinity enrichment, the wheat proteins were cleaved into peptides through tryptic digestion. The extracted proteins were firstly reduced with 10&#x000a0;mM DTT at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;h and alkylated with 20&#x000a0;mM iodoacetamide (IAA) (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA) for 45&#x000a0;min, and were then digested by trypsin (Promega, Madison, USA) as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Trypsin was added at 1:50 and 1:100 trypsin-to-protein mass ratio for the first and the second digestion, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. A high pH reverse-phase HPLC with Agilent 300Extend C18 column (5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m particles, 4.6&#x000a0;mm ID, 250&#x000a0;mm length) (Agilent, Santa Clara, USA) was used to fractionate the resulting peptides into 80 fractions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Thereafter, the separated peptides were combined into 6 fractions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. To enrich peptides with malonylation sites, the combined peptides dissolved in NETN buffer (100&#x000a0;mM NaCl (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA), 1&#x000a0;mM EDTA (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA), 50&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA), 0.5% NP-40 (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA), pH&#x000a0;8.0) were incubated with pan anti-malonyllysine antibody conjugated agarose beads (PTM Biolabs, Hangzhou, China) at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C overnight with gentle shaking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The bound peptides were eluted from the beads with 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid (TFA) (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA) after 4 times washing with NETN buffer and were then cleaned using C18 ZipTips (Merck Millipore, Billerica, USA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>LC-MS/MS analysis</title><p id="Par26">LC-MS/MS analysis of the malonylation peptides was carried out as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Briefly, the peptides cleaned with C18 ZipTips were separated with a reversed-phase analytical column (ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, USA). The gradient was comprised of an increase from 6 to 22% solvent B (0.1% formic acid (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA) in 98% acetonitrile (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, USA)) for 24&#x000a0;min, 22 to 40% for 8&#x000a0;min and climbing to 80% in 5&#x000a0;min then holding at 80% for the last 3&#x000a0;min, all at a constant flow rate of 300&#x000a0;nl/min on an EASY-nLC 1000 UPLC system. The resulting peptides were analyzed by Q Exactive&#x02122; Plus hybrid quadrupole-Orbitrap mass spectrometer (ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, USA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Intact peptides and ion fragments were detected in the Orbitrap at a resolution of 70,000 and 17,500, respectively, with the NCE setting at 30 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. A data-dependent procedure that alternated between one MS scan followed by 20 MS/MS scans was applied for the top 20 precursor ions above a threshold ion count of 5E3 in the MS survey scan with 15.0&#x000a0;s dynamic exclusion. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. An electrospray voltage of 2.0&#x000a0;kV was employed to the LC-MS/MS analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. To generate MS/MS spectra, 5E4 ions were accumulated and automatic gain control (AGC) was used to prevent overfilling of the orbitrap [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. For MS scans, the m/z scan range was 350 to 1800 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Fixed first mass was set as 100&#x000a0;m/z [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Database search</title><p id="Par27">MaxQuant with integrated Andromeda search engine (v.1.5.1.8) was used to process the obtained MS/MS data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The collected tandem mass spectra were searched against <italic>4565_PR_wheat</italic> database concatenated with reverse decoy database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Trypsin/P was specified as cleavage enzyme allowing up to 4 missing cleavages, 5 modifications per peptide and 5 charges; minimum peptide length was set at 7 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Mass error was set to 10&#x000a0;ppm and 0.02&#x000a0;Da for precursor ions and fragment ions, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Carbamidomethylation on Cys was set as fixed modification; malonylation on Lys was set as variable modification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. False discovery rate (FDR) threshold of 1% was specified for protein, peptide and modification site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. All the other parameters in MaxQuant were set as default values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The probability for site localization was set as &#x0003e;&#x02009;0.75 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Bioinformatics analysis</title><p id="Par28">The malonylated proteins were analyzed by Gene Ontology (GO) annotation derived from the UniProt-GOA database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/GOA">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/GOA/</ext-link>) based on biological process, cellular component and molecular function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. InterPro (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/</ext-link>) was used to annotate functional domains of all identified proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Protein pathways were annotated by Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. A two-tailed Fisher&#x02019;s exact test was employed to test the enrichment of the malonylated proteins and a corrected <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered significant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Subcellular localization of the modified proteins was predicated with WoLF PSORT (version PSORT/PSORT II) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The current dataset used to train WoLF PSORT contains over 12,000 animal sequences and more than 2000 plant and fungi sequences respectively. For each protein, WoLF PSORT reported a number to roughly indicate the number of nearest neighbors to the protein which localize to each site. Then, localization sites with the maximum number were selected as the subcellular localization of protein. The model of sequences constituted with amino acids in specific positions of modify-21-mers was analyzed using Motif-x software and the secondary structures of proteins were predicted using NetSurfP software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Only predictions with a minimum probability of 0.5 for one of the different secondary structures (coil, &#x003b1;-helix, &#x003b2;-strand) were considered for analysis. The mean secondary structure probabilities of the malonylated lysine residues were compared with the mean secondary structure probabilities of a control dataset containing all the lysine residues of all the malonylated proteins identified in this study. Cytoscape software was employed to analyze the protein-protein interactions for the malonylated proteins and the protein-protein interaction network was obtained from the STRING database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. BLASTP was carried out to determine the conservation of lysine malonylated proteins between common wheat and other organisms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Immunoprecipitation of dehydroascorbate reductase</title><p id="Par29">The leaves of common wheat were ground in liquid nitrogen and the soluble proteins were extracted as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. After overnight incubation of 1&#x000a0;mg of soluble proteins with or without 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of dehydroascorbate reductase specific antibody (Agrisera, V&#x000e4;nn&#x000e4;s, Sweden), 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of protein A agarose beads (GE Healthcare, Uppsala, Sweden) were added and the solution was incubated for another 1&#x000a0;h. The bound proteins were eluted from the beads with boiled SDS-PAGE sample buffer following 5 times wash with lysis buffer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p id="Par30">Eluted proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE on a 12% gel and probed with dehydroascorbate reductase antibody (1:5000 dilution) and anti-malonyllysine antibody (1:2000 dilution, PTM Biolabs, Hangzhou, China), respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Proteins were visualized using Pierce Fast Western Blot Kit ECL Substrate (ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Identification of lysine malonylated proteins in common wheat</title><p id="Par31">To elucidate the regulatory functions of lysine malonylation in wheat, a proteome-scale analysis of malonylated proteins was performed (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1a). To validate the MS data, the mass error of all the identified peptides was checked, and the total distribution of the mass error was less than 5&#x000a0;ppm, indicating that the mass accuracy of the MS data fit the requirement (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1b). We further checked the distribution of all the peptides, and the results showed that the length of most of the peptides was between 8 and 20 (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1c), which demonstrated that the sample preparation met the standard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. After a large-scale lysine malonylome analysis using LC-MS/MS, a total of 342 lysine malonylation sites in 233 protein groups were identified (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1). Three representative MS/MS spectra of the malonylated peptides were showed in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2. The number of malonylated proteins in common wheat was higher than that in <italic>S. erythraea</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], but less than the number of identified proteins in <italic>B. amyloliquefaciens</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], <italic>E. coli</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and mammals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Dehydroascorbate reductase (DHAR), a protein involved in redox homeostasis under biotic and abiotic stresses and a key component of the ascorbate recycling system, was found to be malonylated on the lysine residue, K157 (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1). Immunoprecipitation coupled with Western blot analysis confirmed malonylation of DHAR in wheat leaves (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3). Proteins can be modified on either one or several amino acid residues. Thus, the number of malonylated sites in the identified proteins was calculated in common wheat. As shown in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4, 75% (175) of malonylated proteins had only one malonylated lysine site, whereas 25% (58) were modified on multiple lysine residues. A similar distribution pattern was also found in <italic>S. erythraea</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. To our knowledge, these findings represent the first report of lysine malonylome in common wheat.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Pattern analysis of malonylated sites</title><p id="Par32">Previous studies have demonstrated the modified site preferences for lysine residues at particular positions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. To map the specific amino acids surrounding the malonylated lysine, we investigated the frequency of different amino acids around the malonylated lysine from &#x02212;&#x02009;10 to +&#x02009;10. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>, the frequency of arginine (R) in position +&#x02009;1 was highest. We further investigated the sequence motifs in all the identified peptides using the motif-x program. In accordance with the heat map of the amino acid compositions of the malonylation sites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>), a motif, K<sup>ma</sup>R (K<sup>ma</sup> indicates the lysine malonylation site), was obtained (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). In addition to K<sup>ma</sup>R, K(X6)K<sup>ma</sup>, K<sup>ma</sup>(X6)K, and K(X5)K<sup>ma</sup> (X represents an unspecified amino acid residue) were also detected in <italic>S. erythraea</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. However, compared with acetylation motifs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and succinylation motifs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], the number of lysine malonylation motifs identified so far was much lower.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Properties of the lysine malonylation peptides in common wheat. <bold>a</bold> Heat map of the amino acid compositions of the malonylation sites showing the frequency of different amino acids around the modified lysine. Red indicates high frequency and green means low frequency. <bold>b</bold> Malonylation sequence motifs for &#x000b1;10 amino acids around the lysine malonylation sites. <bold>c</bold> Probabilities of lysine malonylation in the structures of alpha-helix, beta-strand and coli. <bold>d</bold> Predicted surface accessibility of malonylation sites</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4535_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par33">To elucidate a possible relationship between lysine malonylation sites and protein structure in wheat, we performed a structural analysis of all the identified proteins. Consistent with the results in <italic>B. amyloliquefaciens</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], the malonylation sites do not prefer a certain type of secondary structure such as an alpha-helix or beta-strand (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>), indicating that there is no tendency toward malonylation in common wheat. We further evaluated the surface accessibility of the lysine malonylation sites. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>, compared to 87.48% of all lysine residues, 88.71% of lysine malonylation sites were exposed to a protein surface (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71), indicating that the surface property of proteins is not affected by lysine malonylation. Different from our observations, the lysine malonylation sites were preferably located on the surface of proteins in <italic>B. amyloliquefaciens</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conservation of lysine malonylated proteins</title><p id="Par34">To date, a large number of lysine malonylated proteins have been identified in several prokaryotes and eukaryotes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, the conservation of lysine malonylation in these organisms is unknown. As such, we searched the orthologs of lysine malonylated proteins in common wheat by a protein BLAST search against seven organisms with determined malonylomes: <italic>B. amyloliquefaciens</italic>, <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, <italic>Mus musculus</italic>, <italic>O. sativa</italic>, <italic>S. erythraea</italic> and <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp. PCC 6803<italic>.</italic> Totally, 458 orthologs of the malonylproteins in common wheat were identified in these seven organisms (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>, 161 malonylated proteins have orthologs in <italic>M. musculus</italic> (108 proteins), <italic>H. sapiens</italic> (112 proteins), <italic>Synechocystis</italic> (24 proteins), <italic>O. sativa</italic> (97 proteins), <italic>S. erythraea</italic> (25 proteins), <italic>E. coli</italic> (48 proteins) and <italic>B. amyloliquefaciens</italic> (44 proteins), which account for 69.1% (161/233 proteins) of the total malonylproteins in common wheat. We further classified the malonylated proteins of common wheat depending on the number of their orthologous proteins in other organisms. The results showed that the percentage of completely conserved proteins (have orthologs in all 7 organisms), well-conserved proteins (have orthologs in 5 to 6 organisms), conserved proteins (have orthologs in 3 to 4 organisms) and poorly conserved proteins (have orthologs in 1 to 2 organisms) were 3% (7/233 proteins), 9% (21/233 proteins), 23.6% (55/233 proteins), and 33.5% (78/233 proteins) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), respectively. Furthermore, 30.9% (72/233 proteins) of the malonylated proteins in common wheat was grouped as novel proteins since no orthologs were identified in other organisms (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). These observations suggest that although lysine malonylation is largely conserved in prokaryotes and eukaryotes, different organisms contain unique malonylated proteins with specific functions.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Conservation analysis of lysine malonylated proteins. <bold>a</bold> Number of orthologous malonylproteins in seven organisms with reported malonylomes. <bold>b</bold> A pie chart of conservation of malonylproteins in <italic>B. amyloliquefaciens</italic>, <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>H. sapiens</italic>, <italic>M. musculus</italic>, <italic>O. sativa</italic>, <italic>S. erythraea</italic> and <italic>Synechocystis</italic>. Grouping was performed as follows: Completely conserved, 7 orthologs; Well conserved, 5 to 6 orthologs; Conserved, 3 to 4 orthologs; Poorly conserved, 1 to 2 orthologs; Novel, 0 orthologs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4535_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Functional annotation of malonylated proteins</title><p id="Par35">To further understand the potential roles of malonylated proteins, we performed a GO functional classification analysis in common wheat based on their biological process, cellular component and molecular function. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S3, according to biological process analysis, 123 proteins in metabolic processes, 93 proteins in single-organism processes, and 93 proteins in cellular processes were malonylated, which account for 34, 25 and 25% of all identified proteins in common wheat, respectively. Consistent with these observations, a large proportion of the malonylated proteins were associated with catalytic (44%) and binding (43%) activities based on molecular function analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S3). Cellular component analysis showed that most of the malonylated proteins were located in the cell (38%), macromolecular complex (24%), organelle (22%), membrane (12%) and extracellular region (3%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S3). These results suggest that lysine malonylation may affect the molecular functions of proteins and then regulate multiple biological processes in diverse cellular components in common wheat.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Functional classification of lysine malonylated proteins in common wheat. <bold>a</bold> Classification of malonylated proteins according to biological process. <bold>b</bold> Classification of malonylated proteins according to cellular component. <bold>c</bold> Classification of malonylated proteins according to molecular function. <bold>d</bold> Subcellular localization of the malonylated proteins</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4535_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par36">We further predicted the subcellular localizations of the identified proteins using WoLF PSORT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The results in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref> showed that most of the malonylated proteins in wheat were located in the cytosol (45%) and chloroplast (30%). Interestingly, 11% of the malonylated proteins were localized in the nucleus, including histone H4, histone H2B, histone H2A, and histone H3 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1), confirming the regulatory role of lysine malonylation in post-translational regulation. Furthermore, other malonylated proteins were predicted to be located to the mitochondria (6%), plasma membrane (2%), cytoskeleton (2%), extracellular space (2%) and peroxisome (1%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). These findings indicate that the lysine-malonylated proteins have a broad range of biological functions in common wheat.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Functional enrichment analysis of malonylated proteins</title><p id="Par37">To evaluate the nature of malonylated proteins in wheat, we performed functional enrichment analyses of the GO, KEGG pathway and protein domain. As shown in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S5 and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S4, many modified proteins were associated with the metabolic and catabolic processes in the biological process category. In agreement with these observations, most of the malonylated proteins were found to be involved in enzymatic activities and binding according to the enrichment analysis of molecular function (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S5 and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S4). Consistent with these findings, proteins located to the cytoplasm, macromolecular complex, and DNA bending complex were more likely to be malonylated based on the enrichment analysis of the cellular component (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S5 and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S4). In support of these findings, the proteins associated with carbon metabolism, secondary metabolite biosynthesis, carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms, and amino acid biosynthesis were highly enriched based on the KEGG pathway enrichment analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S5). Moreover, protein domain enrichment analysis showed that proteins with the following domains were more prone to malonylation: NAD(P)-binding, GTP-binding, catalytic and transferase domains (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S6 and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S6).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>KEGG pathway-based enrichment analysis of the malonylation proteins in common wheat</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4535_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Protein interaction network of malonylated proteins</title><p id="Par38">To investigate the cellular processes regulated by lysine malonylation in wheat, a protein interaction network was established with the STRING database using Cytoscape software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S7, 137 malonylated proteins were mapped to the protein network database. According to the algorithm in the Cytoscape software, eight highly interconnected clusters of acetylated proteins were retrieved. The top cluster identified included proteins associated with ribosomes (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S7). The complicated interaction networks of malonylated proteins indicate that a variety of pathways are putatively modulated by lysine malonylation in common wheat.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Protein interaction networks of the malonylation proteins in common wheat</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4535_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Analysis of malonylated proteins involved in the Calvin cycle</title><p id="Par39">In wheat, the Calvin cycle is one of the most important metabolic processes. Previous studies demonstrated that carbohydrate metabolism in Calvin cycle is regulated by drought stress in wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].The Calvin cycle (also known as the Calvin-Benson cycle) is the set of chemical reactions that convert carbon dioxide into carbohydrates and other organic compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The Calvin cycle occurs in chloroplasts during photosynthesis. We found that 30% of the malonylated proteins were located in the chloroplast in common wheat (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). Functional enrichment analysis of the KEGG pathway revealed that the proteins associated with carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms were highly enriched (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). These results suggested that lysine malonylation may play an important role in the Calvin cycle in common wheat. To confirm these observations, we further analyzed the malonylated proteins involved in the Calvin cycle. In agreement with our hypothesis, six enzymes involved in carbon fixation in the Calvin cycle were found to be malonylated, including phosphoglycerate kinase (PGK) (accession no. W5H4V7), glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPD1&#x02013;3) (accession nos. W5GYX5, C7C4X1 and W5G5H3), fructose-bisphosphate aldolase (ALDO) (accession no. W5D0E3), and malate dehydrogenase (MDH) (accession no. W5AIB2) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1). Importantly, all the malonylated sites were located in the functional domains of these enzymes (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1). An example is ALDO carrying the malonylated K225, which is the catalytic site of this enzyme (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). Although ribulose-1.5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (RuBisCO), a central enzyme in the Calvin cycle, was detected as a differentially expressed protein in response to drought stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], this protein was not modified by malonylation. These results suggest that lysine malonylation probably modulates the Calvin cycle in common wheat.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Identified malonylation proteins in Calvin cycle in common wheat. <bold>a</bold> Working scheme of lysine malonylation events involved in Calvin cycle in common wheat. The malonylated proteins were highlighted in red. <bold>b</bold> Three-dimensional structure of protein ALDO with identified malonylation site. The structure was taken from PDB database. The malonylated lysine residue, K225, was indicated by red arrow</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4535_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Comparison among the malonylome, acetylome and succinylome in common wheat</title><p id="Par40">As one type of PTM, lysine malonylation competes with other modifications, such as succinylation and acetylation, for lysine residues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In our previous research, 416 acetylated lysine sites in 277 proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and 330 lysine succinylated modification sites in 173 proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] were identified. To determine whether malonylation, acetylation and succinylation can occur on the same lysine residue, we compared the lysine malonylome with the succinylome and acetylome. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>, 5 proteins were modified by the three PTMs at the same time, including GAPD1 (accession no. W5GYX5), which is one of the key enzymes involved in the Calvin cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]; elongation factor 1-alpha (accession no. Q03033), which is responsible for the transport of amino acyl tRNAs to ribosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]; 14&#x02013;3-3 protein (accession no. L0GED8), which is a negative regulator in response to nutrient sensing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]; translationally controlled tumor protein homolog (accession no. Q8LRM8); and 4-hydroxy-7-methoxy-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-2H-1,4-benzoxazin-2-yl glucoside beta-D-glucosidase 1a (accession no. Q1XIR9) (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1). A total of 16 proteins were modified by both lysine malonylation and acetylation, and 23 proteins were modified by both lysine malonylation and succinylation in wheat (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>). Moreover, lysine acetylation and succinylation can simultaneously happen on 33 proteins (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Overlap among lysine malonylation, lysine succinylation and lysine acetylation in common wheat. <bold>a</bold> Overlap of malonylated proteins, succinylated proteins and acetylated proteins. <bold>b</bold> Overlap of malonylation sites, succinylation sites and acetylation sites. <bold>c</bold> A representative protein, elongation factor 1-alpha (accession no. Q03033), showing the overlap among malonylation, succinylation and acetylation</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2018_4535_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par41">We further compared the lysine residues modified by lysine malonylation, succinylation and acetylation in wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>, 2.3 and 5.6% of the malonylation sites could also be acetylated and succinylated, respectively. Only one lysine site in elongation factor 1-alpha (accession no. Q03033) was simultaneously modified by these three types of modifications (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1<bold>)</bold> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The overlap among malonylation, acetylation and succinylation in elongation factor 1-alpha was shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>. Four malonylated sites at K161, K172, K318 and K427 were identified, and two sites at K161 and K318 were also determined to be succinylated. Moreover, three lysine sites at K62, K161, and K243 were found to be acetylated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>).</p><p id="Par42">Multiple PTMs, including malonylation, succinylation, acetylation and phosphorylation, also occur on the same proteins in <italic>E. coli</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and <italic>S. erythraea</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. A total of 594 lysine malonylation sites were able to be modified by succinylation and acetylation in <italic>E. coli</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In <italic>S. erythraea</italic>, 16 proteins were found to be modified by malonylation, acetylation and phosphorylation at the same time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. These results, together with our findings, indicate that multiple PTMs can occur on the same proteins to coordinately regulate the function of many proteins in common wheat and likely all eukaryotic and prokaryotic organisms.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par43">In this study, a total of 233 malonylated proteins with 342 unique modification sites were identified in common wheat. The identified malonylated proteins are localized in diverse compartments and are involved in multiple biological processes, especially in the Calvin cycle. Protein interaction network analysis demonstrates that numerous pathways are modulated by lysine malonylation. Overlap among the acetylome, succinylome and malonylome in wheat shows coordination among these three important PTMs. The provided dataset illuminates a crucial role of lysine malonylation in common wheat and serves as an important resource for examining and exploring the physiological role of lysine malonylation in all plants.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec20"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4535_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> Systematic analysis of lysine malonylation sites in common wheat. <bold>Figure S2.</bold> Three representative MS/MS spectra of the malonylated peptides. <bold>Figure S3.</bold> Validation of lysine malonylation of DHAR by Western blot analysis. <bold>Figure S4.</bold> Number of malonylation sites per protein in common wheat. <bold>Figure S5.</bold> GO-based enrichment analysis in terms of cellular component (red bars), molecular function (blue bars) and biological process (green bars). <bold>Figure S6.</bold> Domain-based enrichment analysis of malonylated proteins. <bold>Figure S7.</bold> Interaction network of malonylated proteins associated with ribosome. (DOCX 2050 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12864_2018_4535_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> The identified lysine malonylation sites in wheat. <bold>Table S2</bold> Conservation of lysine malonylated proteins. <bold>Table S3</bold> The distribution of proteins in GO terms. <bold>Table S4</bold> Protein GO enrichment based on cellular component, molecular function and biological process. <bold>Table S5</bold> Protein pathway enrichment analysis. <bold>Table S6</bold> Protein domain enrichment analysis. <bold>Table S7</bold> Protein interaction network of identified proteins. (XLSX 141 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AGC</term><def><p id="Par4">Automatic gain control</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ALDO</term><def><p id="Par5">Fructose-bisphosphate aldolase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DHAR</term><def><p id="Par6">Dehydroascorbate reductase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DTT</term><def><p id="Par7">Dithiothreitol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FA</term><def><p id="Par8">Formic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FDR</term><def><p id="Par9">False discovery rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GAPD</term><def><p id="Par10">Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p id="Par11">Gene ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HPLC</term><def><p id="Par12">High performance liquid chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IAA</term><def><p id="Par13">Iodoacetamide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p id="Par14">Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LC&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;MS/MS</term><def><p id="Par15">Liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDH</term><def><p id="Par16">Malate dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PGK</term><def><p id="Par17">Phosphoglycerate kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PTM</term><def><p id="Par18">Post-translational modification</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCA</term><def><p id="Par19">Tricarboxylic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TFA</term><def><p id="Par20">Trifluoroacetic acid</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12864-018-4535-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par44">This work was supported by the agricultural well-breed project in Shandong Province (2016lzgc023), the Major Key Technology Project for Independent Innovation in Shandong Province (2014GJJS0201), the Innovation Team of Wheat for Modern Agricultural Technology System in Shandong Province (SDAIT-04-021-09), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31601624) and the Taishan Scholar Construction Foundation of Shandong Province (tshw20130963). None of these funding sources were involved in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par45">The datasets supporting the results of this article are included within the article and additional files.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>GL and LS designed research; JL, GW, QL and WL performed research; ZG and PM contributed new reagents or analytic tools; JL, GW, QL, WL, ZG, PM, GL and LS analyzed data; JL, GW, QL, WL, ZG, PM, GL and LS wrote the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par46">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par47">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par48">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par49">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Khoury GA, Baliban RC, Floudas CA. Proteome-wide post-translational modification statistics: frequency analysis and curation of the swiss-prot database. Sci Rep. 2011;</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive profiling of lysine acetylproteome analysis reveals diverse functions of lysine acetylation in common wheat</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>21069</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep21069</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26875666?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26875666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of protein lysine succinylation profiles in common wheat</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>309</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-017-3698-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28427325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28427325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Malonylome analysis of rhizobacterium <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> FZB42 reveals involvement of lysine malonylation in polyketide synthesis and plant-bacteria interactions</article-title><source>J Proteome</source><year>2017</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2016.11.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global profiling of protein lysine malonylation in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> reveals its role in energy metabolism</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2060</fpage><lpage>2071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.6b00264</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27183143?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27183143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirschey</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic regulation by lysine malonylation, succinylation, and glutarylation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2308</fpage><lpage>2315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.R114.046664</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25717114?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25717114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pougovkina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Te</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic and biochemical studies of lysine malonylation suggest its malonic aciduria-associated regulatory role in mitochondrial function and fatty acid oxidation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3056</fpage><lpage>3071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M115.048850</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26320211?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26320211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The first identification of lysine malonylation substrates and its regulatory enzyme</article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>M111.012658</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M111.012658</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21908771?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21908771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lysine succinylation and lysine malonylation in histones</article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M111.015875</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22389435?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22389435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lysine malonylome may affect the central metabolism and erythromycin biosynthesis pathway in <italic>Saccharopolyspora erythraea</italic></article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1685</fpage><lpage>1701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.6b00131</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27090497?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27090497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Malonylome analysis reveals the involvement of lysine malonylation in metabolism and photosynthesis in cyanobacteria</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2030</fpage><lpage>2043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.7b00017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28365990?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28365990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mujahid H, Meng X, Xing S, Peng X, Wang C, Peng Z. Malonylome analysis in developing rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) seeds suggesting that protein lysine malonylation is well-conserved and overlaps with acetylation and succinylation substantially. J Proteomics. 2018;170:88&#x02013;98.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lysine malonylation is elevated in type 2 diabetic mouse models and enriched in metabolic associated proteins</article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M114.041947</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25418362?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25418362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TaRAR1 and TaSGT1 associate with TaHsp90 to function in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) seedling growth and stripe rust resistance</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>87</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-015-0298-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25697954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25697954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acetylome analysis reveals the involvement of lysine acetylation in biosynthesis of antibiotics in <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic></article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>20108</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep20108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26822828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26822828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteome-wide analysis of lysine acetylation in the plant pathogen <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>29313</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep29313</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27381557?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27381557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic analysis of the lysine acetylome in <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1019</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-3361-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27964708?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27964708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acetylome analysis reveals the involvement of lysine acetylation in diverse biological processes in <italic>Phytophthora sojae</italic></article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>29897</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep29897</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27412925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27412925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MaxQuant enables high peptide identification rates, individualized p.p.b.-range mass accuracies and proteome-wide protein quantification</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1511</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19029910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19029910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraj</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Selbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A practical guide to the MaxQuant computational platform for SILAC-based quantitative proteomics</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>698</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2009.36</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19373234?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19373234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The KEGG resource for deciphering the genome</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D277</fpage><lpage>D280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh063</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14681412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Obayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams-Collier</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>WoLF PSORT: protein localization predictor</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><issue>Web Server</issue><fpage>W585</fpage><lpage>W587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm259</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17517783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17517783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological sequence motif discovery using motif-x</article-title><source>Curr Protoc Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>Chapter 13</volume><issue>Unit 13</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21901740?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21901740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Markiel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozier</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Baliga</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramage</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2498</fpage><lpage>2504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.1239303</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14597658?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szklarczyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Franceschini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Forslund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STRING v10: protein-protein interaction networks, integrated over the tree of life</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>43</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D447</fpage><lpage>D452</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of protein lysine succinylation profiles and their overlap with lysine acetylation in the marine bacterium <italic>Vibrio parahemolyticus</italic></article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>4309</fpage><lpage>4318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.5b00485</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26369940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26369940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteome-wide identification of lysine succinylation in the proteins of tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>)</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e0147586</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147586</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26828863?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26828863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Budak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Akpinar</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Unver</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Turktas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteome changes in wild and modern wheat leaves upon drought stress by two-dimensional electrophoresis and nanoLC-ESI&#x02013;MS/MS</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-013-0024-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23443681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23443681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The photosynthetic cycle</article-title><source>Bull Soc Chim Biol (Paris)</source><year>1956</year><volume>38</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1233</fpage><lpage>1244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13383309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassham</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Quarck</surname><given-names>UC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intermediates in the photosynthetic cycle</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1956</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-3002(56)90022-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 13363921?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13363921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Succinylome analysis reveals the involvement of lysine succinylation in metabolism in pathogenic <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M114.045922</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25605462?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25605462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Translation elongation factor 1-&#x003b1; gene from <italic>Pichia pastoris</italic>: molecular cloning, sequence, and use of its promoter</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2007</year><volume>74</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-006-0698-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17124582?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17124582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardenas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The TOR kinases link nutrient sensing to cell growth</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>9583</fpage><lpage>9586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.R000034200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11266435?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11266435</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>