<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">pnas</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">pnas</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PNAS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0027-8424</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1091-6490</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Academy of Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5924906</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29632179</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">201719387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1719387115</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biological Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>E3 ubiquitin ligase SOR1 regulates ethylene response in rice root by modulating stability of Aux/IAA protein</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Biao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Si-Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>San-Yuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Xiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Shou-Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jin-Song</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>a</sup>State Key Laboratory of Plant Genomics, Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, <institution>Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, 100101 Beijing, <country>China</country>;</aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>b</sup><institution>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, 100049 Beijing, <country>China</country>;</aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>c</sup>College of Life Sciences and Oceanography, <institution>Shenzhen University</institution>, 518060 Shenzhen, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>2</sup>To whom correspondence may be addressed. Email: <email>sychen@genetics.ac.cn</email> or <email>jszhang@genetics.ac.cn</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by Mark Estelle, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, CA, and approved March 19, 2018 (received for review November 8, 2017)</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Author contributions: H.C. and J.-S.Z. designed research; H.C., B.M., Y.Z., S.-J.H., and X.L. performed research; S.-Y.T. and Q.X. contributed new reagents/analytic tools; H.C., S.-Y.C., and J.-S.Z. analyzed data; and H.C. and J.-S.Z. wrote the paper.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>H.C., B.M., and Y.Z. contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>115</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>4513</fpage><lpage>4518</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 the Author(s). Published by PNAS.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="vor"/><license-p>This open access article is distributed under <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0 (CC BY-NC-ND)</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="pnas.201719387.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><title>Significance</title><p>Auxin signaling components participate in ethylene-mediated inhibition of root elongation. However, the interplay between TIR1/AFB2-auxin-Aux/indole acetic acid (IAA) signaling and ethylene response remains to be elucidated in detail. In this study, we report an E3 ubiquitin ligase soil-surface rooting 1 (SOR1), which targets a noncanonical Aux/IAA protein OsIAA26 for 26S proteasome-mediated degradation. The E3 ligase activity of SOR1 can be repressed by the canonical Aux/IAA protein OsIAA9, which is the target of OsTIR1/AFB2. Our study identifies a potential regulator that modulates auxin-mediated ethylene response at the auxin signaling level.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Plant hormones ethylene and auxin synergistically regulate plant root growth and development. Ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis of Aux/IAA transcriptional repressors by the E3 ubiquitin ligase SCF<sup>TIR1/AFB</sup> triggers a transcription-based auxin signaling. Here we show that rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) soil-surface rooting 1 (SOR1), which is a RING finger E3 ubiquitin ligase identified from analysis of a rice ethylene-insensitive mutant <italic>mhz2/sor1-2</italic>, controls root-specific ethylene responses by modulating Aux/IAA protein stability. SOR1 physically interacts with OsIAA26 and OsIAA9, which are atypical and canonical Aux/IAA proteins, respectively. SOR1 targets OsIAA26 for ubiquitin/26S proteasome-mediated degradation, whereas OsIAA9 protects the OsIAA26 protein from degradation by inhibiting the E3 activity of SOR1. Auxin promotes SOR1-dependent degradation of OsIAA26 by facilitating SCF<sup>OsTIR1/AFB2</sup>-mediated and SOR1-assisted destabilization of OsIAA9 protein. Our study provides a candidate mechanism by which the SOR1-OsIAA26 module acts downstream of the OsTIR1/AFB2-auxin-OsIAA9 signaling to modulate ethylene inhibition of root growth in rice seedlings.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>rice</kwd><kwd>root elongation</kwd><kwd>ethylene response</kwd><kwd>Aux/IAA protein</kwd><kwd>ubiquitination</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="gs1"><funding-source id="sp1">National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)<named-content content-type="funder-id">501100001809</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp1">31530004</award-id></award-group><award-group id="gs2"><funding-source id="sp2">973 project</funding-source><award-id rid="sp2">2015CB755702</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="6"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p content-type="flushleft">Both the plant hormones ethylene and auxin regulate root growth. Recent studies in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> have portrayed an ethylene&#x02013;auxin interaction in regulating root growth, in which the ethylene elevates auxin accumulation and then triggers TIR1/AFB2-mediated signal transduction (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The molecular details that ethylene promotes auxin accumulation have been studied comprehensively, involving ethylene-induced WEI2/ASA-, WEI7/ASB1-, and TAA1-dependent auxin biosynthesis (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) as well as PIN2- and AUX1-facilitated auxin transport (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) in roots. However, the mechanism underlying auxin signaling-mediated ethylene regulation of root growth still requires elucidation.</p><p>Rice is a monocotyledonous and semiaquatic plant, and ethylene plays essential roles in the adaptive growth of rice in water-saturated environments (<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Previously, we have screened for mutants with altered ethylene sensitivity to identify modulators in the regulation of ethylene responses. A set of mutants with an abnormal growth of the roots in the presence of ethylene was identified and named as <italic>mao hu zi</italic> (<italic>mhz</italic>, a Chinese name with an English meaning of cat whiskers) (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Through map-based cloning, several corresponding genes have been identified, including <italic>MHZ7</italic>/<italic>OsEIN2</italic> (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), <italic>MHZ6</italic>/<italic>OsEIL1</italic> (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), <italic>MHZ5</italic> (<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), and <italic>MHZ4</italic>/<italic>OsABA4</italic> (<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). <italic>MHZ7</italic>/<italic>OsEIN2</italic> and <italic>MHZ6</italic>/<italic>OsEIL1</italic> encode proteins homologous to the EIN2 and EIN3 of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ethylene signaling pathway, suggesting that the major components of ethylene signaling are conserved. Moreover, ethylene induces expressions of the carotenoid isomerase gene <italic>MHZ5</italic> and the ABA biosynthesis gene <italic>MHZ4</italic>/<italic>OsABA4</italic> to drive the metabolic flux into the ABA biosynthesis for regulation of rice root growth (<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). These analyses revealed that other plant hormones may modulate ethylene-regulated root growth in rice.</p><p>In this study, we report identification of <italic>MHZ2</italic>/<italic>SOR1</italic> from analysis of a rice root-specific ethylene-insensitive mutant <italic>mhz2</italic>/<italic>sor1-2</italic>. <italic>MHZ2</italic>/<italic>SOR1</italic> encodes an E3 ubiquitin ligase and affects root growth by modulating Aux/indole acetic acid (IAA) protein stability. SOR1 interacts with and ubiquitinates OsIAA26, an atypical Aux/IAA protein, for degradation. OsIAA9, a canonical Aux/IAA protein, connects the SOR1-OsIAA26 signal module to the OsTIR1/AFB2-mediated auxin signaling pathway by interacting with SOR1.</p><sec sec-type="results" id="s1"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2"><title>Identification of Rice <italic>mhz2/sor1</italic> Mutants.</title><p>A set of rice ethylene-response mutants (<italic>mhz</italic>) have been identified in our previous study and the <italic>mhz2</italic> was analyzed in this study. The <italic>mhz2</italic> seedlings showed root-specific defects in ethylene-inhibited root growth at a wide range of hormone concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>). The <italic>mhz2</italic> seedlings also display defects in gravity response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S1<italic>A</italic></ext-link>) and soil-surface rooting phenotypes in the field (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S1<italic>B</italic></ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig01" fig-type="featured" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Characterization of <italic>mhz2</italic>/<italic>sor1</italic> mutant and SOR1 protein. (<italic>A</italic>) Response of wild-type (WT) and <italic>sor1-2</italic> etiolated seedlings to 10 ppm ethylene (ET). (Scale bar, 10 mm.) (<italic>B</italic>) Quantification of the ethylene response of WT and <italic>sor1-2</italic> roots. The root lengths relative to the controls (0 ppm) are shown. Bars indicates SD (<italic>n</italic> &#x02265; 30). (<italic>C</italic>) Diagrams of SOR1 and its truncated version SOR1<sup>T</sup> used for E3 ligase activity studies. Conserved amino acids of RING domain and their positions in full-length protein are shown. (<italic>D</italic>) GST-SOR1<sup>T</sup> protein (&#x0223c;45 kDa) displays E3 ubiquitin ligase activity in vitro. GST itself was used as a negative control. Coomassie Brilliant Blue (CBB) staining served as a loading control. (<italic>E</italic>) C127S mutation disrupts the E3 ligase activity of GST-SOR1<sup>T</sup>. (<italic>F</italic>) Phenotypic analysis of <italic>sor1-2</italic> transformed with <italic>SOR1</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> with or without mutations in the RING domain. <italic>SOR1</italic><sup><italic>SY</italic></sup> harbors C127S and H148Y double mutations. (Scale bar, 10 mm.) (<italic>G</italic>) Quantification of the root ethylene response in WT, mutant, and rescued lines shown in <italic>F</italic>. The data show mean &#x000b1; SD (<italic>n</italic> &#x02265; 30).</p></caption><graphic id="gra1" xlink:href="pnas.1719387115fig01"/></fig><p>We cloned the <italic>MHZ2</italic> gene using a map-based approach (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S2</ext-link>). As <italic>MHZ2</italic> (Os04g01160) is the same as the rice <italic>SOR1</italic> (<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), we renamed the <italic>MHZ2</italic> as <italic>SOR1</italic>. Our mutant <italic>mhz2</italic> was also renamed as <italic>sor1-2</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S2<italic>B</italic></ext-link>) following the original mutant <italic>sor1-1</italic> (<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Three additional mutant alleles were also identified (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S2<italic>B</italic></ext-link>). <italic>SOR1</italic> encodes a plant-specific RING-type protein (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), containing a nuclear localization signal (NLS), a RING domain, and a von Willebrand factor type A (VWA) domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1<italic>C</italic></xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S2<italic>C</italic></ext-link>). SOR1 protein is conserved in other plant species (<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S2<italic>D</italic></ext-link>) and is similar to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> WAV3, which is an E3 ubiquitin ligase and regulates root gravitropism by affecting auxin response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). To further confirm that the <italic>SOR1</italic> mutation was responsible for the ethylene-insensitive phenotype, the full-length genomic DNA fragment of <italic>SOR1</italic> was transformed into the <italic>sor1-2</italic> mutant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S2<italic>E</italic></ext-link>), and the transgene-positive seedlings restored the ethylene-response phenotype and gravity response phenotype (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S2<italic>F</italic></ext-link>). These results indicate that the Os04g01160 locus corresponds to the <italic>SOR1</italic> gene.</p><p>We further examined the genetic relationship between <italic>SOR1</italic> and <italic>MHZ7</italic>/<italic>OsEIN2</italic>, the central component of ethylene signaling in rice (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The <italic>SOR1</italic> mutation suppressed the short root phenotype of the <italic>OsEIN2</italic>-overexpressing seedlings under both normal and ethylene-treated conditions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S3 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></ext-link>), suggesting that the <italic>SOR1</italic> gene acts downstream of <italic>OsEIN2</italic> to regulate root growth.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>SOR1 Functions as an E3 Ubiquitin Ligase in Modulating Ethylene-Inhibited Root Growth.</title><p>Because proteins with a RING domain usually function as E3 ubiquitin ligases (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), we tested whether SOR1 also possesses E3 ligase activity. We expressed a truncated SOR1 version (amino acids 52&#x02013;241) containing the RING domain, which is tagged with GST and referred to as GST-SOR1<sup>T</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1<italic>C</italic></xref>), since expression of the recombinant full-length SOR1 is not successful. In the presence of E1, E2, and ubiquitin, the GST-SOR1<sup>T</sup> had the ability of self-ubiquitination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1<italic>D</italic></xref>). We further introduced mutations at the Cys-127 (C127S) and/or His-148 (H148Y) positions in the RING domain. The C127S mutation in the GST-SOR1<sup>T</sup> version completely disrupted the E3 ligase activity; however, the H148Y mutation does not affect the activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1<italic>E</italic></xref>). These results indicate that the conserved residue Cys-127 is required for SOR1 E3 ligase activity.</p><p>To address whether E3 ligase activity is required for the <italic>SOR1</italic>-mediated root responses to ethylene and gravity, the 35S promoter-driven <italic>SOR1</italic>-coding sequence or its mutant (<italic>SOR1</italic><sup><italic>SY</italic></sup>) harboring the C127S and H148Y double mutations was fused with <italic>green fluorescent protein</italic> (<italic>GFP</italic>) and transformed into the <italic>sor1-2</italic> mutant. <italic>SOR1-GFP</italic> rescued the root sensitivity to both ethylene and gravity; however, <italic>SOR1</italic><sup><italic>SY</italic></sup><italic>-GFP</italic> did not rescue the ethylene-inhibited root growth at 1 ppm but partially rescued at 10 ppm ethylene, and <italic>SOR1</italic><sup><italic>SY</italic></sup><italic>-GFP</italic> largely restored the gravity response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1 <italic>F</italic> and <italic>G</italic></xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S3 <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic></ext-link>). These results indicate that the SOR1 E3 ligase activity is substantially required for the ethylene inhibition of root growth especially at lower ethylene concentration.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>The Ethylene-Insensitivity of <italic>sor1</italic> Is Related to Alteration of Auxin Response.</title><p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, mutations of several proteins required for auxin functions (<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) have been identified to cause defects of ethylene response phenotypes. The defects of the <italic>sor1-2</italic> roots in both ethylene and gravity responses suggest that <italic>SOR1</italic> may mediate ethylene-inhibited root growth through auxin functions. We then tested whether auxin is required for ethylene response in rice roots and found that application of <sc>l</sc>-kynurenine (<sc>l</sc>-Kyn), an inhibitor of auxin biosynthesis (<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), repressed the ethylene-induced inhibition of root growth (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S4 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></ext-link>). Furthermore, the effect of <sc>l</sc>-Kyn on ethylene-regulated root growth could be overcome by supplementation with the auxin analog naphthalene acetic acid (NAA, 20 nM) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S4 <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic></ext-link>). These results indicate that auxin is required for ethylene inhibition of root growth.</p><p>To further examine whether TIR1-mediated nuclear auxin signaling is required for root response to ethylene, the <italic>MiR393a</italic>-overexpressed transgenic plants (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), with the reduction of the auxin receptor gene <italic>OsTIR1</italic>/<italic>AFB2</italic> expression were analyzed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S5<italic>A</italic></ext-link>). We found that these transgenic seedling roots displayed insensitivity to ethylene at a concentration of 1 ppm (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S5 <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic></ext-link>). Furthermore, the application of inhibitors (4-CI-PEO-IAA and auxinole) (<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) blocking the interaction of the receptor and the Aux/IAA protein also reduced the ethylene inhibition of the rice roots (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S6</ext-link>). These results indicate that the auxin pathway is required for ethylene-inhibited root growth in rice, similar to previous findings in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</p><p>We then explored whether the <italic>SOR1</italic> mutation would change the auxin accumulation and/or sensitivity and found that <italic>sor1-2</italic> roots had similar auxin accumulation and similar transporter gene expression in comparison with the wild-type (WT) roots (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S7 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></ext-link>). Moreover, supplementation of exogenous NAA, which is able to override the effect of <sc>l</sc>-Kyn in rice roots (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S4 <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic></ext-link>) and restore the root ethylene sensitivity in mutants defective in auxin production and transport in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), did not restore the root ethylene response and gravity response in the <italic>sor1-2</italic> mutant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S7 <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic></ext-link>). The <italic>sor1-2</italic> roots showed resistance to lower concentrations of NAA in comparison with the wild-type roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>A</italic></xref>), suggesting that <italic>SOR1</italic> mutation may alter auxin response in rice roots.</p><fig id="fig02" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p><italic>SOR1</italic> mutation alters auxin response in rice root. (<italic>A</italic>) Quantification of the auxin response of WT and <italic>sor1-2</italic> roots. The rates of root growth inhibition relative to the controls (0 &#x000b5;M) are shown. Bars indicate SD (<italic>n</italic> &#x02265; 30). (<italic>B</italic>) Ethylene inductions of <italic>OsIAA26</italic>, <italic>OsIAA9</italic>, and <italic>OsIAA20</italic> fully require <italic>SOR1</italic> function. Relative expression of <italic>Aux/IAA</italic> genes in WT and <italic>sor1-2</italic> root tips was evaluated in response to 100 ppm ethylene. (<italic>C</italic>) Auxin inductions of these genes partially require <italic>SOR1</italic> function. NAA (10 &#x000b5;M) was used for treatment. (<italic>D</italic>) Ethylene inductions of <italic>OsIAA26</italic>, <italic>OsIAA9</italic>, and <italic>OsIAA20</italic> require auxin function. The auxin biosynthesis inhibitor <sc>l</sc>-Kyn (10 &#x000b5;M) was used for the treatment. The data show mean &#x000b1; SE. Four independent biological repeats were performed and analyzed. All of the mRNA levels were normalized to <italic>OsACTIN2</italic>. (<italic>E</italic>&#x02013;<italic>G</italic>) Venn diagram shows overlaps between genes induced by NAA or by ethylene (ET) treatment and the genes related by SOR1 or OsEIN2 in rice root tips. The genes regulated more than twofold were used for analysis. ET EIGs, ET ethylene-induced genes; NAA NIGs, NAA-induced genes; SOR1 Reg EIGs, SOR1-regulated ethylene-induced genes; SOR1 Reg NIGs, SOR1-regulated NAA-induced genes; and OsEIN2 Reg EIGs, OsEIN2-regulated ethylene-induced genes.</p></caption><graphic id="gra2" xlink:href="pnas.1719387115fig02"/></fig><p>From our microarray and transcriptome data of the root tips treated with ethylene (National Center for Biotechnology Information: GSE51152 and SRP041468), three <italic>Aux</italic>/<italic>IAA</italic> genes, <italic>OsIAA26</italic>, <italic>OsIAA9</italic>, and <italic>OsIAA20</italic>, relevant to the auxin response were identified as ethylene-responsive genes, and the ethylene-induced expression of these genes fully depended on <italic>SOR1</italic> functions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>B</italic></xref>). However, only around half of auxin-induced expression of these three genes depended on the <italic>SOR1</italic> function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>C</italic></xref>). These results imply that SOR1 is fully required for the ethylene response but only partially required for the auxin response at the molecular level in roots. Moreover, inhibition of auxin synthesis by <sc>l</sc>-Kyn application or repression of auxin signaling by knockdown of auxin receptor genes <italic>OsTIR1</italic>/<italic>AFB2</italic> also blocked ethylene-induced expression of <italic>OsIAA26</italic>, <italic>OsIAA9</italic>, and <italic>OsIAA20</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>D</italic></xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S5<italic>D</italic></ext-link>). Collectively, these results suggest that SOR1 may modulate root responses to ethylene through affecting a portion of the auxin response.</p><p>Transcriptome analysis (BIG Data Center: CRA000688) was further performed to dissect SOR1-modulated gene expression in root tips. We found that SOR1 controlled &#x0223c;77% of the OsEIN2-mediated ethylene-induced genes. It also mediated &#x0223c;70% of auxin-induced genes, among which &#x0223c;56% were ethylene-induced genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2 <italic>E</italic>&#x02013;<italic>G</italic></xref>). These analyses imply that SOR1 affects ethylene response genes, among which a subset belongs to auxin response genes.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>SOR1 Interacts with and Ubiquitinates OsIAA26.</title><p>Since mutation of <italic>SOR1</italic> leads to deficiency of auxin-dependent ethylene response in roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2 <italic>A</italic>&#x02013;<italic>D</italic></xref>), and the reduced root responses of the <italic>MiR393aOE</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S5<italic>B</italic></ext-link>) and <italic>sor1-2</italic>/<italic>SOR1</italic><sup><italic>SY</italic></sup><italic>-GFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1<italic>F</italic></xref>) seedlings to 1 ppm ethylene were very similar, we hypothesized that SOR1 may be involved in the OsTIR1/AFB2-mediated auxin signaling pathway. There are 31 members in the rice Aux/IAA family, and most of these have four conserved domains, i.e., domains I&#x02013;IV. However, a few of these do not have conserved domain II (<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Among SOR1-dependent ethylene-induced <italic>Aux</italic>/<italic>IAA</italic> genes, the <italic>OsIAA9</italic> and <italic>OsIAA20</italic> encode Aux/IAA proteins with conserved domains, whereas the <italic>OsIAA26</italic> encodes an atypical Aux/IAA protein with substitutions in domain II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>A</italic></xref>). OsIAA26 has canonical domain I contributing to transcriptional regulation and shows transcriptional repression activity (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S8</ext-link>). In the presence or absence of IAA, SOR1 could interact with both OsIAA26 and OsIAA9, but not OsIAA20, in a yeast two-hybrid assay. In contrast, in the presence of IAA, the auxin receptor OsTIR1 interacted with OsIAA20, and the auxin receptor OsAFB2 interacted with both OsIAA9 and OsIAA20 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>A</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>SOR1 interacts with and ubiquitinates OsIAA26 protein. (<italic>A</italic>) SOR1 interacts with OsIAA26 and OsIAA9 in a yeast two-hybrid assay. Yeast transformants were grown on the DDO media [synthetic defined (SD) &#x02013;Trp &#x02212;Leu] and on the DQO/X/A media (SD &#x02212;Trp &#x02212;Leu &#x02212;His &#x02212;Ade plus X-&#x003b1;-gal and aureobasidin A) with or without 100 &#x000b5;M IAA. Greenish blue indicates positive interactions. OsIAA9 and OsIAA20 are canonical Aux/IAA proteins with a conserved domain II. OsIAA26 is a noncanonical Aux/IAA protein. Interactions of the three Aux/IAA proteins with auxin receptors OsTIR1 and OsAFB2 were also tested. (<italic>B</italic>) The truncated SOR1 version containing the RING domain (GST-SOR1<sup>T</sup>) ubiquitinates OsIAA26, but not OsIAA9. Asterisks indicate ubiquitinated MBP-OsIAA26 proteins. (<italic>C</italic>) Ubiquitination of OsIAA26 depends on the intact RING finger of SOR1. (<italic>D</italic>) SOR1 associates with OsIAA26 in a pull-down assay. The assay was performed using MBP-OsIAA26 recombinant protein and extracts were prepared from tobacco leaves expressing Myc-SOR1 protein. (<italic>E</italic>) SOR1<sup>C127S</sup>, but not SOR1, can be detected to interact with OsIAA26 in the BiFC assay. Yellow fluorescence indicates positive interactions. (Scale bar, 50 &#x000b5;m.)</p></caption><graphic id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.1719387115fig03"/></fig><p>We further investigated whether SOR1 can ubiquitinate OsIAA26 and OsIAA9. We performed in vitro ubiquitination experiments using the GST-SOR1<sup>T</sup> and the OsIAA26 and OsIAA9 proteins tagged with maltose-binding protein (MBP). While MBP-OsIAA9 was not ubiquitinated, MBP-OsIAA26 can be ubiquitinated by SOR1<sup>T</sup>, and the C127S mutation in the RING domain of SOR1<sup>T</sup> disrupted OsIAA26 ubiquitination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3 <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic></xref>).</p><p>The association of SOR1 with OsIAA26 is further supported by a pull-down assay. Full-length SOR1 proteins expressed in tobacco leaves can be pulled down by incubation with MBP-OsIAA26 proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>D</italic></xref>). Furthermore, we employed bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) assays in tobacco leaf cells to check the interaction between SOR1 and OsIAA26. The yellow fluorescence that represents a positive interaction can be detected in the combination of OsIAA26 and SOR1<sup>C127S</sup>, a version without E3 ligase activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>E</italic></xref>). However, the combination between normal SOR1 and OsIAA26 did not generate a positive interaction signal, probably due to rapid degradation of the ubiquitinated proteins.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>SOR1 Targets OsIAA26 for Degradation.</title><p>To reveal whether OsIAA26 can be targeted directly for degradation by SOR1, the OsIAA26-GFP and SOR1 were coexpressed in tobacco leaves to perform in vitro degradation assays. Results showed that SOR1 promoted degradation of the OsIAA26-GFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4<italic>A</italic></xref>). Moreover, the atypical Aux/IAA protein OsIAA26 can be destabilized by auxin with different incubation times or with different concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4 <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic></xref>), supporting that Aux/IAA proteins with substitutions in domain II could also be degraded slowly by auxin treatment (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). These results indicate that SOR1 facilitates OsIAA26 degradation and auxin may play a positive role in this process.</p><fig id="fig04" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>OsIAA26 is a substrate of SOR1. (<italic>A</italic>) OsIAA26-GFP protein levels in the absence or presence of SOR1. Crude plant protein extracts from tobacco leaves coexpressing SOR1 and OsIAA26-GFP or GFP were incubated at 30 &#x000b0;C for degradation assays. Coomassie Brilliant Blue (CBB) staining served as a loading control. Three independent biological repeats were performed and analyzed, and the relative protein levels were measured using ImageJ software. (<italic>B</italic>) OsIAA26-GFP protein levels in response to IAA at different time points. Ethanol solvent (EtOH) was used as a control. (<italic>C</italic>) OsIAA26-GFP protein levels in response to different concentrations of IAA. Crude plant protein extracts from tobacco leaves expressing OsIAA26-GFP were incubated with IAA for 4 h. (<italic>D</italic>) Stability of MBP-OsIAA26 in protein extracts from various indicated rice seedling roots. <italic>E. coli-</italic>expressed MBP-OsIAA26 proteins were incubated with different plant protein extracts prepared from indicated materials. MBP itself was used as a control. (<italic>E</italic>) Analysis of MBP-OsIAA26 ubiquitination in protein extracts prepared from WT and <italic>sor1-2</italic> with or without MG132 (100 &#x000b5;M) treatment. DMSO was used as a control. MBP-OsIAA26-Ubn indicates ubiquitinated MBP-OsIAA26.</p></caption><graphic id="gra4" xlink:href="pnas.1719387115fig04"/></fig><p>We further employed a cell-free degradation assay system (<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) to explore whether SOR1 regulates OsIAA26 degradation in rice. In these assays, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>-expressed MBP-OsIAA26 proteins were incubated with protein extracts from various rice materials for different times and the remaining MBP-OsIAA26 levels were examined. We found that the loss of SOR1 in the <italic>sor1-2</italic> mutant or the disruption of the SOR1 E3 ligase activity in the <italic>sor1-2/SOR1</italic><sup><italic>SY</italic></sup><italic>-GFP</italic> transgenic plants prevented the degradation of the MBP-OsIAA26 protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4<italic>D</italic></xref>). The reduction of auxin receptors in the <italic>MiR393OE</italic> transgenic plants also slightly prevented MBP-OsIAA26 degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4<italic>D</italic></xref>). We further used the MG132 to inhibit the 26S proteasome-mediated protein degradation and checked the MBP-OsIAA26 ubiquitination status. We found that, in the presence of MG132, the MBP-OsIAA26 is polyubiquitinated in the WT protein extracts but not ubiquitinated in the <italic>sor1-2</italic> extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4<italic>E</italic></xref>). These results indicate that SOR1 is responsible for the MBP-OsIAA26 ubiquitination and facilitates its degradation by the 26S proteasome pathway, and auxin receptors OsTIR1/AFB2 also play some roles in the OsIAA26 degradation process.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>OsIAA9 Interacts with SOR1 and Inhibits Its E3 Ligase Activity.</title><p>From the above experiments, we found that SOR1 could interact with both OsIAA26 and OsIAA9 in the yeast two-hybrid assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>A</italic></xref>); however, the SOR1 could not ubiquitinate OsIAA9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>B</italic></xref>). We further studied the interaction of SOR1 and OsIAA9 by BiFC assay, and found that they could also associate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5<italic>A</italic></xref>). However, unlike the case for SOR1 and OsIAA26, the interaction signal between SOR1 and OsIAA9 was not altered when SOR1 had the E3 ubiquitin ligase activity. Using the pull-down assays, we further found that OsIAA9, different from OsIAA26, interacted with truncated SOR1 version SOR1<sup>T</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5<italic>B</italic></xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S9</ext-link>), and this interaction required an intact RING finger (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S9</ext-link>). These results indicated that OsIAA9 associates with SOR1 at the RING domain, possibly affecting the E3 ubiquitin ligase activity of SOR1.</p><fig id="fig05" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>OsIAA9 protects OsIAA26 from SOR1-mediated degradation. (<italic>A</italic>) SOR1 interacts with OsIAA9 in a BiFC assay. Yellow fluorescence indicates positive interactions. (Scale bar, 50 &#x000b5;m.) (<italic>B</italic>) The truncated SOR1 version containing the RING domain (GST-SOR1<sup>T</sup>) interacts with MBP-OsIAA9 in a pull-down assay. (<italic>C</italic>) OsIAA9 inhibits the E3 ligase activity of GST-SOR1<sup>T</sup> in vitro. MBP was used as a control. (<italic>D</italic>) OsIAA9 reduces SOR1-mediated degradation of OsIAA26. Assays were performed using crude plant protein extracts from tobacco leaves coexpressing SOR1 and OsIAA26-GFP, with or without OsIAA9. Coomassie Brilliant Blue (CBB) staining served as a loading control. Three independent biological repeats were performed and analyzed, and the relative protein levels were measured using ImageJ software. (<italic>E</italic>) Degradation of OsIAA26 in the presence of both SOR1 and OsIAA9 in response to auxin. Assays were performed using protein extracts from tobacco leaves coexpressing SOR1, OsIAA26-GFP, and OsIAA9. Ethanol solvent (EtOH) was used as a control. (<italic>F</italic>&#x02013;<italic>G</italic>) Real-time qPCR analysis for expression of <italic>OsIAA20</italic> and <italic>OsIAA9</italic> in their corresponding overexpressed transgenic lines. The mRNA levels were normalized to <italic>OsACTIN2</italic>. (<italic>H</italic>) Stability of GST-OsIAA26 in protein extracts from indicated transgenic rice seedling roots. <italic>E. coli-</italic>expressed GST-OsIAA26 proteins were incubated with plant protein extracts prepared from indicated materials. GST itself was used as a control.</p></caption><graphic id="gra5" xlink:href="pnas.1719387115fig05"/></fig><p>To test whether OsIAA9 would affect SOR1 E3 ligase activity, we performed in vitro ubiquitination assays, and found that the OsIAA9 can inhibit the E3 ubiquitin ligase activity of SOR1 and thus prevent SOR1-mediated OsIAA26 ubiquitination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5<italic>C</italic></xref>). We further tested the OsIAA9 effect on SOR1-mediated OsIAA26 degradation in in vitro degradation assays using tobacco leaves transiently coexpressing SOR1, OsIAA26, and OsIAA9, and found that OsIAA9 reduced the SOR1-mediated degradation of OsIAA26 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5<italic>D</italic></xref>). When the auxin IAA was included in the assay, the OsIAA9-dependent stabilization of OsIAA26-GFP was affected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5<italic>E</italic></xref>). Moreover, we found that OsIAA26 protein was more stable in <italic>OsIAA9</italic>-overexpressed rice than in WT or <italic>OsIAA20</italic>-overexpressed rice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5 <italic>F</italic>&#x02013;<italic>H</italic></xref>). These results indicate that the OsIAA9 can protect OsIAA26 from SOR1-mediated degradation by inhibiting the E3 ligase activity of SOR1.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>OsIAA9 Degradation Is Mediated by OsTIR1/AFB2 and Facilitated by SOR1.</title><p>Because OsIAA9 is a canonical Aux/IAA protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>A</italic></xref>), and OsIAA9 regulates OsIAA26 stability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5 <italic>D</italic>, <italic>E</italic>, and <italic>H</italic></xref>), we propose that auxin may regulate the SOR1-dependent degradation of OsIAA26 through possible recruitment of the OsIAA9 protein from SOR1 to OsTIR1/AFB2 for ubiquitination and degradation. Pull-down assays were performed and the results showed that the interaction between OsIAA9 and auxin receptor OsAFB2 is enhanced in the presence of NAA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6<italic>A</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="fig06" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Regulation of OsIAA9 stability and a working model for SOR1. (<italic>A</italic>) OsIAA9 interacts with OsAFB2 in the presence of auxin. Crude protein extracts prepared from tobacco leaves expressing OsAFB2 were used to do MBP pull-down assays. (<italic>B</italic>) Stability of MBP-OsIAA9 in protein extracts from various rice materials. <italic>E. coli-</italic>expressed MBP-OsIAA9 proteins were incubated with different plant protein extracts prepared from indicated materials. MBP itself was used as a control. (<italic>C</italic>) A working model for SOR1 functions in auxin-mediated ethylene response. In the absence of ethylene and auxin (<italic>Left</italic>), OsIAA9 inhibits the E3 ligase activity of SOR1 and thus stabilizes OsIAA26, facilitating normal root elongation. In the presence of ethylene and auxin (<italic>Right</italic>), ethylene-triggered IAA accumulation enhanced OsAFB2-mediated degradation of OsIAA9, with the help of SOR1. OsIAA9 removal released the E3 ligase activity of SOR1 and then promoted SOR1-mediated degradation of OsIAA26. The normal root elongation is thus repressed.</p></caption><graphic id="gra6" xlink:href="pnas.1719387115fig06"/></fig><p>We also examined the stability of OsIAA9 when incubated with protein extracts from various rice materials. The MBP-OsIAA9 can be degraded in the WT protein extracts. However, when the auxin receptor gene <italic>OsTIR1/AFB2</italic> expression was reduced in the <italic>MiR393aOE</italic> extracts, the MBP-OsIAA9 protein showed increased stability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6<italic>B</italic></xref>). Similarly, the MBP-OsIAA9 in the <italic>sor1-2</italic> extracts also showed increased longevity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6<italic>B</italic></xref>). In the <italic>sor1-2/SOR1-GFP</italic> plant extracts, the MBP-OsIAA9 degradation was recovered. It is interesting to note that when the SOR1 E3 ligase activity was disrupted in the <italic>sor1-2/SOR1</italic><sup><italic>SY</italic></sup><italic>-GFP</italic>, the MBP-OsIAA9 degradation remained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6<italic>B</italic></xref>). Together, these results indicate that degradation of OsIAA9 protein is mediated by auxin receptor OsTIR1/AFB2 in rice, and OsIAA9 degradation is also facilitated by the presence of SOR1; however, the E3 ligase activity of SOR1 is not required for OsIAA9 degradation.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Alteration of <italic>OsIAA9</italic> and <italic>OsIAA26</italic> Expression Affects Ethylene-Regulated Root Growth.</title><p>Because OsIAA26 is ubiquitinated by SOR1 for degradation and OsIAA9 affects this process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Figs. 3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5</xref>), we further tested whether OsIAA26 and OsIAA9 have any roles in ethylene inhibition of root growth. The <italic>OsIAA26</italic>- and <italic>OsIAA9</italic>-overexpressed transgenic plants were generated and three higher expressers for each transgene were analyzed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S10 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></ext-link>). Both the <italic>OsIAA26</italic>- and <italic>OsIAA9</italic>-overexpressed seedlings showed reduced ethylene sensitivity in roots than the wild-type seedlings did (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S10 <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic></ext-link>). Furthermore, mutations of <italic>OsIAA9</italic> and <italic>OsIAA26</italic> were generated by genome editing using the CRISPR/Cas9 system to further study their roles in root ethylene response (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S11<italic>A</italic></ext-link>). Both <italic>Osiaa9</italic> and <italic>Osiaa26</italic> mutants showed similar ethylene response to WT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S11 <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic></ext-link>). However, mutation of the OsIAA26 protein caused root wave growth in the presence of 10 ppm ethylene (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S11<italic>D</italic></ext-link>). These results suggest that both OsIAA26 and OsIAA9 may function in the reduction of ethylene effects on root growth, and other Aux/IAA proteins may also be involved in ethylene-regulated root growth.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s10"><title>Discussion</title><p content-type="flushleft">E3 ubiquitin ligase-mediated protein degradation plays a central role in ethylene and auxin signaling. The stability of ethylene signaling protein EIN2 is modulated by the two F-box proteins ETP1/2 (<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), while the EIN3 is regulated by another two F-box proteins EBF1/2 (<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref><xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). The auxin receptor is a small family of related F-box proteins (<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), which triggers nuclear auxin signaling by targeting transcriptional repressor Aux/IAA proteins for degradation (<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Here we find that SOR1, a RING finger E3 ubiquitin ligase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1 <italic>C</italic>&#x02013;<italic>E</italic></xref>), ubiquitinates a noncanonical Aux/IAA protein OsIAA26 for degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Figs. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4</xref>), and the OsTIR1/AFB2-auxin-OsIAA9 signaling affects this process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Figs. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>). Our study identifies a potentially unique component of auxin signaling to regulate ethylene-inhibited root growth.</p><p>Noncanonical Aux/IAA proteins can regulate auxin-related phenotypes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>); however, their protein stability cannot be directly modulated by SCF<sup>TIR1</sup> E3 ubiquitin ligase (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In the present study, we discovered that SOR1 ubiquitinates a noncanonical Aux/IAA protein OsIAA26, for degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Figs. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4</xref>). In the in vitro assay, the OsIAA26 appeared to be monoubiquitinated by the truncated SOR1 version SOR1<sup>T</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3 <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic></xref>). However, in the rice protein extracts, the OsIAA26 can be polyubiquitinated by full-length SOR1 as judged from the protein size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4<italic>E</italic></xref>). This difference may be due to the different assay systems used or different SOR1 versions involved. Interaction assays showed that OsIAA26 interacts with full-length SOR1 but not with the truncated SOR1<sup>T</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>D</italic></xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S9</ext-link>); however, the SOR1<sup>T</sup> still ubiquitinates OsIAA26. This fact may suggest that the extra sequences outside the RING finger likely facilitate the ubiquitination process. Other possibilities could not be excluded.</p><p>Moreover, auxin also regulates the OsIAA26 protein degradation likely by OsTIR1/AFB2 receptors through SOR1, because in the <italic>MiR393aOE</italic> plants with reduced <italic>OsTIR1</italic>/<italic>AFB2</italic> expression, the OsIAA26 can be partially stabilized (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4<italic>D</italic></xref>). This fact may be explained by the stabilization of OsIAA9 in <italic>MiR393aOE</italic> plants, which leads to SOR1 inactivation and OsIAA26 stabilization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Figs. 5 <italic>C</italic>, <italic>D</italic>, and <italic>H</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>). It is worth noting that among six noncanonical Aux/IAA proteins in rice, we only studied the OsIAA26, whose gene expression is induced by ethylene and the induction fully depends on SOR1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>B</italic></xref>). Other noncanonical and/or canonical Aux/IAA proteins should be examined to test whether they are also the substrates of SOR1. It is also interesting to study whether SOR1 modulates other components of ethylene/auxin signaling pathways.</p><p>Aux/IAA family proteins usually function as transcriptional repressors (<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) and bind to ARF transcription factors to repress their transcriptional activity (<xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Previous study has shown that HaIAA27 (<xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), one of the Aux/IAA proteins in sunflower, can interact with HaHSFA9, a non&#x02013;ARF-type transcription factor, and represses its transcriptional activity. In this study, we show that OsIAA9, a canonical Aux/IAA protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Figs. 3<italic>A</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>), can function as a repressor for inhibition of the E3 ligase activity of SOR1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5<italic>C</italic></xref>). Considering that SOR1 can interact with both OsIAA26 and OsIAA9 but only ubiquitinate the former, the OsIAA9 may play some inhibitory roles in the SOR1 E3 ubiquitin ligase activity toward its substrate OsIAA26. This conclusion is further supported by the fact that OsIAA9 protects OsIAA26 from degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5 <italic>D</italic> and <italic>H</italic></xref>). This finding widens our understanding of the specific roles of each Aux/IAA protein. The mechanism involving the interplay of the three proteins is still not clear and requires further investigation.</p><p>It should be noted that although SOR1 cannot ubiquitinate OsIAA9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>B</italic></xref>), it assists OsIAA9 degradation, and this assistance does not require E3 ubiquitin ligase activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6<italic>B</italic></xref>). Considering that OsIAA9 can also interact with OsAFB2 in the presence of auxin and be targeted by these receptors for degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Figs. 3<italic>A</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>), SOR1 may act as a facilitator for OsIAA9 degradation in this process. The VWA domain of SOR1 may function to recognize and promote ubiquitinated OsIAA9 for 26S proteasome-mediated degradation. This speculation may be supported by a previous study. Verma et al. (<xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) reported that, during delivery of ubiquitinated substrates to the 26S proteasome, deubiquitination and degradation of substrates delivered by Rad23 require a facilitator activity within the VWA domain of Rpn10. Further studies should clarify the possible functions of the SOR1 VWA domain in the process of Aux/IAA degradation.</p><p>While our study finds that ethylene affects root growth through SOR1-mediated auxin signaling, ethylene may also inhibit the second rate-limiting step at the <italic>YUCCA</italic> gene of auxin biosynthesis to confer auxin levels suboptimal for root cell elongation as in the cases of <italic>Brachypodium</italic> (<xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) and rice (<xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), providing an alternative mechanism of ethylene&#x02013;auxin interaction.</p><p>From our current studies, we propose a model in which SOR1 acts as an E3 ligase in regulating the rice root response to ethylene by modulating Aux/IAA protein stability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6<italic>C</italic></xref>). In the absence of ethylene, the canonical Aux/IAA protein OsIAA9 associates with SOR1 and blocks the SOR1-mediated ubiquitin-related degradation of OsIAA26. In the presence of ethylene, ethylene-triggered auxin accumulation facilitates the interaction of the auxin receptors OsTIR1/AFB2 with OsIAA9, leading to OsIAA9 degradation. A decrease of the OsIAA9 protein releases the E3 ligase activity of SOR1, thereby targeting OsIAA26 for degradation via the ubiquitin/26S proteasome pathway.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s11"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p content-type="flushleft">Details of the experimental programs for ethylene response assay, quantitative real-time PCR analysis, recombinant protein purification, yeast two-hybrid assay, pull-down assay, BiFC assay, in vitro ubiquitination assay, and cell-free degradation assay are provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>SI Materials and Methods</italic></ext-link>. The primers used in this study are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Tables S1 and S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><label>Supplementary File</label><media xlink:href="pnas.1719387115.sapp.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank M. Y. Zhu (Zhejiang University) and M. Y. Zhang [South China Botanical Garden, Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS)] for providing the seeds of <italic>MiR393OE</italic>; K. Hayashi (Okayama University of Science) for providing the chemicals PEO-IAA, 4-CI-PEO-IAA, and auxinole; and J. F. Chu (Center for Plant Hormone Determination, Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, CAS) for IAA measurement. This work is supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant 31530004), the 973 Project (Grant 2015CB755702), and the State Key Laboratory of Plant Genomics.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>This article is a PNAS Direct Submission.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Data deposition: The data reported in this paper have been deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo" xlink:show="new">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo</ext-link> (accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="NCBI:geo" xlink:href="GSE51152" xlink:show="new">GSE51152</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="NCBI:geo" xlink:href="SRP041468" xlink:show="new">SRP041468</ext-link>) and BIG Data Center: CRA000688.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>This article contains supporting information online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719387115/-/DCSupplemental</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swarup</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Ethylene upregulates auxin biosynthesis in Arabidopsis seedlings to enhance inhibition of root cell elongation</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>2186</fpage><lpage>2196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Likhacheva</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Multilevel interactions between ethylene and auxin in Arabidopsis roots</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>2169</fpage><lpage>2185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#x0016f;zicka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Ethylene regulates root growth through effects on auxin biosynthesis and transport-dependent auxin distribution</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>2197</fpage><lpage>2212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Five components of the ethylene-response pathway identified in a screen for weak ethylene-insensitive mutants in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>2992</fpage><lpage>2997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12606727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyt</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>A link between ethylene and auxin uncovered by the characterization of two root-specific ethylene-insensitive mutants in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>2230</fpage><lpage>2242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>TAA1-mediated auxin biosynthesis is essential for hormone crosstalk and plant development</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>133</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18394997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luschnig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaxiola</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grisafi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>EIR1, a root-specific protein involved in auxin transport, is required for gravitropism in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>2175</fpage><lpage>2187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9679062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>AUX1 regulates root gravitropism in Arabidopsis by facilitating auxin uptake within root apical tissues</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>2066</fpage><lpage>2073</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10205161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Sub1A is an ethylene-response-factor-like gene that confers submergence tolerance to rice</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>442</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16900200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The ethylene response factors SNORKEL1 and SNORKEL2 allow rice to adapt to deep water</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>460</volume><fpage>1026</fpage><lpage>1030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19693083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Ethylene signaling in rice</article-title><source>Chin Sci Bull</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>2204</fpage><lpage>2210</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Identification of rice ethylene-response mutants and characterization of MHZ7/OsEIN2 in distinct ethylene response and yield trait regulation</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1830</fpage><lpage>1848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23718947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>MAOHUZI6/ETHYLENE INSENSITIVE3-LIKE1 and ETHYLENE INSENSITIVE3-LIKE2 regulate ethylene response of roots and coleoptiles and negatively affect salt tolerance in rice</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>169</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25995326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Ethylene responses in rice roots and coleoptiles are differentially regulated by a carotenoid isomerase-mediated abscisic acid pathway</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>1081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25841037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Ethylene-induced inhibition of root growth requires abscisic acid function in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) seedlings</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>e1004701</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25330236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Isolation of a novel mutant gene for soil-surface rooting in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Rice (N Y)</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24280269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Functional analysis of the RING-type ubiquitin ligase family of Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><volume>137</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15644464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>The wavy growth 3 E3 ligase family controls the gravitropic response in Arabidopsis roots</article-title><source>Plant J</source><volume>70</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22122664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorick</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>RING fingers mediate ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme (E2)-dependent ubiquitination</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>11364</fpage><lpage>11369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10500182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>SINAT5 promotes ubiquitin-related degradation of NAC1 to attenuate auxin signals</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>419</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12226665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubarsky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieber</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Genetic analysis of ethylene signal transduction in Arabidopsis thaliana: Five novel mutant loci integrated into a stress response pathway</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>139</volume><fpage>1393</fpage><lpage>1409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7768447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>A small-molecule screen identifies L-kynurenine as a competitive inhibitor of TAA1/TAR activity in ethylene-directed auxin biosynthesis and root growth in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>3944</fpage><lpage>3960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22108404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Distinctive expression patterns and roles of the miRNA393/TIR1 homolog module in regulating flag leaf inclination and primary and crown root growth in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>)</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><volume>196</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22846038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>OsTIR1 and OsAFB2 downregulation via OsmiR393 overexpression leads to more tillers, early flowering and less tolerance to salt and drought in rice</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>e30039</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22253868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Rational design of an auxin antagonist of the SCF(TIR1) auxin receptor complex</article-title><source>ACS Chem Biol</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22234040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsurumi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Auxin is a positive regulator for ethylene-mediated response in the growth of Arabidopsis roots</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11266581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Structure and expression analysis of early auxin-responsive Aux/IAA gene family in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>)</article-title><source>Funct Integr Genomics</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16200395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calder&#x000f3;n Villalobos</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>A combinatorial TIR1/AFB-Aux/IAA co-receptor system for differential sensing of auxin</article-title><source>Nat Chem Biol</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22466420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreher</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The Arabidopsis Aux/IAA protein family has diversified in degradation and auxin responsiveness</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16489122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osterlund</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Targeted destabilization of HY5 during light-regulated development of Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>405</volume><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10839542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Control of plant germline proliferation by SCF(FBL17) degradation of cell cycle inhibitors</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>455</volume><fpage>1134</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18948957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Biochemical insights on degradation of Arabidopsis DELLA proteins gained from a cell-free assay system</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>2378</fpage><lpage>2390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19717618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Interplay between ethylene, ETP1/ETP2 F-box proteins, and degradation of EIN2 triggers ethylene responses in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19196655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Plant responses to ethylene gas are mediated by SCF(EBF1/EBF2)-dependent proteolysis of EIN3 transcription factor</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14675532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Potuschak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>EIN3-dependent regulation of plant ethylene hormone signaling by two arabidopsis F box proteins: EBF1 and EBF2</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14675533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagne</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Arabidopsis EIN3-binding F-box 1 and 2 form ubiquitin-protein ligases that repress ethylene action and promote growth by directing EIN3 degradation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>6803</fpage><lpage>6808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15090654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dharmasiri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Plant development is regulated by a family of auxin receptor F box proteins</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15992545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kepinski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouse</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Auxin regulates SCF(TIR1)-dependent degradation of AUX/IAA proteins</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>414</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11713520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Overexpression of the non-canonical Aux/IAA genes causes auxin-related aberrant phenotypes in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><volume>133</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18298415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu-Mitao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kakimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Auxin sensitivities of all Arabidopsis Aux/IAAs for degradation in the presence of every TIR1/AFB</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>1450</fpage><lpage>1459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24880779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guilfoyle</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>AUX/IAA proteins are active repressors, and their stability and activity are modulated by auxin</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>2809</fpage><lpage>2822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guilfoyle</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Aux/IAA proteins contain a potent transcriptional repression domain</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14742873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salehin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>SCFTIR1/AFB-based auxin perception: Mechanism and role in plant growth and development</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25604443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carranco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Espinosa</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto-Dapena</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almoguera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Repression by an auxin/indole acetic acid protein connects auxin signaling with heat shock factor-mediated seed longevity</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>21908</fpage><lpage>21913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21115822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oania</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deshaies</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Multiubiquitin chain receptors define a layer of substrate selectivity in the ubiquitin-proteasome system</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15242647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacheco-Villalobos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sankar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Disturbed local auxin homeostasis enhances cellular anisotropy and reveals alternative wiring of auxin-ethylene crosstalk in Brachypodium distachyon seminal roots</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>e1003564</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23840182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Endogenous auxin is required but supraoptimal for rapid growth of rice (Oryza sativa L.) seminal roots, and auxin inhibition of rice seminal root growth is not caused by ethylene</article-title><source>J Plant Growth Regul</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>