<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art550.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.5.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_AGEE6019 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Agric Ecosyst Environ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Agric Ecosyst Environ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Agriculture, Ecosystems &#x00026; Environment</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0167-8809</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5946712</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0167-8809(17)30429-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2017.09.029</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sustainable intensification through rotations with grain legumes in Sub-Saharan Africa: A review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><email>FrankeAC@ufs.ac.za</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van den Brand</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Soil, Crop and Climate Sciences, University of the Free State, PO Box 339, Bloemfontein 9300, South Africa</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Plant Production Systems, Wageningen University, PO Box 430, 6700 AK Wageningen, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA), c/o ICIPE, PO Box 30772, 00100 Nairobi, Kenya</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>FrankeAC@ufs.ac.za</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>01</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="ppub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>261</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2017 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0005"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="lis0005"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0005">We retrieved 44 publications and 199 observations comparing continuous cereal with grain legume-cereal rotation in SSA.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0010">Cereal after legume yielded on average 0.49&#x000a0;t grain ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or 41% more than continuous cereal.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0015">Sustained residual benefits of legumes with large N applications indicate the importance of non-N effects.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0020">Relevant non-N effects include improved P availability, changes in SOM, and in pest, disease and striga pressure.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="abs0010"><p>We conducted a systematic review of literature on the residual effects of grain legumes in cereal-based systems of sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) to quantify the magnitude and variability of rotational effects, to explore the importance of environmental and management factors in determining variability and to evaluate the evidence of the different mechanisms that explain rotational effects. We retrieved 44 unique publications providing 199 observations comparing continuous cereal performance with that of a grain legume-cereal rotation. The overall mean yield increase of 0.49&#x000a0;t grain&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, equal to an increase of 41% of the continuous cereal yield, is highly significant, but the variability in residual effects is large. Effects were more pronounced in southern Africa, the highlands of East Africa and the Guinea savannah, and less in the humid forest/derived savannah of West Africa and the Sudano-Sahelian zone. Maize showed stronger yield responses after a legume than millet and sorghum. Agro-ecological zone and cereal type were however confounded. All grain legume types significantly improved cereal yields, with stronger residual effects observed after soybean and groundnut than after cowpea. Fertiliser N application to cereals reduces the residual effects of legumes, but the response at 60&#x02013;120&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> still equalled 0.32&#x000a0;t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or 59% of the response when no N is applied. The sustained benefits with large N applications indicate the importance of non-N effects. While mechanisms for improved soil P availability after grain legumes have been studied in some detail, it remains uncertain how important these are in farmers&#x02019; fields. Grain legumes are unlikely to have a major influence on the availability of nutrients other than N and P, or on soil pH. Beneficial impacts of grain legumes on soil organic matter content can occur if legumes contribute to a greater overall cropping productivity, but studies generally report no such impacts. Evidence of impacts of grain legumes on weeds is limited to striga. Studies on the impacts on nematode pressure in cereals are inconclusive, probably because legumes act as a host for some of the key nematode genera that harm maize. The impact on the pressure of other pests and diseases in cereals is probably important, but evidence on this from SSA is lacking. Future research on N<sub>2</sub>-fixation by grain legumes and residual N benefits should focus on explaining the wide variability observed among sites. There is a clear need for more detailed mechanistic studies to assess the occurrence and relevance of non-N effects of grain legumes, particularly in relation to common pests and diseases in cereals.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwd0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Cereals</kwd><kwd>Nitrogen fixation</kwd><kwd>Phosphorus</kwd><kwd>Biotic factors</kwd><kwd>Residual benefits</kwd><kwd>Smallholder farmers</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="par0025">Diversification and intensification through inclusion of grain legumes in cereal, root or tuber based cropping systems represents a key technology in the drive towards the sustainable intensification of agriculture in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) (<xref rid="bib0685" ref-type="bibr">Vanlauwe et al., 2014</xref>). Grain legumes fix atmospheric nitrogen gas (N<sub>2</sub>) that can contribute to the nitrogen (N) economy of fields, provide other rotational benefits to subsequent crops, produce <italic>in situ</italic> high-quality organic residues with a high N concentration and a low C to N ratio, and thereby contribute to integrated soil fertility management (ISFM) (<xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">Giller, 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0680" ref-type="bibr">Vanlauwe et al., 2010</xref>). Their protein-rich food and feed products have a good market demand in SSA where marketing channels are available (<xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">Chianu et al., 2011</xref>). The wide range of grain legume crops and varieties with different growth durations and other characteristics suggest that legumes have a potential niche in a wide range of farming systems in SSA. Legume production may be enhanced by replacing cereals or other non-legume crops, by intensifying crop production (instead of fallowing land or including legumes as an intercrop with cereals), or by expanding the area of farmland. Quantifying the rotational effect of grain legumes on subsequent crops is important for understanding the adoption potential of legume technologies as well as their impact on sustainability of production. Grain legumes often yield less and demand more labour than cereal crops due to labour-intensive manual harvesting, threshing, weeding and sowing practices (<xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0515" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al., 2014</xref>). The rotational effects of legumes on cereal yields may nevertheless make legume-cereal rotations more attractive in terms of productivity and economic performance than continuous cereal cropping (<xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al., 2014</xref>). However, the impact of legumes on subsequent cereals is highly variable, depending on soil fertility status, agro-ecological conditions, crop type and management, which in turn are affected by farmers&#x02019; diverse socio-economic conditions (<xref rid="bib0505" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al., 2006</xref>). Quantifying and understanding the variability in rotational benefits will help in the tailoring of legume technologies to environments in SSA where they work best.</p><p id="par0030">The various rotational effects of grain legumes on subsequent crops can be divided into &#x02018;N-effects&#x02019; and &#x02018;non-N-effects&#x02019;, also known as &#x02018;other rotational effects&#x02019;. Nitrogen effects refer to the improved N nutrition of a subsequent non-legume crop and the associated reduction in N-fertiliser demand as a result of the N<sub>2</sub>-fixing capabilities of legumes. The amount of N<sub>2</sub> fixed depends on the genetic potential of the legume, the rhizobia and the symbiosis, and on the ability of legumes to establish their symbiosis which depends on the environment and management (<xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">Giller, 2001</xref>). In case where most of the fixed N<sub>2</sub> is removed at crop harvest, the field N balance of a legume crop is close to zero or even negative. Nevertheless, in such a situation more N may be available for the subsequent crop than after a cereal. This can be due to an N-sparing effect (the absence of soil N depletion compared with a cereal grown without sufficient N input) or reduced N immobilisation of soil mineral N due to the lower C-to-N ratio of legume residues (<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2014</xref>). N-effects from legumes depend on the amount of N fertiliser applied to the subsequent crop and in general are more pronounced in N-poor than in N-rich environments. Comparing the nitrogen budget of a non-legume crop following a legume with that of continuous non-legume crops where little N is applied allows estimation of the N-effect in terms of additional yield or N uptake (<xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">Giller, 2001</xref>). However, this approach tends to overestimate the N effects, and it often remains impossible to assign an increase in yield or N uptake of a non-legume crop after a legume to an increase in N availability or to other rotational effects, or their interaction. Isotope dilution methods may be used to directly estimate the N carry-over to subsequent crops, but these approaches are open to multiple interpretations (<xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">Chalk et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="par0035">&#x02018;Non-N-effects&#x02019; of legumes refers to impacts mediated by biotic factors such as the occurrence of pests, weeds and diseases, and abiotic factors such as changes in the availability of water or nutrients other than N, changes in soil pH, or changes in soil organic matter and soil structure. While many studies in SSA assessed N dynamics in legumes by measuring N<sub>2</sub>-fixation rates, legume field N balances and N uptakes by subsequent crops, the non-N-effects effects are often neglected. Nevertheless, the non-N-effects may be of great importance. For instance, in environments with intense striga pressure (<italic>Striga asiatica</italic> or <italic>S. hermonthica</italic>), a non-host legume crop can drastically reduce the striga seedbank leading to lower striga densities and strong yield increases of cereals in rotation relative to continuous cereal cultivation (<xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0580" ref-type="bibr">Rusinamhodzi et al., 2012</xref>). Also in temperate climates, the impact of legumes on biotic factors can be as important as the N effects where soil N is limiting (<xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">Kirkegaard et al., 2008</xref>). However, the question remains how widespread such strong impacts of legumes on biotic constraints of subsequent crops are. Apart from biotic stresses, legumes may influence the activities of other rhizosphere organisms that stimulate or suppress plant growth or available nutrients. The biotic impact of pests and diseases occurring belowground are hard to quantify, which explains why they receive little attention in field studies. An additional complexity to quantify some of the non-N-effects of an abiotic nature is the slow rate at which they change. Impacts of crop rotations on soil fertility parameters such as soil organic matter contents, soil structure and water holding capacity are typically only visible in longer-term experiments including several cropping cycles, which are scarce in SSA.</p><p id="par0040">We are unaware of any recent studies that synthesise and structure the knowledge on the rotational benefits of grain legumes in the (sub-)tropics. Given that much less fertiliser is used in SSA than in other regions of the world, the contributions of N<sub>2</sub>-fixation are particularly important (<xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr">Giller et al., 2013</xref>). Here we review the literature on the rotational effects of grain legumes, with a specific emphasis on SSA. Cropping systems in SSA outside the humid forest zone tend to be dominated by cereals, particularly maize, millet, sorghum and rice, combined with root and tuber crops where rainfall is adequate (<xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Dixon et al., 2001</xref>). Specifically we: 1) Quantified the magnitude and variability of rotational effects of legumes on subsequent cereals; 2) Explored the importance of environmental and management factors in determining variability in rotational effects; and 3) Evaluated the evidence of the different mechanisms that explain rotational effects of legumes on subsequent crops.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Literature search</title><p id="par0045">We systematically searched the Web of Science with the terms &#x0201c;legume* AND maize AND rotation&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;legume* AND sorghum AND rotation*&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;legume* AND millet AND rotation*&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;legume* AND rice AND rotation*&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;legume* AND rotation* AND Africa&#x0201d; and selected publications on experiments in SSA. Checking the references of the papers retrieved yielded six more papers. We also included a study from the current special issue. Only publications presenting primary source data from on-station or on-farm field experiments were included in the subsequent analysis. Legume-cereal mixed cropping experiments were excluded for two reasons: i) they are difficult to compare with monocrops of legumes and cereals and ii) the impacts on crop productivity depend strongly on spatial and temporal crop patterns. A requirement for inclusion of a study was that the cereal crops belonged to the same variety across treatments and were managed in the same way (including nutrient application rates). Where experiments were unbalanced, results from treatments were selected in such a way to ensure that treatments with cereal after cereal and cereal after legume were comparable. Where publications described experiments replicated across countries, districts representing different agro-ecologies, or different legumes or cereals, each comparison was considered separately. Similarly, if rotational cycles were repeated or N fertiliser treatments were applied to the cereal, results from individual cycles and N treatments were used. Results were averaged in case studies were conducted in multiple locations within the same districts or agro-ecology, or when studies included additional treatments such as different soil cultivation types or fertiliser applications to legumes. To compose the scatter graphs in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> however, all individual treatments that could be extracted from the publications were used. To assess impacts per region, we divided studies from West Africa into three broad agro-ecological zones (AEZs): the humid forest/derived savannah (&#x0003e;1200&#x000a0;mm rain, &#x0003e;250 growing days per annum), the drier Guinea savannah (700&#x02013;1200&#x000a0;mm rain, 150&#x02013;250 growing days per annum), and the arid Sudano-Sahelian zone (&#x0003c;700&#x000a0;mm rain, &#x0003c;150 growing days per annum). Studies from Southern and East Africa were too few to be divided. A search on the Web of Science using the terms &#x0201c;tuber AND legume AND Africa&#x0201d; yielded few publications on legume-tuber mixed cropping, supporting the choice to focus our study exclusively on legume-cereal rotations.</p><p id="par0050">To disentangle the different types of rotational effects of grain legumes on cereals, we extended our literature search with terms such as &#x0201c;N nutrition OR P nutrition&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;N fertiliser replacement&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;pest&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;weed&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;disease&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;soil structure&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;organic matter&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;pH&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;nematodes&#x0201d; in combination with &#x0201c;cereal* AND legume*&#x0201d;. Again, we focused on studies from SSA but in this case, studies from other parts of the world that provide insights into the mechanisms at play were also included. We reviewed estimates of the amount of nitrogen fixed and net N inputs by different grain legumes in SSA.</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Data analysis</title><p id="par0055">We tested for significant impacts of the factors: (1) agro-ecological zone (AEZ), (2) cereal type, (3) legume type, (4) N application rate to the cereal and (5) the number of rotational cycles on the mean cereal grain yield in continuous cereal, in legume-cereal rotations. As cereal crops, we distinguished maize, sorghum, millet and &#x02018;other cereals&#x02019;; legume crops were cowpea, groundnut, soybean, pigeonpea and &#x02018;other legumes&#x02019;. N application rates were categorised into no N applied, 15&#x02013;50&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and &#x0003e;60&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; the rotational cycles as 1 (1st rotational cycle) or &#x0003e;1 (2nd or higher rotational cycle). The precision of the reported means was expressed in the different publications as standard error of the mean (SEM), standard error of the (between-treatment) difference (SED), least significant difference (LSD), standard deviation (SD) and coefficient of variation (CV). In case SEM was not reported, it was calculated from available information on SED, LSD, SD and CV, as appropriate. In the subsequent analysis, the data were weighted inversely proportional to the square of the SEM in question (that is, inversely proportional to the variance of the mean). Studies that did not give an indication of variability (<xref rid="bib0605" ref-type="bibr">Sauerborn et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib0595" ref-type="bibr">Sanginga et al., 2002</xref>, <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Bado et al., 2006a</xref>, <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">Bado et al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">Bloem et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="bib0320" ref-type="bibr">Kamanga et al., 2010</xref>) were excluded from these statistical analysis. In the first instance, mean yields were analysed statistically using a mixed model with the fixed effects treatment (continuous cereal versus legume-cereal rotation) and cereal type, and the random effects pair, experiment x treatment and district x treatment. The factor &#x0201c;pair&#x0201d; matched each mean yield in legume-cereal rotation to the associated control yield (continuous cereal). In some experiments, mean yields for legume-cereal rotation were reported for different legumes, and/or for different levels of N and different rotational cycles. In order to model the potential correlation of treatment differences within experiments, the experiment x treatment random effect was fitted. Similarly, in order to model the potential correlation of treatment differences when experiments were carried out in the same geographic district, the district x treatment random effect was fitted. From the mixed model analysis, mean yields for the two treatments were calculated (continuous cereal versus legume-cereal rotation), as well as the difference between mean yields with associated 95% confidence interval and <italic>p</italic>-value. Similarly, mean yields for each cereal type and AEZ were calculated (SAS least squares (LS) means). Degrees of freedom and standard errors of estimates were adjusted using the Kenward-Roger (KR) method. In a sensitivity analysis, the mixed model analysis was repeated respectively fitting the treatment x cereal type and treatment x AEZ interaction terms. In the event, neither of these terms was statistically significant. Furthermore, in order to investigate the potential effect of legume type, a model was fitted with the fixed effects treatment, cereal type, legume type and treatment x legume type interaction. The potential effects of N application rate and of number of rotational cycles, were analysed in the same way. No inferential statistical analysis were made with regard to the impact of abiotic factors other than N application rate and of biotic factors, as the number of relevant papers on these topics did not allow such analysis</p><p id="par0060">Maximum response curves in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> were obtained using boundary analysis (<xref rid="bib0610" ref-type="bibr">Shatar and McBratney, 2004</xref>) by regression of an exponential curve through the 95th percentile of yield responses after a legume (response variable) in the control yield ranges of [0&#x02013;0.5], [0.5&#x02013;1.0], [1.0&#x02013;1.5], [1.5&#x02013;2.0], [2.0&#x02013;3.0], [3.0&#x02013;5.0] and (&#x0003e;5.0&#x000a0;t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), using the average control yields in these ranges as the explanatory variable. Means predicted by the statistical model and the associated <italic>p</italic>-values are presented in <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Data presented in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and in <xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> are based on the data as reported by the studies. &#x02018;<italic>n</italic>&#x02019; in tables indicates the number of observations.</p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Overview of the available studies</title><p id="par0065">We found 44 unique publications that assessed the impact of grain legumes on subsequent cereal yields in SSA (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). These publications provided 199 comparisons between the cereal yield after a cereal and the cereal yield after a grain legume. Most studies were from West Africa (28 publications); within West Africa, most were conducted in the Guinea savannah (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Only one study was situated in the humid forest zone (southern Cameroon) (<xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">Jemo et al., 2006</xref>). No studies were found from Central Africa. In East Africa, studies were limited to the mid- to high altitude areas of Kenya and Uganda (1000&#x02013;1600&#x000a0;m altitude, &#x0003e;1200&#x000a0;mm rain, two growing seasons and 250&#x02013;365 growing days per annum). Studies from southern Africa were all conducted in the savannahs of the interior regions (600&#x02013;1200&#x000a0;mm rain, a single growing season and 100&#x02013;250 growing days per annum), except for one study (<xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">Bloem et al., 2009</xref>) conducted in the sub-humid east coast of South Africa (600&#x02013;800&#x000a0;mm) which was excluded from analyses of effects of AEZs. Most studies (33 publications) focused on maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) as a rotational cereal crop, with fewer studies including sorghum (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> [L.] Moench), millet (<italic>Pennisetum glaucum</italic> [L.] R. Br.), rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) or finger millet (<italic>Eleusine coracana</italic> L.) (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In the Sudano-Sahelian zone, only millet and sorghum were used as rotational crops.<table-wrap id="tbl0005" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Number of unique publications (<italic>n</italic>) on rotational effects of legumes on cereals per AEZ and the countries where the trials were conducted and the cereal crops assessed. The number between brackets indicates the number of studies for a country/cereal crop. One publication contained data from both the derived and the Guinea savannah of West Africa, three studies included two cereals, one study contained observations from two countries.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0180">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Region</th><th align="left">AEZ</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">Countries</th><th align="left">Cereal crops</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">East Africa</td><td align="left">Highlands</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">Kenya (4), Uganda (1)</td><td align="left">maize (4), finger millet (1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Southern Africa</td><td align="left">Savannah and coastal region</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">Zimbabwe (5), Malawi (3), Mozambique (1), South Africa (1), Tanzania (1)</td><td align="left">maize (10), sorghum (1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">West Africa</td><td align="left">Humid forest/Derived Savannah</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">Ghana (2), Benin (1), Cameroon (1), Nigeria (1)</td><td align="left">maize (5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Guinea Savannah</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">Nigeria (10), Ghana (4), Burkina Faso (2), Benin (1)</td><td align="left">maize (13), sorghum (3), rice (1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sudano-Sahelian zone</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">Burkina Faso (2), Mali (3), Niger (3)</td><td align="left">millet (6), sorghum (3)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl0015" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Cereal grain yield in continuous cereal, cereal yield after a legume, yield response to a legume, and the significance of yield responses and of interactions between factors and yield responses, presented by AEZ, cereal type, legume type, the number of rotational cycles and N application category. Mean yields and yield responses (t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), the associated standard errors (SE) and <italic>p</italic>-values were estimated by the statistical model.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0190">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Factor</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">Yield in continuous cereals</th><th align="left">Yield after a legume</th><th align="left">SE of yields</th><th align="left">Yield response</th><th align="left">SE of yield response</th><th align="left">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Overall mean</td><td align="left">199</td><td align="left">1.20</td><td align="left">1.69</td><td align="left">0.23</td><td align="left">0.49</td><td align="left">0.09</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Savannahs of southern Africa</td><td align="left">27</td><td align="left">1.65</td><td align="left">2.34</td><td align="left">0.30</td><td align="left">0.69</td><td align="left">0.18</td><td align="left">0.0005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Highlands of East Africa</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">2.24</td><td align="left">2.86</td><td align="left">0.32</td><td align="left">0.62</td><td align="left">0.21</td><td align="left">0.0074</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Humid forest/Derived savannah</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">1.59</td><td align="left">1.81</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.21</td><td align="left">0.21</td><td align="left">0.334</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Guinea savannah</td><td align="left">74</td><td align="left">2.14</td><td align="left">2.66</td><td align="left">0.21</td><td align="left">0.52</td><td align="left">0.18</td><td align="left">0.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sudano-Sahelian zone</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">1.16</td><td align="left">1.44</td><td align="left">0.22</td><td align="left">0.28</td><td align="left">0.17</td><td align="left">0.138</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>AEZ x yield response</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.351</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maize</td><td align="left">131</td><td align="left">1.96</td><td align="left">2.53</td><td align="left">0.15</td><td align="left">0.57</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Millet</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">1.11</td><td align="left">1.43</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.32</td><td align="left">0.21</td><td align="left">0.134</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sorghum</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">1.06</td><td align="left">1.18</td><td align="left">0.39</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.26</td><td align="left">0.647</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other cereal</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">0.93</td><td align="left">1.26</td><td align="left">0.78</td><td align="left">0.33</td><td align="left">0.42</td><td align="left">0.445</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cereal type x yield response</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.435</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cowpea</td><td align="left">91</td><td align="left">1.21</td><td align="left">1.60</td><td align="left">0.23</td><td align="left">0.40</td><td align="left">0.09</td><td align="left">0.0004</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Groundnut</td><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">1.22</td><td align="left">1.84</td><td align="left">0.23</td><td align="left">0.62</td><td align="left">0.11</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Soybean</td><td align="left">47</td><td align="left">1.18</td><td align="left">1.80</td><td align="left">0.23</td><td align="left">0.62</td><td align="left">0.10</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pigeonpea</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">1.23</td><td align="left">1.66</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.43</td><td align="left">0.11</td><td align="left">0.0005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Other legume</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">1.24</td><td align="left">1.61</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.36</td><td align="left">0.11</td><td align="left">0.0023</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Legume type x yield response</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1st rotational cycle</td><td align="left">150</td><td align="left">1.49</td><td align="left">1.97</td><td align="left">0.13</td><td align="left">0.48</td><td align="left">0.10</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2nd or subsequent cycles</td><td align="left">49</td><td align="left">2.08</td><td align="left">2.57</td><td align="left">0.16</td><td align="left">0.49</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.0003</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Rotational cycle x yield response</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.907</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0&#x000a0;N</td><td align="left">77</td><td align="left">0.97</td><td align="left">1.51</td><td align="left">0.24</td><td align="left">0.54</td><td align="left">0.11</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15&#x02013;50&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">1.16</td><td align="left">1.65</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.49</td><td align="left">0.15</td><td align="left">0.0025</td></tr><tr><td align="left">60&#x02013;120&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left">53</td><td align="left">1.92</td><td align="left">2.25</td><td align="left">0.26</td><td align="left">0.32</td><td align="left">0.14</td><td align="left">0.0248</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>N application x yield response</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.204</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0030"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec0035"><label>3.1</label><title>Magnitude and variability of cereal grain responses</title><sec id="sec0040"><label>3.1.1</label><title>Overview of responses</title><p id="par0070">An overview of the reported responses of cereal grain yields after a previous grain legume relative to continuous cereal cropping, averaged per legume crop, per district and over rotational cycles, is given in <xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. In almost all cases, the grain yield of a cereal crop after a legume crop was greater than the grain yield of continuous cereal crops. The most common grain legume crops assessed were cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> (L.) Walp.), soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic> (L.) Merr), groundnut (<italic>Arachis hypogaea</italic> L.) and pigeonpea (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> (L.) Millsp.) (<xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). These were studied in all AEZs except for the Sudano-Sahelian zone where the focus was on cowpea and groundnut that are well adapted to drier conditions. Other legume crops included were common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.), Lima bean (<italic>Phaseolus lunatus</italic> L.), lablab (<italic>Lablab purpureus</italic> (L.) Sweet) and Bambara groundnut (<italic>Vigna subterranea</italic> (L.) Verdc.). Most studies assessed residual effects of several legume species simultaneously. The study by <xref rid="bib0580" ref-type="bibr">Rusinamhodzi et al. (2012)</xref> was excluded from further analyses of mean effects, as the extremely strong increase in maize yield after pigeonpea (&#x02248;5&#x000a0;t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or 800% increase), largely caused by a strong reduction in striga pressure, had a disproportionately strong influence on the results and was considered atypical.<table-wrap id="tbl0010" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Overview of cereal grain yield response to a preceding legume relative to continuous cereal yield in the same season(s) (control yield). Results from additional treatments, sites within the same agro-ecology and different rotational cycles were averaged per publication. Eleven publications contained data on multiple cereal crops and/or districts and therefore occur more than once. The right columns indicates fertiliser treatments and to which crop nutrients were applied, and the number of rotational cycles. N fertiliser treatments are applied to the cereal unless mentioned otherwise.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0185">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">AEZ/Source</th><th align="left">Country</th><th align="left">District</th><th align="left">Cereal type</th><th align="left">Control yield (t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th colspan="5" align="left">Change in cereal yield after legume (% relative to control yield)<hr/></th><th align="left">Fertiliser treatment (crop)</th><th align="left">No. of cycles</th></tr><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left"/><th align="left"/><th align="left"/><th align="left"/><th align="left">Cowpea</th><th align="left">Groundnut</th><th align="left">Soybean</th><th align="left">Pigeonpea</th><th align="left">Other legume (type)</th><th align="left"/><th align="left"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="12" align="left"><italic>East Africa</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Anyanzwa et al. (2010)</xref></td><td align="left">Kenya</td><td align="left">Teso</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.55</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">28</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">Kihara et al. (2010)</xref></td><td align="left">Kenya</td><td align="left">Nyanza</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">3.48</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">47</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">P (legume &#x00026; maize)</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0515" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al. (2014)</xref></td><td align="left">Kenya</td><td align="left">Kakamega</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.14</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">70</td><td align="left">43</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">2 (common bean)/45 (Lima bean)/78 (lablab)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0515" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al. (2014)</xref></td><td align="left">Kenya</td><td align="left">Siaya</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.12</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">80</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">23 (common bean)/69 (Lima bean)/143 (lablab)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0515" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al. (2014)</xref></td><td align="left">Kenya</td><td align="left">Vihiga</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.87</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">68</td><td align="left">41</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">5 (common bean)/50 (Lima bean)/103 (lablab)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0555" ref-type="bibr">Rao and Mathuva (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Kenya</td><td align="left">Machakos</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.46</td><td align="left">117</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">Ebanyat et al. (2010)</xref></td><td align="left">Uganda</td><td align="left">Pallisa</td><td align="left">finger millet</td><td align="left">0.87</td><td align="left">143</td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">52 (green gram)</td><td align="left">P (legume)</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12" align="left">&#x02028;&#x02028;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12" align="left"><italic>Southern Africa</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0320" ref-type="bibr">Kamanga et al. (2010)</xref></td><td align="left">Malawi</td><td align="left">Dowa</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">0.62</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">142 (pigeonpea/groundnut)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">MacColl (1989)</xref></td><td align="left">Malawi</td><td align="left">Lilongwe</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">3.02</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Malawi</td><td align="left">Dowa</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.47</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">22</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Malawi</td><td align="left">Mchinji</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.30</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">56</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Malawi</td><td align="left">Salima</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">3.75</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">33</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0580" ref-type="bibr">Rusinamhodzi et al. (2012)</xref></td><td align="left">Mozambique</td><td align="left">Manica</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">0.66</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">765</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">N &#x00026; P (legume)</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">Bloem et al. (2009)</xref></td><td align="left">South Africa</td><td align="left">Western Cape</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">6.03</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">Bloem et al. (2009)</xref></td><td align="left">South Africa</td><td align="left">Eastern Cape</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.98</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr">Marandu et al. (2013)</xref></td><td align="left">Tanzania</td><td align="left">Muheza</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">0.34</td><td align="left">92</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">87</td><td align="left">92 (green gram)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">Kasasa et al. (1999)</xref></td><td align="left">Zimbabwe</td><td align="left">Harare</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.81</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">113</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">Kasasa et al. (1999)</xref></td><td align="left">Zimbabwe</td><td align="left">Hurungwe</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">0.37</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">237</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0445" ref-type="bibr">Mupangwa et al. (2012)</xref></td><td align="left">Zimbabwe</td><td align="left">Matobo</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.11</td><td align="left">119</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">Ncube et al. (2007)</xref></td><td align="left">Zimbabwe</td><td align="left">Matobo</td><td align="left">sorghum</td><td align="left">0.52</td><td align="left">131</td><td align="left">131</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">123</td><td align="left">82 (Bambara groundnut)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0640" ref-type="bibr">Thierfelder et al. (2012)</xref></td><td align="left">Zimbabwe</td><td align="left">Shawva</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.25</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0735" ref-type="bibr">Zingore et al. (2008)</xref></td><td align="left">Zimbabwe</td><td align="left">Murewa</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">0.40</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">25</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12" align="left">&#x02028;&#x02028;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12" align="left"><italic>West Africa &#x02212; Humid forest/Derived savannah</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">Diels et al. (2006)</xref></td><td align="left">Benin</td><td align="left">Sekou</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.57</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">58</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">Jemo et al. (2006)</xref></td><td align="left">Cameroon</td><td align="left">Southern Cameroon</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.48</td><td align="left">57</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">35</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Adjei-Nsiah et al. (2007)</xref></td><td align="left">Ghana</td><td align="left">Brong Ahafo</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.76</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">58</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Adjei-Nsiah et al. (2008)</xref></td><td align="left">Ghana</td><td align="left">Brong Ahafo</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.19</td><td align="left">42</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al. (2008)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Oyo State</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.52</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">4</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12" align="left">&#x02028;&#x02028;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12" align="left"><italic>West Africa &#x02212; Guinea savannah</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0500" ref-type="bibr">Oikeh et al. (2010)</xref></td><td align="left">Benin</td><td align="left">Couffa and Dongo</td><td align="left">rice</td><td align="left">0.99</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">36</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Bado et al. (2006a)</xref></td><td align="left">Burkina Faso</td><td align="left">Houet</td><td align="left">sorghum</td><td align="left">0.64</td><td align="left">211</td><td align="left">186</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N, P, K, Ca and Mg (legume)</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">Bado et al. (2013)</xref></td><td align="left">Burkina Faso</td><td align="left">Houet</td><td align="left">sorghum</td><td align="left">1.52</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">Dakora and Keya (1997)</xref></td><td align="left">Ghana</td><td align="left">Tolon-Kumbungu</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">3.15</td><td align="left">101</td><td align="left">104</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">70</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">Dakora et al. (1987)</xref></td><td align="left">Ghana</td><td align="left">Tolon-Kumbungu</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.40</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">58</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">Horst and H&#x000e4;rdter (1994)</xref></td><td align="left">Ghana</td><td align="left">Tolon-Kumbungu</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.36</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">P (maize)</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0605" ref-type="bibr">Sauerborn et al. (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Ghana</td><td align="left">Tolon-Kumbungu</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">0.65</td><td align="left">151</td><td align="left">207</td><td align="left">191</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0605" ref-type="bibr">Sauerborn et al. (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Ghana</td><td align="left">Tolon-Kumbungu</td><td align="left">sorghum</td><td align="left">0.57</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">77</td><td align="left">117</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">Carsky et al. (1999)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Bauchi state</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.66<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">Carsky et al. (1999)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Kaduna state</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.35<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">Carsky et al. (2001)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Kaduna state</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">0.27<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al. (2008)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Kaduna state</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.03</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">91</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">Horst et al. (2001)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Kaduna state</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">6.06</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">8 (common bean)</td><td align="left">P (legume &#x00026; maize)</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">Horst et al. (2001)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Plateau state</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">3.15</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02212;11</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">12 (common bean)</td><td align="left">P (legume &#x00026; maize)</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">Kolawole et al. (2007)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Kaduna State</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.39</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">22</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0495" ref-type="bibr">Oikeh et al. (1998)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Kaduna state</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">4.20</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">24</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0595" ref-type="bibr">Sanginga et al. (2002)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Niger state</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">1.22</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">71</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0730" ref-type="bibr">Yusuf et al. (2009b)</xref></td><td align="left">Nigeria</td><td align="left">Kaduna state</td><td align="left">maize</td><td align="left">2.01</td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">47</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">N</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12" align="left">&#x02028;&#x02028;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="12" align="left"><italic>West Africa &#x02212; Sudano-Sahelian zone</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Bado et al. (2006b)</xref></td><td align="left">Burkina Faso</td><td align="left">Kouar&#x000e9;</td><td align="left">sorghum</td><td align="left">0.47</td><td align="left">101</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Bagayoko et al. (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Burkina Faso</td><td align="left">Gourma</td><td align="left">sorghum</td><td align="left">0.47</td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">Bagayoko et al. (1996)</xref></td><td align="left">Mali</td><td align="left">S&#x000e9;gou</td><td align="left">millet</td><td align="left">1.43</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">Kouyat&#x000e9; et al. (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Mali</td><td align="left">S&#x000e9;gou</td><td align="left">sorghum</td><td align="left">1.39</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">Kouyat&#x000e9; et al. (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Mali</td><td align="left">S&#x000e9;gou</td><td align="left">millet</td><td align="left">1.15</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0590" ref-type="bibr">Samak&#x000e9; et al. (2006)</xref></td><td align="left">Mali</td><td align="left">Mopti</td><td align="left">millet</td><td align="left">0.43</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Bagayoko et al. (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Niger</td><td align="left">Dosso</td><td align="left">millet</td><td align="left">0.74</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Bagayoko et al. (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Niger</td><td align="left">Tillab&#x000e9;ri</td><td align="left">millet</td><td align="left">0.94</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Bationo and Ntare (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Niger</td><td align="left">Tillab&#x000e9;ri</td><td align="left">millet</td><td align="left">0.77</td><td align="left">39</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Bationo and Ntare (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Niger</td><td align="left">Tillab&#x000e9;ri</td><td align="left">millet</td><td align="left">0.61</td><td align="left">84</td><td align="left">66</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Bationo and Ntare (2000)</xref></td><td align="left">Niger</td><td align="left">Dossa</td><td align="left">millet</td><td align="left">0.84</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02212;7</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr">Klaij and Ntare (1995)</xref></td><td align="left">Niger</td><td align="left">Niamey</td><td align="left">millet</td><td align="left">0.43</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0005"><label>a</label><p id="npar0010">No continuous cereal included so the fallow-cereal treatment was used as the control.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0045"><label>3.1.2</label><title>Impacts of control yield, AEZ, and cereal and legume type</title><p id="par0075">The absolute response of cereals to rotation with grain legumes, as estimated by the statistical model, was 0.49&#x000a0;t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, equal to a 41% increase relative to the continuous cereal yield (<xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The largest relative increases in grain yields in a cereal crop following a legume were observed when the control yield of continuous cereals was small, and declined exponentially with larger control yields (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A), as also observed by <xref rid="bib0670" ref-type="bibr">Vanlauwe et al. (2001)</xref> for different maize-based systems in West Africa responding to legume and other organic inputs. Assuming the control yield in continuous cereal is an indicator of soil fertility, this suggests that under poor soil fertility the impact of growing a preceding legume can be large. Yet when constraints not addressed by rotation with legumes are overriding, the impact can be minimal. Absolute increases in cereal yield after a legume were overall largest with continuous cereal yields above 2&#x000a0;t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). At large control yields, absolute yield responses to the incorporation of a legume may still be substantial (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). Observations of absolute yield increases with control yields above 3&#x000a0;t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were too few to estimate reliably potential maximum yield responses when control yields were large.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Relative (A) and absolute (B) grain yield increase of cereal after different types of legumes, relative to the yield of continuous cereal, plotted against continuous cereal grain yield. The curved lines indicate the upper boundary of maximum yield increases.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0165">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="par0080">Grain yields of cereals varied among AEZs (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A &#x00026; <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Generally, cereals yielded poorly in the Sudano-Sahelian zone, presumably due to low and erratic rainfall leading to soil moisture stress. Smaller mean yield increases that were not significant were observed after grain legumes in the Sudano-Sahelian zone, as well as the humid forest/derived savannah of West Africa. Studies from the Guinea savannah of West Africa and from southern Africa and East Africa reported larger, significant cereal yield responses to rotation with legumes. The regional differences in responses to a preceding legume reflect the production potential of the relevant grain legumes in the regions. In the Sudano-Sahelian zone, the productivity of legumes is generally small due to the short growing season and frequent occurrences of drought, limiting the residual impacts on a subsequent cereal, and cereal yields were likely also to be constrained by water availability (e.g. <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">Kouyat&#x000e9; et al. (2000)</xref>). Grain legume production is often poor in the humid forest/derived savannah due to moist and warm conditions leading to strong biotic pressures (e.g. <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al. (2008)</xref>). While rainfall is plentiful in the highlands of East Africa, the production environment is favourable for legume crops due to the relatively cool temperatures.<fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Box plots of cereal grain yield in continuous (cont.) cereal and legume (leg.)-cereal rotations separated by (A) the main agro-ecological zones, (B) cereal type, (C) legume type and (D) the number of rotational cycles. The whiskers represent the 2nd and 98th percentile of the observations.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0170">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="par0085">Differences in cereal yields among the AEZs were strongly influenced by the cereal crop grown (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B &#x00026; <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). In the Sudano-Sahelian zone of West Africa, only millet and sorghum were evaluated, while maize dominated in the other zones where 86% of the observations were on maize. The yield responses of millet and sorghum to a preceding legume were smaller and not significant, in contrast to maize showing larger and significant responses (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B &#x00026; <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). All millet trials were conducted in the Sudano-Sahelian zone that has a relatively low production potential for both legumes and cereals. Moreover, millet in the Sudano-Sahelian zone gives rather variable responses to N fertiliser (<xref rid="bib0650" ref-type="bibr">Traore et al., 2015</xref>), and the N benefits of growing legumes to millet may also be inconsistent. Studies on sorghum were conducted across different agro-ecological zones in SSA, with most observations from the Guinea savannah, and poor sorghum yields were observed across all areas, suggesting that sorghum has a smaller potential yield than maize. Due to the strong confounding between AEZ and cereal type, interactions between AEZ and yield responses and between cereal type and yield responses were not significant (<xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><p id="par0090">All legume types had a significant residual effect on cereal yield (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>C; <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). A significant interaction between legume type and yield response was observed, and the mean effects from soybean and groundnut were larger than from cowpea. Nevertheless in some cases, strong residual effects of cowpea were reported (<xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">Horst and H&#x000e4;rdter, 1994</xref>, <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">Horst et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0640" ref-type="bibr">Thierfelder et al., 2012</xref>). Cowpea has the ability to grow well in poor sandy soils and dry environments and the poorer response of cereals to a preceding legume may be related to the more marginal environments in which cowpea is often grown. While some general differences between legume crops in their ability to fix N<sub>2</sub> and the net N contribution can be identified (see Section <xref rid="sec0060" ref-type="sec">3.2.1</xref>), N<sub>2</sub>-fixation is also strongly influenced by environmental and varietal characteristics, and differences in residual effects between legume types are not necessarily a reflection of N<sub>2</sub>-fixing abilities.</p><p id="par0095">The number of rotational cycles did not affect the cereal yield response to a legume (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>D; <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). While the benefits of incorporating legumes for cereal yields are expected to increase over time, the number of studies reporting data over multiple rotational cycles was too small to observe this (<xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Cereal yields increased after the first rotational cycle in both continuous cereal and cereal after a legume. This might be the result of researchers and field technicians improving their skills in trial implementation over time.</p></sec><sec id="sec0050"><label>3.1.3</label><title>Interactions with N and P fertiliser</title><p id="par0100">The application of 15&#x02013;50&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> reduced the relative response of cereals from 56% (no&#x000a0;N applied) to 42%, and applying 60&#x02013;120&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> further reduced it to 17% (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> &#x00026; <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Also the absolute response declined from 0.54 to 0.32&#x000a0;t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> from no N to 60&#x02013;120&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> applied. Nevertheless, the yield response to a preceding legume was significant in all N application classes (<xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). If we assume that applying 60&#x02013;120&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> strongly reduces or eliminates N as a limiting factor of cereal growth under smallholder conditions in SSA, the considerable response of cereals at 60&#x02013;120&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> indicates the importance of other (non-N) rotational effects of legumes. When assuming that N-effects and non-N-effects are cumulative, the response at 60&#x02013;120&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N can be used to partition the response at 0N into non-N effects (equal to the response at 60&#x02013;120&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N or 59% of the total response at 0N) and N effects (the remaining response or 41% of the total response at 0N). It is likely however that N-effects and non-N-effects act synergistically. An improved availability of N to a cereal as a result of a preceding legume can lead to non-N-effects (e.g. an improved disease tolerance), while the non-N-effects of legumes may lead to better N recovery by a cereal.<fig id="fig0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Box plots of (A) percentage grain yield increase of cereal after a legume crop, relative to the yield in continuous cereal, and (B) cereal grain yield in continuous (cont.) cereal and legume (leg.)-cereal rotations, at different N application rates to cereals. The whiskers represent the 2nd and 98th percentile of the observations.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0175">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="par0105">Only few studies assessed interactions with P fertiliser in continuous cereal and legume-cereal systems in SSA (<xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">Horst and H&#x000e4;rdter, 1994</xref>, <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">Horst et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">Ebanyat et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">Kihara et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0580" ref-type="bibr">Rusinamhodzi et al., 2012</xref>). Although some legumes have the ability to mobilise poorly-available soil P sources (see Section <xref rid="sec0065" ref-type="sec">3.2.2</xref>), additional P fertiliser is often essential for good grain legume growth and N<sub>2</sub> fixation (<xref rid="bib0490" ref-type="bibr">Ogoke et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0565" ref-type="bibr">Ronner et al., 2016</xref>). Better growth of a legume and the residual effects of P fertiliser applications can lead to enhanced residual effects in a subsequent cereal (<xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">Horst et al., 2001</xref>). P fertiliser may also be applied directly to the cereal crop, thereby enhancing growth and N use efficiency (<xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">Kihara et al., 2010</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0055"><label>3.2</label><title>Abiotic factors</title><sec id="sec0060"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Nitrogen</title><p id="par0110"><xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> provides a summary of studies assessing N<sub>2</sub>-fixation and net N benefits from grain legumes in SSA. Most studies have been conducted on cowpea, groundnut and soybean. The range in grain yield of the common grain legumes is comparable with maximum yields up to 2.1&#x02013;2.9&#x000a0;t grain ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. However, smaller maximum yields were reported for common bean, lablab and Bambara nut, perhaps due to the fewer studies conducted. All grain legumes have the potential to derive a large proportion of plant-derived N from atmospheric N<sub>2</sub> and fix substantial amounts of N<sub>2</sub> (often over 100&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), with the exception of common bean that is often, though not always, a relatively poor N<sub>2</sub>-fixer (<xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">Graham, 1981</xref>, <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">Giller, 1990</xref>). Bambara nut had only modest biomass production in the few studies available and therefore fixed relatively low amounts of N<sub>2</sub>. The N harvest index of any grain legume is small when grain fill is hampered due to drought, heat stress or nutrient limitations. Soybean and common bean potentially have high N harvest indices (<xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), because of the high protein concentration of the grains. However, as leaves of many soybean and common bean varieties senesce and fall before harvest, high N harvest indices reported in the literature may be partly due to an underestimation of the N returned to the soil before harvest. The net N input from N<sub>2</sub>-fixation, assuming stover remains in the field and grain is removed, and considering aboveground plant parts only, can be negative when the proportion of N derived from N<sub>2</sub>-fixation is small and/or most of the N is removed in the grain (<xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">Giller and Cadisch, 1995</xref>). The largest net N input rates are found when N<sub>2</sub>-fixation rates are high and the N harvest index is poor, for instance with indeterminate varieties. The large range in values of N<sub>2</sub>-fixation parameters within species reported in <xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> is due largely to variability in environmental conditions, e.g. agro-ecological conditions (<xref rid="bib0510" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al., 2007</xref>), and management, e.g. P fertiliser applications (<xref rid="bib0490" ref-type="bibr">Ogoke et al., 2003</xref>), as well as the wide range of varieties available for most grain legumes. Varieties differ in duration, ability to nodulate with rhizobia present in the soil, productivity, dry matter and N harvest index, all of which affect the net N input from legumes. In general, longer duration, more indeterminate varieties with a high stover biomass production (also called dual-purpose varieties) fix more N<sub>2</sub> and provide more residual N and soil fertility benefits (<xref rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr">Mapfumo et al., 1999</xref>, <xref rid="bib0600" ref-type="bibr">Sanginga, 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0615" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2003</xref>), though smallholder farmers often prefer shorter duration, more determinate grain-type varieties with a high dry matter and N harvest index (<xref rid="bib0625" ref-type="bibr">Snapp and Silim, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Adjei-Nsiah et al., 2008</xref>). The additional N taken up by a cereal after a legume (<xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) can be the result of an enhanced N supply and of an increased N demand due to other rotational effects. Only a limited fraction of the N in legume residues is available for uptake by the subsequent cereal. <xref rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr">Laberge et al. (2011)</xref> using labelled <sup>15</sup>N techniques at a site in the Sudan savannah reported that 40% of the N in cowpea residues remaining in the field could be retrieved in the top 30&#x000a0;cm of the soil at the beginning of the next planting season and 10% of the residual N was taken up by a subsequent millet. <xref rid="bib0595" ref-type="bibr">Sanginga et al. (2002)</xref> found that, at a site in the Guinea savannah, 17&#x02013;33% of the N in soybean residues is taken up by a subsequent maize crop, depending on maize cultivar. Despite this low fraction of legume N in residues available for uptake by a subsequent cereal, the ranges in net N input from N<sub>2</sub>-fixation and additional N taken up by a subsequent cereal are comparable (<xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), probably because legumes also enhance N demand of the subsequent cereal through other rotational effects. Some studies estimated an N fertiliser replacement value of legumes (<xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). This value indicates how much N fertiliser should be added to a cereal following a cereal to produce the same grain yield achieved by a cereal in rotation with a legume without N fertiliser applied to the cereal. N replacement values are generally in line with the observed net inputs from N<sub>2</sub>-fixation.<table-wrap id="tbl0020" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Observed ranges in yields, amounts of N<sub>2</sub> fixed and net N inputs by different grain legumes in SSA grown as sole crops, considering aboveground plant parts only and assuming stover remains in the field and grain is removed (updated from <xref rid="bib0255" ref-type="bibr">Giller et al., 1997</xref>).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0195">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Grain legume</th><th align="left">Grain yield (t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">Stover yield (t&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">N from N<sub>2</sub> fixation (%)</th><th align="left">Amount of N<sub>2</sub> fixed (kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">N in stover (kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">N harvest index (%)</th><th align="left">Net input from N<sub>2</sub>-fixation (kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">Additional N taken up by subsequent cereal (kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">N fertiliser replacement value (kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Cowpea <xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">0.1&#x02013;2.7</td><td align="left">0.3&#x02013;2.1</td><td align="left">18&#x02013;96</td><td align="left">4&#x02013;201</td><td align="left">19&#x02013;150</td><td align="left">21&#x02013;49</td><td align="left">6&#x02013;125</td><td align="left">2&#x02013;59</td><td align="left">10&#x02013;80</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Groundnut <xref rid="tblfn0015" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td align="left">0.2&#x02013;2.1</td><td align="left">1.0&#x02013;3.1</td><td align="left">19&#x02013;79</td><td align="left">10&#x02013;124</td><td align="left">50&#x02013;145</td><td align="left">14&#x02013;45</td><td align="left">&#x02212;11&#x02013;43</td><td align="left">7&#x02013;73</td><td align="left">60&#x02013;67</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Soybean <xref rid="tblfn0020" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></td><td align="left">0.3&#x02013;2.4</td><td align="left">1.1&#x02013;3.9</td><td align="left">9&#x02013;96</td><td align="left">3&#x02013;302</td><td align="left">4&#x02013;110</td><td align="left">28&#x02013;84</td><td align="left">&#x02212;62&#x02013;89</td><td align="left">10&#x02013;77</td><td align="left">6&#x02013;65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pigeonpea <xref rid="tblfn0025" ref-type="table-fn">d</xref></td><td align="left">0.1&#x02013;2.9</td><td align="left">0.3&#x02013;7.9</td><td align="left">28&#x02013;100</td><td align="left">1&#x02013;97</td><td align="left">9&#x02013;103</td><td align="left">5&#x02013;44</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;82</td><td align="left">10&#x02013;33</td><td align="left">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Common bean <xref rid="tblfn0030" ref-type="table-fn">e</xref></td><td align="left">0.3&#x02013;1.3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">3&#x02013;56</td><td align="left">1&#x02013;31</td><td align="left">8&#x02013;19</td><td align="left">34&#x02013;87</td><td align="left">&#x02212;25&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Lablab <xref rid="tblfn0035" ref-type="table-fn">f</xref></td><td align="left">0.1&#x02013;1.4</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">48&#x02013;72</td><td align="left">54&#x02013;172</td><td align="left">41&#x02013;205</td><td align="left">9&#x02013;22</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;131</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Bambara nut <xref rid="tblfn0040" ref-type="table-fn">g</xref></td><td align="left">0.1&#x02013;0.6</td><td align="left">1.0&#x02013;3.2</td><td align="left">35&#x02013;72</td><td align="left">21&#x02013;68</td><td align="left">20&#x02013;99</td><td align="left">3&#x02013;35</td><td align="left">8&#x02013;57</td><td align="left">5&#x02013;24</td><td align="left">33</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0010"><label>a</label><p id="npar0015"><xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Adjei-Nsiah et al. (2008)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">Dakora et al. (1987)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0575" ref-type="bibr">Rusinamhodzi et al. (2006)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0510" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0540" ref-type="bibr">Pule-Meulenberg and Dakora (2009)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">Belane and Dakora (2010)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">Nyemba and Dakora (2010)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Bado et al. (2006a)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">Chikowo et al. (2004)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0390" ref-type="bibr">Makoi et al. (2009)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0700" ref-type="bibr">Vesterager et al. (2008)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">Ncube et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr">Laberge et al. (2011)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0455" ref-type="bibr">Naab et al. (2009)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0305" ref-type="bibr">Jones (1974)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Anyanzwa et al. (2010)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0730" ref-type="bibr">Yusuf et al. (2009b)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Adeboye et al. (2006)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">Kaleem (1989)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">Horst and H&#x000e4;rdter (1994)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr">Marandu et al. (2013)</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0015"><label>b</label><p id="npar0020"><xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">Dakora et al. (1987)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0510" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0540" ref-type="bibr">Pule-Meulenberg and Dakora (2009)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">Nyemba and Dakora (2010)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0435" ref-type="bibr">Mokgehle et al. (2014)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Bado et al. (2006a)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0305" ref-type="bibr">Jones (1974)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">MacColl (1989)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">Kaleem (1989)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">Ncube et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">Kaleem (1989)</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0020"><label>c</label><p id="npar0025"><xref rid="bib0500" ref-type="bibr">Oikeh et al. (2010)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0530" ref-type="bibr">Osunde et al. (2003)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0615" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al. (2003)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0525" ref-type="bibr">Okogun et al. (2005)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0510" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">Laberge et al. (2009)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr">Mapope and Dakora (2016)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0600" ref-type="bibr">Sanginga (2003)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">MacColl (1989)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0520" ref-type="bibr">Okereke and Eaglesham (1993)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">Kasasa et al. (1999)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0595" ref-type="bibr">Sanginga et al. (2002)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0735" ref-type="bibr">Zingore et al. (2008)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0730" ref-type="bibr">Yusuf et al. (2009b)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0645" ref-type="bibr">Thuita et al. (2012)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Adeboye et al. (2006)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">Carsky et al. (1997)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">Carsky et al. (1999)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">Kaleem (1989)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr">Mapope and Dakora (2016)</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0025"><label>d</label><p id="npar0030"><xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">Ncube et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">Chikowo et al. (2004)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">MacColl (1989)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">Cobbina (1995)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr">Mapfumo et al. (1999)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr">Marandu et al. (2013)</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0030"><label>e</label><p id="npar0035"><xref rid="bib0510" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">Nyemba and Dakora (2010)</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0035"><label>f</label><p id="npar0040"><xref rid="bib0510" ref-type="bibr">Ojiem et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">MacColl (1989)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0525" ref-type="bibr">Okogun et al. (2005)</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0040"><label>g</label><p id="npar0045"><xref rid="bib0540" ref-type="bibr">Pule-Meulenberg and Dakora (2009)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">Nyemba and Dakora (2010)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">Ncube et al. (2007)</xref>; <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">Kaleem (1989)</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="par0115">The belowground N contributions of legumes are often neglected in the calculation of N field balances of legume crops. The contribution of N through roots and rhizodeposits can be substantial, though the precise quantification is difficult (<xref rid="bib0715" ref-type="bibr">Wichern et al., 2008</xref>). In a review of literature, <xref rid="bib0715" ref-type="bibr">Wichern et al. (2008)</xref> found that on average 33% of the total plant N in legumes (average across different legume species) is found belowground with a range of 14 to 74%. A large part of that N, on average 64%, is found in rhizodeposits (exudates, sloughed off cells and fine roots). Nitrogen in rhizodeposits is readily available for plant uptake, while larger roots usually have high C-to-N ratios, decompose slowly and immobilise N over a prolonged period (e.g. <xref rid="bib0655" ref-type="bibr">Urquiaga et al. (1998)</xref>). Given that belowground plant-derived N of legumes usually remains in the field after crop harvest (with the exception of groundnut roots that may be removed from the field together with the stover), neglecting the belowground N contribution can substantially underestimate the field N balance of legumes. This could explain why the residual N effects of legumes can be larger than expected given the aboveground net N balance of the legumes. Belowground plant-derived N of soybean growing in the derived and Guinea savannah of West Africa was found to constitute 16% and 23% respectively of the total plant N, with 70% of the belowground N found in the rhizodeposits (<xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">Laberge et al., 2009</xref>). Adding belowground N to an N field balance of soybean, taking the N fixation rate into account and assuming stover remains in the field, changed the field balance from +2 to +13&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the derived savannah and from +56 to +95&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the northern Guinea savannah. Another study with cowpea in the Sudan savannah (<xref rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr">Laberge et al., 2011</xref>) reported that 52% of cowpea-derived N was located belowground (which seems a rather high proportion), with 85% of this N in rhizodeposits. Adding belowground N to the N field balance changed the balance from +9 to +22&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;N&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. We found no other studies from SSA that quantified belowground N contributions of legumes.</p></sec><sec id="sec0065"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Phosphorus</title><p id="par0120">An adequate supply of phosphorus is key for good growth and effective N<sub>2</sub>-fixation by legumes. While P fertiliser is needed in the P deficient soils of SSA, some legumes are able to mobilise less-labile forms of P compared with cereals. Recycling legume residues that contain P taken up by the legume can improve the P nutrition of a cereal in a cereal-legume rotation. Given that legume grain typically has a P concentration two to three times higher than that of the residues (<xref rid="bib0470" ref-type="bibr">Nijhof, 1987</xref>) and a harvest index of around 0.35 under normal growing conditions, about 35&#x02013;50% of the P in the aboveground parts is present in crop residues. Whereas most research focused on leguminous cover crops, among the grain legumes, cowpea (<xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">Jemo et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0545" ref-type="bibr">Pypers et al., 2006</xref>), soybean (<xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">Jemo et al., 2006</xref>), pigeonpea (<xref rid="bib0475" ref-type="bibr">Noriharu et al., 1990</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">Kamh et al., 2002</xref>, <xref rid="bib0560" ref-type="bibr">Richardson et al., 2009</xref>), chickpea (<xref rid="bib0560" ref-type="bibr">Richardson et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">Mat Hassan et al., 2012</xref>), faba bean (<xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">Mat Hassan et al., 2012</xref>) and white lupin (<xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">Gardner et al., 1983</xref>, <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">Braum and Helmke, 1995</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">Mat Hassan et al., 2012</xref>) have been found to access less-labile forms of P under P-deficient conditions. Grain legumes acquire poorly available P through three main mechanisms: i) mobilisation of non-labile P through the release of root exudates; ii) access to more of the labile P through a finer root architecture, and iii) enhanced associations with mycorrhiza. Lupin is unique among grain legumes in having cluster roots (<xref rid="bib0465" ref-type="bibr">Neumann et al., 2000</xref>) and is not discussed further. In addition to accessing less-labile forms of P, legumes can improve P acquisition by maize through modification of soil biological and chemical properties.</p><p id="par0125">Under P-deficient conditions, the roots of crops can release organic anions and organic acids that modify the chemistry of the rhizosphere and mobilise various forms of inorganic P. Exuded organic anions replace phosphate ions on sorption sites and mobilise P bound in humic-metal complexes (<xref rid="bib0560" ref-type="bibr">Richardson et al., 2009</xref>). In addition, <xref rid="bib0475" ref-type="bibr">Noriharu et al. (1990)</xref> and <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">Kamh et al. (2002)</xref> showed that pigeonpea can take up P from Fe/Al-phosphates through exudation of piscidic and malonic acid. The exudation of organic acids also lowers the pH of the rhizosphere, which may increase the solubility of P in some soils. H<sup>+</sup> released in the rhizosphere to counterbalance anions that leave decreases the pH of the soil solution (<xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">Hinsinger, 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Adeboye et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0550" ref-type="bibr">Pypers et al., 2007</xref>, <xref rid="bib0560" ref-type="bibr">Richardson et al., 2009</xref>). Especially N<sub>2</sub>-fixing legumes were found to have a net positive excess of cations over anions entering their roots and are therefore expected to release more H<sup>+</sup> than non-N<sub>2</sub>-fixing crops (<xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">Hinsinger, 2001</xref>). Faba bean, pigeonpea, chickpea, cowpea and white lupin have been found to release more and more effective organic acids than cereals (e.g.<xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">Gardner et al., 1983</xref>, <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">Jemo et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0545" ref-type="bibr">Pypers et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0560" ref-type="bibr">Richardson et al., 2009</xref>). Another way in which plants can mobilise P is by increased release of extracellular phosphatases that mineralise soil organic P in the rhizosphere (<xref rid="bib0560" ref-type="bibr">Richardson et al., 2009</xref>). <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">Kamh et al. (1999)</xref> and <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">Kamh et al. (2002)</xref> related efficient P acquisition of pigeonpea to its large phosphatase activity. <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">Jemo et al. (2006)</xref> related P-efficiency of soybean varieties to high activity of root surface phosphatases. The P mobilizing exudates released by legume roots turn over rapidly (<xref rid="bib0480" ref-type="bibr">Nuruzzaman et al., 2005</xref>). They can affect the P acquisition of an intercropped cereal, but it is unlikely that a subsequent cereal in a rotation directly benefits from P mobilizing root exudates. A change in pH, however, can affect the dissolution of P in a subsequent season, as hypothesised by <xref rid="bib0550" ref-type="bibr">Pypers et al. (2007)</xref>.</p><p id="par0130">With mechanisms similar to those used to access poorly available soil P, legumes can improve the utilisation of phosphate rock (PR) in a legume-cereal rotation under P-deficient conditions, leading to increased yield and P-uptake of a subsequent maize crop. <italic>Mucuna pruriens</italic> and lablab enhanced solubilisation of PR compared with maize (<xref rid="bib0665" ref-type="bibr">Vanlauwe et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib0550" ref-type="bibr">Pypers et al., 2007</xref>), probably due to decreases in soil pH induced by the legume (<xref rid="bib0550" ref-type="bibr">Pypers et al., 2007</xref>). Both studies report increases in the labile P pool of the topsoil after the legumes were grown, but the measures of P availability did not correspond with observed increases in yield and P uptake from the subsequent maize crop. Whereas <xref rid="bib0665" ref-type="bibr">Vanlauwe et al. (2000)</xref> concluded that legumes not only increase the immediately available P pool, but also less labile P pools, <xref rid="bib0550" ref-type="bibr">Pypers et al. (2007)</xref> suggest that the legume in the rotation has other positive, possible microbiological effects in the soil which enhanced maize growth.</p><p id="par0135">Differences in root morphology may account for changes in P uptake. <xref rid="bib0480" ref-type="bibr">Nuruzzaman et al. (2005)</xref> found that although faba bean was better at taking up P from the soil than maize, faba bean did not exudate much organic anions. Instead, the extensive root system of faba bean explored a large volume of soil and was able to access more P (and other nutrients) than maize. <xref rid="bib0570" ref-type="bibr">Rose et al. (2010)</xref> found that the strong P uptake from P efficient faba bean genotypes in an acid soil was strongly correlated with root growth traits. In soybean, variability in P uptake efficiencies between varieties has been associated with differences in root hair development (length and density) (<xref rid="bib0660" ref-type="bibr">Vandamme et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p id="par0140">Through associations with arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi, legume may access poorly available P. Differences in P uptake efficiency in soybean has been associated, to some extent, with colonisation by AM fungi (<xref rid="bib0660" ref-type="bibr">Vandamme et al., 2013</xref>). The cultivation of legumes in rotation with cereals may also lead to higher AM infection rates of cereal roots (see Section <xref rid="sec0100" ref-type="sec">3.3.3</xref>) which may help to enhance P uptake. <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Alvey et al. (2001)</xref> reported increased cereal shoot P concentrations and P uptake, together with higher AM infection rates in cereals following legumes, relative to continuous cereals in SSA.</p><p id="par0145">The effectiveness of mechanisms in enabling efficient uptake of P depends on soil characteristics. Different varieties of the same species may exploit different mechanisms to take up P. In an acid soil, efficient P uptake from P efficient faba bean genotypes was strongly correlated with root growth traits. In an alkaline soil, P efficient varieties had the highest malate exudation (<xref rid="bib0440" ref-type="bibr">Muhr et al., 2002</xref>, <xref rid="bib0570" ref-type="bibr">Rose et al., 2010</xref>). Only those P-efficient varieties increased subsequent maize yield (<xref rid="bib0570" ref-type="bibr">Rose et al., 2010</xref>). Also <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">Jemo et al. (2006)</xref> and <xref rid="bib0660" ref-type="bibr">Vandamme et al. (2013)</xref> reported that certain cowpea and soybean varieties are more efficient at taking up P than others.</p></sec><sec id="sec0070"><label>3.2.3</label><title>Other nutrients and pH</title><p id="par0150">While the legume tree <italic>Senna siamea</italic> has shown the ability to recycle Ca from a subsoil to the top soil in the West African derived savannah (<xref rid="bib0675" ref-type="bibr">Vanlauwe et al., 2005</xref>), it is unlikely that shallowly rooting annual grain legumes have such abilities. Legumes take up nutrients other than N and P and thereby influence the availability of these nutrients to a subsequent cereal crop, depending on nutrient removal rates and crop residue management. While in theory it is possible that legumes affect the availability of nutrients other than N and P through changes in soil structure or soil microbial activities, we found no evidence for such mechanisms.</p><p id="par0155">Legume have the ability to induce soil acidification (<xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">Haynes, 1983</xref>) (see also Section <xref rid="sec0065" ref-type="sec">3.2.2</xref>) and long-term legume pastures have been associated with declines in pH and increased levels of extractable manganese and aluminium potentially toxic to many agricultural plants (<xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">Bromfield et al., 1983</xref>). Soils that are already mildly acid and light-textured sandy soils are the most prone to acidification. While annual grain legumes also have a soil acidifying effect (<xref rid="bib0720" ref-type="bibr">Yan et al., 1996</xref>), a decline in soil pH should be less of a concern in an annual legume crop rotated with a cereal. Moreover, decomposition of legume residues can counteract soil acidification and even help to increase pH (<xref rid="bib0635" ref-type="bibr">Tang and Yu, 1999</xref>). As a result, legume-cereal rotations in SSA have been associated with a higher soil pH than continuous cereal rotation (<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Alvey et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">Marschner et al., 2004</xref>) with reported increases in pH between 0.1 and 1.3, though results are inconsistent with some reporting no changes in pH (<xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Bationo and Ntare, 2000</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec0075"><label>3.2.4</label><title>Soil organic matter, soil structure and soil moisture</title><p id="par0160">Compared with cereals, legume residues are relatively rich in N with a narrow C-to-N ratio. These characteristics favour rapid decomposition and release of N to subsequent crops. Further, the amount of residual biomass produced by grain legumes is usually less than that of cereals, giving less C input from grain legumes into the soil. Comparisons of soil C contents after legume-cereal rotations with continuous cereal cropping in SSA generally do not show significant differences (<xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Bationo and Ntare, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al., 2008</xref>, <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0725" ref-type="bibr">Yusuf et al., 2009a</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Anyanzwa et al., 2010</xref>), although this may be due to the limited duration (&#x0003c;4&#x000a0;years) of most trials. The main plausible way through which the incorporation of grain legumes into cereal-based system could enhance soil C contents is through an enhanced productivity of a subsequent cereal crop, or through intercropping systems with enhanced total biomass production (<xref rid="bib0590" ref-type="bibr">Samak&#x000e9; et al., 2006</xref>). Indirectly, the availability of legume residues at smallholder farms can facilitate integrated crop-livestock production, offering incentives for improved conservation of residues over dry seasons and enhanced C inputs through animal manure, especially in arid areas where most organic matter on the soil surface after crop harvest disappears during the dry season (<xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al., 2008</xref>). Enhancement of soil organic matter contents after grain legumes may results in changes in soil structure and soil moisture availability and in turn on yields of subsequent crops. Evidence for direct effects of legumes on soil structure is scarce. <xref rid="bib0450" ref-type="bibr">Mytton et al. (1993)</xref> observed an improvement in crumb structure of clay soils under grass-clover mixtures compared with pure grass swards in Wales. Grain legumes have been associated with a reduced water uptake and sparing of soil water, leading to increased water availability in a subsequent cereal, relative to continuous cereals (<xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al., 2002</xref>). We found no studies observing this in SSA, and this effect may not be relevant in large parts of SSA that have long dry seasons during which most soil available water gets depleted in the rooted zone. <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">Ncube et al. (2007)</xref> reported that grain legumes in a field experiment in Zimbabwe used more soil water than sorghum at a depth of 0&#x02013;55&#x000a0;cm, but differences in soil moisture disappeared after the first single large rain event at the start of the next growing season.</p></sec><sec id="sec0080"><label>3.2.5</label><title>Allelopathy</title><p id="par0165">The only case we could identify where deleterious residual impacts of legumes have been attributed to allelopathy is with mung bean (<italic>Vigna radiata)</italic> in continuous cropping (<xref rid="bib0710" ref-type="bibr">Waller et al., 1994</xref>) or on other crops (<xref rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr">Lertmongko et al., 2011</xref>). There appears to be no evidence of allelopathic effects with other grain legumes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0085"><label>3.3</label><title>Biotic factors</title><sec id="sec0090"><label>3.3.1</label><title>Weeds</title><p id="par0170">Green manure legumes, such as <italic>Mucuna pruriens, Pueraria phaseoloides</italic> and <italic>Desmodium</italic> spp., and fodder legumes, such as <italic>Stylosanthes guianensis</italic>, have the ability to effectively suppress obnoxious weeds in the derived savannah of West Africa (<xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">Chikoye and Ekeleme, 2003</xref>) and in East Africa (<xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">Kifuko-Koech et al., 2012</xref>). Grain legumes tend not to have the same weed-suppressing ability (<xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">Chikoye et al., 2008</xref>). In high input systems relying on herbicides for weed control, incorporating grain legumes into maize-based systems allows farmers to use herbicides with different modes of action, although this benefit is lost if glyphosate-resistant crops are grown continuously. As smallholders typically rely on weeding by hand or through animal traction, legume crops with enhanced weed-suppressing ability relative to other crops would be advantageous, but there is little evidence for this. However, legumes can be of great benefit in reducing the impact of parasitic weeds. In SSA, the obligate parasitic weeds <italic>Striga asiatica</italic> or <italic>S. hermonthica</italic> (both referred to as striga below) are widespread and cause massive yield loss in cereals.<xref rid="fn0005" ref-type="fn">1</xref></p><p id="par0175">Legumes are non-hosts of striga and appear to trigger &#x02018;suicidal&#x02019; germination of striga seed, thereby reducing the seedbank directly and preventing replenishment of the seedbank, while the longevity of striga seed in moist soil appears to be limited (<xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">Gb&#x000e8;hounou et al., 2003</xref>). Signalling molecules excreted by plant roots called strigolactones induce the germination of obligate parasitic plants such as striga, as well as the growth of beneficial AM fungi, that help the plant to access poorly-available soil P (<xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">Bouwmeester et al., 2007</xref>). A wide range of plant species including legumes excretes strigolactones. The presence of strigolactones can lead to suicidal germination of striga seed when excreted by a non-host, as striga needs to germinate within the close vicinity of the roots of a host plant to survive. The excretion of strigolactones is stimulated by P deficiencies. Plant exudates usually contain more than one strigolactone and differences in composition exist even within varieties (<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Awad et al., 2006</xref>), creating possibilities for breeders to screen legumes varieties for their ability to stimulate suicidal germination. However, given the multiple roles of strigolactones as signalling molecules and as growth regulators within the plant and the influence of the environment on the excretion of strigolactones (<xref rid="bib0585" ref-type="bibr">Ruyter-Spira et al., 2013</xref>), screening and selecting striga varieties for this ability is likely to be difficult. The reduction in striga seedbank resulting from a legume crop can strongly benefit the yield of a subsequent cereal crop (<xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">Ellis-Jones et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">Franke et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0580" ref-type="bibr">Rusinamhodzi et al., 2012</xref>). Natural fallows often harbour grass weeds that can serve as a host of striga attacking cereals, allowing striga to set seed and replenish its seed bank. Legume-cereal intercropping can help in suppressing striga, but the continued cultivation of a cereal in the field provides a host for striga (<xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">Carsky et al., 1994</xref>, <xref rid="bib0535" ref-type="bibr">Oswald, 2005</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">Kifuko-Koech et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="bib0425" ref-type="bibr">Midega et al., 2014</xref>). The boost in soil fertility from growing legumes also plays a strong role in rendering cereal crops less susceptible to damage by striga.</p></sec><sec id="sec0095"><label>3.3.2</label><title>Pests and diseases</title><p id="par0180">A reduced pest and diseases pressure for cereal crops is frequently mentioned as a key reason to rotate with grain legumes. Evidence of such benefits in SSA however is surprisingly limited. Rotating maize with cowpea or soybean has been found to increase attacks by stem borer (<italic>Busseola fascu</italic>) in maize in southern Cameroon (<xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">Chabi-Olaye et al., 2005a</xref>). The improved nutritional status of maize plants rotated with legumes appeared to increase attacks, but also improved plant vigour resulting in a net benefit for the plant. Intercropping cereals with non-host legumes, such as lablab, cowpea, soybean, or other non-host crops, such as cassava, does help to reduce attacks by Lepidopterous stem borer including <italic>Busseola fascu</italic> in different parts of SSA (<xref rid="bib0620" ref-type="bibr">Skovg&#x000e5;rd and P&#x000e4;ts, 1996</xref>, <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">Chabi-Olaye et al., 2005b</xref>, <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr">Maluleke et al., 2005</xref>), most likely by disrupting host-plant finding (<xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">Calatayud et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="par0185">The best studied impacts of legumes on pests and diseases concern impacts on nematodes. Nematodes can substantially limit cereal productivity and nematode population density and damage potential increase with cereal cropping intensity (<xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">Coyne and Plowright, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib0630" ref-type="bibr">Talwana et al., 2008</xref>). Although a wide range of nematode pests is associated with cereals, only a few are of economic importance, depending on geography and circumstances. In SSA, various studies confirm the negative impact of nematodes on maize, mostly <italic>Pratylenchus</italic> spp. and <italic>Meloidogyne</italic> spp. (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Afolami and Fawole, 1991</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">Kagoda et al., 2011</xref>). These nematodes however tend to have wide host ranges including legumes and various weed species, limiting the possibilities to use rotational legumes to control them (<xref rid="bib0705" ref-type="bibr">Viaene et al., 2013</xref>). Moreover, these nematodes can damage legumes&#x02019; growth abilities as well. <italic>Meloidogyne</italic> spp. for instance has been found to reduce soybean&#x02019;s ability to fix atmospheric N<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">Coyne and Oyekanmi, 2007</xref>).</p><p id="par0190">Studies from SSA (all conducted in West Africa) do not provide a consistent picture regarding grain legumes&#x02019; ability to suppress parasitic nematodes. <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Bagayoko et al. (2000)</xref> observed that groundnut reduces parasitic nematode populations in a groundnut/sorghum intercrop systems, relative to sole sorghum in the Sudano-Sahelian zone, whereas sole groundnut had the lowest nematode population densities, indicating groundnut is a poor host for the nematode groups assessed (<italic>Helicotylenchus</italic> sp., <italic>Rotylenchus</italic> sp. and <italic>Pratylenchus</italic> sp.). Cowpea intercropped with millet on the other hand did not appear to suppress nematodes or even exacerbated nematode pressure in millet. This is in line with <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Bado et al. (2011)</xref> who found that cowpea-sorghum rotations increased nematode counts in sorghum by 1.5&#x02013;2.0 times, while groundnut-sorghum rotation reduced counts in the sorghum rhizosphere and roots 17 to 19 times, relative to continuous sorghum. <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Alvey et al. (2001)</xref> reported 60&#x02013;80 times more nematodes in roots of continuously-cropped millet than that in roots of millet following cowpea or groundnut in the Sudano-Sahelian zone. They did not distinguish between the two legume crops. <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">Marschner et al. (2004)</xref> on the other hand found inconsistent effects of groundnut on nematode densities in rotational maize and sorghum crops, relative to continuous cereal, in soils from the Sudan and the Guinea savannah.</p></sec><sec id="sec0100"><label>3.3.3</label><title>Other effects on the soil microbiota</title><p id="par0195">DNA techniques such as PCR-DGGE have shown that bacterial species composition in soil under rotation is clearly distinct from soils under continuous cereal cultivation in SSA (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Alvey et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">Marschner et al., 2004</xref>). Grain legume-cereal systems in SSA have been associated with changes such as higher AM infection rates (<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Bagayoko et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Alvey et al., 2001</xref>) with up to 20% more roots infected, higher soil bacterial C and N levels (<xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">Marschner et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Adeboye et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0725" ref-type="bibr">Yusuf et al., 2009a</xref>), a lower microbial biomass C-to-N ratio (<xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">Marschner et al., 2004</xref>) and a higher fungal biomass (<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Adeboye et al., 2006</xref>) in the rhizosphere of cereals, relative to continuous cereals. Apart from direct effects on symbionts such as rhizobia or mycorrhiza that for instance help plants to access soil P (see Section <xref rid="sec0065" ref-type="sec">3.2.2</xref>), it is unclear what changes in soil microbe populations contribute to cereal growth (<xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">Marschner et al., 2004</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec0105"><label>4</label><title>Final remarks and recommendations</title><p id="par0200">Our review of the literature shows that rotational benefits of grain legumes on cereal yields are substantial and widespread. While there may be a positive bias in reporting, the consistent responses at multiple sites differing in climate or soil fertility provide strong support that cereal yields are enhanced after grain legumes. The residual effects of grain legumes should take a prominent place when evaluating the pros and cons of sustainable intensification with grain legumes. We did not consider some of the wider cropping and farming system effects of grain legumes in this review. For instance, grain legumes can make up an important component of an ISFM strategy increasing overall crop productivity and soil fertility beyond N benefits (<xref rid="bib0680" ref-type="bibr">Vanlauwe et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0690" ref-type="bibr">Vanlauwe et al., 2015</xref>). While grain legumes on their own are unlikely to increase soil organic matter contents (see Section <xref rid="sec0075" ref-type="sec">3.2.4</xref>), increased residue inputs as a result of a successful ISFM strategy can do so. Residues of grain legumes also play an important role in integrated crop-livestock systems, which offer opportunities and challenges to optimise natural resource use and organic input applications to crops (<xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">Duncan et al., 2016</xref>). We did not consider grain legume-cereal intercropping systems which are common in parts of SSA (e.g. common bean-maize mixed cropping in East Africa and cowpea relay cropping in cereals in West Africa). While the N<sub>2</sub>-fixing capacities of grain legumes are maintained in an intercrop, though at a lower rate due to competition with the cereal, the benefits of grain legumes as a non-host of pests, diseases and striga in cereals could be strongly reduced.</p><p id="par0205">Future research on N<sub>2</sub>-fixation by grain legumes and residual N benefits in SSA should focus on explaining the wide variability observed between sites. We retrieved only two studies that assessed residual benefits on a relatively large (&#x0003e;15) number of farmers&#x02019; fields (<xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">Kolawole et al., 2007</xref>, <xref rid="bib0740" ref-type="bibr">van Vugt et al., 2017</xref>) and only the latter study attempted to disentangle the factors behind the observed variability. Measuring the rotational effects along with the relevant covariates on a large number of farmers&#x02019; fields, for instance through simple two-treatment (legume-cereal vs. continuous cereal) comparisons (<xref rid="bib0695" ref-type="bibr">Vanlauwe et al., in press</xref>), would provide better understanding of the sources of variability in rotational effects under farmers&#x02019; diverse environmental and socio-economic conditions (e.g. see <xref rid="bib0565" ref-type="bibr">Ronner et al. (2016)</xref> on legume responses to inputs). As there is a fair understanding of mechanisms how grain legumes can affect P availability in the subsequent cereal, future research should focus on assessing if and where these mechanisms are relevant in farmers&#x02019; fields. The other non-N benefits of grain legumes are still poorly quantified and understood in SSA, with the exception of legumes&#x02019; impact on striga population dynamics. Clearly, there is a need for more detailed mechanistic studies to highlight non-N effects, particularly in relation to common pests and diseases in cereals. Also in relation to biotic factors, a key question is if and under which conditions benefits of enhanced pest and disease suppression can be expected to occur in farmers&#x02019; fields.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adeboye</surname><given-names>M.K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwuafor</surname><given-names>E.N.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbenin</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of crop rotation and nitrogen fertilization on soil chemical and microbial properties in a Guinea savanna alfisol of Nigeria</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>281</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>107</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adjei-Nsiah</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuyper</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leeuwis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abekoe</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating sustainable and profitable cropping sequences with cassava and four legume crops: effects on soil fertility and maize yields in the forest/savannah transitional agro-ecological zone of Ghana</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><volume>103</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adjei-Nsiah</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuyper</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leeuwis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abekoe</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobbinah</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakyi-Dawson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Farmers&#x02019; agronomic and social evaluation of productivity, yield and N<sub>2</sub>-fixation in different cowpea varieties and their subsequent residual N effects on a succeeding maize crop</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>80</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>209</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afolami</surname><given-names>S.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fawole</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic>Pratylenchus sefaensis</italic> Fortuner 1973 on growth and yield of <italic>Zea mays</italic> L. cv. FARZ-7 under continuous cropping</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>138</volume><year>1991</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>138</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagayoko</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buerkert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cereal/legume rotations affect chemical properties and biological activities in two West African soils</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>231</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>54</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buerkert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cereal/legume rotation effects on rhizosphere bacterial community structure in west African soils</article-title><source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source><volume>37</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anyanzwa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okalebo</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Othieno</surname><given-names>C.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waswa</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of conservation tillage, crop residue and cropping systems on changes in soil organic matter and maize&#x02013;legume production: a case study in Teso District</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>88</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>47</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusumoto</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamioka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>k.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of strigolactones, germination stimulantd for the root parasitic plants <italic>Striga</italic> and <italic>Orobanche</italic>, produced by maize, millet and sorghum</article-title><source>Plant Growth Regul.</source><volume>48</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>227</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bado</surname><given-names>B.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cescas</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of cowpea and groundnut contributions to soil fertility and succeeding sorghum yields in the Guinean savannah zone of Burkina Faso (West Africa)</article-title><source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source><volume>43</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>176</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bado</surname><given-names>B.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lompo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segda</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedogo</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cescas</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Long-term effects of cropping systems and fertilization on crop production, soil characteristics and nitrogen cycling in the Guieans and Sudanian savannah zones of Burkina Faso (West Africa)</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Management Practices for Improving Sustainable Crop Production in Tropical Acid Soils</source><year>2006</year><publisher-name>International Atomic Energy Agency</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bado</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawadogo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thio</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Troare</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cescas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nematode infestation and N-effect of legumes on soil and crop yields in legume-sorghum rotations</article-title><source>Agric. Sci.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bado</surname><given-names>B.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cescas</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedogo</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cescas</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Traore</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of legumes on nitrogen (N) fertilizer recommendations for succeeding sorghum in the Guinea savannah of West Africa</article-title><source>Afr. J. Agric. Res.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>6416</fpage><lpage>6421</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagayoko</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Traore</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eskridge</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pearl millet/cowpea cropping systems yield and soil nutrient levels</article-title><source>Afr. Crop Sci. J.</source><volume>4</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>462</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagayoko</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buerkert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lung</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;mheld</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cereal/legume rotation effects on cereal growth in Sudano-Sahelian West Africa: soil mineral nitrogen, mycorrhizae and nematodes</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>218</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>116</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntare</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rotation and nitrogen fertilizer effects on pearl millet, cowpea and groundnut yield and soil chemical properties in a sandy soil in the semi-arid tropics, West Africa</article-title><source>J. Agric. Sci.</source><volume>134</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>284</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belane</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakora</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Symbiotic N2 fixation in 30 field-grown cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> L: Walp.) genotypes in the Upper West Region of Ghana measured using 15N natural abundance</article-title><source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source><volume>46</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>198</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bloem</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trytsman</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological nitrogen fixation in resource-poor agriculture in South Africa</article-title><source>Symbiosis</source><volume>48</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Raez</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;card</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rhizosphere communication of plants, parasitic plants and AM fungi</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braum</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>White lupin utilizes soil phosphorus that is unavailable to soybean</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>176</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bromfield</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cumming</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Change in soil pH, manganese and aluminium under subterranaen clover pasture</article-title><source>Aust. J. Exp. Agric. Anim. Husb.</source><volume>23</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>191</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calatayud</surname><given-names>P.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Ru</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulthess</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecology of the African maize stalk borer, <italic>Busseola fusca</italic> (Lepidoptera: noctuidae) with special reference to insect-plant interactions</article-title><source>Insects</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26462824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carsky</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndikawa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suppression of <italic>Striga hermonthica</italic> on sorghum using a cowpea intercrop</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><volume>30</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>358</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carsky</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abaidoo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dashiell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen contribution of soybean crop on subsequent maize in the Guinea savanna zone</article-title><source>Afr. Crop Sci. J.</source><volume>5</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carsky</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyewole</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrated soil management for the savanna zone of W: Africa: legume rotation and fertilizer N</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>55</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>105</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carsky</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyewole</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of early season cowpea to late season maize in the savanna zone of West Africa</article-title><source>Biol. Agric. Hortic.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>315</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chabi-Olaye</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulthess</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgemeister</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of grain legumes and cover crops on maize yield and plant damage by <italic>Busseola fusca</italic> (Fuller) (Lepidoptera: noctuidae) in the humid forest of southern Cameroon</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><volume>108</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chabi-Olaye</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulthess</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgemeister</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationships of intercropped maize, stem borer damage to maize ield and land-use efficiency in the humid forest of Cameroon</article-title><source>Bull. Entomol. Res.</source><volume>95</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16197562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chalk</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peoples</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boddey</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Unkovich</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardener</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methodologies for estimating nitrogen transfer between legumes and companion species in agro-ecosystems: a review of 15-N enriched techniques</article-title><source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source><volume>73</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil nitrogen dynamics and crop residues. A review</article-title><source>Agron. Sustain. Dev.</source><volume>34</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>442</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chianu</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nkonya</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mairura</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chianu</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akinnifesi</surname><given-names>F.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological nitrogen fixation and socioeconomic factors for legume production in sub-Saharan Africa: a review</article-title><source>Agron. Sust. Dev.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>154</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chikowo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mapfumo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyamugafata</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Woody legume fallow productivity, biological N<sub>2</sub>-fixation and residual benefits to two successive maize crops in Zimbabwe</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>262</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>315</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chikoye</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekeleme</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cover crops for cogongrass (<italic>Imperata cylindrica</italic>) management and effects on subsequent corn yield</article-title><source>Weed Sci.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>797</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chikoye</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekeleme</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lum</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Legume-maize rotation and nitrogen effects on weed performance in the humid and subhumid tropics of West Africa</article-title><source>Crop Prot.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>647</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cobbina</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbage yield of pigeonpea (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic>) accessions in a humid tropical environment as affected by pruning management</article-title><source>J. Agric. Sci.</source><volume>125</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>232</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyekanmi</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Symbiotic nitrogen fixation of two soybean genotypes as affected by root-knot nematodes and microsymbionts</article-title><source>J. Biol. Sci.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1226</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0180"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plowright</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nematode threats to intensifying smallholder upland rice production in the Guinea savannah of C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire</article-title><source>Trop. Sci.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dakora</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keya</surname><given-names>S.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of legume nitrogen fixation to sustainable agriculture in Sub-Saharan Africa</article-title><source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source><volume>29</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>817</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0190"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dakora</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aboyinga</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Apaseku</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of N2 fixation in groundnut (<italic>Arachis hypogaea</italic> L.) and cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> L. Walp) and their relative N contribution to a succeeding maize crop in Northern Ghana</article-title><source>MIRCEN J. Appl. Microbiol. Biotech.</source><volume>3</volume><year>1987</year><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>399</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0195"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dercon</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pypers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Loon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merckx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihou</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Improving sustainable intensification of cereal-grain legume cropping systems in the savannahs of West Africa: quantifying residual effects of legumes on maize, enhancing P mobilization by legumes and studying long-term soil organic matter (som) dynamics</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Management Practices for Improving Sustainable Crop Production in Tropical Acid Soils</source><year>2006</year><publisher-name>International Atomic Energy Agency</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0200"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulliver</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Improving Farmers' Livelihoods in a Changing World</chapter-title><year>2001</year><publisher-name>FAO/World Bank</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rome and Washington DC</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0205"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachewe</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekonnen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valbuena</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachier</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lule</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erenstein</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crop residue allocation to livestock feed, soil improvement and other uses along a productivity gradient in Eastern Africa</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><volume>228</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>110</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0210"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebanyat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jager</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delve</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bekunda</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of heterogeneity in soil fertility on legume-finger millet productivity, farmers&#x02019; targeting and economic benefits</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>87</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>231</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0215"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellis-Jones</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Douthwaite</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussaini</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyewole</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olanrewaju</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An assessment of integrated <italic>Striga hermonthica</italic> control and early adoption by farmers in northern Nigeria</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>368</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0220"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis-Jones</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarawali</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussaini</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kureh</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chikoye</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Douthwaite</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyewole</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olanrewaju</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating and scaling-up integrated <italic>Striga hermonthica</italic> control technologies among farmers in northern Nigeria</article-title><source>Crop Prot.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>868</fpage><lpage>878</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0225"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laberge</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyewole</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison between legume technologies and fallow, and their effects on maize and soil traits, in two distinct environments of the West African savannah</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>82</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0230"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwuafor</surname><given-names>E.N.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nziguheba</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dercon</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandeplas</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does crop-livestock integration lead to improved crop productivity in the savanna of West Africa?</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>455</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0235"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Brand</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Which farmers benefit most from sustainable intensification?: An ex-ante impact assessment of expanding grain legume production in Malawi</article-title><source>Europ. J. Agron.</source><volume>58</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0240"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parbery</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The acquisition of phosphorus by <italic>Lupinus albus</italic> L</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>70</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>124</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0245"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gb&#x000e8;hounou</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verkleij</surname><given-names>J.A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Longevity of Striga seeds reconsidered: results from a field study on purple witchweed (<italic>Striga hermonthica</italic>) in Benin</article-title><source>Weed Sci.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>940</fpage><lpage>946</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0250"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadisch</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fiuture benefits from biological nitrogen fixation: an ecological approach</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>174</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>277</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0255"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadisch</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehaliotis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakala</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mafongoya</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Building soil nitrogen capital in Africa</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Buresh</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Replenishing Soil Fertility in Africa</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>ASA, CSSA, SSSA</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Madison, Wisconsin</publisher-loc><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>192</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0260"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abaidoo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baijukya</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boahen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dashiell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kantengwa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wolf</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woomer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>N2Africa: putting nitrogen fixation to work for smallholder farmers in Africa</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Asten</surname><given-names>P.J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blomme</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Agro-ecological Intensification of Agricultural Systems in the African Highlands</source><year>2013</year><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>174</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0265"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment and improvement of nitrogen fixation in tropical <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L</article-title><source>Soil Use Manag.</source><volume>6</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0270"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Nitrogen Fixation in Tropical Cropping Systems</chapter-title><edition>2nd edition</edition><year>2001</year><publisher-name>CABI Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Wallingford, UK</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0275"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some problems of nodulation and symbiotic nitrogen fixation in <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.: a review</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><year>1981</year><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0280"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil acidification induced by leguminous crops</article-title><source>Grass Forage Sci.</source><volume>38</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0285"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinsinger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioavailability of soil inorganic P in the rhizosphere as affected by root-induced chemical changes: a review</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>237</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>195</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0290"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0290"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e4;rdter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rotation of maize with cowpea improves yield and nutrient use of maize compared to maize monocropping in an alfisol in the northern Guinea Savanna of Ghana</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>160</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>183</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0295"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jibrin</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chude</surname><given-names>V.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agronomic measures for increasing P availability to crops</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>237</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>223</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0300"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0300"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jemo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abaidoo</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchienkoua</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorus benefits from grain-legume crops to subsequent maize grown on acid soils of southern Cameroon</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>284</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>397</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0305"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0305"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of previous crop on yield and nitrogen response of maize at Samaru, Nigeria</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><volume>10</volume><year>1974</year><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0310"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0310"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kagoda</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derera</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tongoona</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of resistance to nematodes in inbred maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) and maize hybrids</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><volume>182</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>393</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0315"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0315"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaleem</surname><given-names>F.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Assessment of Nitrogen Fixtion by Legumes and Their Relative N Contribution to a Succeeding Maize Crop., Annual Report 1988/89</chapter-title><year>1989</year><publisher-name>Nynkpala Agricultural Experimental Station</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Tamale, Ghana</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0320"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0320"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamanga</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waddington</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk analysis of maize-legume crop combinations with smallholder farmers varying in resource endowment in central Malawi</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0325"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0325"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostafa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mobilization of soil and fertilizer phosphate by cover crops</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>211</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>27</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0330"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0330"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chude</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiesler</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mobilization of phosphorus contributes to positive rotational effects of leguminous cover crops on maize grown on soils from northern Nigeria</article-title><source>J. Plant Nutr. Soil Sci.</source><volume>165</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>572</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0335"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0335"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasasa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mpepereki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Musiyiwa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makonese</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Residual nitrogen benefits of promiscuous soybeans to maize under field conditions</article-title><source>Afr. Crop Sci. J.</source><volume>7</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>382</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0340"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0340"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kifuko-Koech</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pypers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okalebo</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Othieno</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Z.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kipkoech</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of Desmodium spp. and cutting regimes on the agronomic and economic performance of Desmodium-maize intercropping systems in western Kenya</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><volume>137</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>107</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0345"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0345"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waswa</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimetu</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chianu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stragetic phosphorus application in legume-cereal rotations increases land productivity and profitability in Western Kenya</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0350"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0350"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkegaard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krpinsky</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Layzell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Break crop benefits in temperate wheat production</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><volume>107</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>195</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0355"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0355"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klaij</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntare</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rotation and tillage effects on yield of pearl millet (<italic>Pennisetum glaucum</italic>) and cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic>), and aspects of crop water balance and soil fertility in a semi-arid tropical environment</article-title><source>J. Agric. Sci.</source><volume>124</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0360"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0360"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolawole</surname><given-names>G.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manyong</surname><given-names>V.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugbabe</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallays</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dercon</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwuafor</surname><given-names>E.N.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Falaki</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merckx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deckers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollens</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Balanced nutrient management system technologies in the northern Guinea savanna of Nigeria: validation and perspective</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waswa</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimetu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Advances in Integrated Soil Fertility Management in Sub-Saharan Africa: Challenges and Opportunities</source><year>2007</year><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</publisher-loc><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>678</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0365"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0365"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kouyat&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franzluebbers</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juo</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossner</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tillage, crop residue, legume rotation, and green manure effects on sorghum and millet yields in the semiarid tropics of Mali</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>225</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>151</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0370"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0370"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laberge</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambus</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f8;gh-Jensen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen rhizodeposition from soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic>) and its impact on nutrient budgets in two contrasting environments of the Guinean savannah zone of Nigeria</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>84</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>58</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0375"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0375"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laberge</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haussmann</surname><given-names>B.I.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambus</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f8;gh-Jensen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cowpea N rhizodeposition and its below-ground transfer to a co-existing and to a subsequent millet crop on a sandy soil of the Sudano-Sahelian eco-zone</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>340</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>382</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0380"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0380"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lertmongko</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarobol</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Premasthira</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allelopathic effecs of mungbean (<italic>Vigna radiata</italic>) on subsequent crops</article-title><source>Kasetsart J. Nat. Sci.</source><volume>45</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>773</fpage><lpage>779</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0385"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0385"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacColl</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) at bunda: Malawi.II . yield in short rotations with legumes</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><volume>25</volume><year>1989</year><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>374</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0390"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0390"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makoi</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chimphango</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakora</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of legume plant density and mixed culture on symbiotic N2 fixation in five cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> L: Walp.) genotypes in South Africa</article-title><source>Symbiosis</source><volume>48</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0395"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0395"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maluleke</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addo-Bediako</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayisi</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of maize/lablab intercropping on Lepidopterous stem borer infestation in maize</article-title><source>J. Econ. Entomol.</source><volume>98</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15889728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0400"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0400"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mapfumo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mpepereki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mafongoya</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dinitrogen fixation by pigeonpea of different maturity types on granitic sandy soils in Zimbabwe</article-title><source>Symbiosis</source><volume>27</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>318</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0405"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0405"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mapope</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakora</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>N<sub>2</sub> fixation, carbon accumulation, and plant water relations in soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic> L. Merrill) varieties sampled from farmers' fields in South Africa, measured using <sup>15</sup>N and <sup>13</sup>C adundance</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><volume>221</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0410"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0410"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marandu</surname><given-names>A.E.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Semu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mrema</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyaki</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of legume rotations to the nitrogen requirements of a subsequent maize crop on a rhodic ferralsol in Tanga, Tanzania</article-title><source>Tanzania J. Agric. Sci.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0415"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0415"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marschner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joergensen</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piepho</surname><given-names>H.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buerkert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Legume rotation effects on early growth and rhizosphere microbiology of sorghum in West African soils</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>264</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>334</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0420"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0420"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mat Hassan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marschner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grain legume pre-crops and their residues affect the growth, P uptake and size of P pools in the rhizosphere of the following wheat</article-title><source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source><volume>48</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>785</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0425"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0425"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Midega</surname><given-names>C.A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salifu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittchar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Z.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cumulative effects and economic benefits of intercropping maize with food legumes on <italic>Striga hermonthica</italic> infestation</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><volume>155</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>152</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0430"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0430"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waddington</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derksen</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cropping sequence affects wheat productivity on the semiarid northern Great Plains</article-title><source>Can. J. Plant Sci.</source><volume>82</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>318</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0435"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0435"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mokgehle</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakora</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in N<sub>2</sub> fixation and N contribution by 25 groundnut (<italic>Arachis hypogaea</italic> L.) varieties grown in different agro-ecologies: measured using 15N natural abundance</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><volume>195</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>172</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0440"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0440"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muhr</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarawali</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultze-Kraft</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil mineral N dynamics and maize grain yields following Centrosema macrocarpum and Stylosanthes guianensis: effects of different rotations and varying levels of N fertiliser</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><volume>78</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>209</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0445"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0445"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mupangwa</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Twomlow</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced tillage, mulching and rotational effects on maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.): cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> (Walp) L.) and sorghum (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> L. (Moench)) yields under semi-arid conditions</article-title><source>Field Crops Res.</source><volume>132</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>148</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0450"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0450"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mytton</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cresswell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colbourn</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvement in soil structure associated with white clover</article-title><source>Grass Forage Sci.</source><volume>48</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0455"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0455"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naab</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chimphango</surname><given-names>S.M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakora</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>N2 fixation in cowpea plants grown in farmers' fields in the Upper West Region of Ghana, measured using 1N natural abundance</article-title><source>Symbiosis</source><volume>48</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0460"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0460"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ncube</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Twomlow</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimes</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Productivity and residual benefits of grain legumes to sorghum under semi-arid conditions in southwestern Zimbabwe</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>299</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0465"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0465"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Massonneau</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langlade</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinkelaker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hengeler</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romveld</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinoia</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological aspects of cluster root function and development in phosphorus-deficient white lupin (<italic>Lupinus albus</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Ann. Bot.</source><volume>85</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>919</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0470"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0470"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nijhof</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The Concentration of Macro-Elements in Economic Products and Residues of (sub)Tropical Field Crops</chapter-title><year>1987</year><publisher-name>Staff working paper Centre for World Food Studies</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Wageningen, the Netherlands</publisher-loc><fpage>52</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0475"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0475"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noriharu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arihara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshihara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorus uptake by pigeon pea and its role in cropping systems of the Indian subcontinent</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>248</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17815599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0480"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0480"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nuruzzaman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambers</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veneklaas</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorus benefits of different legume crops to subsequent wheat grown in different soils of Western Australia</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>271</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>187</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0485"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0485"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyemba</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakora</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating N2 fixation by food grain legumes in farmers&#x02019; fields in three agro-ecological zones of Zambia, using 15N natural abundance</article-title><source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source><volume>46</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>470</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0490"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0490"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogoke</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carsky</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Togun</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dashiell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of P fertilizer application on N balance of soybean crop in the guinea savanna of Nigeria</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><volume>100</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>159</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0495"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0495"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oikeh</surname><given-names>S.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chude</surname><given-names>V.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carsky</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Legume rotation in the moist tropical savanna: managing soil nitrogen dynamics and cereal yields in farmers' fields</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><volume>34</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>83</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0500"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0500"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oikeh</surname><given-names>S.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houngnandan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abaidoo</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimou</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tour&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akintayo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrated soil fertility management involving promiscuous dual-purpose soybean and upland NERICA enhanced rice productivity in the savannas</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>88</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0505"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0505"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ojiem</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Socio-ecological niche: a conceptual framework for the integration of legumes in smallholder farming systems</article-title><source>Int. J. Agric. Sustain.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>93</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0510"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0510"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ojiem</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Niche-based assessment of contributions of legumes to the nitrogen economy of Western Kenya smallholder farms</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>292</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0515"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0515"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ojiem</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benefits of legume&#x02013;maize rotations: assessing the impact of diversity on the productivity of smallholders in Western Kenya</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><volume>168</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0520"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0520"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okereke</surname><given-names>G.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaglesham</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nodulation and nitrogen fixation by 79 promiscuous soyabean genotypes in a soil in East Nigeria</article-title><source>Agron. Afr.</source><volume>2</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>136</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0525"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0525"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okogun</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abaidoo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dashiell</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On-farm evaluation of biological nitrogen fixation potential and grain yield of Lablab and two soybean varieties in the northern Guinea savanna of Nigeria</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>73</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>275</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0530"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0530"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osunde</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okogun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responses to rhizobial inoculation by two promiscuous soybean cultivars in soils of the Southern Guinea savanna zone of Nigeria</article-title><source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source><volume>37</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0535"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0535"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oswald</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Striga control &#x02212; technologies and their dissemination</article-title><source>Crop Prot.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>342</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0540"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0540"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pule-Meulenberg</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakora</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the symbiotic dependency of grain and tree legumes on N2 fixation for their N nutrition in five agro-ecological zones of Botswana</article-title><source>Symbiosis</source><volume>48</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0545"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0545"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pypers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Loon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abaidoo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolders</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merckx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant-available p for maize and cowpea in P-deficient soils from the Nigerian northern Guinea Savanna&#x02013;comparison of E-and L-values</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>283</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>264</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0550"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0550"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pypers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huybrighs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abaidoo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolders</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merckx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does the enhanced P acquisition by maize following legumes in a rotation result from improved soil P availability?</article-title><source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>2555</fpage><lpage>2566</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0555"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0555"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathuva</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Legumes for improving maize yields and income in semi-arid Kenya</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><volume>78</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>137</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0560"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0560"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hocking</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant mechanisms to optimise access to soil phosphorus</article-title><source>Crop Past. Sci.</source><volume>60</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>143</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0565"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0565"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ronner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dianda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edeh</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ukem</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Heerwaarden</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding variability in soybean yield and response to P-fertilizer and rhizobium inoculants on farmers' fields in northern Nigeria</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><volume>186</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>145</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0570"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0570"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Damon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rengel</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorus-efficient faba bean (<italic>Vicia faba</italic> L.) genotypes enhance subsequent wheat crop growth in an acid and an alkaline soil</article-title><source>Crop Past. Sci.</source><volume>61</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1009</fpage><lpage>1016</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0575"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0575"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rusinamhodzi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murwira</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyamangara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cotton&#x02013;cowpea intercropping and its N<sub>2</sub> fixation capacity improves yield of a subsequent maize crop under Zimbabwean rain-fed conditions</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>287</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>336</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0580"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0580"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rusinamhodzi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbeels</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyamangara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maize&#x02013;grain legume intercropping is an attractive option for ecological intensification that reduces climatic risk for smallholder farmers in central Mozambique</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><volume>136</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0585"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0585"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruyter-Spira</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Babili</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Krol</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biology of strigolactones</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23182342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0590"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0590"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samak&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stomph</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kropff</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smaling</surname><given-names>E.M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrated pearl millet management in the Sahel: effects of legume rotation and fallow management on productivity and Striga hermonthica infestation</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>286</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>257</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0595"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0595"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okogun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dashiell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The contribution of nitrogen by promiscuous soybeans to maize based cropping the moist savanna of Nigeria</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>241</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>231</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0600"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0600"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of biological nitrogen fixation in legume based cropping systems; a case study of West Africa farming systems</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>252</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0605"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0605"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauerborn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprich</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercer-Quarshie</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crop rotation to improve agricultural production in sub-Saharan Africa</article-title><source>J. Agron. Crop Sci.</source><volume>184</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0610"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0610"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shatar</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McBratney</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Boundary-line analysis of field-scale yield response to soil properties</article-title><source>J. Agric. Sci.</source><volume>142</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>560</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0615"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0615"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carsky</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dashiell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil N balance as affected by soybean maturity class in the Guinea savanna of Nigeria</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><volume>100</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>240</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0620"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0620"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skovg&#x000e5;rd</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e4;ts</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of intercropping on maize stemborers and their natural enemies</article-title><source>Bull. Entomol. Res.</source><volume>86</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>607</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0625"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0625"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snapp</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silim</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Farmer preferences and legume intensification for low nutrient environments</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>245</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>192</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0630"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0630"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talwana</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butseya</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tusiime</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Occurence of plant parasitic nematodes and factors that enhance population build-up in cereal-based cropping systems in Uganda</article-title><source>Afr. Crop Sci. J.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0635"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0635"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of chemical composition of legume residues and initial soil pH on pH change of a soil after residue incorporation</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>215</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0640"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0640"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thierfelder</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheesman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusinamhodzi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative analysis of conservation agriculture systems: benefits and challenges of rotations and intercropping in Zimbabwe</article-title><source>Field Crop Res.</source><volume>137</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>250</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0645"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0645"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thuita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pypers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okalebo</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Othieno</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muema</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesueur</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Commercial rhizobial inoculants significantly enhance growth and nitrogen fixation of a promiscuous soybean variety in Kenyan soils</article-title><source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source><volume>48</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>96</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0650"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0650"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traore</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Descheemaeker</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbeels</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rufino</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate variability and change in southern Mali: learning from farmer perceptions and on-farm trials</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>634</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0655"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0655"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urquiaga</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadisch</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>B.J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boddey</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of decomposition of roots of tropical forage species on the availability of soil nitrogen</article-title><source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source><volume>3</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>2099</fpage><lpage>2106</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0660"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0660"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renkens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pypers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolders</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merckx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Root hairs explain P uptake efficiency of soybean genotypes grown in a P-deficient Ferralsol</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>369</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>282</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0665"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0665"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nwoke</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carsky</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deckers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merckx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of rock phosphate by crops on a representative toposequence in the Northern Guinea savanna zone of Nigeria: response by <italic>Mucuna pruriens</italic>, <italic>Lablab purpureus</italic> and maize</article-title><source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source><volume>32</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>2063</fpage><lpage>2077</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0670"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0670"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Combined Application of Organic Matter and Fertilizer. Sustaining Soil Fertility in West Africa. SSSA Special Publication No. 58</chapter-title><year>2001</year><publisher-name>Soil Science Society of America and America Society of Agronomy</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Madison, USA</publisher-loc><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0675"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0675"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihou</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tossah</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merckx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Senna siamea</italic> trees recycle Ca from a Ca-rich subsoil and increase topsoil pH in agroforestry systems in the West African derived savanna zone</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><volume>269</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>296</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0680"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0680"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bationo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chianu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merckx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokwunye</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohiokpehai</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pypers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smaling</surname><given-names>E.M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woomer</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrated soil fertility management Operational definition and consequences for implementation and dissemination</article-title><source>Outlook Agric.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0685"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0685"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gockowski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huising</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masso</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nziguheba</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Asten</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable intensification and the smallholder African farmer</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Environ. Sustain.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0690"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0690"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Descheemaeker</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huising</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merckx</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nziguheba</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zingore</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrated soil fertility management in sub-Saharan Africa: unravelling local adaptation</article-title><source>Soil</source><volume>1</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>508</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0695"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0695"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanlauwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond averages: new approaches to understand heterogeneity and risk of technology success or failure in smallholder farming</article-title><source>Expl. Agric.</source><year>2017</year><comment>in press</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0700"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0700"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vesterager</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f8;gh-Jensen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of cropping history and phosphorus source on yield and nitrogen fixation in sole and intercropped cowpea&#x02013;maize systems</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>80</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0705"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0705"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viaene</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Biological and cultural control</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plant Nematology</source><edition>2nd edition</edition><year>2013</year><publisher-name>CAB International</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>410</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0710"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0710"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y.F.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Allelopathic activity of naturally occurring compounds frommung bean (<italic>Vigna radiata</italic>) and their surrounding soil</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Inderjit</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakshini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Einhellig</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Allelopathy: Organisms, Processs and Applications</source><year>1994</year><publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>257</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0715"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0715"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wichern</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberhardt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joergensen</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen rhizodeposition in agricultural crops Methods, estimates and future prospects</article-title><source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0720"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0720"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil pH changes during legume growth and application of plant material</article-title><source>Biol. Fertil. Soils</source><volume>23</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>242</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0725"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0725"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abaidoo</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwuafor</surname><given-names>E.N.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olufajo</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rotation effects of grain legumes and fallow on maize yield: microbial biomass and chemical properties of an Alfisol in the Nigerian savanna</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><volume>129</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>331</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0730"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0730"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwuafor</surname><given-names>E.N.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abaidoo</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olufajo</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanginga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grain legume rotation benefits to maize in the northern Guinea savanna of Nigeria: fixed-nitrogen versus other rotation effects</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>84</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>139</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0735"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0735"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zingore</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murwira</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delve</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variable grain legume yields, responses to phosphorus and rotational effects on maize across soil fertility gradients on African smallholder farms</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosyst.</source><volume>80</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0740"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0740"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Vugt</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giller</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding variability in the benefits of BNF and soybean-maize rotations on smallholder farmers' fields in Malawi</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><year>2017</year><comment>in press, (this issue)</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Prof. Robert Schall from the University of the Free State for his contributions to the statistical analysis. We thank the <funding-source id="gs0005">Bill &#x00026; Melinda Gates Foundation</funding-source> for funding through a grant to Wageningen University to support the project N2Africa: Putting Nitrogen Fixation to Work for Smallholder Farmers in Africa (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.N2Africa.org" id="intr0005">www.N2Africa.org</ext-link>).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn0005"><label>1</label><p id="npar0005"><italic>Striga gesnerioides</italic> attacks cowpea and is not discussed here.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>