<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with OASIS Tables v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing-oasis-article1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Commun Integr Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Commun Integr Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KCIB</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">kcib20</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Communicative &#x00026; Integrative Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1942-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6132424</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1502586</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19420889.2018.1502586</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mapping of quantitative trait loci related to primary rice root growth as a response to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">S. MASUDA ET AL.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">COMMUNICATIVE &#x00026; INTEGRATIVE BIOLOGY</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>Sachiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>Kazuhiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kazama</surname><given-names>Yuri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kisara</surname><given-names>Chiharu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>Shoko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>Eiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Minamisawa</surname><given-names>Kiwamu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Tadashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0004"><sup>d</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="AFF0001"><label>a</label><institution>Graduate School of Life Sciences, Tohoku University</institution>, Sendai, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="AFF0002"><label>b</label><institution>RIKEN, Center for Sustainable Resource Science</institution>, Yokohama City, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="AFF0003"><label>c</label><institution>Institute for Sustainable Agro-ecosystem Services, Graduate School of Agricultural and Life Sciences, The University of Tokyo</institution>, Tokyo, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="AFF0004"><label>d</label><institution>Graduate School of Agricultural Science, Tohoku University</institution>, Sendai, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">CONTACT Kazuhiro Sasaki <email xlink:href="sasaki@isas.a.u-tokyo.ac.jp">sasaki@isas.a.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email><institution>Institute for Sustainable Agro-ecosystem Services, Graduate School of Agricultural and Life Sciences, The University of Tokyo</institution>, <addr-line>1-1-1, Midoricho, Nishitokyo</addr-line>, Tokyo, 188-0002, <country>Japan</country></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage seq="8">1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="kcib-11-03-1502586.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p><italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510 has been known as the plant growth-promoting endophyte; however, the growth-promotion effect is dependent on the plant genotype. Here, we aimed to identify quantitative trait loci (QTL) related to primary root length in rice at the seedling stage as a response to inoculation with B510. The primary root length of &#x0201c;Nipponbare&#x0201d; was significantly reduced by inoculation with B510, whereas that of &#x0201c;Kasalath&#x0201d; was not affected. Thus, we examined 98 backcrossed inbred lines and four chromosome segment substitution lines (CSSL) derived from a cross between Nipponbare and Kasalath. The primary root length was measured as a response to inoculation with B510, and the relative root length (RRL) was calculated based on the response to non-inoculation. Three QTL alleles, <italic>qRLI-6</italic> and <italic>qRLC-6</italic> on Chromosome (Chr.) 6 and <italic>qRRL-7</italic> on Chr. 7 derived from Kasalath increased primary root length with inoculation (RLI), without inoculation, (RLC) and RRL and explained 20.2%, 21.3%, and 11.9% of the phenotypic variation, respectively. CSSL33, in which substitution occurred in the vicinity region of <italic>qRRL-7</italic>, showed a completely different response to inoculation with B510 compared with Nipponbare. Therefore, we suggest that <italic>qRRL-7</italic> might strongly control root growth in response to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>Primary rice root growth</kwd><kwd>quantitative trait locus</kwd><kwd><italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510</kwd><kwd>plant growth-promoting bacteria</kwd><kwd>plant genotype</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry, and Fisheries</named-content></funding-source><award-id>PMI-0002</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="25"/><page-count count="6"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Bacterial endophytes ubiquitously colonize the internal tissues of plants worldwide [<xref rid="CIT0001">1</xref>]. The beneficial effects of endophytes on host plants, such as increased crop yield and protection from pathogens, have been well characterized [<xref rid="CIT0001">1</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0002">2</xref>]. The genus <italic>Azospirillum</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0003">3</xref>] promotes plant growth and is thus used as a plant-promoting agronomic application [<xref rid="CIT0004">4</xref>]. <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510 was isolated from the surface-sterilized stem of a rice plant (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) [<xref rid="CIT0005">5</xref>]. This bacterium can increase the disease resistance of the host plant [<xref rid="CIT0006">6</xref>] and promote the growth of newly generated leaf and shoot biomass in rice plants under greenhouse conditions [<xref rid="CIT0007">7</xref>]. Under field conditions, <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 increases tiller numbers in rice, resulting in grain yield increases of 17% [<xref rid="CIT0007">7</xref>]. However, inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 can reduce rice plant growth depending on plant genotype and environmental conditions; inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 significantly increased the tiller number in most indica cultivars, whereas tiller numbers in several japonica cultivars were significantly decreased under standard nitrogen fertilization [<xref rid="CIT0008">8</xref>]. These results suggested that yield enhancements could be link to the combinations of strains and host plant genotypes as well as nitrogen fertilization level. Indeed, inoculation of 12 mustard (<italic>Brassica juncea</italic> L.) genotypes with a mixture of <italic>Azospirillum</italic> strains showed biomass changes of &#x02013; 30% to 160%, compared with the control [<xref rid="CIT0009">9</xref>]. The differential growth yields depended on strain-host genotype combinations were also observed in maize, wheat, and rice [<xref rid="CIT0010">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="CIT0012">12</xref>]. They are likely controlled via strong interactions between the plant and <italic>Azospirillum</italic>. However, the molecular mechanisms or genetic loci associated with responses to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> strains in different rice cultivars have not yet been identified.</p><p>Colonization studies suggested that endophytes use the natural cracks at the lateral roots and root hairs emergence site as entry sites in rhizosphere [<xref rid="CIT0013">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="CIT0015">15</xref>]. Thus, plant-endophyte interaction actively occurs in the rhizosphere. Successful inoculation results in changes the root morphology and phytohormonal balance which are also attributed to successful inoculation [<xref rid="CIT0016">16</xref>]. <italic>A. brasilense</italic> Sp245 inhibits root growth of wheat, whereas the root length is recovered as similar length to control when a mutant strain lacking indole acetic acid (IAA) productivity is inoculated [<xref rid="CIT0017">17</xref>]. These results suggest that the effect on root growth is due to IAA produced by <italic>A. brasilense</italic> Sp245. <italic>Azospirillum</italic> inoculation changes the pro&#x0fb01;les of rice secondary metabolites [<xref rid="CIT0018">18</xref>] and the transcriptional level of genes related to auxin and ethylene signaling depend on the combination of bacterial strain and plant genotype [<xref rid="CIT0016">16</xref>]. Therefore, root morphology and secondary metabolite pro&#x0fb01;ling such as plant hormones revealed specific responses of host plant to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> strains.</p><p>In the present study, we clarified that inoculation of Nipponbare, japonica cultivar, and Kasalath, indica cultivar, with B510 resulted in differences in primary root growth. In Nipponbare, inoculation with B510 showed a negative effect; primary root growth was delayed compared to plants which were not inoculated. In contrast, when Kasalath was inoculated, primary root growth showed little or no change compared to plants without inoculation. To identify quantitative trait loci (QTL) related to the primary root growth in rice we used 98 backcrossed inbred lines (BILs) and four chromosome segment substitution lines (CSSL9, CSSL31, CSSL32, and CSSL33) derived from a cross between Nipponbare and Kasalath. We evaluated primary root growth as an index of response to inoculation with B510. Our results might generate new insights into the interaction of <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. with the host plant.</p></sec><sec id="S0002"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="S0002-S2001"><title>Plant materials</title><p>A total of 98 BILs and four CSSLs derived from a cross between the <italic>indica</italic> rice cultivar Kasalath and the <italic>japonica</italic> rice cultivar Nipponbare were used. These lines were developed by the Rice Genome Project of the National Institute of Agrobiological Sciences, Japan and kindly provided along with information on their genotypic profiles by the Rice Genome Resource Centre (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rgrc.dna.affrc.go.jp/">http://www.rgrc.dna.affrc.go.jp/</ext-link>). BILs, CSSLs, and the parental cultivars were grown and harvested in paddy fields of the Experimental Farm Station, Graduate School of Life Sciences, Tohoku University, Kashimadai, Osaki, Miyagi, Japan.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2002"><title>Bacterial inoculation and plant growth condition</title><p><italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 was cultured in nutrient broth (Difco Laboratories, Detroit, MI, USA) at 30&#x000b0;C for 16&#x000a0;h, centrifuged at 5,000 rpm for 3&#x000a0;min, washed twice with sterile distilled water, and a bacterial suspension was prepared in sterile water. The bacterial suspension was diluted to 1.3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>7</sup>&#x02013;1.3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>2</sup> cells ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to examine the dose response of B510 on the parental cultivars, Nipponbare and Kasalath. A concentration range of 1.6&#x02013;3.6&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup> cells ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was used for the inoculation of BILs and CSSLs. Rice seeds were germinated on two filter papers (Toyo Roshi Kaisha Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) in a Petri dish (6 cm in diameter). The filter papers and petri dishes were autoclaved at 121&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;min before use. The seeds by immersion in water at 55&#x000b0;C for 20&#x000a0;min and then, in 2.4% sodium hypochlorite (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Osaka, Japan) for 15&#x000a0;min. Finally, the seeds were rinsed over 5 times and shaken 3 times for 5&#x000a0;min each with sterile water. Ten seeds were placed on filter papers, inoculated with 5&#x000a0;ml of the bacterial suspension at different concentrations if needed, and incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 2 d. We treated the seeds with 5&#x000a0;ml of sterile water as a control (without inoculation). A rice seed with or without B510 inoculation was placed on a 0.25% agarose gel (Wako Pure Chemical Industries) with 1/10 strength hydroponic solution [<xref rid="CIT0019">19</xref>] in a glass tube and incubated at 26&#x000b0;C for 6 d in a growth chamber (light 16h, dark 8h). Each inoculation experiment was performed with 5 plants. After incubation, the primary root length was measured, and the relative root length was calculated as follows:</p><p>Relative root length (RRL) (%)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;average of root length with inoculation (RLI)/average of root length without inoculation (RLC) &#x000d7;&#x000a0;100.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2003"><title>Genotyping and QTL analysis</title><p>BILs were genotyped using 245 genome-wide restriction fragment length polymorphisms (RFLPs) as described by Lin et al. [<xref rid="CIT0020">20</xref>]. Linkage analysis was performed using Mapmaker/EXP 3.0 [<xref rid="CIT0021">21</xref>], whereas QTL analysis using QTL Cartographer 2.5 [<xref rid="CIT0022">22</xref>]. For composite interval mapping, the log-likelihood (LOD) thresholds (2.9 for root length with inoculation and 3.1 for root length with no inoculation and relative root length) were selected from 1,000 permutations tested at the 5% level. The percentage of total phenotypic variation explained by QTL was estimated for each trait and expressed by the <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> value. Two QTL positions on the same chromosome were considered different when the distance of the nearest marker was greater than 10 cM. To confirm the effect of <italic>qRRL-7</italic>, RLC and RLI were compared in CSSLs substituted with Kasalath segments in the vicinity of region <italic>qRRL-7</italic> in a Nipponbare genetic background. Significant differences between RLC and RLI in each CSSL and parental line were calculated using <italic>t</italic>-tests (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;10).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S0003"><title>Results</title><p>The primary root growth of Nipponbare was significantly reduced in response to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 (<xref rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>). The primary root growth of Nipponbare in response to inoculation with 10<sup>2</sup> cells ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was lower than 40&#x000a0;mm, whereas that without inoculation was 118&#x000a0;mm (<xref rid="F0001">Figure 1(a</xref>,<xref rid="F0001">c</xref>,<xref rid="F0001">e</xref>)). In contrast, the primary root growth of Kasalath was slightly decreased with the increasing <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 concentration, but no significant differences were observed (<xref rid="F0001">Figure 1(a</xref>,<xref rid="F0001">d</xref>,<xref rid="F0001">f</xref>). To identify the gene trait loci of primary root growth in response to <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 inoculation, we subsequently inoculated to BILs and CSSLs with this bacterium at the concentration of 10<sup>6</sup> cells ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Length of primary root growth is used as an index of QTL analysis.<fig id="F0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19420889.2018.1502586-F0001</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Root length and relative root length of &#x0201c;Nipponbare&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Kasalath&#x0201d; seedlings in response to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510 (10<sup>2</sup> cells ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) compared with the control (without inoculation) at 6&#x000a0;days post-inoculation. (a) Root length of Nipponbare (open circle) and Kasalath (closed circle) seedlings (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5); (b) Relative root length of Nipponbare (open bar) and Kasalath (closed bar) seedlings. Nipponbare (c and e) and Kasalath (d and f) seedlings with (c and d) or without (e and f) inoculation.</p></caption><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="kcib-11-03-1502586-g001"/></fig></p><p>The frequency distribution of RLI, RLC, and RRL showed continuous variation (<xref rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>). Based on this phenotypic variation, QTL analyzes were performed, and two putative QTL associated with RLI, one QTL associated with RLC, and one QTL associated with RRL were detected (<xref rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>, <xref rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>). The putative QTL for RLI were mapped near C724 on Chromosome (Chr.) 1 (<italic>qRLI-1</italic>) and near R1888 on Chr. 6 (<italic>qRLI-6</italic>); for RLC near R1608 on Chr. 6 (<italic>qRLC-6</italic>); and for RRL near R1789 on Chr. 7 (<italic>qRRL-7</italic>) (<xref rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>). The alleles <italic>qRLI-6, qRLC-6</italic>, and <italic>qRRL-7</italic> derived from Kasalath increased RLI, RLC, and RRL and explained 20.2%, 21.3%, and 11.9% of the phenotypic variation, respectively (<xref rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>). The allele <italic>qRLI-1</italic> derived from Nipponbare increased RLI and explained 9.7% of the phenotypic variation (<xref rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19420889.2018.1502586-T0001</object-id><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Location and effect of quantitative trait loci (QTLs) related to the root length in response to inoculation or no inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510 and the relative root length.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Trait <sup>a</sup></th><th align="center">QTL</th><th align="center">Chr.</th><th align="center">Interval <sup>b</sup></th><th align="center" char=".">LOD</th><th align="center" char="."><italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic>&#x000a0;<sup>c</sup> (%)</th><th align="center" char="."><italic>A</italic>&#x000a0;<sup>d</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">RLI</td><td align="center"><italic>qRLI-1</italic></td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center"><italic>R2414/<underline>C724</underline></italic></td><td align="char" char=".">3.4</td><td align="char" char=".">9.7</td><td align="char" char=".">19.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center"><italic>qRLI-6</italic></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center"><italic>R11/<underline>R1888</underline></italic></td><td align="char" char=".">6.2</td><td align="char" char=".">20.2</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;25.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RLC</td><td align="center"><italic>qRLC-6</italic></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center"><italic>R1888/<underline>R1608</underline></italic></td><td align="char" char=".">6.2</td><td align="char" char=".">21.3</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;31.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RRL</td><td align="center"><italic>qRRL-7</italic></td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center"><italic>R1789/C596</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">3.7</td><td align="char" char=".">11.9</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;29.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup> RLI, root length in response to inoculation; RLC, root length in response to no inoculation, RRL, relative root length</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup> The nearest RFLP marker to the QTL is underlined.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>c</sup> Proportion of the phenotypic variation explained by the nearest marker of QTL.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>d</sup> Additive effect of the allele from Nipponbare compared with that from Kasalath.</p></fn><fn><p>* Putative QTLs with significant LOD scores on 1,000 permutations tested at the 5% level.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="F0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19420889.2018.1502586-F0002</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Frequency distribution of (a) root length in response to without inoculation; (b) root length in response to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510; and (c) relative root length of 98 backcrossed inbred lines derived from a cross between &#x0201c;Kasalath&#x0201d; (black arrowhead) and &#x0201c;Nipponbare&#x0201d; (white arrowhead).</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="kcib-11-03-1502586-g002"/></fig><fig id="F0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19420889.2018.1502586-F0003</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Mapping of quantitative trait loci (QTL) for root length in response to without inoculation (RLC) or inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510 (RLI), and relative root length (RRL) on a rice linkage map. Black, white, and grey boxes indicate the QTL region for RLI, RLC, and RRL, respectively. Box length indicates the 1-LOD confidence interval of putative QTL. White and black arrowheads show the positions of LOD peaks that indicate positive alleles from &#x0201c;Nipponbare&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Kasalath,&#x0201d; respectively.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="kcib-11-03-1502586-g003"/></fig></p><p>To confirm the effect of <italic>qRRL-7</italic>, we compared the primary root growth of Nipponbare, Kasalath, CSSL9, CSSL31, CSSL32, and CSSL33. CSSL9, CSSL31, and CSSL32 showed a significantly lower RLI than RLC, whereas RRL ranged from 0.5% to 12.8% with no significant differences compared with that of Nipponbare. In contrast, the RRL of CSSL33 was 165.4% and significantly different from that of Nipponbare and other CSSLs. Based on the phenotypic and genotypic data of CSSLs, we mapped the location of <italic>qRRL-7</italic> between C847 and C213 (<xref rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, the primary root growth of Nipponbare and Kasalath responded to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510. The bacterium caused a stronger reduction in root length in Nipponbare at much lower inoculum concentrations (10<sup>2</sup> cells ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <xref rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>) but not in Kasalath. The B510 triggers the induction of the genes potentially involved in hormone signaling such as auxin, salicylic acid and ethylene in rice roots, the transcriptional changes of those genes, however, is dependent on rice cultivar [<xref rid="CIT0016">16</xref>]. The expression of the genes such as auxin and ethylene signaling genes are downregulated when B510 is inoculated to Nipponbare. These results suggested that root growth inhibition of Nipponbare by B510 could depend on the plant hormones.</p><p>We succeeded to map QTL related to primary rice root growth in response to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510. On the long arm of Chr. 6, we detected a QTL for RLI (<italic>qRLI-6</italic>) as well as a QTL for RLC (<italic>qRLC-6</italic>) based on the phenotypic variation of BILs in the primary root growth in response to with or without B510 inoculation, respectively. These results indicate that <italic>qRLC-6</italic> controls the primary root growth at the early seedling stage and probably affects <italic>qRLI-6</italic> in this study. In this region, a major QTL, namely <italic>qRL6.1</italic>, associated with root length has been previously detected in a population derived from a cross between the <italic>japonica</italic> cultivar Koshihikari and Kasalath [<xref rid="CIT0023">23</xref>]. The allele <italic>qRL6.1</italic> derived from Kasalath increased the root length in response to various nitrogen concentrations under hydroponic conditions [<xref rid="CIT0023">23</xref>]. The allele <italic>qRLC-6</italic> might be identical to <italic>qRL6.1</italic>, since both QTLs are derived from Kasalath and increased the root growth under the different condition such as hydroponic and glass tube conditions. We also detected a QTL for RRL (<italic>qRRL-7</italic>) that explained the variation in the primary root growth between Nipponbare and Kasalath. Therefore, <italic>qRRL-7</italic> might strongly control root growth in response to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 and explain related differences between Nipponbare and Kasalath. The allelic effect of <italic>qRRL-7</italic> was also confirmed based on the phenotype of CSSL33 (<xref rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>). CSSL33, which substituted the vicinity region of <italic>qRRL-7</italic>, showed completely different response to inoculation with B510 compared with Nipponbare. Based on the phenotypic and genotypic data of CSSLs, we succeeded to map the location of <italic>qRRL-7</italic> between C847 and C213 (<xref rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>). In the candidate genomic region of <italic>qRRL-7</italic>, the expression of <italic>Os07g0664000</italic> is induced by B510 inoculation in <italic>japonica</italic> cultivars [<xref rid="CIT0016">16</xref>]. <italic>Os07g0664000</italic> probably encodes short-chain dehydrogenases/reductases, which are enzymes of the NAD(P)(H)-dependent oxidoreductases family [<xref rid="CIT0024">24</xref>]. In the amino acid sequences of <italic>Os07g0664000</italic> in Nipponbare and Kasalath, two amino acid substitutions (R55G and R113H) were found between them (Figure S1). These results suggested that those amino acid residues may be involved in the different primary root growth by B510 inoculation. In addition, <italic>Os07g0664000</italic> expressed as well by infection with the fungus phytopathogen <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0025">25</xref>]. Therefore, <italic>qRRL-7</italic> might be also involved in the interaction of microorganisms, including bacteria and fungi, with the host plant. However, further research is needed to validate whether <italic>Os07g0664000</italic> is the responsible gene of <italic>qRRL-7</italic> and also reveal the underlying molecular mechanism that controls the root growth in response to <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 inoculation on Nipponbare and Kasalath. To this end, using inoculated CSSL33 with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510 and evaluating agronomic traits, including the tiller number, under paddy field conditions might help to understand the function of <italic>qRRL-7</italic>.<fig id="F0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19420889.2018.1502586-F0004</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Graphical representation of the root length of &#x0201c;Nipponbare,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Kasalath,&#x0201d; and chromosome segment substitution lines (CSSLs) in response to no inoculation (white) or inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510 (grey). Percentages indicate the relative root length of each line. * and *** indicate significant differences between no inoculation and inoculation at <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001, respectively.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="kcib-11-03-1502586-g004"/></fig></p><p>Overall, inoculation with B510 increased the tiller number of a <italic>japonica</italic> rice cultivar, resulting in increased grain yield under paddy field conditions [<xref rid="CIT0007">7</xref>]. However, the positive effect on the tiller number has been found to depend on rice genotype [<xref rid="CIT0008">8</xref>]. Thus, expanding the practical usage of bio-fertilizers, including <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510, requires an understanding of the mechanisms of interaction between rice genotypes and inoculants.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="S0005"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors.</p></sec><sec id="S0006" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>Supplementary data for this article can be accessed <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19420889.2018.1502586">here</ext-link>.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM7966"><caption><title>Supplemental Material</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="kcib-11-03-1502586-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d37e952" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santoyo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno-Hagelsieb</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>del Carmen Orozco-Mosqueda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Plant growth-promoting bacterial endophytes</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Res</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>183</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26805622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Community-and genome-based views of plant-associated bacteria: plant-bacterial interactions in soybean and rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>1398</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20685969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baldani</surname><given-names>JI.</given-names></name></person-group>
<chapter-title>The genus <italic>Azospirillum</italic></chapter-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>, editors. <source>The Prokaryotes</source>. <publisher-loc>New York (NY)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labandera-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Agronomic applications of <italic>Azospirillum</italic>: an evaluation of 20 years worldwide field inoculation</article-title>. <source>Soil Biol Biochem</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1601</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbeltagy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Endophytic colonization and in planta nitrogen fixation by a <italic>Herbaspirillum</italic> sp. isolated from wild rice species</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>5285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11679357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minamisawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Effects of colonization of a bacterial endophyte, <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. B510a on disease resistance in rice</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2599</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Awazaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title><italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510 enhances rice growth and yield</article-title>. <source>Microbe Environ</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Impact of plant genotype and nitrogen level on rice growth response to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> sp. strain B510 under paddy field conditions</article-title>. <source>Soil Sci Plant Nutr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>636</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>644</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesava Rao</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arunachalam</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tilak</surname><given-names>KVBR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Genotype-dependent response to <italic>Azospirillum</italic> treatment in yield and nitrogenase activity in <italic>Brassica juncea</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr Sci</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>609</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia De Salomone</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobereiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Maize genotype effects on the response to <italic>Azospirillum</italic> inoculation</article-title>. <source>Biol Fert Soils</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattarai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Yield responses of Nepalese spring wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) cultivars to inoculation with <italic>Azospirillum</italic> spp. of Nepalese origin</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>EPB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Didonet</surname><given-names>CCG</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Agronomical performance of upland rice cultivars inoculated with <italic>Azospirillum brasilense</italic> depends on the plant genotype</article-title>. <source>Commun Soil Sci Plant Anal</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1762</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broek</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gool</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Spatial-temporal colonization pattern of <italic>Azospirillum brasilense</italic> on the wheat root surface and expression of the bacterial <italic>nifH</italic> gene during association</article-title>. Mol Plant Microbe Interact. <year>1993</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>592</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>600</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steenhoudt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderleyden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Azospirillum, a free-living nitrogen-fixing bacterium closely associated with grasses: genetic, biochemical and ecological aspects</article-title>. FEMS Microbiol Rev. <year>2000</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>506</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morisaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Endophytic bacteria in the rice plant</article-title>. <source>Microbe Environ</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drogue</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanguin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chamam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Plant root transcriptome profiling reveals a strain-dependent response during <italic>Azospirillum</italic>-rice cooperation</article-title>. Front Plant Sci. <year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spaepen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobbelaere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Croonenborghs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Effects of <italic>Azospirillum brasilense</italic> indole-3-acetic acid production on inoculated wheat plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>312</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanguin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bellvert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Plant secondary metabolite profiling evidences strain-dependent effect in the <italic>Azospirillum-Oryza sariva</italic> association</article-title>. Phytochemistry. <year>2012</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mae</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohira</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The remobilization of nitrogen related to leaf growth and senescence in rice plants (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1067</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1074</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mapping quantitative trait loci controlling seed dormancy and heading date in rice, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L., using backcross inbred lines</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>997</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1003</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrahamson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>MAPMAKER: an interactive computer package for constructing primary genetic linkage maps of experimental and natural populations</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3692487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>Windows QTL Cartographer 2.5 [internet]</source>. <publisher-loc>North Carolina (NC)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Statistics, North Carolina State University</publisher-name>; [<comment>cited</comment>
<year>2010</year>
<month>10</month>
<day>20</day>]. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://statgen.ncsu.edu/qtlcart/WQTLCart.htm">http://statgen.ncsu.edu/qtlcart/WQTLCart.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Obara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebitani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Fine-mapping of qRL6.1, a major QTL for root length of rice seedlings grown under a wide range of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> concentrations in hydroponic conditions</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>547</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20390245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Witzel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weidner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Surabhi</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Comparative analysis of the grain proteome fraction in barley genotypes with contrasting salinity tolerance during germination</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sawers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oakeley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Tissue-adapted invasion strategies of the rice blast fungus Magnaporthe oryzae</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>3177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3187</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20858844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>