<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6323737</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-018-1589-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome-wide dynamic network analysis reveals a critical transition state of flower development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Fuping</given-names></name><address><email>zhangfuping16@mails.ucas.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiaoping</given-names></name><address><email>xpliu@sdu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Aidi</given-names></name><address><email>zhangaidi@wbgcas.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Zhonglin</given-names></name><address><email>13121397123@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Luonan</given-names></name><address><email>lnchen@sibs.ac.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8041-0592</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiujun</given-names></name><address><email>zhangxj@wbgcas.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000119573309</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9227.e</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Plant Germplasm Enhancement and Specially Agriculture, Wuhan Botanical Garden, </institution><institution>Chinese Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, 430074 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1797 8419</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410726.6</institution-id><institution>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, 10049 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000119573309</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9227.e</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Systems Biology, Innovation Center for Cell Signaling Network, Institute of Biochemistry and Cell Biology, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, </institution><institution>Chinese Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, 200031 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>11</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The flowering transition which is controlled by a complex and intricate gene regulatory network plays an important role in the reproduction for offspring of plants. It is a challenge to identify the critical transition state as well as the genes that control the transition of flower development. With the emergence of massively parallel sequencing, a great number of time-course transcriptome data greatly facilitate the exploration of the developmental phase transition in plants. Although some network-based bioinformatics analyses attempted to identify the genes that control the phase transition, they generally overlooked the dynamics of regulation and resulted in unreliable results. In addition, the results of these methods cannot be self-explained.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">In this work, to reveal a critical transition state and identify the transition-specific genes of flower development, we implemented a genome-wide dynamic network analysis on temporal gene expression data in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> by dynamic network biomarker (DNB) method. In the analysis, DNB model which can exploit collective fluctuations and correlations of different metabolites at a network level was used to detect the imminent critical transition state or the tipping point. The genes that control the phase transition can be identified by the difference of weighted correlations between the genes interested and the other genes in the global network. To construct the gene regulatory network controlling the flowering transition, we applied NARROMI algorithm which can reduce the noisy, redundant and indirect regulations on the expression data of the transition-specific genes. In the results, the critical transition state detected during the formation of flowers corresponded to the development of flowering on the 7th to 9th day in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Among of 233 genes identified to be highly fluctuated at the transition state, a high percentage of genes with maximum expression in pollen was detected, and 24 genes were validated to participate in stress reaction process, as well as other floral-related pathways. Composed of three major subnetworks, a gene regulatory network with 150 nodes and 225 edges was found to be highly correlated with flowering transition. The gene ontology (GO) annotation of pathway enrichment analysis revealed that the identified genes are enriched in the catalytic activity, metabolic process and cellular process.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">This study provides a novel insight to identify the real causality of the phase transition with genome-wide dynamic network analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-018-1589-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Time-course gene expression data</kwd><kwd>Gene regulatory network (GRN)</kwd><kwd>Dynamical network biomarker (DNB)</kwd><kwd>Phase transition</kwd><kwd>Flower development</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>61402457</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiujun</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Project of Cause Control Theory</institution></funding-source><award-id>1716315XJ00200303</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiujun</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>CAS Pioneer Hundred Talents Program</institution></funding-source><award-id>201601</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiujun</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par13">The flowering plants undergo a succession of developmental phases during their life cycle including germination, seedling, flowering and fruiting. As a special pattern of plant development, phase transition is crucial for the survival and reproduction of the plant, and the failure implementation of phase transition will result in the dysfunction of development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The phase transitions related to plant development include the seed-to-seedling transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], the juvenile-to-adult vegetative transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], the vegetative-to-reproductive transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], the heterotrophic-to-autotrophic transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], the initiation-to-maturation floral transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and so on. These developmental phase transitions form the main functional mechanisms in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">Among the developmental phase transitions, flowering transition has been extensively studied by the experimental biologists because flowering is an irreversible transformation from vegetative to reproductive growth, an important qualitative process, a key stage of plant development, and a reproduction for offspring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The flowering process include three phases, i.e. the floral induction phase, the floral primordia phase, and the floral organs development phase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. During these phases, a series of genes such as flowering time controlling genes, meristem identity genes and floral organ identity genes are involved in the regulation of flowering transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">To understand the mechanism of flowering transition, a series of intensive studies on flower development were implemented in recent years and the results provided some crucial clues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. For example, it is reported that flower development is firstly characterized by dramatic changes in morphology such as floral patterning, floral organ size and floral organ specification. These changes are regulated by a great number of regulators like transcriptional factors and miRNAs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The growth cone is transformed from differentiation of leaves to differentiation of flower buds in the ontogeny of higher plant, which marks the transition from vegetative growth to reproductive growth or the beginning of flower development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">In recent years, it has become increasingly clear that the phase transitions were controlled by distinct genetic circuit incorporating endogenous and environmental cues, such as the interaction between NF-YC and CLF, the interaction between miR156 and miR173 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], and so on. These genes are involved the regulation of phase transition by undergoing regular changes to form a complex gene regulatory network (GRN) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The flowering mechanism of the model plant <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is relatively clear with a flowering gene regulatory network involving signal transduction networks such as photoperiod, autonomous, vernalization, and gibberellin pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. More and more researches demonstrate that the flowering developmental gene regulatory networks provide an important breakthrough for better understanding the inherent mechanism of flowering transition.</p><p id="Par17">Attribute to the advances of next-generational sequencing technology, bioinformatics and computational biology expedited the process of biological research by genome-wide transcriptome analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Transcriptome analysis provides a perfect approach to study biological problem because it gives not only a global view of gene expression patterns including biological function enrichment but also a predictive dimension by identifying a set of co-expressed genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. With above advantages, bioinformatics analysis of high-throughput transcriptome data provides a powerful tool to address the issues in exploring the mechanism of the phase transition in a genome-wide scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">The transcriptome analysis by predicting GRN has been used to discover the regulatory mechanism in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Different types of tools have been developed to infer large-scale GRNs from the gene expression data, such as correlation-based methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], mutual information-based method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] and regression-based methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Our group previously have developed some GRN inference tools such as NARROMI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], PCA-CMI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and CMI2NI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. These methods have greatly improved the accuracy of GRN inference by reducing the noisy, redundant and indirect regulations.</p><p id="Par19">Recently, the predictive GRN was used to analyze the phase transition and some novel genes controlling the seed-to-seedling phase transition in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> were identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Not only that, the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> floral transition process was deciphered by integrating a protein-protein interaction network and gene expression data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. For the traditional analysis methods, it is difficult to catch up the truth of complex phase transitions with the traits of temporal and spatial dynamics with polygene interactions. Moreover, the research has focused on the mechanism of flower development under undifferentiated stem cells but not the mechanism of floral organ transformation to maturation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In addition, the current methods have not fully used the dynamics character of phase transition and not necessarily catch the real regulators controlling the phase transitions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. While the time-course transcriptome data with multiple replicates provide the materials for the bioinformatics analysis to identify the regulators of phase transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">With more and more time-course high-throughput transcriptome data available, some dynamic network analysis-based bioinformatics tools have been developed and widely used to study the complex biological mechanism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. For example, the dynamic network biomarker identification tool, named DNB, was developed to detect the biomarker [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. In this method, a complex biological process (e.g., differentiation processes, aging processes, and phase transition of the cell cycle, etc.) is divided into three phases or states, i.e. the before-transition state, the critical transition state, and the after-transition state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. In a focal system, a drastic or qualitative transition from the critical transition state to the post-transition state corresponds to a bifurcation point in the dynamical systems theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. When the system is near to a critical point, a dominant group of biomarkers become bifurcate. The biomarkers can be defined by three conditions: isolated subnetwork or functional module, high fluctuation of the members, strong correlation between any pair of its members while weak correlation between members and non-members [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Dynamic network analysis with a solid theory support has been successfully applied to real biological data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">In this work, to provide a new insight into the flowering developmental transition, we performed a genome-wide dynamic network analysis on the time-course gene expression data in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. The dataset with 14 stages of flowering from initiation to maturity and 3 replicates for each stage provides a dynamic process of flowering development. The genes that control the phase transition can be identified by the difference of weighted correlations between the genes interested and the other genes in the global network. To construct the gene regulatory network controlling the flowering transition, we applied NARROMI algorithm which can reduce the noisy, redundant and indirect regulations on the expression data of the transition-specific genes. The results were validated by biological experimental analysis and the predicted transition state is consistent with the real transition state of the flowering in phenotype. We also performed a similar analysis of temporal gene expression profiling dataset of rice flower development to support the conclusions drawn. Ultimately, we detected a critical transition state of flower development in rice. This work provides a novel insight into the identification of the transition state and the key causal genes that control flowering transition by dynamic network analysis of time-course gene expression data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>A dynamic network biomarker(DNB) model for detecting critical transition state of complex biological systems</title><p id="Par22">In the phase transition model, a complex biological process (e.g., differentiation processes, aging processes, and changes in the phases of the cell cycle) can be generally divided into the three stages, i.e. the before-transition state, the critical transition state, and the after-transition state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The before-transition state is relatively stable but may change gradually because of certain internal and external motivators (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The critical transition state can be understood as the limit of the before-transition state just before a critical transition. Not only that, but it can be easily reverted to the before-transition state by the appropriate external interventions and thus it is considered reversible. While the after-transition state is stable and irreversible even with intensive interventions. Through the identification of dynamic network biomarkers(DNBs), we can control the complex system to avoid the development of the system toward the bad state. In other words, controlling the &#x0201c;causes&#x0201d; of the development of the system can avoid the occurrence of &#x0201c;effects&#x0201d; or change the shape of &#x0201c;effects&#x0201d;. It is crucial to crush the source of trouble in the egg to achieve the ideal effect of achieving effective control of complex systems at a lower cost.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The outline representation of critical transition state by DNB based on time-series gene expression data. <bold>a</bold> The progression of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development from the time of initiation to maturation can be divided into three states, i.e., the before-transition state, the critical transition state, and the after-transition state. A system at the before-transition state or the after-transition state is stable with high resilience. <bold>b</bold> In the critical transition state, deviations of the DNB members increase drastically, and the correlation between any two molecules increases. This critical phenomenon does not appear at the before-transition and the after-transition states. <bold>c</bold> The DNB members show large fluctuations in their expressions at the critical transition state, compared with smaller fluctuations of the expressions at the before- or after- transition states</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">The theoretical basis for detecting DNBs was summarized by the following conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b and c). Briefly, DNB is an observable subnetwork composed of a set of special molecules in the original system which satisfies the following four requirements only at the critical state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par24">DNB molecules or markers are highly fluctuating, i.e. deviations of the DNB members(genes) increase drastically (high SD<sub><italic>d</italic></sub>).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par25">All members of DNBs are highly co-expressed, i.e. correlations among DNB members become stronger (high PCC<sub><italic>d</italic></sub>).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par26">DNB members are almost independent of non-DNB members. DNB is an isolated subnetwork or functional module, i.e. the correlation between any DNB molecules and other non-DNB decreases (low PCC<sub><italic>o</italic></sub>).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par27">There are no drastic deviations or correlations among all non-DNB molecules in the system.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par28">To detect a reliable and unambiguous signal of the critical transition state, a composite index(CI) is proposed as follows<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{CI}=\left({\mathrm{SD}}_d\cdotp {\mathrm{PCC}}_d\right)/{\mathrm{PCC}}_o, $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi>CI</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>SD</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>PCC</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>PCC</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where SD<sub><italic>d</italic></sub> and PCC<sub><italic>d</italic></sub> are average standard deviation(SD) and average <italic>Pearson</italic> correlation coefficient(PCC) of all molecules in DNB module <italic>d</italic> respectively, while PCC<sub><italic>o</italic></sub> is the average correlation between molecules in <italic>d</italic> and others that are not in <italic>d</italic>. When a biological system approaches a critical transition state, CI provides a reliable and significant early-warning signal. Among all the responsive CI modules, the maximum one is most likely to be the DNB that corresponds to the critical stage of the system.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Pipeline of genome-wide dynamic network analysis</title><p id="Par29">To provide a new insight into the flowering developmental transition, we performed a genome-wide dynamic network analysis on the time-course gene expression data in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. The dataset with 14 stages of flowering from initiation to maturity and 3 replicates for each stage provides a dynamic process of flowering development. However, the dynamic network analysis to effectively reveal the critical developmental stage with a key sub-network is still a challenge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In addition, the data with matched case and control samples are not available. Therefore, the effective data processing become crucial to identify the DNBs for the flower developmental transition.</p><p id="Par30">Previous studies have shown that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowers are sequentially activated so that the flowers in their inflorescence are at different stages of development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. It also has been found that the top-head flowers of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> inflorescence remain quite synchronized throughout the flower development and therefore the time-series gene expression data of flowering could be obtained [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. To overcome the lack of data with the matched case and control samples, the sample in former time point was designated as the control sample, and the neighbor later sample was designed as case sample. And then the 14 different developmental stages from initial to mature were divided into 13 case-control combinations with which we can detect the phase transition of Arabidopsis flower development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The flow diagram for revealing the critical transition state. <bold>a</bold> With samples in previous and the current time points designated as the control and case sample respectively. The 14 different developmental stages from initial to mature were divided into 13 combinations. <bold>b</bold> We applied DNB method to reveal a critical differentiation state of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development by comparing the control and case samples. <bold>c</bold> To construct the gene regulatory network controlling the flowering transition, we applied NARROMI algorithm on the expression data of the transition-specific genes. The NARROMI algorithm removes noisy regulations with low pair-wise correlations and redundant regulations from indirect regulators using ordinary differential equation-based recursive optimization (RO) and information theory-based mutual information (MI), respectively. The dotted line without arrowhead denotes non-regulation (redundant), the dotted arrow denotes the indirect regulation (redundant) and the solid arrow denotes the true regulation. <bold>d</bold> We also analyzed key regulatory factors and key metabolic pathways which were closely related to the phase transition of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowering development from the time of initiation to maturation time</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par31">The DNB model which is powerful than the traditional differential expression analysis was applied to detect the critical differentiation state of flower development from the time of initiation to maturation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). NARROMI algorithm which can reduce the noisy, redundant and indirect regulations on the expression data of the transition-specific genes was used to construct the gene regulatory network controlling the flowering transition (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. With the identified DNBs, key regulatory factors and metabolic pathways closely related to the phase transition of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development from the time of initiation to maturation were analyzed (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>The identified critical transition state in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development</title><p id="Par32">Identifying the critical differentiation stage or critical transition state of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development from the time of initiation to maturation is crucial to clarify the molecular mechanism that regulates plant flowering. However, the traditional methods based on differential expression analysis failed to detect the critical state due to the lack of significant differential expressions of molecules in the before-transition and critical transition states. To overcome this problem, the DNB model was developed to measure collective fluctuations of molecules taking place of the traditional differential expression analysis (see Methods). Traditional methods often rely on the differential expressions of molecules, while the DNB model uses both differential correlations and differential deviations among molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Despite of the weak differential expression among genes in the before-transition state and the critical transition state, significant differential correlations and deviations among genes existed in these two states.</p><p id="Par33">We implemented the DNB model on the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development datasets (NCBI access no. GSE64581) to identify the critical transition and the genes of flower development from the time of initiation to maturation. Specifically, we compared the samples in previous time point as the control sample with the samples in current time point as the case sample. Ultimately, the 14 different developmental stages from initial to mature were divide into 13 sampling time points. The critical transition state of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowering was detected in the before-transition and after-transition state at the 11th sampling point of the flower formation shown by the red star (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Identification of the critical transition state of flower development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. The DNB scores at 13 sampling time points is shown in the FIGURE. For the black curve, the DNB score increased sharply from the 10th point and reached the peak at the 11th point. The 11th sampling time point annotated by the red star is designated as a critical transition state, which corresponds to the comparison of growth on the 7th to 9th day of Arabidopsis flower development</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par34">The 11th sampling time point shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> corresponded to the comparison of growth on the 7th to 9th day of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development. Moreover, the development of flower inflorescence was largely synchronous until day 7. For the later time-points, only the development of flowers at the tip of the inflorescence (arrowheads) remained synchronized after phenotypic assessment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In order to verify the biological and statistical significance of the identified DNBs, we conducted bootstrap analysis and the results showed that the identified DNBs for flowering development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> were highly significant compared with the randomly chosen gene sets (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>The identified genes controlling the transition of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development</title><p id="Par35">Ryan et al. revealed that the development of Arabidopsis flower inflorescence was largely synchronous until day 7. After that, only the development of flowers at the tip of the inflorescence remained synchronized after phenotypic assessment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. As result of our analysis, the predicted critical transition state from timepoint 7th to 9th day was consistent with their experimental results. In other words, the critical transition state detected during the formation of flowers corresponded to the development of flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. All identified DNB members corresponding to the critical state of flower formation were listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S1,&#x000a0;and the detailed description of DNB members was&#x000a0;listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S2. Functional categories for up- and down-regulated genes in DNB module were shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, these genes were crucial for flowering transition. Moreover, functional categories for other genes in DNB module were shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Table S1.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Functional categories for up- and down-regulated genes in the DNB module of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene name</th><th>Fold change</th><th>Transition state</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4">Transcription factors</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;RAP2.6</td><td>0.73</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>AP2/B3-like, related to AP2 6(RAP2.6)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AGL46</td><td>0.19</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>MADS box transcription factor</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT2G31370</td><td>1.74</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Basic-leucine zipper transcription factor</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT5G46030</td><td>2.12</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>transcription elongation factor-like protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT4G33280</td><td>0.71</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>AP2/B3-like transcriptional factor family protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT1G21580</td><td>1.66</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Zinc finger C-&#x000d7;8-C-&#x000d7;5-C-&#x000d7;3-H type family</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ZAP1</td><td>4.05</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>zinc-dependent activator protein-1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;WRKY36</td><td>0.07</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>WRKY DNA-binding protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT1G59675</td><td>1.21</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>F-box family protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;NAP</td><td>2.37</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>NAC-like, activated by AP3/PI(NAP)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT1G76590</td><td>1.63</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>PLATZ transcription factor family protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;RIE1</td><td>0.28</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>RING-finger protein for embryogenesis</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT4G25610</td><td>0.35</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>C2H2-like zinc finger protein</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Protein kinase activity</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT3G46270</td><td>3.83</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>receptor protein kinase-like protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">&#x02003;AT3G15240</td><td>3.61</td><td rowspan="2">up-regulated</td><td>Serine/threonine-protein kinase WNK</td></tr><tr><td/><td>(With No Lysine)-like protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT1G67720</td><td>0.42</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>Leucine-rich repeat protein kinase family protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT3G23310</td><td>0.75</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>AGC kinase family protein</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Ras signaling pathway</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AGL46</td><td>0.19</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>MADS box transcription factor</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Plant hormone signal transduction</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;SHY2</td><td>0.61</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>AUX/IAA transcriptional regulator family protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AIR12</td><td>0.79</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>auxin-induced in root cultures-like protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;IAA18</td><td>1.98</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>indole-3-acetic acid inducible 18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">ABA signaling pathway</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;HIS1&#x02013;3</td><td>0.79</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>histone H1&#x02013;3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;SLAH2</td><td>1.22</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>SLAC1 homologue 2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT4G25610</td><td>0.35</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>C2H2-like zinc finger protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT4G33280</td><td>0.71</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>AP2/B3-like transcriptional factor family protein</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AT1G59675</td><td>1.21</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>F-box family protein</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>A more reliable gene co-expression network controlling critical transition</title><p id="Par36">A DNB module containing 233 genes about <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development from the time of initiation to maturation was detected using the DNB model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. With the gene expression data of these transition-specific genes, we used NARROMI algorithm which can remove the redundant and indirect regulations to construct the gene co-expression network controlling the flowering transition.&#x000a0;Network inference file was listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Table S3, and we got two new files by processing the file.&#x000a0;The degree of correlation between each pair of DNB members of Arabidopsis flower development was&#x000a0;listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Table S4, and the node properties file for the network was listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Table S5.</p><p id="Par37">By applying the NARROMI approach to the 233 genes of the DNB module, we constructed a more accurate and reliable gene regulatory network of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowering transition. The file of gene regulatory network was listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: Table S6.&#x000a0;Ultimately, the members of DNB module and the correlations among members were visualized in a molecular network consisting of 150 nodes with 225 edges. In the network, node color reflects the standard deviation of the corresponding genes and the strength of correlations reflected by edge width, where a wider edge corresponds to a higher correlation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Three key subnetworks in the DNB module are clustered separately because the standard deviation of the corresponding genes and the strength of correlations in these subnetworks were significantly different, and we deemed these distinct regions as the most representative of this critical transition (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>DNB members and correlations among these molecules were visualized in molecular networks by using Cytoscape. Node color reflects the standard deviation of the corresponding genes. The strength of correlations is represented by edge width, where a wider edge corresponds to a higher correlation. For clarity, the strength of correlations was also reflected by edge color. <bold>a</bold> A more reliable co-expression gene regulatory network of the Arabidopsis floral transition. <bold>b</bold> Three key subnetworks in DNB given separately</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Functional classification of DNB members during the critical transition state</title><p id="Par38">The critical transition state during the formation of flowers was identified by DNB approach, and it corresponded to the development of flowering on the 7th to 9th day in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. To evaluate the potential functions of DNB members, GO assignments were used to classify the functions of DNB members during the critical transition of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development.</p><p id="Par39">In the biological process category, two GO terms, i.e. small molecule catabolic process and plant-type cell wall biogenesis were enriched significantly in most DNB members (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). In the cellular component category, there were plenty of DNB members associated with AP-type membrane coat adaptor complex, secondary cell wall, and intrinsic component of mitochondrial inner membrane (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). In the molecular function category, ion antiporter activity was enriched significantly in most genes of the DNB module, and phosphate ion transmembrane transporter activity, serine-type endopeptidase inhibitor activity and L-ascorbic acid binding were similarly enriched in the DNB module (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>GO terms function enrichment analysis of DNB members. <bold>a</bold> biological process, (<bold>b</bold>) cellular component, (<bold>c</bold>) molecular function. The <italic>p</italic>-values are plotted on a linear scale. The size of the dot is proportional with the number of annotated genes for the respective GO term and its coloring represents the number of significantly differentially expressed genes, with the dark red points having more genes then the yellow ones</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">All the other overrepresented GO terms of DNB members in the three GO categories (biological process, cellular component, and molecular function) were listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. And the&#x000a0;metabolic pathways were listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: Table S2. To further analyze key regulatory factors that control the phase transition from initiation to maturation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development, we inferred a transcriptional module that links key regulatory factors with their potential targets (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Significance of GO terms obtained by R package topGO</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>GO</th><th>GO.ID</th><th>Term</th><th>Annotated</th><th><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="10">biological process</td><td>GO:0044282</td><td>small molecule catabolic process</td><td>196</td><td>0.0044</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0009832</td><td>plant-type cell wall biogenesis</td><td>174</td><td>0.00428</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0006643</td><td>membrane lipid metabolic process</td><td>101</td><td>0.00801</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0009640</td><td>photomorphogenesis</td><td>95</td><td>0.00081</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0032101</td><td>regulation of response to external stimu...</td><td>85</td><td>0.00713</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0090691</td><td>formation of plant organ boundary</td><td>16</td><td>0.00943</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0010244</td><td>response to low fluence blue light stimu...</td><td>9</td><td>0.00719</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0010264</td><td>myo-inositol hexakisphosphate biosynthet...</td><td>8</td><td>0.00617</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0000967</td><td>rRNA 5&#x02032;-end processing</td><td>7</td><td>0.00401</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0052746</td><td>inositol phosphorylation</td><td>5</td><td>0.00133</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10">cellular component</td><td>GO:0030119</td><td>AP-type membrane coat adaptor complex</td><td>18</td><td>0.015</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0031304</td><td>intrinsic component of mitochondrial inn...</td><td>18</td><td>0.052</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0009531</td><td>secondary cell wall</td><td>16</td><td>0.053</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0005880</td><td>nuclear microtubule</td><td>7</td><td>0.031</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0016442</td><td>RISC complex</td><td>5</td><td>0.047</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0031332</td><td>RNAi effector complex</td><td>5</td><td>0.047</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0034098</td><td>VCP-NPL4-UFD1 AAA ATPase complex</td><td>3</td><td>0.014</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0032541</td><td>cortical endoplasmic reticulum</td><td>2</td><td>0.022</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0000312</td><td>plastid small ribosomal subunit</td><td>2</td><td>0.041</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0005971</td><td>ribonucleoside-diphosphate reductase com...</td><td>2</td><td>0.051</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10">molecular function</td><td>GO:0099516</td><td>ion antiporter activity</td><td>94</td><td>0.0125</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0015114</td><td>phosphate ion transmembrane transporter ...</td><td>26</td><td>0.0019</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0004867</td><td>serine-type endopeptidase inhibitor acti...</td><td>22</td><td>0.0018</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0031418</td><td>L-ascorbic acid binding</td><td>13</td><td>0.008</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0048038</td><td>quinone binding</td><td>10</td><td>0.0031</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0005242</td><td>inward rectifier potassium channel activ...</td><td>10</td><td>0.013</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0016639</td><td>oxidoreductase activity, acting on the C...</td><td>6</td><td>0.0041</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0050284</td><td>sinapate 1-glucosyltransferase activity</td><td>4</td><td>0.004</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0004148</td><td>dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase activity</td><td>4</td><td>0.0069</td></tr><tr><td>GO:0016629</td><td>12-oxophytodienoate reductase activity</td><td>3</td><td>0.0082</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Transcriptional modules predicted to regulate the floral transition. <bold>a</bold> There are a number of GO terms (orange hexagons) which are significantly overrepresented (P, 0.01) in the DNB module.&#x000a0;<bold>b</bold> Several GO terms (orange hexagons) that are significantly overrepresented (P, 0.01) within the DNB module (circles) are shown together with co-expressed genes (light blue Circles)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>The detected key genes of the critical transition</title><p id="Par41">We not only discovered a critical transition which occurred between the seventh and ninth days of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development, but also found that 24 genes in this DNB module participate in stress reaction process, as well as in other floral-related pathways (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). Biological and abiotic stresses negatively affect plant growth and development including flowering and thus reduce productivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Adversity related genes included disease-, ABA-, JA-, drought-, low temperature and salt-related genes, i.e. CBP20, NAP, AT4G33280, RAP2.6, ECA1, AT5G38760, WRKY36, HIS1&#x02013;3, AT1G73490, RIE1, AT1G52650, AT4G08520, AT1G59675, etc. Many of these genes such as RIE1, ECA1 and NAP were predominantly expressed from or after the 9th day which is the pollen formation stage. Thus, these genes might be play a vital role in the formation of microspores and the differentiation of pollen grains to a large extent.</p><p id="Par42">The cap-binding protein complex (CBC) plays an important role in RNA metabolism because the CBC binds to the caps of all RNA polymerase II transcripts. As one subunit of the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> CBC, the Cap Binding Protein 20 (CBP20) was determined to be involved in normal plant growth and development as well as RNA metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Studies have found that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cbp20 null mutant exhibited abnormal development of leaves and flowers and showed increased sensitivity to salt stress, which suggests that CBP20 has a synergistic effect in salt stress response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Moreover, the drought-tolerant cbp20 mutant could maintain normal growth and development under drought stress, which might also point to a new cellular output mechanism as targets of the ABA regulatory pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. The plant specific NAM/ATAF1/2/CUC2 (NAC) transcription factors play important roles in abiotic stress-response signaling. We found that two NAC-like genes named NAP and NAP57 (activated by AP3/PI) as two of the important DNB members involved in a trifurcate feed-forward pathway of the drought stress response and their expression at the critical transition state was different from other periods.</p><p id="Par43">Moreover, we also found NAP12 to be involved in the gametogenesis of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> with two genes of ECA1 (Early Culture Abundant 1) gametogenesis-related family genes, AT5G60945 and AT5G36657. The ECA1 family proteins can be activated transcriptionally during the transition of microspores from the gametophytic to the embryogenic pathway. In addition, RIE1 and LEA (AT5G38760), two genes in the DNB module were found to be involved in the embryonic development of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. A RIE1 gene encoding a RING-H2 zinc-finger protein was identified in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, and it might be a membrane-associated protein, possibly relating to chloroplast. The late embryogenesis Abundant (LEA) protein family plays a role in drought stress tolerance. How to improve reproductive development by this transition depended on the interactions between regulatory factors. These regulators were important for signal transduction to control the transition of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development.</p><p id="Par44">The APETALA2 (AP2) transcription factors (TFs) plays an important dynamic role in the embryo development, seedling built, flowering as well as stress response process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Two genes including RAP2.6 and AP2/B3-like (AT4G33280) were identified by DNB method. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> transcription factors RAP2.6 and AP2/ERF were found to be involved not only in ABA, salt and drought stress responses, but also in stamen emergence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. WRKY genes are a family of regulatory genes isolated from plants. WRKY proteins encoded by WRKY genes constitute a large family of plant-specific transcription factors. WRKY36, one of the WRKY gene family members, was identified in DNB module. Recent research found that UVR8 interacts with WRKY36 to regulate HY5 transcription and hypocotyl elongation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, while we found that WRKY36 plays an important role in the critical transition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>].</p><p id="Par45">As result of our analysis, 233 genes were identified to be highly fluctuated at the transition state and formed the DNB module. More importantly, a high percentage of genes with maximum expression in pollen was detected, which were predominantly expressed from or after the 9th day. For example, we found that two NAC-like genes named NAP and NAP57 (activated by AP3/PI) as two of the important DNB members were involved in a trifurcate feed-forward pathway of the drought stress response and they were up-regulated at the critical transition state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Numerous studies have shown that class B MADS-box genes (AP3/PI) are crucial for stamen development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Thus, the critical transition state detected during the formation of flowers was regarded as the pollen formation stage.</p><p id="Par46">Some genes involved in cell differentiation were detected in this DNB module with predominant expression at late stages of flower development. These genes were predominantly expressed from or after the 9th day which is the pollen formation stage. For example, the regulator of ovule and seed development SEEDSTICK (STK) was significantly upregulated between days 7 and 9 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. DUO POLLEN1 (DUO1), a regulator of male germline development, was found for the first time to be expressed at the same stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. And thus, these genes may be involved to a large extent in the differentiation of microspores into pollen grains. Gene Ontology (GO) analysis also showed that secondary cell wall synthesis related genes were enriched significantly in this critical transition (GO:0009531). The tapetum was developed from the secondary cell wall, which was the important component of pollen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. While many changes in gene expression may be owing to the activation of specific gene sets during the late pollen development, genes with significant regulatory functions such as genes coding APETALA2 (AP2) transcription factors and MADS-domain proteins often show intermittent expression at various stages of flower development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].</p><p id="Par47">Genes involved in different plant hormone responses such as abscisic acid, auxin, and jasmonic acid were also detected as enriched significantly in this DNB module. This discovery is consistent with the known roles of these hormones in various biological processes in the late-stage flower development, such as the formation of stamen and pollen as well as the maturation of petals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. For example, AGL46 (AT2G28700), encoding the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> MADS-box transcription factor was found to be involved in the CCKR signaling map, gonadotropin-releasing hormone receptor pathway, PDGF signaling pathway, interleukin signaling pathway, Ras Pathway and p38 MAPK pathway by KEGG analysis. Studies have shown that members of the MADS-box gene family play vital roles in flower development from early determination of floral meristem identity to later determination of floral organ primordial identity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. In a nutshell, the critical transition state detected during the formation of flowers and key regulators identified in the transition might answer the complex mechanisms of floral organ formation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>A critical transition state of flower development in Rice</title><p id="Par48">To support the conclusions drawn, a similar analysis was performed on the flowering development data in rice. The dataset with spatio-temporal gene expression profiling throughout entire growth in rice was downloaded from the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database under the accession number GSE21396 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo</ext-link>). The dataset include 15 time-points and 3 replicates for flowering development from initiation to maturity in rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. To overcome the lack of distinction between the case sample and the control sample in this dataset, we compared the samples in both the previous and current time points. The samples in previous and current time points were designated as the control and case samples respectively. Thus, 15 different developmental stages from initial to mature were divided into 14 combinations for the detection of the critical transition. The pipeline of genome-wide dynamic network analysis was performed on the processed data with 14 combinations and a critical transition state of flower development was detected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The critical transition state detected during the formation of flowers corresponded to the development of specific floral organs (anther and pistil) in rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>].<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Identification of the DNB of flower development in rice. The DNB scores at 14 sampling time points is shown in the FIGURE. For the black curve, the DNB score increased sharply from the 7th point and reached the peak at the 8th point. The 8th sampling time point annotated by the red star is designated as a critical transition state, which corresponds to the development of specific floral organs (anther and pistil) in rice</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par49">Not only that, we also detected the DNB biomarkers with 206 genes that may herald the imminent critical transition during the formation of flowers. The genes detected in the critical transition state were listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">10</xref>: Figure S3. The anther showed a unique growth characteristic in which most anther-specific genes were expressed only in a particular developmental stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. We found that a pollen-specific gene (LOC4341399) coding for a pollen-specific leucine-rich repeat extensin-like protein was up-regulated in the critical transition. This result indicated that our researches can conduce to reveal the complex regulatory mechanisms of gene expression during anther growth and development as well as pollen germination.</p><p id="Par50">The Gene Ontology (GO) analysis exhibited that protein kinase-encoding genes were significantly enriched among the down-regulated genes (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The results indicated that several signal transduction pathways involved in protein phosphorylation might undergo complex changes during this critical transition phase. Several transcription factors including 3&#x02009;F-box-, 1&#x02009;U-box-, 2 MYB-family genes were also up-regulated during this critical transition phase. Many studies have indicated that F-box proteins constituted one of the eukaryotic protein families, which played pivotal roles in regulating various developmental processes of plants. For example, a F-box gene DDF1 was a crucial genetic factor with pleiotropic effects in the development of rice floral organs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. CSA, a gene encoding the R2R3 MYB transcription factor which preferentially expressed in anther tapetal cells was identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. These researches indicated that the F-box-, U-box-, MYB-family genes detected in this critical transition phase might be play pivotal roles in regulating anther development in rice. Other up- and down-regulated genes also play a crucial role in the process of rice pollen development.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Functional categories for up- and down-regulated genes in the DNB module of rice flower development</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene name</th><th>Fold change</th><th>Transition state</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Os04g0417400</td><td>6.80</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>U box domain containing protein.</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4340069</td><td>1.93</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>DNA-binding protein (Homeodomain-leucine zipper transcription factor)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4346839</td><td>1.82</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Disease resistance protein family protein.disease resistance protein RGA5-like</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4341399</td><td>1.74</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>pollen-specific leucine-rich repeat extensin-like protein 1</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4326659</td><td>1.59</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Cytochrome P450 monooxygenase CYP72A5</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4338660</td><td>1.56</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>UDP-sulfoquinovose synthase, chloroplast precursor (Sulfolipid biosynthesis protein)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4345661</td><td>1.43</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Myb-like protein (transcription factor CSA-like)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4324767</td><td>1.36</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>TPR-like domain containing protein.</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4339280</td><td>1.36</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Cyclin-like F-box domain containing protein (F-box protein At5g46170)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4332901</td><td>1.32</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Sugar transporter-like protein</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4324342</td><td>1.32</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Plant lipid transfer/seed storage/trypsin-alpha amylase inhibitor domain containing protein</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4351030</td><td>1.32</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4341957</td><td>1.31</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Macrophage migration inhibitory factor family protein</td></tr><tr><td>LOC112936214</td><td>1.32</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>eukaryotic cysteine peptidase active site family protein (putative F-box protein At5g15660)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4324302</td><td>1.37</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>Myb-related protein 5 (transcription factor MYB59)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4338652</td><td>1.31</td><td>up-regulated</td><td>ABC transporter G family member 23</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4338416</td><td>0.79</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>ABC-1 domain containing protein (protein ACTIVITY OF BC1 COMPLEX KINASE 3, chloroplastic)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4329899</td><td>0.71</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>Galactosyltransferase associated protein kinase p58/GTA (Cell division cycle 2-like 2)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4348579</td><td>0.78</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>Protein kinase APK1B (EC 2.7.1.-)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4338491</td><td>0.76</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>Ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4350151</td><td>0.76</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>probable sucrose-phosphate synthase 5</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4349274</td><td>0.75</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>Zn-finger, RING domain containing protein (NEP1-interacting protein 1)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4335569</td><td>0.69</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>Helicase-like protein</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4324503</td><td>0.57</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>Ribosomal protein S8 family protein.</td></tr><tr><td>LOC4335392</td><td>0.49</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>Allergen V5/Tpx-1 related family protein (pathogenesis-related protein 1)</td></tr><tr><td>LOC9272032</td><td>0.35</td><td>down-regulated</td><td>probable LRR receptor-like serine/ threonine-protein kinase At1g51810</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par51">These results supported the conclusions drawn on the development of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower. Therefore, the transcriptomic profiling analysis using DNB and MARROMI method could provide new insight to characterize the formation of flowers and detect key regulatory factors that might control the transition from initiation to maturation in Arabidopsis flower development.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par52">The formation of flowers is one of the main models for studying the regulation mechanisms of plant growth and development. In past botanical studies, the floral transition was recognized as the progression from vegetative growth to reproductive growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Although some network-based bioinformatics analyses attempted to identify the phase transition which indicate the progression from vegetative growth to reproductive, there is no research on identifying the critical transition stage of flower formation from the time of initiation to maturation. Differentiation of floral organs is more complex than other parts of the plant, especially the formation of pollen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. In this study, we discovered a critical transition stage of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development using the DNB theory. It is the first time that DNB model has been used in plant research. We found that the phase transition occurred between the seventh and ninth days of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development. The development of flowers on a given inflorescence was uniformly synchronized until day 7, then the expression of flowering related genes has changed dramatically. Not only that, we found that this critical transition state detected during the formation of flowers corresponded to the development of specific floral organs (anther). We also detected the DNB members composed by 233 genes that may herald the imminent critical transition during the formation of flowers. Moreover, the interactions between these genes also regulate the critical transition process.</p><p id="Par53">To construct the gene regulatory network controlling the flowering transition, we applied NARROMI algorithm which can reduce the noisy, redundant and indirect regulations on the expression data of the transition-specific genes. We further found that 24 genes in this DNB module participate in stress reaction process, as well as in other floral-related pathways such as gametogenesis and embryo development. Our research here suggests that previously unknown regulatory genes identified in the transition region might be through known regulatory mechanisms to promote the formation of flowers. Therefore, a further study of co-expressed genes in the transition region might answer the connection between co-expressed genes and critical transition.</p><p id="Par54">In addition, the highlight of this article is the effective combination of DNB and NARROMI methods. In contrast to the traditional methods or biomarkers based on differential expressions of molecules, DNB method can identify a critical transition state of a complex biological process based on collective fluctuations and correlations of different metabolic molecules at the network level. Thus, even if there are no significant differential expressions in the before-transition state and the critical transition state, we can detect significant differential correlations and deviations in these two states by DNB method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p><p id="Par55">In contrast to the traditional methods to construct the gene regulatory network controlling the flowering transition, NARROMI algorithm can reduce the noisy, redundant and indirect regulations on the expression data of the transition-specific genes. Firstly, NARROMI algorithm can calculate the causal intensity between gene pairs by quantifying the non-linear correlation mutual information (MI), so that we can reduce interference regulators with low correlation. Then, ordinary differential equation-based recursive optimization (RO) is used to gradually reduce the redundant and indirect regulations. Ultimately, we obtained a topology of a non-linear sparse gene regulatory network by network integration which was the most similar gene regulatory network to the real network. NARROMI algorithm could be regard as a further improvement of the DNB model.</p><p id="Par56">We also performed a similar analysis of temporal gene expression profiling dataset of rice flower development to support the conclusions drawn. Ultimately, we detected a critical transition state of flower development in rice. This critical transition state detected during the formation of flowers corresponded to the development of specific floral organs (anther and pistil) in rice. Not only that, we also detected the DNB members composed by 206 genes that may herald the imminent critical transition during the formation of flowers. We found that the genes detected in this critical transition phase might be play pivotal roles in regulating anther development in rice. These results supported the conclusions drawn on the development of Arabidopsis flowering. In addition to the application of DNB and NARROMI algorithm to detect the critical state of Arabidopsis flowering transition, they can be used to detect the critical transition of any biological process.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par57">We studied the flower developmental phase transition from the time of initiation to maturation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> using dynamic network biomarker model. The critical transition state of flowering development was detected and a cluster of genes as dynamic network biomarkers controlling the phase transition of flower development from the initiation to maturation were identified. In contrast to the traditional methods based on differential gene expression analysis, our analysis can exploit collective fluctuations and correlations of different metabolites at a network level to identify a critical transition state of a complex biological process. We also detected the dynamic network biomarkers composed of several genes that may herald the imminent critical transition during the formation of flowers. To construct the gene regulatory network controlling the flowering transition, we applied NARROMI algorithm on the expression data of the transition-specific genes. The redundancy reduction technique-based network reconstruction method NARROMI algorithm could be regard as a further improvement of the dynamic network biomarker model, which can reduce noisy and indirect regulations to improve the accuracy of the network inference. Our research suggests that the critical transition state detected during the formation of flowers and key regulators identified in the transition might answer the complex mechanisms of floral organ formation. The bioinformatics analysis used in this work can also be used to detect the critical state of any biological process.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Gene expression data collection</title><p id="Par58">The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower developmental gene expression profiling dataset was downloaded from the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database under the accession number GSE64581 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo</ext-link>). The dataset includes 14 different time-points with 3 replicates of gene expression data from initiation to maturity, i.e. 0d, 1d, 1.5d, 2d, 2.5d, 3d, 3.5d, 4d, 4.5d, 5d, 7d, 9d, 11d and 13d (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). The data was downloaded from GEO database already pre-processed, and we followed procedure outlined in Ryan et al., 2015 and some other protocol. Ryan et al.&#x02019;s article is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par59">The data was downloaded from GEO database was a time-courses gene expression matrix. The horizontal row indicated the expression value of one gene in different samples, and the column represented the expression value of the gene pool of one sample. We used the function &#x02018;genelowvalfilter&#x02019; in MATLAB to filter genes. After removing those genes whose expression values were less than a certain threshold, we used the remaining genes for further processing. Because some of the transcriptional changes are caused by specific gene regulatory events or tremendous alterations in floral size and morphology during the flower development, we compared the gene expression level between consecutive as well as neighbor (within a 2d time interval) time-points to minimize the effect of morphological changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Network inference</title><p id="Par60">In general, a mathematical model based on mass action kinetics and Michaelis&#x02013;Menten kinetics can describe the transcriptional regulation process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. However, the noise inherited in the gene expression data can decrease the performance of these models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Therefore, to improve the accuracy of the network inference, NARROMI algorithm was used to reduce noisy, redundant and indirect regulations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. It initially calculates the causal strength between gene pairs by quantifying the non-linear correlation mutual information (MI), which can reduce noisy regulations in gene expression data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Then, ordinary differential equation-based recursive optimization (RO) is used to gradually reduce the redundant and indirect regulations to obtain a final topology of a non-linear sparse gene regulatory network (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c). The script that was used to apply the NARROMI algorithm was listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM11" ref-type="media">11</xref>: Script 1.&#x000a0;By comparing with GENIE3, ARACNE etc., NARROMI outperformed these popular methods in most cases, thereby verifying its effectiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p id="Par61">To obtain a more reliable gene co-expression network, a composite index is proposed combining mutual information(MI) and recursive optimization(RO)-based estimation of parameters:<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \beta =\operatorname{sign}\left({\beta}^{\mathrm{RO}}\right)\left(\omega \left|{\beta}^{\mathrm{RO}}\right|+\left(1-\omega \right){\beta}^{\mathrm{MI}}\right) $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>sign</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>RO</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close="|" open="|"><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>RO</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>MI</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sup>MI</sup> is the MI value which is positive, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sup>RO</sup> is the regulatory strength (positive or negative) inferred by RO algorithm, sign(<italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sup>RO</sup>) is the sign (<underline>+</underline>) of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sup>RO</sup>, |<italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sup>RO</sup>| is the absolute of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sup>RO</sup> and parameter &#x003c9; is the weighting coefficient. The final regulatory strength is decided by the parameter <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>, and the network topology is then determined.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>GO enrichment and visualization</title><p id="Par62">The identified DNB members were analyzed for functional enrichment analysis by R package topGO 2.30.1. The topGO package provided tools for testing GO terms while accounting for the topology of the GO graph. Different test statistics and different methods for eliminating local similarities and dependencies between GO terms can be implemented and applied. The enrichment analysis process consists of input of normalized gene expression measurements, gene-wise correlation or differential expression analysis, enrichment analysis of GO terms, interpretation and visualization of the results. The data preparation process is critical before running the enrichment test. The user needs to provide the gene universe, GO annotations and either a criteria for selecting interesting genes (e.g. differentially expressed genes) from the gene universe or a score associated with each gene. The GO database used in our research was a set of annotation maps describing the entire Gene Ontology assembled using data from GO Version: 3.5.0.</p><p id="Par63">Moreover, we also analyzed key regulatory factors and key metabolic pathways that were closely related to DNB of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development from initiation to maturation time (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d). The results of the gene regulatory networks were imported in Cytoscape (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cytoscape.org">www.cytoscape.org</ext-link>) for visualization.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Regulatory circuits and regulators prediction</title><p id="Par64">We further predicted the regulatory circuits and regulators controlling the critical transition based on the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Gene Regulatory Information Server (AGRIS; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arabidopsis.med.ohio-state.edu">http://arabidopsis.med.ohio-state.edu</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. We can obtain a comprehensive resource for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene regulatory studies from the AGRIS. There are three interlinked databases, AtTFDB, AtcisDB and AtRegNet. The updated and comprehensive information on transcription factors (TFs) could be obtain from AtTFDB, which is the key to study the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene regulatory networks.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec18"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S4.</bold> Comparison results of the DNB-based method, bootstrap analysis. (DOCX 313 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM2_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> List of genes for the DNB module during <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development. (TXT 2 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM3_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S2.</bold> Detailed description of the identified DNB module for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development. (TXT 95 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM4_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> Functional categories for the DNB members of Arabidopsis flower development. (TXT 7 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM5_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S3.</bold> Network inference file. (TXT 32 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM6_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S4.</bold> The degree of correlation between each pair of DNB genes during Arabidopsis flower development. (TXT 7 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM7_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 7:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S5.</bold> Node properties file for the network. (TXT 4 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM8_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 8:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S6.</bold> The gene regulatory network Cytoscape file. (TXT 7 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM9_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 9:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S2.</bold> The DNB members of Arabidopsis flower development enriched GO terms and metabolic pathways. (TXT 2 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM10"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM10_ESM.txt"><label>Additional file 10:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S3.</bold> The DNB members of flower development in rice. (TXT 9 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM11"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1589_MOESM11_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 11:</label><caption><p><bold>Script 1.</bold> Tair_DNB_narromi. (DOCX 14 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ABA</term><def><p id="Par4">Abscisic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CBC</term><def><p id="Par5">Cap-binding protein complex</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DNB</term><def><p id="Par6">Dynamic network biomarker</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ECA1</term><def><p id="Par7">Early Culture Abundant 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GRN</term><def><p id="Par8">Gene regulatory network</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LEA</term><def><p id="Par9">Late embryogenesis Abundant</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MI</term><def><p id="Par10">Mutual information</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCC</term><def><p id="Par11">Pearson correlation coefficient</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RO</term><def><p id="Par12">Recursive optimization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr. P.T. Ryan (Smurfit Institute of Genetics, Trinity College Dublin) for providing Arabidopsis floral gene expression data and members of our labs for discussion. We also thank O.O. Collins (University of Chinese Academy of Sciences) for providing invaluable assistance in writing this article.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par65">This work was supported by grants from National Natural Sciences Foundation of China(NSFC), no.61402457, CAS Pioneer Hundred Talents Program and the National Project of Cause Control Theory, no.1716315XJ00200303.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par66">The data sets are included within the article and its Additional files.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>X.Z. designed the research; F.Z. performed the research, F.Z. analyzed the data; L.C., Z.J., X.L. and A.Z. provided many critical suggestions and approved the manuscript; F.Z. and X.Z. wrote the article. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rougvie</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrinsic and extrinsic regulators of developmental timing: from miRNAs to nutritional cues</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2005</year><volume>132</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>3787</fpage><lpage>3798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01972</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16100088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16100088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal and developmental timing of flowering</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2010</year><volume>61</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1001</fpage><lpage>1013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04148.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20409274?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20409274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishizaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishihama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamato</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-option of a photoperiodic growth-phase transition system during land plant evolution</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3668</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms4668</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24752248?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24752248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarty</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of the seed to seedling developmental phase transition by the LAFL and VAL transcription factor networks</article-title><source>Wiley Interdiscipl Rev Dev Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wdev.126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moose</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sisco</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glossy15 controls the epidermal juvenile-to-adult phase transition in maize</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1343</fpage><lpage>1355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.6.10.1343</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12244224?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12244224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transition from vegetative to reproductive phase</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(00)00137-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11163170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11163170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thelen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plastid isoform of triose phosphate isomerase is required for the postgerminative transition from heterotrophic to autotrophic growth in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.071837</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20097871?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20097871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Maoileidigh</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Drost</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwasniewska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosse</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Graciet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quint</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellmer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of gene expression during Arabidopsis flower development from the time of initiation to maturation</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>488</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1699-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26126740?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26126740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The control of developmental phase transitions in plants</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2011</year><volume>138</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>4117</fpage><lpage>4129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.063511</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21896627?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21896627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Frohlich</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppenheimer</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>dePamphilis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The floral genome: an evolutionary history of gene duplication and shifting patterns of gene expression</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>12</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2007.06.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17658290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17658290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wellmer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Riechmann</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene networks controlling the initiation of flower development</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2010.09.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20947199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20947199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA topoisomerase Ialpha affects the floral transition</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>173</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>642</fpage><lpage>654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.16.01603</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27837087?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27837087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tetrahydrofolate modulates floral transition through epigenetic silencing</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>174</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1274</fpage><lpage>1284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.16.01750</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28450424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28450424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jiang L, Li D, Jin L, Ruan Y, Shen WH, Liu C. Histone lysine methyltransferases BnaSDG8.A and BnaSDG8.C are involved in the floral transition in Brassica napus. Plant J. 2018;95(4):672-85.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Martignago</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Goretti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerise</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Somssich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Rosa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Galbiati</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazzaro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic transcription factor complexes modulate the floral transition in Rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>29</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2801</fpage><lpage>2816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.17.00645</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29042404?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29042404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellaire</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ischebeck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Staedler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinhaeuser</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parameswaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schonenberger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weckwerth</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism and development - integration of micro computed tomography data and metabolite profiling reveals metabolic reprogramming from floral initiation to silique development</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2014</year><volume>202</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12631</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24350948?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24350948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putterill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Macknight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>It's time to flower: the genetic control of flowering time</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><year>2004</year><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.20021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15057934?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vendramin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction and optimization of a large gene Coexpression network in maize using RNA-Seq data</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>175</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>568</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.00825</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28768814?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28768814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribone</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ligterink</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilhorst</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Predictive Coexpression</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Network identifies novel genes controlling the seed-to-seedling phase transition in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>170</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2218</fpage><lpage>2231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.01704</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26888061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26888061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vesty</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Saidi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moody</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitbread</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Needs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The decision to germinate is regulated by divergent molecular networks in spores and seeds</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2016</year><volume>211</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>952</fpage><lpage>966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27257104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27257104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting critical state before phase transition of complex biological systems by hidden Markov model</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2143</fpage><lpage>2150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw154</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27153710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27153710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harkey</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Olex</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>DiNapoli</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetrow</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Muday</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of transcriptional and receptor networks that control root responses to ethylene</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>176</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>2095</fpage><lpage>2118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.00907</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29259106?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29259106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canonical correlation analysis for RNA-seq co-expression networks</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>41</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e95</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt145</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23460206?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23460206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Garbey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran-son-Tay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Berceli</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstructing regulatory networks from the dynamic plasticity of gene expression by mutual information</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>41</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e97</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt147</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23470995?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23470995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basso</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolovitzky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalla-Favera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Califano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reverse engineering of regulatory networks in human B cells</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2005</year><volume>37</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1532</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15778709?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15778709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>di Bernardo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring genetic networks and identifying compound mode of action via expression profiling</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>301</volume><issue>5629</issue><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1081900</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12843395?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12843395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantone</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Marucci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Iorio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Belcastro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Santini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>di Bernardo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>di Bernardo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosma</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A yeast synthetic network for in vivo assessment of reverse-engineering and modeling approaches</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>137</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2009.01.055</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19327819?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19327819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honkela</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Girardot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlong</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattray</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Model-based method for transcription factor target identification with limited data</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>7793</fpage><lpage>7798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0914285107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20385836?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20385836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Richer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NARROMI: a noise and redundancy reduction technique improves accuracy of gene regulatory network inference</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts619</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23080116?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23080116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring gene regulatory networks from gene expression data by path consistency algorithm based on conditional mutual information</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr626</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22088843?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22088843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conditional mutual inclusive information enables accurate quantification of associations in gene regulatory networks</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1315</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25539927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25539927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Part mutual information for quantifying direct associations in networks</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2016</year><volume>113</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>5130</fpage><lpage>5135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1522586113</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27092000?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27092000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bassel</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaab</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerjets</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasnogor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Holdsworth</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Provart</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide network model capturing seed germination reveals coordinated regulation of plant cellular phase transitions</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>9709</fpage><lpage>9714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1100958108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21593420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21593420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deciphering the Arabidopsis floral transition process by integrating a protein-protein interaction network and gene expression data</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>153</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1492</fpage><lpage>1505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.153650</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20530214?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20530214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dinh</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Farcot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The logic of the floral transition: reverse-engineering the switch controlling the identity of lateral organs</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e1005744</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005744</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28931004?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28931004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Roudier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Heese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Gey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowack</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Renou</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Grini</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Colot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Polycomb repressive complex 2 controls the embryo-to-seedling phase transition</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e1002014</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21423668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21423668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wils</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene-regulatory networks controlling inflorescence and flower development in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2017</year><volume>1860</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2016.07.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Danilevskaya</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Abadie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A gene regulatory network model for floral transition of the shoot apex in maize and its dynamic modeling</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e43450</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043450</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22912876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22912876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall-Colon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cirrone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquino</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Leran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rock</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Temporal transcriptional logic of dynamic regulatory networks underlying nitrogen signaling and use in plants</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>6494</fpage><lpage>6499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1721487115</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29769331?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29769331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time to build on good design: resolving the temporal dynamics of gene regulatory networks</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>6325</fpage><lpage>6327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1807707115</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29871952?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29871952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting early-warning signals for sudden deterioration of complex diseases by dynamical network biomarkers</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>342</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep00342</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22461973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22461973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early diagnosis of complex diseases by molecular biomarkers, network biomarkers, and dynamical network biomarkers</article-title><source>Med Res Rev</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/med.21293</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23775602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23775602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovery of dynamical network biomarkers (DNB) during the progression of atherosclerosis using multiple omic techniques and systems biology</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>70</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>C34</fpage><lpage>C35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2017.07.119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Landzberg</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovering a critical transition state from nonalcoholic hepatosteatosis to nonalcoholic steatohepatitis by lipidomics and dynamical network biomarkers</article-title><source>J Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jmcb/mjw016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26993042?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26993042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting tissue-specific early warning signals for complex diseases based on dynamical network biomarkers: study of type 2 diabetes by cross-tissue analysis</article-title><source>Brief Bioinform</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbt027</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23620135?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23620135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying critical differentiation state of MCF-7 cells for breast cancer by dynamical network biomarkers</article-title><source>Front Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>252</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2015.00252</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26284108?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26284108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early flower development in arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1990</year><volume>2</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.2.8.755</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2152125?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2152125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakuraba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis transcription factor NAC016 promotes drought stress responses by repressing AREB1 transcription through a trifurcate feed-forward regulatory loop involving NAP</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1771</fpage><lpage>1787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00222</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26059204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26059204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kierzkowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kmieciak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Piontek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojtaszek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Szweykowska-Kulinska</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarmolowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis CBP20 targets the cap-binding complex to the nucleus, and is stabilized by CBP80</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2009</year><volume>59</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>814</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03915.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19453442?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19453442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative proteomics analysis reveals that the nuclear cap-binding complex proteins arabidopsis CBP20 and CBP80 modulate the salt stress response</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2495</fpage><lpage>2510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr4012624</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24689873?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24689873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tompa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Deak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Olmedilla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnabas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New phenotypes of the drought-tolerant cbp20 Arabidopsis thaliana mutant have changed epidermal morphology</article-title><source>Plant Biol (Stuttg)</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1438-8677.2010.00343.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krishnaswamy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kav</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of four APETALA2-family genes (RAP2.6, RAP2.6L, DREB19 and DREB26) in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>75</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-010-9711-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21069430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21069430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis AP2/ERF transcription factor RAP2.6 participates in ABA, salt and osmotic stress responses</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2010</year><volume>457</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2010.02.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20193749?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20193749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nag</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DORNROSCHEN-LIKE, an AP2 gene, is necessary for stamen emergence in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>65</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-007-9210-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17682829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17682829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UVR8 interacts with WRKY36 to regulate HY5 transcription and hypocotyl elongation in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Nat Plants</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41477-017-0099-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29379156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29379156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Maoileidigh</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Graciet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellmer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene networks controlling Arabidopsis thaliana flower development</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2014</year><volume>201</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12444</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23952532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23952532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary analysis of MIKCc-type MADS-box genes in gymnosperms and angiosperms</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>895</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00895</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28611810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28611810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tapetum degeneration retardation is critical for aliphatic metabolism and gene regulation during rice pollen development</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssn028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19825565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19825565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hormonal regulation of flower development</article-title><source>J Plant Growth Regul</source><year>2010</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00344-010-9180-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonio</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Namiki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Motoyama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takehisa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamatsuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusaba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirochika</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Field transcriptome revealed critical developmental and physiological transitions involved in the expression of growth potential in japonicarice</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-11-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21226959?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21226959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dwarf and deformed flower 1, encoding an F-box protein, is critical for vegetative and floral development in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2012</year><volume>72</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>829</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2012.05126.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22897567?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22897567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbon starved anther encodes a MYB domain protein that regulates sugar partitioning required for rice pollen development</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.073668</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20305120?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20305120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Burrage</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Burrage</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carletti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stochastic delay differential equations for genetic regulatory networks</article-title><source>J Comput Appl Math</source><year>2007</year><volume>205</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cam.2006.02.063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lozoya</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Woychik</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Leveraged Signal-to-Noise ratio (LSTNR) method to extract differentially expressed genes and multivariate patterns of expression from Noisy and low-replication RNAseq data</article-title><source>Front Genet</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>24</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2018.00176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29456555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steuer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurths</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Daub</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Weise</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Selbig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mutual information: detecting and evaluating dependencies between variables</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>S231</fpage><lpage>S240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/18.suppl_2.S231</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12386007?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12386007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davuluri</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaniswamy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grotewold</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AGRIS: Arabidopsis gene regulatory information server, an information resource of Arabidopsis cis-regulatory elements and transcription factors</article-title><source>BMC Bioinf</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-4-25</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>