<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5914031</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1284</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-018-1284-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Population structure, genetic diversity and downy mildew resistance among <italic>Ocimum</italic> species germplasm</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1629-909X</contrib-id><name><surname>Pyne</surname><given-names>Robert M.</given-names></name><address><email>rpyne97@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Honig</surname><given-names>Josh A.</given-names></name><address><email>josh.honig@rutgers.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vaiciunas</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name><address><email>vaiciunas@sebs.rutgers.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wyenandt</surname><given-names>Christian A.</given-names></name><address><email>wyenandt@njaes.rutgers.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>James E.</given-names></name><address><email>jimsimon@rutgers.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8796</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430387.b</institution-id><institution>Department of Plant Biology, </institution><institution>Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey, </institution></institution-wrap>Foran Hall, 59 Dudley Rd, New Brunswick, NJ 08901 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>69</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The basil (<italic>Ocimum</italic> spp.) genus maintains a rich diversity of phenotypes and aromatic volatiles through natural and artificial outcrossing. Characterization of population structure and genetic diversity among a representative sample of this genus is severely lacking. Absence of such information has slowed breeding efforts and the development of sweet basil (<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L.) with resistance to the worldwide downy mildew epidemic, caused by&#x000a0;the&#x000a0;obligate oomycete <italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic>. In an effort to improve classification of relationships 20 EST-SSR markers with species-level transferability were developed and used to resolve relationships among a diverse panel of 180 <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions with varying response to downy mildew.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">Results obtained from nested Bayesian model-based clustering, analysis of molecular variance and unweighted pair group method using arithmetic average (UPGMA) analyses were synergized to provide an updated phylogeny of the <italic>Ocimum</italic> genus. Three (major) and seven (sub) population (cluster) models were identified and well-supported (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) by PhiPT (&#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub>) values of 0.433 and 0.344, respectively. Allelic frequency among clusters supported previously developed hypotheses of allopolyploid genome structure. Evidence of cryptic population structure was demonstrated for the k1 <italic>O. basilicum</italic> cluster suggesting prevalence of gene flow. UPGMA analysis provided best resolution for the 36-accession, DM resistant k3 cluster with consistently strong bootstrap support. Although the k3 cluster is a rich source of DM resistance introgression of resistance into the commercially important k1 accessions is impeded by reproductive barriers as demonstrated by multiple sterile F1 hybrids. The k2 cluster located between k1 and k3, represents a source of transferrable tolerance evidenced by fertile backcross progeny. The 90-accession k1 cluster was largely susceptible to downy mildew with accession &#x02018;MRI&#x02019; representing the only source of DM resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">High levels of genetic diversity support the observed phenotypic diversity among <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions. EST-SSRs provided a robust evaluation of molecular diversity and can be used for additional studies to increase resolution of genetic relationships in the <italic>Ocimum</italic> genus. Elucidation of population structure and genetic relationships among <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. germplasm provide the foundation for improved DM resistance breeding strategies and more rapid response to future disease outbreaks.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-018-1284-7) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Ocimum</italic> spp.</kwd><kwd>Downy mildew resistance</kwd><kwd>EST-SSRs</kwd><kwd>Population structure</kwd><kwd>Genetic diversity</kwd><kwd>Polyploid</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>USDA-Special Crops Research Initiative</institution></funding-source><award-id>2011-51181-30646</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100006031</institution-id><institution>United States - Israel Binational Agricultural Research and Development Fund</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>US-4947-16R</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>USDA - National Institute of Food and Agriculture</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016-68004-24931</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par31">The genus <italic>Ocimum</italic> is estimated to contain approximately 64 herbaceous annual and perennial plant species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The primary center of diversity is described as being in Tropical Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], while a secondary center exists in Tropical Asia and a tertiary center exists in the New World tropics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. A number of species are cultivated and processed throughout the world for application in medicinal, dietary supplement, essential oil, food flavoring and culinary industries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L., sweet basil, is among the most economically important culinary herbs in the United States, Europe and Israel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Plant breeding efforts have largely targeted sweet basil for improved disease resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], chilling tolerance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and novel volatile profiles (chemotypes) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par32"><italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. demonstrate relatively high rates of outcrossing in the presence of pollinators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], while readily self-pollinating in their absence. The flexibility of this reproductive system has been exploited by natural and artificial selection, likely serving as a catalyst for morphological and volatile diversification of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In addition, cytological investigation suggests this genus has also undergone extensive genome augmentation resulting in ploidy variation. While the x&#x02009;=&#x02009;12 basic chromosome&#x000a0;number is considered stable in tetraploid (2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4&#x000d7;&#x02009;=&#x02009;48) <italic>O. basilicum</italic>, different ploidies have been reported across other <italic>Ocimum</italic> species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Dual basic chromosome numbers of 8 and 12 have been proposed for two major &#x02018;Basilicum&#x02019; and &#x02018;Sanctum&#x02019; groups, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. More recently, studies involving nuclear DNA content support the hypothesis of x&#x02009;=&#x02009;12 as the genus-wide basic chromosome number with some cases of aneuploidy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This explanation accounts for dysploidy, which has proven to be a persistent phenomenon in plant evolutionary biology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The 386 Mbp <italic>O. tenuiflorum (</italic>syn. <italic>O. sanctum</italic>) genome was reported to be a diploid (2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;2&#x000d7;&#x02009;=&#x02009;16) supporting the existence of an x&#x02009;=&#x02009;8 basic chromosome number and suggesting <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> is a diploid species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Thus, competing theories of major genome structure remain prevalent in the <italic>Ocimum</italic> genus.</p><p id="Par33">Examination of chromosome pairing behavior suggests allopolyploidy likely explains the polyploid genome structure in basil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. For instance, karyological investigation of <italic>O. basilicum</italic> and <italic>O. basilicum</italic> x <italic>O. americanum</italic> F<sub>1</sub> hybrids found no evidence of tetravalent and little trivalent formation (4-8% of pollen mother cells) demonstrating high levels of preferential pairing within sub-genomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Relatively high levels of inter-specific hybridization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] suggest allopolyploid formation to be more likely than autopolyploidy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. This hypothesis is also supported by genotype data from simple sequence repeat (SSR) and single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers in the <italic>O. basilicum</italic> MRI x SB22 F<sub>2</sub> mapping family demonstrated that&#x000a0;disomic segregation providing molecular evidence for an allotetraploid (AABB) <italic>O. basilicum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par34">In addition to variation in ploidy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], a variety of factors including unknown geographic origin and phenotypic diversity complicate classification of relationships among <italic>O. basilicum</italic> and the greater <italic>Ocimum</italic> genus. Taxonomical incongruencies are also widespread throughout the literature and among seed distributors. Furthermore, absence of standardized descriptors or voucher specimens for particular cultivars has been particularly problematic in classifying <italic>O. basilicum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Species of economic salience such as <italic>O. x citriodorum</italic>, <italic>O. americanum</italic> and <italic>O. basilicum</italic> var<italic>. citriodorum</italic> are cited interchangeably throughout the literature making comparison across studies challenging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Despite attempts to standardize nomenclature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] the species epithets continue to be used redundantly.</p><p id="Par35">Morphological characters and volatile composition (chemotype) have been used to estimate genetic diversity in the <italic>Ocimum</italic> genus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Classification based on phenotypic characters is problematic in that homologous similarities may be difficult or impossible to discriminate from traits resulting from convergent evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Reliance upon analyses using these metrics may be particularly damaging in the context of plant breeding, which relies heavily upon genetic relationships among germplasm to make informed decisions with regard to selection and crossing decisions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Nevertheless, the most comprehensive study of <italic>Ocimum</italic> to date remains that of Paton et al., which relied exclusively upon morphological characters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Results of this study delineated three major divisions in the genus or subgenera corresponding into <italic>Ocimum</italic>, <italic>Nautochilus</italic> and <italic>Gymnocium</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Subgenera <italic>Ocimum</italic> is further divided into three sections including <italic>Gratissima</italic>, <italic>Hiantia</italic>, and <italic>Ocimum</italic>, where <italic>O. basilicum</italic> and <italic>O. americanum</italic> was placed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p><p id="Par36">Molecular phylogenetic approaches have employed RAPD and/or AFLP markers to determine relationships among nine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], twelve [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], twenty-two [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], twenty-eight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and thirty seven [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions. DNA markers from three plastid regions were used by Paton et al. to classify 12 <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions within the Lamiaceae family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. More recently, inter-simple sequence repeat (ISSR) markers were found to have higher polymorphism information content (PIC) and greater resolving power than chloroplast DNA (cpDNA) <italic>psbA-trnH</italic> markers following cluster analysis of 12 accessions representing 8 <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Despite being the preferred marker systems for phylogenetic analyses, neither SSR nor SNP markers have been used to classify relationships among <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions. SSRs are considered advantageous because they are multi-allelic, polymorphic, reproducible, ubiquitous throughout the genome and amenable to high-throughput genotyping with multiplexed PCR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Expressed sequence tag (EST) derived SSRs (EST-SSRs) are particularly desirable for genetic diversity and mapping studies due to their location in coding regions and transferability across related germplasm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) <italic>O. basilicum</italic> EST library was recently used to develop polymorphic SSRs and genotype the MRI x SB22 mapping population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par37">The deficit of available sweet basil genetic and genomic resources relative to other cultivated plant species has been highlighted in recent years by a worldwide downy mildew (DM) epidemic caused by the oomycete pathogen <italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. As demonstrated by extensive breeding across plant species affected by downy mildew, deployment of genetic resistance is an essential management strategy for effective disease control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Recent reports of Mefenoxam resistant <italic>P. belbahrii</italic> isolates in Israel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] and Italy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] exacerbate the need for resistant cultivars. However, development of resistant sweet basil varieties has been dramatically slowed by a severe lack of knowledge regarding genetic similarity between elite <italic>O. basilicum</italic> and exotic <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. germplasm rich in sources of resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. This has rendered attempted introgression of resistant loci into sweet basil accessions subject to rudimentary trial and error by laborious cross-pollinations between elite and exotic breeding lines. Among 27&#x000a0;F<sub>1</sub> hybrids evaluated by Ben-Naim et al., those considered &#x02018;highly resistant&#x02019; were completely sterile [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">Population structure is among the analyses most needed to better elucidate relationships among <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. Model-based clustering is a powerful analysis method frequently used to infer association of individuals into distinct populations from multilocus data sets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Association of germplasm into distinct populations provides essential a priori information needed to avoid issues of sterility while monitoring potential narrowing of the genetic pool among breeding populations. Furthermore, detection of cryptic population structure is an important prerequisite to association mapping (AM) of alleles with traits of interest (i.e. disease resistance) by avoiding false positive associations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Identification of population structure and estimation of genetic diversity among <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. is needed to provide a more robust breeding response to future biotic or abiotic stresses.</p><p id="Par39">In this study no designations of species/relationships are considered to provide an unbiased update of basil phylogenetics and first insights into population structure. We hypothesized that SSR markers developed from the available NCBI EST database could be employed to increase resolution of genetic relationships among a diverse panel of 180 <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions by population structure and genetic diversity analyses. Evaluation of these accessions for response to downy mildew provides insight into the distribution of downy mildew resistance within the <italic>Ocimum</italic> genus and has important implications for disease resistance breeding strategies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Response to <italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic></title><p id="Par40">Significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) were detected among 180 genotypes evaluated for response to DM (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Eighty-two accessions (46%) demonstrated a mean DS&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0 (considered resistant) of which 33 (18%) exhibited no sporulation (DS&#x02009;=&#x02009;0). A large proportion (17%) of the accessions with mean DS&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0 were Rutgers breeding lines with MRI-conferred DM resistance (DM<sub>MRI</sub>). DM susceptibility was widespread, however, with 71 accessions (40%) having DS&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;3.0 (considered highly susceptible). The remaining 26 accessions (15%) were in an intermediate range of DS between 1 (10%) and 3 (50%) representing levels of DM tolerance. A single accession, PI 511865, segregated for response to DM indicating heterozygosity among loci controlling resistance in this accession.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>EST-SSR polymorphism</title><p id="Par41">The 20 EST-SSR markers used in this study were pre-screened for unambiguous PCR amplification and demonstrated a low percentage of null genotypes. A list of DNA sequence and melting temperatures (T<sub>m</sub>) associated with EST-SSR markers can be found in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>. A minimum of 90% and an average of 96% of individuals were successfully genotyped across all EST-SSR markers. A total of 269 unique alleles were amplified across the 180 <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. panel and 2 outgroup <italic>Nepeta cateria</italic> accessions (CN3 and CR9). The average PIC across 20 EST-SSR markers was 0.14, ranging from 0.01 to 0.48 and 6 to 24 alleles per marker (locus) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The average number of alleles/locus across the full panel was 1.86 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Description of 20 EST-SSR markers used to classify 180-accession panel of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>MarkerID</th><th>Genbank/Contg ID</th><th>Repeat Motif</th><th>Alleles</th><th>PIC</th><th>Product Size</th><th>LG</th><th>Position (cM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>OBNJR2sg33</td><td>DY333933</td><td>(AC)16</td><td>19</td><td>0.01-0.45</td><td>271-299</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td char="." align="char">82.7</td></tr><tr><td>OBNJR2cn29</td><td>Contig1138</td><td>(AC)16</td><td>11</td><td>0.02-0.45</td><td>246-448</td><td char="." align="char">13</td><td char="." align="char">54.6</td></tr><tr><td>OBNJR2sg04</td><td>DY343638</td><td>(GA)17</td><td>27</td><td>0.01-0.48</td><td>268-357</td><td char="." align="char">13</td><td char="." align="char">40.2</td></tr><tr><td>OBNJR2sg30</td><td>DY336727</td><td>(AG)22</td><td>20</td><td>0.01-0.42</td><td>241-279</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3sg124</td><td>DY331703</td><td>(GCC)6</td><td>11</td><td>0.01-0.40</td><td>161-327</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3sg19</td><td>DY343509</td><td>(TCA)6</td><td>6</td><td>0.01-0.46</td><td>195-432</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">18.9</td></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3cn298</td><td>Contig2510</td><td>(CTA)6</td><td>9</td><td>0.01-0.42</td><td>298-322</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3cn359</td><td>Contig2911</td><td>(GGC)6</td><td>11</td><td>0.01-0.31</td><td>161-292</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3cn362</td><td>Contig2969</td><td>(TGA)6</td><td>7</td><td>0.02-0.45</td><td>225-243</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">78.0</td></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3sg155</td><td>DY325572</td><td>(GTT)7</td><td>8</td><td>0.02-0.40</td><td>188-263</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3sg168</td><td>DY323726</td><td>(GAA)7</td><td>11</td><td>0.01-0.44</td><td>297-390</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3sg113</td><td>DY335879</td><td>(CCT)7</td><td>12</td><td>0.01-0.32</td><td>313-392</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3cn56</td><td>Contig582</td><td>(AGG)7</td><td>10</td><td>0.01-0.45</td><td>169-240</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">84.7</td></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3cn74</td><td>Contig715</td><td>(CAG)7</td><td>12</td><td>0.01-0.43</td><td>211-244</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3sg145</td><td>DY328393</td><td>(GCT)8</td><td>15</td><td>0.01-0.45</td><td>271-313</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3cn03</td><td>Contig100</td><td>(CCA)10</td><td>15</td><td>0.01-0.44</td><td>198-262</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3cn210</td><td>Contig1890</td><td>(AAG)11</td><td>14</td><td>0.01-0.43</td><td>266-302</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3cn240</td><td>Contig2142</td><td>(ATA)16</td><td>24</td><td>0.01-0.37</td><td>254-370</td><td char="." align="char">19</td><td char="." align="char">88.7</td></tr><tr><td>OBNJR3sg13</td><td>DY344184</td><td>(ACA)10</td><td>14</td><td>0.01-0.36</td><td>271-312</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>OBNJR4cn17</td><td>Contig2461</td><td>(AAAT)5</td><td>13</td><td>0.01-0.41</td><td>164-365</td><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of allele distribution among clusters resulting from primary and secondary (nested) model-based cluster analyses</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Cluster</th><th>Sample size</th><th>Total alleles</th><th>Average alleles per locus</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>k1</td><td>90</td><td>3081</td><td>1.75</td></tr><tr><td>k2</td><td>16</td><td>709</td><td>2.23</td></tr><tr><td>k3</td><td>36</td><td>907</td><td>1.34</td></tr><tr><td>Admixture</td><td>38</td><td>1812</td><td>2.58</td></tr><tr><td>k1.1</td><td>51</td><td>1760</td><td>1.76</td></tr><tr><td>k1.2</td><td>28</td><td>953</td><td>1.74</td></tr><tr><td>k2.1</td><td>8</td><td>363</td><td>2.27</td></tr><tr><td>k2.2</td><td>7</td><td>301</td><td>2.18</td></tr><tr><td>k3.1</td><td>7</td><td>189</td><td>1.41</td></tr><tr><td>k3.2</td><td>18</td><td>452</td><td>1.33</td></tr><tr><td>k3.3</td><td>11</td><td>266</td><td>1.30</td></tr><tr><td>Admixture</td><td>50</td><td>2225</td><td>2.49</td></tr><tr><td>Overall</td><td>180</td><td>6509</td><td>1.86</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Population structure and allele frequency</title><p id="Par42">Primary model-based clustering (population structure) analysis provided unambiguous evidence (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>) for three major clusters k1 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;90), k2 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;16) and k3 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;36) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). The remaining 38 accessions were considered admixed due to <italic>qI</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.70 and/or genotypes of bi-parental origin from different clusters (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The average number of alleles per locus among clusters differed with values of 1.75, 2.23 and 1.34 corresponding to k1, k2 and k3, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Furthermore, clear differences were observed in the distribution of alleles per locus among clusters derived from primary population structure analysis. The majority of loci in the k1 cluster had 2 alleles (57%), nearly twice the 33% observed for single-allele loci. A more even distribution was observed in the k2 cluster with 22%, 37% and 36% for one, two and three alleles per locus. This rate of tri-allelic loci is in stark contrast to the &#x0003c;&#x02009;1% in k1 and k3 clusters and suggests three homozygous, homeologous loci among a proportion of markers in k2 cluster. A majority of loci in k3 cluster were mono-allelic, twice that of the 30% bi-allelic loci. Finally, the number of alleles for loci of admixed accessions was relatively evenly distributed from 1 to 4 ranging from 18% to 32%. Five alleles were observed in an additional 4.3% of admixed loci. A total of 1812 alleles and an average of 2.58 alleles per locus (highest among all clusters) were detected for the 38 admixed accessions indicating heterozygosity.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Primary and nested population structure for 180-accession panel of <italic>Ocimum</italic> species. Primary and secondary (nested) model-based clustering analysis using Structure ver 2.2.3 software for panels of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions using 20 EST-SSR markers. <bold>a</bold> Major clusters (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) (top histogram) and sub-clusters (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) (bottom histogram) derived from primary and nested clustering iterations. Ten accessions were admixed and nested population structure could not be inferred due to unknown parentage of admixed primary cluster membership (white bars). <bold>b</bold> Major clusters (K&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) (top histogram) and sub-clusters (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2,5,7) (bottom three histograms). &#x00394;K statistic values for K&#x02009;=&#x02009;2-10 (right). Accessions are ordered according to the unweighted pair group method using arithmetic average (UPGMA) clustering</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1284_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par43">Secondary (nested) population structure analysis provided evidence for seven clusters (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) among 142 non-admixed accessions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Two (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2) and three (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) sub-clusters within k2 (k2.1 and k2.2) and k3 (k3.1, k3.2 and k3.3.), respectively, were strongly supported by the &#x00394;K statistic (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>). Greatest support was provided for two (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2) sub-clusters, k1.1 and k1.2, among the 90-accession k1 primary cluster containing commercial sweet basil accessions. However, evidence was also provided for five (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5) and seven (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) sub-clusters (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>), suggesting cryptic population structure extant within this most economically important grouping. Nested population structure could not be determined for 9 accessions with admixed cluster membership from k1 and k3. Among these accessions, <italic>qI</italic> for either cluster (k1 or k3) failed to exceed 0.7 and could not be assigned due to unknown parentage. An additional 12 accessions had <italic>qI</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.70 (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) after being subjected to the nested population structure analysis and were considered admixed.</p><p id="Par44">The average (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) and distribution of the alleles per locus for sub-clusters was similar to the major primary clusters of k1 and k2. The range of alleles per locus among k1, k2 and k3 sub-clusters were 1.74-1.76, 2.18-2.27 and 1.30-1.41, respectively, indicating a high level of consistency with regard to allelic diversity. Interestingly, a relatively high percentage (11.2%) of null alleles occurred among accessions of sub-cluster k3.2.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Molecular variance</title><p id="Par45">Analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) was performed using 142 and 130 non-admixed accessions determined by primary and nested model-based cluster analysis, respectively. Inter-population differentiation was supported at the <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 level for primary and nested population structure with &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub> values of 0.433 and 0.344, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The molecular variance due to differences within populations for nested clustering was 66% as compared to 57% from primary clustering. All pairwise &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub> values for (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) clusters were significantly different (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The majority of pairwise &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub> values were highly significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) for the seven (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) clusters derived from nested analysis (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). However, k3.1, k3.2 and k3.3 failed to demonstrate evidence for population differentiation based on AMOVA results (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). These three sub-clusters contributed 51% of the total within population sum of squares (SS<sub>WP</sub>) while representing only 5.4% of the accessions included in the AMOVA (data not shown). Thus, high within population genetic variation coupled with a lower sample size may have lowered resolution for differentiation of these sub-clusters.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Analyses of molecular variance (AMOVA) for non-admixed panel of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. using 20 EST-SSR markers among clusters resulting from primary and secondary (nested) model-based cluster analyses</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Clustering Iteration</th><th>Source</th><th>df<sup>a</sup></th><th>Sum of squares</th><th>Mean square</th><th>Estimated &#x003c3;<sup>2</sup></th><th>Molecular &#x003c3;<sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3">Primary<sup>b</sup></td><td>Among<sup>d</sup></td><td>2</td><td>997.3</td><td>498.6</td><td>13.0</td><td>43%</td></tr><tr><td>Within<sup>e</sup></td><td>139</td><td>2367.4</td><td>17.0</td><td>17.0</td><td>57%</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>141</td><td>3364.7</td><td/><td>30.0</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Nested<sup>c</sup></td><td>Among</td><td>6</td><td>996.9</td><td>166.1</td><td>9.0</td><td>34%</td></tr><tr><td>Within</td><td>123</td><td>2108.7</td><td>17.1</td><td>17.1</td><td>66%</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>129</td><td>3105.7</td><td/><td>26.1</td><td>100%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Degrees of freedom</p><p><sup>b</sup>Primary model-based clustering iteration (<italic>K&#x02009;=&#x02009;3</italic>). &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.433; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p><p><sup>c</sup>Nested model-based clustering iteration (<italic>K&#x02009;=&#x02009;7</italic>). &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.344; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p><p><sup>d</sup> Among clusters</p><p><sup>e</sup>Within clusters</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Pairwise &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub> estimates for clusters resulting from the primary model-based cluster analyses</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Cluster</th><th>k1</th><th>k2</th><th>k3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>k1</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>k2</td><td>0.576</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>k3</td><td>0.392</td><td>0.356</td><td>0.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>All &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub> estimates were highly significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Pairwise &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub> estimates for resulting from the secondary model-based cluster analyses</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sub-Cluster</th><th>k1.1</th><th>k1.2</th><th>k2.1</th><th>k2.2</th><th>k3.1</th><th>k3.2</th><th>k3.3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>k1.1</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>k1.2</td><td>0.057</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>k2.1</td><td>0.572</td><td>0.600</td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>k2.2</td><td>0.539</td><td>0.560</td><td>0.042<sup>NS</sup></td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>k3.1</td><td>0.376</td><td>0.389</td><td>0.354</td><td>0.243<sup>*</sup></td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>k3.2</td><td>0.418</td><td>0.406</td><td>0.361</td><td>0.289</td><td>0.000<sup>NS</sup></td><td>0.000</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>k3.3</td><td>0.433</td><td>0.420</td><td>0.339</td><td>0.276</td><td>0.034<sup>NS</sup></td><td>0.021<sup>NS</sup></td><td>0.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>NS</sup>not significantly different <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05, <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; all other &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub> estimates were highly significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Characterization of genetic relationships</title><p id="Par46">A cophenetic correlation value of <italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.934 indicated strong goodness of fit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] between the genetic similarity matrix used and the UPGMA dendrogram generated. Furthermore, the UPGMA dendrogram is in agreement with the placement of accessions for all major clusters (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) determined by population structure analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>-<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">b</xref>). The k1 cluster demonstrated generally lower genetic diversity as evidenced by high Jaccard similarity coefficient values (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Importantly, accessions within the k1 cluster largely grouped consistent with known pedigree information available for 61% of accessions. The k2 cluster divides, according to nested population structure, into two clades of comparable genetic diversity. Although delineation of k3 into three sub-clusters was not supported by AMOVA, high bootstrap support values provide evidence of distinct groupings with high statistical backing (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). UPGMA grouping among k1 accessions did not demonstrate the same level of bootstrap support, however, this was not unexpected considering the ambiguity of nested model-based cluster&#x000a0;analysis results.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Primary population structure and UPGMA clustering for 180-accession panel of <italic>Ocimum</italic> species. Unweighted pair group method using arithmetic average (UPGMA) dendrogram aligned with primary model-based clustering of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. 180-accession panel and 2 outgroup accessions (1 and 2) using 20 EST-SSR markers. Genetic distance was calculated using the Jaccard Similarity Coefficient (x-axis) and bootstrap support&#x000a0;values are the result of 1000 permutations with support value greater than 0.500 shown. Three clusters (<italic>K</italic>) were inferred using Structure ver 2.2.3 and membership to each cluster is represented by proportion of yellow, orange or blue colors within horizontal lines corresponding to each accession. Numbers right of membership histograms correspond to accessions. Response to downy mildew is indicated resistant (R)&#x02009;=&#x02009;DS&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0, intermediate (I)&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;DS&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;3.0 or susceptible (S)&#x02009;=&#x02009;DS&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3.0. Accessions with response R* share a single source of resistance conferred by accession MRI. The figure is divided into two segments <bold>a</bold> (left) and <bold>b</bold> (right)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1284_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par47">The k1 cluster roots to a single major node that can be further divided into three distinct groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). This k1 cluster includes a commercial sweet basil clade that begins with &#x02018;Caesar&#x02019; (Accession 3) and ends with &#x02018;Lettuce Leaf Heirloom&#x02019; (Accession 31).&#x000a0;Included are all accessions classified as <italic>O. basilicum</italic> such as the commercially important variety &#x02018;Nufar&#x02019; (acc.&#x000a0;19) originally developed for FOB resistance and widely cultivated worldwide. In addition, all chilling (acc. 8-16) and FOB (acc. 13, 20-23, 27) tolerant Rutgers breeding lines are included in this group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). A second major k1 clade includes two lineages RUMS (acc. 33-39) and RU4S (acc. 40-46, 48-59) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>) derived from breeding for DM<sub>MRI</sub> resistance. The resistant genotypeMRI (acc.&#x000a0;47) is centrally located among accessions in these lineages. USDA-GRIN accession PI 197442 (acc.&#x000a0;60) and all remaining k1 accessions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>) vary substantially in phenotype and aromatic volatile composition (data not published). Accessions in this k1 clade are primarily cultivated for specialty or ornamental markets with the exception of &#x02018;Eleonora&#x02019; (acc.&#x000a0;69), a variety marketed for commercial fresh market consumption.</p><p id="Par48">A k1 x k2 admixed, hybrid clade is supported by UPGMA analysis and can be observed at the top of Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>. This clade includes F<sub>1</sub>, F<sub>2</sub> or F<sub>2:3</sub> progeny with low or no fertility&#x000a0;from a&#x000a0;k1 x k2&#x000a0; bi-parental cross. PI 172996 (acc.&#x000a0;116) and &#x02018;Sweet Dani&#x02019; (acc.&#x000a0;115) comprise all k2 parents with the exception of RU_SB22XLIME_F1 (acc.&#x000a0;97) and PI_652060XRU_SB17_F1 (acc.&#x000a0;98).</p><p id="Par49">The k2 cluster corresponds to a major clade, which is further divided into two groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Nested population structure analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>) and bootstrap support values (0.504 and 0.744) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>) are both in agreement with this sub-division. Accessions in this cluster are described by their sources as <italic>O. basilicum</italic>, <italic>O. citriodorum</italic> or <italic>O. americanum</italic> (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Three accessions cluster separately from&#x000a0;all other k2 accessions and constitute a k2 x k3 hybrid grouping. Another k1 x k3 admixed clade is well-supported (0.938) and includes three F<sub>1</sub> hybrids derived from a cross between DM resistant k3 parent &#x02018;Spice&#x02019; (acc.&#x000a0;139) and three different k1 accessions. Two additional USDA-GRIN accessions, PI 414201 (acc.&#x000a0;140) and PI 414203 (acc.&#x000a0;141), are included in this clade and parentage is unknown.</p><p id="Par50">Although the division of k3 into sub-clusters k3.1, k3.2 and k3.3 suggested by nested population structure analysis was not supported by the pairwise &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub> estimates (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>), UPGMA provides evidence of clear delineations within this major cluster (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). The k3.1 cluster includes 7 phenotypically indistinguishable accessions sourced from commercial seed companies and the USDA-GRIN. This cluster is highly supported (1.00) and evidently an autonomous population (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Another well-supported clade (0.997) is the k3.2 cluster (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), which includes 11 accessions beginning with PI 500952 (acc.&#x000a0;175) through PI 500942 (acc.&#x000a0;171). UPGMA analysis suggests this cluster represents a rather substantial juncture from the rest of the panel as it and subsequent clades are considered more basal than even the two <italic>Nepeta cataria</italic> outgroup accessions CN3 and CR9 according to UPGMA clustering. The k3.2 cluster is phenotypically homogenous and labeled <italic>O. x africanum</italic> according to the USDA-GRIN system. The k3.3 cluster includes basal most clades of the UPGMA dendrogram and the highest levels of genetic diversity based on Jaccard Similarity Coefficient genetic distance estimates shown as branch lengths in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>. All accessions within this clade, supported by a 0.509 bootstrap value, are classified <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> according to their sources (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Within this clade bootstrap support values of 0.875, 0.977 and 0.897 support grouping of three more closely related pairs of accessions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). PI 511865 (acc.&#x000a0;182) is labeled <italic>O. selloi</italic> and&#x000a0;groups (0.980) with the phenotypically similar &#x02018;Green Pepper Basil&#x02019; (acc.&#x000a0;181) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> and <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> accessions were used as outgroups in a previous AFLP-based assessment of basil phylogenetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], but did not include <italic>O. selloi</italic> found to be more basal in this study.</p><p id="Par51">A number of additional accessions have membership to the k3.3 sub-cluster yet are more distally located from the basal end of the dendrogram (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). This includes phenotypically similar PI 652052&#x000a0;(acc. 145) and &#x02018;Camphor&#x02019;&#x000a0;(acc. 149); the former is classified <italic>O. x africanum</italic> by the USDA-GRIN, but more likely <italic>O. kilimandsharicum</italic> based on morphology and as described by Ben-Naim et al. [41]. These accessions group within a clade supported by a bootstrap support value of 0.907 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). A second, well-supported (0.867) clade included those with inferred ancestry to k3.3 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). These accessions are classified <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> by commercial and USDA-GRIN sources (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Strong bootstrap support and phenotypic homogeneity among these two sets of accessions indicate UPGMA best resolves these k3 relationships.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Geographic distribution among clusters</title><p id="Par52">In contrast to the greater panel, information regarding origin is available for the majority of k3 accessions (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). All accessions in the k3.2 cluster were collected in Zambia indicating this grouping may be native to south-central Africa. Accessions in k3.1 and k3.3 are far less geographically congruent. Sub-cluster k3.3 includes diverse New and Old World geographic collections ranging from South America (PI 511865; Uruguay) to South East Asia (PI 652055; Sri Lanka) to Sub-Saharan Africa (PI 652064; Tanzania). The collection locations of four known accessions in k2.1 are split between Turkey (PI 172996; PI 172998) and Iran (PI 253157; 296391) suggesting a Middle-Eastern grouping. The remaining k2.1 accessions are cultivars with unknown parentage developed for a volatile composition high in monoterpenoids geranial and neral (i.e. citral). The k2.2 sub-cluster includes PI 652060 and PI 652061 collected in Pakistan and India, respectively, however, geographic origin of the remaining five accessions are unknown. The k1 cluster is comprised of largely commercial and Rutgers breeding lines in which parentage or geographical origin of parents is unknown. Ten of 12 USDA-GRIN accessions were collected in Turkey, Iran or Macedonia.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Distribution of DM resistance</title><p id="Par53">Two unique sources of DM resistance (mean DS&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0), MRI (acc. 47) and Kivumbisi Lime x RUSB_17 F1 (acc.&#x000a0;83), were identified in the major cluster k1. The former accession has been used to develop DM<sub>MRI</sub> resistant breeding lines, while the latter is a sterile F<sub>1</sub> hybrid with DM resistance conferred from the admixed accession 153 ('Kivumbisi Lime'). Apart from these two sources of resistance, the k1 cluster was largely DM susceptible with a mean DS of 3.6. Seven accessions demonstrated an intermediate response to DM (1.0&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;DS&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;3.0) and may be incorporated into breeding strategies targeting durable resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par54">The frequency of DM intermediate and resistant accessions increased with genetic distance from the k1 cluster. Intermediate resistance was observed among the majority of k2 accessions reflected by the 2.27 mean DS for this cluster. Interestingly, the k2.1 mean DS of 1.5 was lower than for k2.2 (mean DS&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.4) for which the lowest DS was 2.9 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Major cluster k3 is the primary source of DM resistance (mean DS&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.36) with 29 resistant, 4 intermediate and one susceptible genotype. The highly supported (bootstrap&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.867) clade of four accessions 156 - 159 exhibited hypersensitive response (HR). This response was not completely effective in preventing sporulation for these accessions such as 159 (PI 652057) (DS&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.57) (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Downy mildew response phenotype distribution among <italic>Ocimum</italic> species clusters. Distribution of disease severity among sub-clusters derived from secondary (nested) model-based clustering analysis using Structure ver 2.2.3 software</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1284_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par55">Fourteen F<sub>1</sub> hybrid accessions developed from DM resistant parents demonstrated resistance with the exception of SB17 x 172996&#x000a0;F1 (acc.100) with DS&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.75. These results are in agreement with previous evaluation of F<sub>1</sub> progeny providing corroborating evidence of dominant gene action [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Three k1 x k3 DM resistant F<sub>1</sub> hybrids developed from &#x02018;Spice&#x02019;&#x000a0;(acc.133), &#x02018;Kivumbisi Lime&#x02019;&#x000a0;(acc. 153) and &#x02018;Camphor&#x02019;&#x000a0;(acc. 149) exhibit introgressed k3 resistance but were completely sterile. Hybrids from k1 accessions crossed with&#x000a0;DM resistant and intermediate k2.1 accessions PI 172996&#x000a0;(acc. 116) and &#x02018;Sweet Dani&#x02019;&#x000a0;(acc. 115) demonstrated low fertility that could be overcome, however, an intermediate and susceptible response was observed for the respective F1 progeny (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Thus, unlike k3 accessions resistance did not appear to be under dominant gene control and requires further investigation to characterize the mechanism of DM response.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Population structure and genetic diversity</title><p id="Par56">Model-based and UPGMA clustering analyses provide evidence of three distinct delineations and 15.6% admixture among the 180 <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accession panel. Nested population structure analysis provides additional evidence for seven sub-populations. Greatest support (&#x00394;<italic>K</italic>) was provided for two distinct populations (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2) nested within the most economically important <italic>O. basilicum</italic> k1 cluster. However, the possibility of five and seven sub-populations could not be discounted (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). Cryptic population structure in the k1 cluster may be attributed to extensive interbreeding, which is particularly prevalent in the <italic>O. basilicum</italic> species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. High levels of admixture were also observed for the K&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 and K&#x02009;=&#x02009;7 population models (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>), further supporting the exchange of genomic content potentially as a function of natural and purposeful outcrossing. This is most evident in the k1.2 cluster, where both admixture (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>) and genetic distance increase (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>) proceeding towards the basal end of the dendrogram containing a large proportion of cultivars and USDA-GRIN accessions (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). These results indicate plant breeding and natural outcrossing have maintained some level of genetic diversity within this economically salient cluster of accessions.</p><p id="Par57">The k1 cluster was the largest in this study with 90 accessions, yet best evidence was provided for only two sub-clusters, which was also the case for the 16-accessions&#x000a0;in k2. Furthermore, the 36-accession k3 cluster resolved into three sub-clusters and may potentially contain additional populations based on interpretation of UPGMA analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). While these results do not necessarily suggest a bottleneck in k1, the k2 and k3 clusters clearly exhibit far greater genetic diversity. Introgression of accessions from the k2 and k3 clusters would be advantageous in broadening the k1 (<italic>O. basilicum</italic>) gene pool.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Taxonomical discrepancies</title><p id="Par58">Results of this study find genetic distance and population inference is often not correlated with reported accession collection location, phenotype or even species epithet. Conflicting and redundant nomenclature in the literature, the USDA-GRIN system and commercial seed sources have confounded accurate species-level assignment to important <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Phenotype appears to be somewhat predictive of genotype in clusters k3.1 and k3.2, however, leaf shape, habit, flower morphology and volatile composition are clearly heterogeneous among the remaining sub-clusters. For instance, k2.1 accessions 115 ('Sweet Dani') and 116 (PI 172996) group within a single clade (0.553), however, Sweet Dani exhibits no anthocyanins and a volatile composition that is 68% citral [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], while PI 172996 exhibits leaf and stem anthocyanins and a volatile composition 91% methyl chavicol [USDA-GRIN]. Meanwhile, k1.2 cluster&#x000a0;accesions 77 ('Queenette') and 78 ('Sweet Thai') contain stem anthocyanins and high methyl chavicol comparable to PI 172996. Although phenotype-based classification may provide some predictive measure of genetic relatedness, applications such as plant breeding require highly accurate and precise understanding of relations among accessions in order to construct effective selection strategies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Ploidy and reproductive barriers</title><p id="Par59">Interesting differences in the mean and distribution of alleles per locus were observed among major and sub-clusters in this study. The majority of non-admixed accessions included in the panel are considered highly inbred and therefore homozygous across loci. Given this general assumption, some inferences can be made with regard to ploidy. A majority bi-allelic loci among k1 accessions suggests this cluster is an allotetraploid with two homozygous loci representing two sub-genomes. This system has been previously observed for the well-characterized allotetraploid genomes of <italic>Brassica napus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. One and two alleles per locus were observed in 33 and 57% of loci in the k1 cluster, respectively. These results are similar to the distribution of alleles per locus in a 240 EST-SSR marker survey using inbred k1 genotypes SB22 and MRI, in which a polymorphic subset also demonstrated disomic inheritance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par60">Among accessions in the k2 cluster, a 36% rate of three alleles per locus provides evidence of three homeologous loci, suggesting an allohexaploid genome. Previous investigations of cytology and nuclei acid content for the species <italic>O. africanum</italic> (syn. <italic>O. citriodorum</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] suggested an allohexaploid (2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6&#x000d7;&#x02009;=&#x02009;72) genome structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Allelic distribution and cluster analysis in this study both support the hypothesis of an allohexaploid <italic>O. africanum</italic> k2 cluster and a need for nomenclature to be standardized across these accessions. Confusingly, USDA-GRIN accessions in the strongly supported (0.997) sub-cluster (k3.2) are labeled as <italic>O. xafricanum</italic>, illustrating the continued <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. taxonomic issues and a need for revision of nomenclature. Hybridization of k1 and k2 accessions was previously characterized as an interspecific crosses with low fertility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. All 17&#x000a0;k1 x k2&#x000a0;F<sub>1</sub>, F<sub>2</sub> and F<sub>2:3</sub> accessions in this study demonstrated low fertility. This is in agreement with a previous report of low fertility of the PI 172996&#x000a0;(acc. 116) x &#x02018;Peri&#x02019; F<sub>1</sub> hybrid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. In this study <italic>O. basilicum</italic> accession &#x02018;Peri&#x02019; is replaced with SB17 (acc. 20)&#x000a0;and used as recurrent parent to generate the RU172S BC<sub>1</sub> progeny (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Three RU172S BC<sub>1</sub> individuals demonstrated increased fertility relative to the F<sub>1</sub>, suggesting restoration of reproductive viability may be correlated with increased k1 membership and providing a platform for development of near isogenic lines (NILs). Thus, introgression of traits such as disease resistance from k2 accessions to commercial sweet basil is possible through backcross breeding.</p><p id="Par61">A majority (60%) of single allele loci among k3 accessions was nearly two- and three-fold greater than k1 and k2, respectively. One of two scenarios are likely to explain the predominance of single-allele EST-SSRs among k3 accessions. First, it is possible that a divergent sub-genome is shared among k3 accessions, but does not have adequate homology for transferability of SSR markers derived from <italic>O. basilicum</italic> EST database. This would suggest a system similar to triplicated <italic>Brassica</italic> genomes in which <italic>B. napus</italic> AACC and <italic>B. juncea</italic> AABB have only the A genomes in common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. A second possibility is the complete absence of a sub-genome, which would suggest k3 as a diploid cluster. A diploid genome hypothesis was previously proposed for k3 <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> and <italic>O. tenuiforum</italic> accessions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], which have consistently lower 2C-values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Furthermore, the recently sequenced genome of <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> genotype &#x02018;CIM Ayu&#x02019; is described as a diploid (2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;2&#x000d7;&#x02009;=&#x02009;16) with a 386 Mbp genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], more than ten-fold less than tetraploid <italic>O. basilicum</italic> based on 2C estimates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Koroch et al. [13] reported a 2C-value for k3.3 accession 160 (PI 652066,&#x000a0;<italic>O. campechianum</italic>) significantly lower (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) than k3.1 accession 143 (PI 652059, <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic>). Accession&#x000a0;182 (PI 511865) was the most basal accession in this study (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), yet is reported to have a 2C-value comparable to PI 652059&#x000a0;(acc. 143) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Thus, comparison of previously reported nucleic acid content with allelic distribution, genetic distance estimates and cluster analyses in this study suggest a complex <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. genome evolution with multiple chromosomal accumulation and/or deletion events.</p><p id="Par62">Three F<sub>1</sub> progeny of k3.1 accession 139 ('Spice') hybridized with <italic>O. basilicum</italic> k1.1 accessions 22 (RUSB_09), 6 ('DiGenova') and 47 (MRI) form a well-supported (0.938) clade with admixed accessions 135 (PI 414201) and 136 (PI&#x000a0;414203) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Sterility among these progeny suggest a major reproductive barrier between commercially important <italic>O. basilicum</italic> k1.1 accessions and highly supported (1.00) k3 clade. Ben-Naim et al. reported F<sub>1</sub> sterility among progeny of DM resistant accessions 161 (PI 500945) and 168 (PI 500950) hybridized with <italic>O. basilicum</italic> accession &#x02018;Peri&#x02019; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. These accessions are found in the k2.2 sub-cluster suggesting the k1 x k3&#x000a0;F1 sterility barrier extends to this more basal clade (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Surprising k1 <italic>qI</italic> among a number of non-hybrid k3 accessions 149-155 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>) suggests the possibility of recently shared ancestry between these clusters. However, sterility among Kivumbisi Lime x SB17 progeny demonstrates high k1.1 <italic>qI</italic> does not correspond to fertility. Viable F<sub>1</sub> progeny could not be obtained from cross-pollination of k1.1 and k3.3 accessions. This is consistent with at least one previous report of attempted <italic>O. basilicum</italic> x <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> hybridization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p><p id="Par63">Although evidence of varying ploidy levels is a suspected cause of reproductive barriers among wide crosses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] the exact mechanism remains unclear. Comparative genomic analysis of cultivated and wild <italic>Solanum</italic> spp. demonstrate seed and pollen infertility can be controlled by a small number of loci with shared evolutionary history [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Further investigation is needed to determine the cause of infertility among <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Distribution of DM resistance and breeding</title><p id="Par64">Forty-three unique sources of genetic resistance to DM are identified from greenhouse screening in this study. These&#x000a0;resistant&#x000a0; accessions are heavily concentrated in the k3 cluster with 29 from 7 species according to the sources from which they were obtained (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). An additional 9 resistant&#x000a0;accessions had majority k3 <italic>qI</italic> membership and UPGMA placement among k3 accessions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). 116 (PI 172996), 117 (PI 172998) and 119 (PI 296391) were first identified as having little or no disease incidence by Pyne et al. 2013. These accessions demonstrated minimal leaf sporulation in this study (DS&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.63) and were determined to be in a population (k2) distinct from commercial sweet basil (k1). MRI&#x000a0;(acc. 47) represents the only source of DM resistance (DM<sub>MRI</sub>) identified in the <italic>O. basilicum</italic> k1 cluster. Recently discovered QTL <italic>dm11.1</italic> demonstrated dominant gene action conferred by MRI&#x000a0;(acc.47), but detection of additional minor QTL explained additional phenotypic variance and a somewhat complex mechanism for highest levels of resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par65">These accessions represent candidates for field confirmation of resistance to <italic>P. belbahrii</italic> and, ultimately, DM resistance breeding. Ben-Naim et al. found DM response in greenhouse and field experiments to be largely correlated. Response of accessions common across this and previous greenhouse studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] is generally consistent with minor differences. Differential disease response of genotypes across studies may be due to a number of confounding effects including environment, inoculum concentration and rating system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Another possibility of greater consequence to disease control is the potential occurrence of pathogen evolution resulting in races exhibiting differential host virulence. Proliferation of races is common among the most economically devastating downy mildews such as <italic>Pseudoperonospora cubensis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], <italic>Bremia lactuca</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] and <italic>Hyaloperonospora brassicae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Phylogenetic characterization of <italic>P. belbahrii</italic> isolates is needed to determine the range of genetic diversity and identify possible extant pathogen races.</p><p id="Par66">Candidacy of accessions for DM resistance breeding is contingent upon sexual compatibility and reproductive capacity with commercial sweet basil found in sub-cluster k1.1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). DM resistance from k1.1 accession&#x000a0;47 (MRI) is the only documented characterization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] and introgression of genetic resistance beyond F<sub>1</sub> progeny. Partial sterility observed for k1 x k2 crosses appears to be surmountable by backcrossing as demonstrated by the &#x02018;RU172S17&#x02019; BC<sub>1</sub> accessions 89-92 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). This represents a potential strategy for introduction of k2 genomic DNA associated with important traits such as&#x000a0;intermediate DM&#x000a0;resistance (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) and FOB resistance available in many of these accessions. An intermediate DM response (DS&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.75) for the SB17 x PI 172996&#x000a0;F1 hybrid was significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) higher than resistant parent PI 172996 and closer to the mid-parent DS of 2.18 suggesting resistance may be quantitative. The heritability of DM resistance from k2 accessions such as PI 172996 is unclear and requires further investigation.</p><p id="Par67">The k3 cluster represents a rich source of genetic resistance. Furthermore, consistent non-significant differences in disease response for F<sub>1</sub> progeny and their resistant parent indicate dominant gene action is widespread among these candidates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Qualitative and, in particular, single dominant gene control of DM is well documented across plant species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. HR in <italic>O. tenuiflorum</italic> accessions 156-159 indicates effector triggered immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], a response distinct from the remaining k3 accessions in which no signs or symptoms were observed. It remains unclear whether these accessions have evolved unique resistance genes, but nonhost resistance is more likely among distant relatives of susceptible k1 accessions. Introgression of nonhost resistance from wild lettuce relatives <italic>Lactuca serriola</italic> and <italic>Lactuca saligna</italic> to commercial <italic>L. sativa</italic> is being used to build durable DM resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Further investigation is needed to identify redundancy of resistant genes, especially among closely related accessions. </p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par68">Results of this study provide a robust characterization of population structure, genetic diversity and response to DM among <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. EST-SSRs provide a useful tool for increased resolution of this genus through continued germplasm collection and genotyping. Although evidence is concurrent for allotetraploid and allohexaploid genomes among economically important k1 and k2 clusters, respectively, the highly diverse and DM resistance-rich k3 cluster remains complicated by discrepancies in reports of genome size. Characterization of subgenomes as shared or distinct among allopolyploid species and identification of a diploid progenitor(s) are needed to elucidate genome structure.</p><p id="Par69">As breeding among specialty crops becomes increasingly prevalent, more sophisticated tools will be required. This trend is evidenced in <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. by recent development of a first draft genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], de novo meta-transcriptomics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>] and genetic/QTL mapping [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Determination of major and cryptic population structure as well as phylogenetic classification among DM resistant candidates provides another important resource for accelerated genetic improvement.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par70">A 180-accession panel of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. was selected to provide a genus-wide representation of genetic diversity, while targeting germplasm developed primarily for improved performance in important agronomic traits at Rutgers University (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Eight chilling (&#x0201c;RUCB&#x0201d;) and 7 <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>basilici</italic> (FOB) (&#x0201c;RUSB&#x0201d;) tolerant <italic>O. basilicum</italic> inbred lines were selected. Twenty-nine breeding lines were included from two lineages (&#x0201c;RU4S&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;RUMS&#x0201d;) selected for DM resistance. Eighteen F<sub>1</sub> hybrids were developed from hybridization of 9 <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions of varying DM response with 4 DM-susceptible <italic>O. basilicum</italic> inbred lines. All cross-pollinations were performed according to Pyne et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Seven F<sub>2</sub> selections and a single F<sub>2:3</sub> individual were included. Four first-generation backcross lines selected for FOB resistance (&#x0201c;RU172S&#x0201d;) were also included. Remaining accessions were obtained from either commercial seed companies or the USDA-GRIN repository (Aimes, IA), ultimately representing 10 species according to these sources. Finally, two catnip (<italic>Nepeta cataria</italic>) accessions (CN3 and CR9) were included as outgroup species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Disease rating (phenotypic evaluation)</title><p id="Par71">Seed from commercial, USDA-GRIN and inbred accessions were planted in Fafard Growing Mix 2 (Sun Gro Horticulture, Agawam, MA) and germinated under intermittent misting. Hybrid and non-flowering accessions (&#x02018;Pesto Perpetuo&#x02019;, &#x02018;GCB&#x02019; and &#x02018;Pezou&#x02019;) were cloned by vegetative cutting from mother plants under intermittent misting. The <italic>P. belbahrii</italic> isolate collected at the Rutgers Agricultural Research and Extension Center (RAREC) in 2013 and maintained on susceptible check variety &#x02018;DiGenova&#x02019; was used in this study. Inoculum was prepared and applied to first true leaf sets according to Pyne et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Eight seedlings (individuals) per each accession were inoculated and disease ratings were performed 10&#x000a0;days post inoculation (DPI) corresponding to the interval at which disease severity plateaus under these greenhouse conditions. Individual plants were assigned a disease severity score using an ordered categorical scale in which 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;no sporulation, 1&#x02009;=&#x02009;1-10%, 2&#x02009;=&#x02009;11-25%, 3&#x02009;=&#x02009;26-50%, 4&#x02009;=&#x02009;51-100% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. A disease severity score&#x000a0;(DS) was assigned to each accession from the average of 8 individuals for two, repeated experiments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>EST-SSR genotyping</title><p id="Par72">Young leaves were harvested from axillary nodes of each accession in this study, frozen and then ground using mortar and pestle. Genomic DNA (gDNA) was extracted from ~&#x02009;80&#x000a0;mg of ground leaf tissue for all accessions using the E.N.Z.A. SP Plant DNA Kit (Omega BioTek, Norcross, GA).</p><p id="Par73">A set of 240 EST-SSR markers were previously developed and used to genotype the accessions MRI and SB22 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Preliminary experiments identified 20 di-, tri- and tetranucleotide repeat markers demonstrating reliable, unambiguous amplification across replicated PCR evaluations in a diverse subset of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp. accessions. Given the putative allopolyploid genome structure of these species, markers were considered to be amplified in shared sub-genomes and, thus, orthologous. Seven of the 20 selected markers were previously mapped to&#x000a0;a sweet basil linkage map developed from MRI x SB22 F<sub>2</sub> mapping population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. All primers were synthesized by Integrated DNA technologies (Coralville, IA). Multiplexed PCR was performed using conditions and fluorescent dyes (FAM, NED, PET and VIC) previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Fragments generated from PCR were separated by capillary electrophoresis using an ABI 3500xL Genetic Analyzer (Life Technologies Corporation, Carlsbad, CA). Genemapper 4.1 (Applied Biosystems) software was used to determine fragment size for alleles across all accessions and exported for downstream analysis.</p><p id="Par74">Polyploidy is a confounding factor in population genetic studies due to the complication of allelic configuration among genotypes. In allopolyploid accessions of a single ploidy amplification of loci in independent sub-genomes provides a platform for conversion to a diploid SSR genotyping system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Accurate, multi-allelic (codominant) genotype assignment of complex germplasm panels with multiple ploidy levels in the absence of subgenome assignment exceeds current data analysis capabilities. Genotype data in this study was therefore scored as binary (presence&#x02009;=&#x02009;1; absence/null&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) as suggested by Honig et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. SSR markers absent of any alleles (primer site mutation) or having many (&#x0003e;&#x02009;6) alleles (non-specific primer binding) were considered null and coded &#x02018;0&#x02019;. Genotypes were coded &#x02018;-1&#x02019; in the case of missing data. Polymorphic information content (PIC) was calculated for individual alleles using the formula 2P<sub>i</sub>Q<sub>i</sub>, where P<sub>i</sub> is the frequency of presence and Q<sub>i</sub> is the frequency of absence for a given allele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. The binary genotype matrix for all accessions and SSR markers used in this study can be found in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Phenotype data analysis</title><p id="Par75">Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed using R software to determine whether the effect of genotype was significant with respect to the response variable, DS. The agricolae package in R was used to perform DS mean separation using Tukey&#x02019;s honest significant difference (HSD) test with &#x003b1;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05. All accessions were included in this analysis with the exception of PI 511865, which was found to segregate and, thus, could not be treated as a single genotype.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Population structure analysis</title><p id="Par76">To determine population structure, a nested Bayesian model-based clustering approach described by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>] was implemented with Structure ver 2.3.4 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] to infer assignment of individuals to <italic>K</italic> clusters and sub-clusters. This approach has been effective in identifying important major and cryptic population structure in various plant species including apple [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>], cotton [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] and rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. All simulations were performed using the &#x02018;admixture model&#x02019; with &#x02018;correlated allele frequencies&#x02019;. The algorithm was executed with parameters set to a burnin of 100,000 followed by 200,000 Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) repetitions with 10 replicated runs per <italic>K</italic>. Initial (primary) Structure analysis was performed for <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 &#x02013; 15 using all 180 accessions to determine major delineations in overall population structure. Evanno&#x02019;s method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>] was employed to&#x000a0;provide an estimate of the most likely number of clusters using Structure Harvester software v0.6.94 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>] to determine the natural logarithm probability Pr(X|K) and ad hoc &#x00394;K statistic (mean(|L&#x0201d;(<italic>K</italic>)|) / sd(L(<italic>K</italic>)) from membership coefficient (<italic>qI</italic>) matrices. Following selection of the optimal <italic>K</italic> for all replicated runs, the FULLSEARCH algorithm of CLUMPP software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>] was used to identify the optimal permuted order of <italic>qI</italic> matrices with the greatest pairwise similarity. The average of this permutation provided the best <italic>qI</italic> matrix representation, which was visualized using DISTRUCT software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>].</p><p id="Par77">Determinations of the <italic>qI</italic> threshold at which to infer cluster assignment vary by study, but range from <italic>qI</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>] &#x02013; 0.8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Inclusion of wide crosses (F<sub>1</sub>, F<sub>2</sub> and BC<sub>1</sub>) in this study provided a measure of high admixture, which informed the selection of 0.70 as an appropriate <italic>qI</italic> threshold. Thus, accessions were assigned to the cluster for which <italic>qI</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.70, while those with a maximum <italic>qI</italic> less than 0.70 were considered admixed. In addition, hybrid (F<sub>1</sub>, F<sub>2</sub>, F<sub>2:3</sub>) and first backcross (BC<sub>1</sub>) accessions with parentage assigned to two different clusters were considered admixed.</p><p id="Par78">Nested (secondary) Structure analysis was performed separately for non-admixed accessions of each cluster ascertained from the primary analysis. Algorithm parameters were identical to that of the primary analysis but included <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1-10. Hybrid and backcross accessions were then assigned to sub-clusters by replacing the primary <italic>qI</italic> with secondary <italic>qI</italic> determined for each parent. Accessions for which parentage was unknown were excluded from secondary Structure analysis. Assignment to sub-clusters was repeated using the same admixture criteria as in the primary analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>AMOVA</title><p id="Par79">The integrity of clusters derived from population structure was further investigated by performing an analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) using GenAlEx 6.501 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. A Nei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>] genetic distance matrix was first calculated using the binary genotype matrix previously described for the model-based clustering analyses. Two separate AMOVA were performed to partition within and among population estimated and molecular variance (&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>) components. Statistical significance of pairwise genetic distance among (i) primary and (ii) secondary clustering iterations were used to calculate the pairwise population PhiPT (&#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub>) test statistic, which provides a measure of interpopulation genetic diversity with intra-individual (heterozygosity) variation suppressed. The &#x003a6;<sub>PT</sub> statistic was calculated for all pairwise cluster combinations, which were determined significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) by 999 random permutations of the data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>UPGMA</title><p id="Par80">To investigate genetic relationships among accessions in the full panel, unweighted pair group method using arithmetic average (UPGMA) clustering was performed with Numerical Taxonomy System (NTSYSpc) ver 2.21q software (Exeter Software, Setauket, New York, USA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Genotype data from outgroup accessions CN3 and CR9 (<italic>Nepata cataria</italic>) were added to the same binary genotype matrix used for population structure and AMOVA analyses resulting in a total of 182 accessions. A genetic similarity matrix was generated using the Jaccard similarity coefficient method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>] in the NTSYSpc SIMQUAL module. Cluster analysis was then performed by UPGMA in the SAHN module and the output was visualized as a dendrogram with the TREE module. A Mantel test was performed with 999 test permutations using the MXCOMP module to determine goodness of fit between the genetic similarity matrix and the UPGMA dendrogram converted to cophenetic values with the COPH module. Finally, the original binary genotype matrix was resampled 1000 times using the RESAMPLE module and the results were used as input for the CONSENS module to calculate bootstrap values using the majority rule method and a minimum support value of 0.500.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec24"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1284_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p>Description of 180-accession panel of <italic>Ocimum</italic> spp., cluster membership and response to downy mildew (<italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic>) reported as disease severity. (PDF 115&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1284_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p>Primer sequences and melting temperatures (T<sub>m</sub>) for the EST-SSRs used in this study. (PDF 52&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1284_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p>Structure Harvester output for primary model-based clustering using Structure ver 2.3.4 software. Plot of &#x00394;<italic>K</italic> (left) and LnP(D) (right) for <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 &#x02013; 15. (PDF 126&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1284_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p>Structure Harvester output for secondary (nested) model-based clustering using Structure ver 2.3.4 software. Plots of &#x00394;<italic>K</italic> (left) and LnP(D) (right) for <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 &#x02013; 10. Three nested analyses shown for k1 (top), k2 (middle) and k3 (bottom) primary clusters. (PDF 215&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1284_MOESM5_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p>Genotype data. Binary matrix of accessions (rows) and alleles (columns). (XLSX 186&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AM</term><def><p id="Par4">Association mapping</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AMOVA</term><def><p id="Par5">Analysis of molecular variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANOVA</term><def><p id="Par6">Analysis of variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BC</term><def><p id="Par7">Backcross generation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cDNA</term><def><p id="Par8">Chloroplast DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cM</term><def><p id="Par9">CentiMorgan</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DM</term><def><p id="Par10">Downy mildew</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DM<sub>MRI</sub></term><def><p id="Par11">MRI-conferred downy mildew resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DPI</term><def><p id="Par12">Days post inoculation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DS</term><def><p id="Par13">Disease severity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EST</term><def><p id="Par14">Expressed sequence tag (EST)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FOB</term><def><p id="Par15"><italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>basilica</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>gDNA</term><def><p id="Par16">Genomic DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HR</term><def><p id="Par17">Hypersensitive response</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HSD</term><def><p id="Par18">Tukey&#x02019;s honest significant difference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ISSR</term><def><p id="Par19">Inter-simple repeat markers</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MCMC</term><def><p id="Par20">Markov Chain Monte Carlo</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NCBI</term><def><p id="Par21">National Center for Biotechnology Information</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NIL</term><def><p id="Par22">Near isogenice lines</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NTSYSpc</term><def><p id="Par23">Numerical Taxonomy System</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PIC</term><def><p id="Par24">Polymorphism information content</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNP</term><def><p id="Par25">Single nucleotide polymorphism</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SSR</term><def><p id="Par26">Simple sequence repeat</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SS<sub>WP</sub></term><def><p id="Par27">Within population sum of squares</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>T<sub>m</sub></term><def><p id="Par28">Melting temperature</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UPGMA</term><def><p id="Par29">Unweighted pair group method using arithmetic average</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>USDA-GRIN</term><def><p id="Par30">United States Department of Agriculture National Genetic Resources Program</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-018-1284-7) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We wish to thank Dr. Todd Wehner (North Carolina State University) and Dr. Stacy Bonos (Rutgers University) for their review and suggestions with regard to this manuscript. We thank the New Jersey Agricultural Experiment Station (NJAES) and the New Use Agriculture and Natural Plant Products Program (NUANNP) for their expertise and support of this research.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par81">Funds in support of this research were provided from multiple sources. A United States United Department of Agriculture (USDA) Special Crops Research Initiative Award No. 2011-51181-30646 funded a graduate assistantship/doctoral degree for RMP. This USDA-SCRI grant in combination with a USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture (NIFA) Award No. 2016-68004-24931 provided funds for acquisition of commercial plant varieties, greenhouse space, DNA extractions and genotyping work. A Binational Agricultural Research &#x00026; Development (BARD) Award No. US-4947-16R and NIFA HATCH projects NJAES 12131 and 1005685 provided additional funding for genotyping work and greenhouse facilities, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par82">A table of all genotypes and SSR allele calls used for statistical analysis in this study is submitted as Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>Design of experimentation was performed by RMP, JES and CAW. CAW provided expertise in downy mildew screening including inoculation procedures and plant response phenotyping. RMP performed DNA extraction, genotyping and greenhouse downy mildew response phenotyping. JV coordinated laboratory work and provided expertise in SSR allele calling to ensure accurate DNA fragment length data. RMP performed data analyses with supervision JH. Interpretation of data was performed by RMP and JH. CAW, JH and JES supervised the writing and revision of this manuscript. JES and JH coordinated resources and personnel necessary to complete this research. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par83">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par84">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par85">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hiltunen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Ocimum</italic>: an overview of classification and relationships</article-title><source>Basil: the genus Ocimum</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>Amersterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harwood Academic Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldsbrough</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity of basil (<italic>Ocimum</italic> spp.) based on RAPD markers</article-title><source>J Am Soc Hortic Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>99</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Springate</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Suddee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Otieno</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Grayer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny and evolution of basils and allies (Ocimeae, Labiatae) based on three plastid DNA regions</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2004</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2003.08.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15019625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15019625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Janick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basil: a source of essential oils</article-title><source>Advances in new crops</source><year>1990</year><publisher-loc>Portland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Timber Press</publisher-name><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>489</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Putievsky E, Galambosi B. Production systems of sweet basil. In: Hiltunen R, Holm Y, editors. Basil: the genus Ocimum. Amsterdam: Harwood Academic Publishers; 1999. p. 39&#x02013;61.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaimovitsh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Putievesky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inheritance of resistance to fusarium wilt in sweet basil</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2006</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ribeiro P, Simon JE. Breeding sweet basil for chilling tolerance: ASHS; 2007. p. 302&#x02013;5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Sweet Dani&#x0201d;: a new culinary and ornamental basil</article-title><source>Hortscience</source><year>1997</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>149</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nation</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Janick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of outcrossing in basil</article-title><source>Hortic Sci</source><year>1992</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1222</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khosla</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tawi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><collab>Group S</collab></person-group><article-title>Karyomorphological studies in genus Ocimum</article-title><source>Cytologia (Tokyo)</source><year>1985</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1508/cytologia.50.253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pushpangandan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobti</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytogentical studies in the genus <italic>Ocimum</italic>. I. Origin of <italic>O. americanum</italic>, cytotaxonomical and experimental proof</article-title><source>Cytologia</source><year>1982</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1508/cytologia.47.575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carovi&#x00107;-Stanko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Liber</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Besendorfer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Javornik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohanec</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic relations among basil taxa (O<italic>cimum</italic> L.) based on molecular markers, nuclear DNA content, and chromosome number</article-title><source>Plant Syst Evol</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00606-009-0251-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koroch</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Belanger</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of nuclear DNA content of cultivated <italic>Ocimum</italic> species by using flow cytometry</article-title><source>Isr J Plant Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1560/IJPS.59.3-4.183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escudero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n-Bravo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayrose</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Mazuecos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiz-Palacios</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hipp</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Karyotypic changes through dysploidy persist longer over evolutionary time than polyploid changes</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e85266</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085266</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24416374?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24416374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unravelling the genome of holy basil: an &#x0201c;incomparable&#x0201d; &#x0201c;elixir of life&#x0201d; of traditional Indian medicine</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>413</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1640-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26017011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26017011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schemske</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathways, mechanisms, and rates of Polyploid formation in flowering plants</article-title><source>Annu Rev Ecol Syst</source><year>1998</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.29.1.467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pyne R, Honig J, Vaiciunas J, Koroch AR, Wyenandt CA, Bonos SA, et al. A first linkage map and downy mildew resistance QTL discovery for sweet basil (<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic>) facilitated by double digestion restriction site associated DNA sequencing (ddRADseq). PLoS One. 2017; 10.1371/journalpone.0184319.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carovi&#x00107;-Stanko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Liber</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Politeo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Striki&#x00107;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Milos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular and chemical characterization of the most widespread <italic>Ocimum</italic> species</article-title><source>Plant Syst Evol</source><year>2011</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00606-011-0471-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Putievesky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taxonomic problems and cytotaxonomic relationships between and within varieties of <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> and related species (Labiateae)</article-title><source>Kew Bull</source><year>1996</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/4117026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Suddee S, Paton AJ, Parnell JAN. Taxonomic revision of tribe Ocimeae Dumort. (Lamiaceae) in continental South East Asia III. Ociminae. Kew Bull. 2005;60:3&#x02013;75.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carovi&#x00107;-Stanko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;alinovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grd&#x001d0;a</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liber</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Satovic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficiency of morphological trait descriptors in discrimination of <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. accessions</article-title><source>Plant Biosyst</source><year>2011</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/11263504.2011.558677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grayer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kite</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstone</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Putievsky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infraspecific taxonomy and essential oil chemotypes in sweet basil, <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic></article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>1996</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(96)00429-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8987875?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8987875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical characterization of basil (Ocimum spp.) based on volatile oils</article-title><source>Flavour Fragr J</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ffj.1513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hiltunen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Ocimum</italic>: an overview of classification and relationships</article-title><source>Basil: the genus <italic>Ocimum</italic></source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Hardwood Academic</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Simpson MG. Plant systematics. 2nd ed. Amsterdam: Elsevier/Academic Press; 2010.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Principles of cultivar development</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>MacMillan Publishing Company</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledda</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grassi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological characterization, essential oil composition and DNA genotyping of <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. cultivars</article-title><source>Plant Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2004.04.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Grayer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity of <italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic> L. based on volatile oil constituents, flavonoids and RAPD markers</article-title><source>Biochem Syst Ecol</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0305-1978(00)00062-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11152947?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baskaran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shasany</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaresan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Higher efficiency of ISSR markers over plastid <italic>psbA-trnH</italic> region in resolving taxonomical status of genus <italic>Ocimum</italic> L</article-title><source>Ecol Evol</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>7671</fpage><lpage>7682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhawan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite markers: an overview of the recent progress in plants</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2011</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-010-0286-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramchiary</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhandapani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genic microsatellite markers in <italic>brassica rapa</italic>: development, characterization, mapping, and their utility in other cultivated and wild brassica relatives</article-title><source>DNA Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsr017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21768136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21768136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Younas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of a core set of single-locus SSR markers for allotetraploid rapeseed (<italic>Brassica napus</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-2027-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23238763?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23238763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belbahri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Calmin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pawlowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefort</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic analysis and real time PCR detection of a presumbably undescribed <italic>Peronospora</italic> species on sweet basil and sage</article-title><source>Mycol Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1276</fpage><lpage>1287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0953756205003928</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16279421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16279421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyenandt</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyne</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Homa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Basil downy mildew (<italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic>): discoveries and challenges relative to its control</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2015</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-02-15-0032-FI</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25894318?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25894318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Langenberg</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehner</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojiambo</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausbeck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Quesada-Ocampo</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resurgence of <italic>Pseudoperonospora cubensis</italic>: the causal agent of cucurbit downy mildew</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2015</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>998</fpage><lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-11-14-0334-FI</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25844827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25844827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Call</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Criswell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehner</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grumet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance of cucumber cultivars to a new strain of cucurbit downy mildew</article-title><source>Hortscience</source><year>2012</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maisonneuve</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebeda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Christopoulou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeuken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rationalization of genes for resistance to <italic>Bremia lactucae</italic> in lettuce</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2016</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-016-1687-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaknin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Naim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Galperin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First report of the occurrence and resistance to Mefenoxam of <italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic>, causal agent of downy mildew of basil (<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic>) in Israel</article-title><source>Plant Dis Sci Soc</source><year>2013</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>692</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-12-12-1126-PDN</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pintore I, Gilardi G, Gullino ML, Garibaldi A. Detection of mefenoxam-resistant strains of <italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic>, the causal agent of basil downy mildew, transmitted through infected seeds. Phytoparasitica. 2016; 10.1007/s12600-016-0538-x.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Collina M, Merighi M, Turan C, Pirondi A, Minuto G, Brunelli A. First report of resistance of <italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic>, causal agent of downy mildew of basil, to Mefenoxam in Italy. Plant Dis. 2016;100:1787.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ben-Naim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Falach</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance against basil downy mildew in <italic>Ocimum</italic> species</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2015</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>778</fpage><lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-11-14-0295-R</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25844828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25844828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djalali Farahani-Kofoet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Romer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selecting basil genotypes with resistance against downy mildew</article-title><source>Sci Hortic</source><year>2014</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2014.09.036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyenandt</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Susceptibility of basil cultivars and breeding lines to downy mildew (<italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic>)</article-title><source>Hortscience</source><year>2010</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1416</fpage><lpage>1419</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2000</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>945</fpage><lpage>959</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10835412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckler</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Status and prospects of association mapping in plants</article-title><source>Plant Genome</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3835/plantgenome2008.02.0089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohlf</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>NTSYSpc: numerical taxonomy system</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Setauket</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Exeter Publishing, Ltd.</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putievesky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravid</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Haimovich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Katzir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crossability and relationship between <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L</article-title><source>J Herbs Spices Med Plants</source><year>1999</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1300/J044v06n03_02</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic structure, linkage disequilibrium and association mapping of verticillium wilt resistance in elite cotton (<italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L.) germplasm population</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e86308</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086308</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24466016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24466016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cheng F, Wu J, Wang X. Genome triplication drove the diversification of <italic>Brassica</italic> plants. Horticultural Research. 2014;1:14024. 10.1038/hortres.2014.24.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Moyle LC, Nakazato T. Comparative genetics of hybrid incompatibility: sterility in two Solanum species crosses. Genetics. 2008;1453:1437&#x02013;53.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agrios</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plant pathology</source><year>2005</year><edition>5</edition><publisher-loc>Burlington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier Academic Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ojiambo PS, Gent DH, Quesada-Ocampo LM, Hausbeck MK, Holmes GJ. Epidemiology and population biology of <italic>Pseudoperonospora cubensis</italic>: a model system for Management of Downy Mildews. Annu Rev Phytopathol. 2015;53:223&#x02013;46.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pink</surname><given-names>DAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Holub</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of resistance to downy mildew in <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> and breeding towards durable disease control for UK vegetable production</article-title><source>Plant Pathol</source><year>2012</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2011.02539.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pyne</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koroch</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyenandt</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inheritance of resistance to downy mildew in sweet basil</article-title><source>J Am Soc Hortic Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>403</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irish</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Correll</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>de Los Reyes</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of a resistance locus (<italic>Pfs-1</italic>) to the spinach downy mildew pathogen (<italic>Peronospora farinosa</italic> f. sp. <italic>spinaciae</italic>) and development of a molecular marker linked to Pfs-1</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2008</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>894</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-98-8-0894</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18943207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epinat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitrat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inheritance of resistance of three lines of muskmelon (<italic>Cucumis melo</italic>) to downy mildew (<italic>Pseudoperonospora cubensis</italic>)</source><year>1989</year><publisher-loc>Charleston</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Proc Cucurbitaceae: Evaluation and Enhancement of Cucurbit Germplasm</publisher-name><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plant immune system</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>444</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05286</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17108957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17108957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Niks</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeuken</surname><given-names>MJW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic dissection of <italic>Lactuca saligna</italic> nonhost resistance to downy mildew at various lettuce developmental stages</article-title><source>Plant Pathol</source><year>2009</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>932</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2009.02066.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Guo L, Allen KS, Deiulio GA, Zhang Y, Madeiras AM, Wick RL, et al. A de-novo-assembly-based data analysis pipeline for plant obligate parasite metatranscriptomic studies. Front Plant Sci. 2016;7:925. 10.3389/FPLS.2016.00925.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meena</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangwan</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>De novo sequencing and comparative analysis of holy and sweet basil transcriptomes</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>588</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-588</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25015319?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25015319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pyne</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koroch</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyenandt</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid screening approach to identify resistance to basil downy mildew (<italic>Peronospora belbahrii</italic>)</article-title><source>Hortscience</source><year>2014</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1041</fpage><lpage>1045</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Noordijk</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bink</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Meulenbroek</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite allele dose and configuration establishment (MADCE): an integrated approach for genetic studies in allopolyploids</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-12-25</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22340438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22340438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honig</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Averello</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaiciunas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonos</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of bentgrass (<italic>Agrostis</italic>) cultivars and accessions based on microsatellite (SSR) markers</article-title><source>Genet Resour Crop Evol</source><year>2016</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1139</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10722-015-0307-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e4;h&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Erkinaro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Niemel&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Primmer</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life-history and habitat features influence the within-river genetic structure of Atlantic salmon</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2638</fpage><lpage>2654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2007.03329.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17594436?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17594436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urrestarazu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Denanc&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyader</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guisnel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Feugey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the genetic diversity and structure across a wide range of germplasm reveals prominent gene flow in apple at the European level</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>130</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-016-0818-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27277533?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27277533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nachimuthu VV, Muthurajan R, Duraialaguraja S, Sivakami R, Pandian BA, Ponniah G, et al. Analysis of population structure and genetic diversity in rice germplasm using SSR markers: an initiative towards association mapping of agronomic traits in Oryza Sativa. Rice (N Y). 2015;8:30. 10.1186/s12284-015-0062-5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Evanno G, Regnaut S, Goudet J. Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation study. Mol Ecol. 2005;14:2611&#x02013;20.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Earl DA, Bridgett M. STRUCTURE HARVESTER: a website and program for visualizing STRUCTURE output and implementing the Evanno method. Conserv Genet Resour. 2012;4:359&#x02013;61</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CLUMPP: a cluster matching and permutation program for dealing with label switching and multimodality in analysis of population structure</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1801</fpage><lpage>1806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm233</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17485429?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rosenberg NA. DISTRUCT: a program for the graphical display of population structure. Mol Ecol Resour. 2004;4:137&#x02013;8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taranto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Agostino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripodi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide SNP discovery and population structure analysis in pepper (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic>) using genotyping by sequencing</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>943</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-3297-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27871227?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27871227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peakall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smouse</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GenAlEx 6.5: genetic analysis in excel. Population genetic software for teaching and research &#x02014; an update</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2537</fpage><lpage>2539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts460</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22820204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic distance between populations</article-title><source>Am Soc Nat</source><year>2010</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/282771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaccard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nouvelles recherches Sur la distribution florale</article-title><source>Bull la Soc Vaudoise des Sci Nat</source><year>1908</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>270</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>