<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6280398</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1526</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-018-1526-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome-wide characterization and phylogenetic analysis of <italic>GSK</italic> gene family in three species of cotton: evidence for a role of some <italic>GSKs</italic> in fiber development and responses to stress</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Lingling</given-names></name><address><email>wll_198927@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Zhaoen</given-names></name><address><email>yangzhaoen0925@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Bin</given-names></name><address><email>18837299076@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Daoqian</given-names></name><address><email>yudaoqian88@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Ji</given-names></name><address><email>liuji@caas.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Qian</given-names></name><address><email>15201609648@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qanmber</surname><given-names>Ghulam</given-names></name><address><email>gqkhan12@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><address><email>liyi20050901@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Lili</given-names></name><address><email>biolll@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Yongjun</given-names></name><address><email>yongjunlin@mail.hzau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Zuoren</given-names></name><address><email>yangzuoren4012@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Fuguang</given-names></name><address><phone>0372-2562204</phone><email>aylifug@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.464267.5</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Cotton Biology, Key Laboratory of Biological and Genetic Breeding of Cotton, </institution><institution>Institute of Cotton Research, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Anyang, 455000 Henan China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 4137</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.35155.37</institution-id><institution>National Key Laboratory of Crop Genetic Improvement and National Centre of Plant Gene Research, </institution><institution>Huazhong Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, 430070 People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>330</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The glycogen synthase kinase 3/shaggy kinase (GSK3) is a serine/threonine kinase with important roles in animals. Although <italic>GSK3</italic> genes have been studied for more than 30&#x02009;years, plant <italic>GSK</italic> genes have been studied only since the last decade. Previous research has confirmed that plant <italic>GSK</italic> genes are involved in diverse processes, including floral development, brassinosteroid signaling, and responses to abiotic stresses.</p></sec><sec><title>Result</title><p id="Par2">In this study, 20, 15 (including 5 different transcripts) and 10 <italic>GSK</italic> genes were identified in <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. raimondii</italic> and <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, respectively. A total of 65 genes from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, rice, and cotton were classified into 4 clades. High similarities were found in GSK3 protein sequences, conserved motifs, and gene structures, as well as good concordance in gene pairwise comparisons (<italic>G. hirsutum</italic> vs. <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> vs. <italic>G. raimondii</italic>, and <italic>G. arboreum</italic> vs. <italic>G. raimondii</italic>) were observed. Whole genome duplication (WGD) within At and Dt sub-genomes has been central to the expansion of the <italic>GSK</italic> gene family. Furthermore, <italic>GhSK</italic> genes showed diverse expression patterns in various tissues. Additionally, the expression profiles of <italic>GhSKs</italic> under different stress treatments demonstrated that many are stress-responsive genes. However, none were induced by brassinolide treatment. Finally, nine co-expression sub-networks were observed for <italic>GhSKs</italic> and the functional annotations of these genes suggested that some <italic>GhSK</italic>s might be involved in cotton fiber development.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">In this present work, we identified 45 <italic>GSK</italic> genes from three cotton species, which were divided into four clades. The gene features, muti-alignment, conversed motifs, and syntenic blocks indicate that they have been highly conserved during evolution. Whole genome duplication was determined to be the dominant factor for <italic>GSK</italic> gene family expansion. The analysis of co-expressed sub-networks and tissue-specific expression profiles suggested functions of <italic>GhSKs</italic> during fiber development. Moreover, their different responses to various abiotic stresses indicated great functional diversity amongst the <italic>GhSKs</italic>. Briefly, data presented herein may serve as the basis for future functional studies of GhSKs.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-018-1526-8) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>GSK3 (glycogen synthase kinase 3/shaggy kinase)</kwd><kwd>Cotton</kwd><kwd>Genome duplication</kwd><kwd>Fiber development</kwd><kwd>Abiotic stress</kwd><kwd>Co-expression network</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the National Natural Science Foundation of China </institution></funding-source><award-id>No. 31501345</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Fuguang</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Young Elite Scientist Sponsorship Program by CAST</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par22">Glycogen synthase kinase 3 (GSK3), which is also known as the SHAGGY-like protein kinase, is a non-receptor serine/threonine protein kinase and involved in vital signal transduction pathways in eukaryotes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In mammals, GSK3 exists as two isoforms, namely GSK3&#x003b1; and GSK3&#x003b2;, both of which help to regulate glycogen metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. GSK3 was first reported as an enzyme-inactivating kinase in rabbit skeletal muscle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The products of GSK3 homologs were confirmed to be involved in several physiological processes in animals, including protein synthesis, glycogen metabolism, regulation of transcription factor activity, determination of cell fate, and tumorigenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Additionally, GSK3 is a key component of the animal Wnt signaling pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">The plant <italic>GSK3</italic> genes appear to be more diverse than the corresponding animal genes, as evidenced by the fact that there are ten <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> genes and nine rice genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The plant <italic>GSK3</italic> genes were as diverse in function as animal isoforms. Biochemical and genetic analyses demonstrated that different plant GSK3 members affect disparate processes, such as development, stress responses, and signaling pathways, by phosphorylation of different protein substrates. In <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>AtSK11</italic> and <italic>AtSK12</italic> were highly expressed during the early stages of differentiation of the floral primordium. These two genes were subsequently expressed in specific regions, including the pollen-containing area of the anther, carpels, petals, and sepal primordial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Previous studies revealed that <italic>AtSK31</italic>, which was localized mainly to the nuclei of developing tissues, was highly expressed in floral organs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Moreover, overexpression of different <italic>AtSK32</italic> isoforms in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> resulted in different phenotypes. Two mutations of AtSK32, Lys167, and Arg178 (homologous to the critical active site residues Lys85 and Arg96 of mammal GSK3&#x003b2;) were generated by site-directed mutagenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. However, overexpression of wild-type or catalytically inactive mutant (i.e., encoding a K167A mutation) <italic>AtSK32</italic> gene in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> produced no observable effects. Nevertheless, overexpression of <italic>AtSK32</italic>-<italic>R178A</italic> displayed shorter pedicels and smaller petals compared with wild-type controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Moreover, ASK&#x003b1;/AtSK11, which was an <italic>A. thaliana</italic> GSK3, regulated stress resistance by activating Glc-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD). Increased G6PD activity accompanied with decreased reactive oxygen species levels have been observed in <italic>ASK&#x003b1;</italic>-overexpressing plants under stress conditions, especially during salt stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. GSK3/SHAGGY-like kinase (AtSK21) gain-of-function mutations or over-expressing transgenetic lines inhibited the brassinosteroid (BR) signaling pathway and led to BR-deficiency and suppression of BR-induced responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Upregulating the expression level of <italic>OsGSK3</italic> in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa L.</italic> &#x02018;Nipponbare&#x02019;) enhanced its tolerance to salt, cold, drought and mechanical injury, and abscisic acid (ABA) responsiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. There are ongoing studies aimed at comprehensively examining <italic>GSK3</italic> family members in various plant species, even though the number of putative <italic>GSK3</italic> genes is relatively low.</p><p id="Par24">Cotton fibers, which are the premier natural fiber derived from the seedcoat epidermal cells, are the most important renewable resource used by the textile industry. The genus <italic>Gossypium</italic> that includes approximately 50 species, of which four are cultivated for their cotton fibers (i.e., <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. herbaceum</italic>, 2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;2X&#x02009;=&#x02009;AA&#x02009;=&#x02009;26; <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> (upland cotton), and <italic>G. barbadense</italic> (sea island cotton), 2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4X&#x02009;=&#x02009;AADD&#x02009;=&#x02009;52) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. <italic>Gossypium raimondii</italic>, another diploid, carries a D-genome and only produces very short and coarse seed fibers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> is the most widely cultivated cotton species and accounts for more than 90% of the global cotton fiber yield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. This allotetraploid species contains two different sets of chromosomes (i.e., A and D) evolved as a result of inter-specific hybridization during the Pleistocene about 1&#x02013;2 million years ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Cotton fiber development is a complicated process involving several phytohormones, including auxin, ethylene, gibberellins (GAs), and BRs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The BIN2 protein, as a negative regulator of BR signaling pathway, was a well-characterized GSK3 that could affect the activities of phytohormone-signaling pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Additionally, the complete genome sequencing of <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> now allow genome-wide analyses of any gene family in cotton [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. However, there have been no systematic investigations of the <italic>GSK</italic> gene family from these three cotton species. Considering the functional importance of the <italic>GSK</italic> gene family, we conducted an in silico genome-wide search and analysis to identify and characterize the <italic>GSK</italic> gene family members of <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, and <italic>G. raimondii</italic>. We subsequently analyzed a multi-sequence alignment, gene loci, gene structures, promoter <italic>cis</italic>-elements, conserved protein motifs, phylogenetic relationships, gene expression profiles, and a weighted gene co-expression sub-network analysis. The results described herein may be useful for further functional characterizations of cotton GSKs. Our data may also help to clarify the mechanism underlying the regulatory effects of GSKs during cotton development, growth, and responses to stress conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title><p id="Par25"><italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L. &#x02018;<italic>cv CCRI24</italic>&#x02019; plants were grown in mixed soil under glasshouse conditions [14&#x02009;h light (28~&#x02009;34&#x02009;&#x000b0;C)/ 10&#x02009;h dark (24~&#x02009;27&#x02009;&#x000b0;C); 150&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;2</sup>&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>]. To analyze organ- and tissue-specific gene expression patterns in &#x02018;CCRI24&#x02019;, plants were grown under field conditions in Zhengzhou, China following standard crop management practices. Flower (whole flower at 0 dpa) and ovule samples were collected at 1, 3, 5&#x02009;days post-anthesis (dpa). Additionally, isolated fibers were collected at 7, 10, 15, and 20 dpa. Stages of the tissues collected were chosen as described in previously published research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Three biological replicates were collected for each sample. All collected samples were immediately frozen in the liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for RNA extraction and subsequent analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Abiotic stress assays and BL treatment</title><p id="Par26">The expression patterns of <italic>GhSK</italic> genes in response to various environmental stresses and brassinolide treatment were analyzed. For abiotic stresses, phenotypically similar <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> potted seedlings grown in a glasshouse up to the three-true-leaves stage (four weeks old) were selected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Each treatment consisted of three biological replicates of the individual seedling. For brassinolide treatment, seedlings were cultured in deionized water supplemented with 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;M brassinolide, and leaf samples were collected at 0, 0.5, 1, 3, 5&#x02009;h. The cold and heat treatments involved incubations at 4 and 38&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, respectively. To simulate dehydration stress, cotton seedlings were irrigated with 20% polyethylene glycol (PEG) instead of water. Additionally, cotton seedling roots were immersed in 300&#x02009;mM NaCl solutions to assess the effects of salt stress. The true leaves were collected at 1, 3, 6, and 12&#x02009;h for all of the abiotic stresses performed as described in previously published investigations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. All collected leaf samples were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for subsequent RNA isolation and cDNA synthesis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>RNA isolation and quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction analysis</title><p id="Par27">Total RNA was extracted from collected cotton tissues/organs using the RNAprep Pure Plant Kit (TIANGEN, Beijing, China). First-strand cDNA was synthesized using the PrimeScript&#x02122; RT Reagent Kit, during which the genomic DNA was eliminated with gDNA Eraser (Perfect Real Time; Takara, Dalian, China). The quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) primers were designed by the Primer Premier 5.0 software. <italic>Histone 3</italic> (GenBank accession no. AF024716) was selected as the reference gene. The qRT-PCR was conducted using SYBR Premix Ex Taq&#x02122; (Tli RNase H Plus) (Takara) and ABI 7900 qRT-PCR System (Applied Biosystems, CA, USA). The PCR program was as follows: 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;s; 40&#x02009;cycles of 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;s and 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;s. The 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> method was applied to calculate the relative expression level of all target genes as compared to control treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Identification of cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes</title><p id="Par28">The latest version of the <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and rice genome, protein sequence and annotation databases were downloaded at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org/">http://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plants.ensembl.org/index.html">http://plants.ensembl.org/index.html</ext-link> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], respectively. Additionally, the genome sequence versions of the <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> (NAU, Version 1.1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], <italic>G. raimondii</italic> (JGI, version2.0) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] available from COTTONGEN (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cottongen.org">https://www.cottongen.org</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] and <italic>G. arboreum</italic> (PacBio-Gar-Assembly-v1.0, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://bioinfo.ayit.edu.cn/downloads/">ftp://bioinfo.ayit.edu.cn/downloads/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] were used to identify GSK proteins and their corresponding nucleotide sequences. The cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes and encoded proteins were identified via a BLAST search using all of the <italic>A. thaliana ASK</italic> gene and encoded protein sequences as queries. For protein analyses, the following parameters were used: e-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;1e-5 and coverage ratio&#x02009;=&#x02009;50%. Moreover, the definition of the Pkinase (PF00069.23) domain was downloaded from Pfam: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pfam.janelia.org/">http://pfam.janelia.org/</ext-link> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], and then the hidden Markov model (HMM) was used to verify the GSKs from the three cotton species. The identified <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, rice, <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> genes were renamed as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] based on their order of phylogenetic clustering.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Multiple-sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="Par29">A sequence alignment of full-length protein sequences from the three analyzed cotton species, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, and rice was prepared using MUSCLE: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/muscle/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/muscle/</ext-link> and saved in the ClustalW format. Meanwhile, a phylogenetic analysis of the <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, rice, and cotton GSKs was conducted using the MEGA 6.0 program, with 1000 bootstrap replications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. An unrooted Neighbor-joining, as well as Minimum-Evolution tree were constructed using the Poisson model method using the same alignment file.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Comparison of chromosomal distributions, exon/ intron structures, and protein domains among a, D, and AD cotton genomes</title><p id="Par30">The genomic distribution of the cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes was analyzed by MapInspect software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mapinspect1.software.informer.com/">https://mapinspect1.software.informer.com/</ext-link>) according to the start positions indicated in <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, and <italic>G.raimondii</italic> databases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The intron/ exon structures were examined using the Gene Structure Display Server 2.0 program (http:/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gsds.cbi.pku.edu.cn">gsds.cbi.pku.edu.cn</ext-link>/). Meanwhile, the cotton GSK domains were predicted with the MEME (Multiple Expectation Maximization for Motif Elicitation) online tool: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://meme-suite.org/tools/meme">http://meme-suite.org/tools/meme</ext-link> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] using the following parameters: motif width 6&#x02013;200 residues and the maximum number of motifs&#x02009;=&#x02009;20. The mast.xml file exported from MEME was used to generate the motif images using TBtools_master (version 0.49991) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/CJ-Chen/TBtools">https://github.com/CJ-Chen/TBtools</ext-link>). The conserved motif logos were downloaded from MEME as well.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Synteny and gene duplications analysis</title><p id="Par31">The <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> genome data were searched using a BLAST-Like Alignment Tool (BLAT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] to identify tandem duplications which were defined as multilocus genes located in adjacent regions or separated by uniform intergenic regions. Sequences with coverage &#x0003e;&#x02009;90% and similarity &#x0003e;&#x02009;95% were designated as tandem duplicates.</p><p id="Par32">We performed the synteny analysis of <italic>GSK</italic> genes among the three cotton species included in this study (i.e., <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> vs. <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> vs. <italic>G. raimondii</italic>, and <italic>G. arboreum</italic> vs. <italic>G. raimondii</italic>). BLAT was used for the pairwise comparison of <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> gene sets and to identify the homologous genomic regions. Finally, the syntenic blocks were visualized using the default parameters of the Circos (version 0.69) program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Analysis of the promoter cis-regulatory elements</title><p id="Par33">The 2-kb sequences upstream of the cotton <italic>GhSK</italic> genes (i.e., putative promoter regions) were obtained by BLAST searches of the cotton genome data using whole gene IDs. Potential <italic>cis</italic>-acting regulatory elements of the extracted sequences were subsequently subjected to PlantCARE database analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/plantcare/html/">http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/plantcare/html/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. The identified <italic>cis</italic>-elements were drawn using a custom script in the R program (version 3.20; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Biophysical properties of <italic>GSK</italic> genes from three cotton species</title><p id="Par34">The three genome sets of cotton GSK protein sequences were analyzed using ExPASy-ProtParam tool: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.expasy.org/protparam/">http://web.expasy.org/protparam/</ext-link> to calculate the number of amino acids, molecular weight, and theoretical pI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Meanwhile, the subcellular localization of these genes was predicted with ProComp 9.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.softberry.com/berry.phtml?group=programs&#x00026;subgroup=proloc&#x00026;topic=protcomppl">http://www.softberry.com/berry.phtml?group=programs&#x00026;subgroup=proloc&#x00026;topic=protcomppl</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Weighted co-expression sub-network analysis of <italic>GhSK</italic> genes</title><p id="Par35">The weighted gene co-expression sub-network analysis (WGCNA) of the <italic>GhSK</italic> genes was conducted using the <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> TM-1 transcriptome sequencing data downloaded from the NCBI Sequence Read Archive database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The network construction and module detection were performed using the &#x02018;cuttreeDynamic&#x02019; and &#x02018;mergeCloseModules&#x02019; by &#x0201c;WGCNA&#x0201d; R package (version 1.4.9) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], the parameters were set as follows: The power was 9; the minModuleSize was 30 and the cutHeight was 0.25. Finally, we visualized the sub-network using Cytoscape (version 3.4.0) program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. An additional investigation of the putative functions of <italic>GhSK</italic> genes and their co-expression genes was based on Gene Ontology (GO) and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) enrichment analyses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Gene expression patterns analyzed using published transcriptomic data</title><p id="Par36">The high-throughput <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> TM-1 transcriptome sequencing data were used to investigate the <italic>GhSK</italic> gene expression patterns in vegetative tissues, fiber tissues, floral organs, and dry seed. The log10 transformed Fragments Per Kilobase of transcript per Million fragments (FPKM) mapped values of the 20 <italic>GhSK</italic> genes were calculated to generate heatmaps with the local Multiple Arrays Viewer program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mybiosoftware.com/mev-4-6-2-multiple-experiment-viewer.html">http://www.mybiosoftware.com/mev-4-6-2-multiple-experiment-viewer.html</ext-link>). The accession numbers and related sample information of the data used in this study are listed in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1.1, S1.2 and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par37">Data analyses here were executed through one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and a Dunnett&#x02019;s test at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was performed. Taking the biological significance of the differential expression into account, we assumed a two-fold cut-off value for analyzing the stress and hormone induction or inhibition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. The expression levels were designated as &#x02018;induced&#x02019; or &#x02018;inhibited&#x02019; only when the differences met the specified criteria.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Genome-wide characterization of cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes</title><p id="Par38">After removing redundant sequences, 20, 10, and 15 <italic>GSK</italic> genes were identified in <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, and <italic>G. ramondii</italic> genomes, respectively. To avoid the possibility of confusion and overlap with the gene names used, we renamed these genes as <italic>GhSKs</italic>, <italic>GaSKs</italic>, and <italic>GrSKs</italic>. The genes were numbered sequentially according to the subfamilies to which they were assigned after phylogenetic analysis (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the putative cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Subfamily</th><th>Gene ID</th><th>Proposed name</th><th>Amino acid length</th><th>MW (KDa)</th><th>PI</th><th>Subcellular location</th><th>Location</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="9">Clade I</td><td>Gh_D11G2830</td><td>GhSK11</td><td>407</td><td>46.20</td><td>8.59</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>D24: 58071261&#x02013;58,074,075(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_A11G3270</td><td>GhSK12</td><td>407</td><td>46.20</td><td>8.59</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Scaf3045_A11: 160892&#x02013;163,705(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_A12G1106</td><td>GhSK13</td><td>409</td><td>46.41</td><td>8.69</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>A12: 64114146&#x02013;64,116,909(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_D12G1230</td><td>GhSK14</td><td>409</td><td>46.31</td><td>8.58</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>D25: 40170076&#x02013;40,172,846(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga11G0763</td><td>GaSK11</td><td>407</td><td>46.23</td><td>8.59</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Ga11:13088074&#x02013;13,090,884(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga12G1683</td><td>GaSK12</td><td>409</td><td>46.37</td><td>8.58</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Ga12:26213850&#x02013;26,216,616(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.007G308500.1</td><td>GrSK11</td><td>407</td><td>46.20</td><td>8.59</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr07:52192786&#x02013;52,197,103(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.007G308500.3</td><td>GrSK11&#x02013;1</td><td>407</td><td>46.20</td><td>8.59</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr07:52192786&#x02013;52,197,103(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.008G136600.1</td><td>GrSK12</td><td>409</td><td>46.36</td><td>8.58</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr08:38585110&#x02013;38,589,107(+)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="14">Clade II</td><td>Gh_D06G2142</td><td>GhSK21</td><td>381</td><td>43.24</td><td>8.74</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>D19:63261021&#x02013;63,263,915(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_D09G2469</td><td>GhSK22</td><td>382</td><td>43.10</td><td>8.74</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Scaf4332_D22:137949&#x02013;141,233(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_D09G2468</td><td>GhSK23</td><td>381</td><td>43.38</td><td>8.83</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Scaf4332_D22:123124&#x02013;126,295(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_A09G0713</td><td>GhSK24</td><td>381</td><td>43.32</td><td>9.02</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>A09:52861382&#x02013;52,864,569(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_A09G0712</td><td>GhSK25</td><td>376</td><td>42.64</td><td>8.88</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>A09:52841598&#x02013;52,844,894(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_A06G2020</td><td>GhSK26</td><td>385</td><td>43.72</td><td>8.69</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Scaf1340_A06:43052&#x02013;45,877(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga06G2433</td><td>GaSK21</td><td>381</td><td>43.24</td><td>8.74</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Ga06:130210718&#x02013;130,213,627(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga09G0899</td><td>GaSK22</td><td>376</td><td>42.59</td><td>8.84</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Ga09:59971361&#x02013;59,974,663(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga09G0900</td><td>GaSK23</td><td>382</td><td>43.55</td><td>8.89</td><td>Cytoplasmic</td><td>Ga09:59988594&#x02013;59,991,790(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.010G241600.3</td><td>GrSK21</td><td>381</td><td>43.24</td><td>8.74</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr10:61087060&#x02013;61,090,705(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.010G241600.2</td><td>GrSK21&#x02013;1</td><td>381</td><td>43.24</td><td>8.74</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr10:61085419&#x02013;61,090,069(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.006G089300.1</td><td>GrSK22</td><td>382</td><td>43.22</td><td>8.74</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr06:32530678&#x02013;32,535,037(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.006G089300.2</td><td>GrSK22&#x02013;1</td><td>381</td><td>43.10</td><td>8.74</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr06:32530521&#x02013;32,535,037(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.006G089400.1</td><td>GrSK23</td><td>381</td><td>43.34</td><td>8.74</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr06:32546669&#x02013;32,551,023(+)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="12">Clade III</td><td>Gh_A08G0285</td><td>GhSK31</td><td>469</td><td>52.95</td><td>8.75</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>A08:3329052&#x02013;3,334,479(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_D08G1440</td><td>GhSK32</td><td>471</td><td>53.14</td><td>8.38</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>D21:47361120&#x02013;47,366,590(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_D11G0907</td><td>GhSK33</td><td>470</td><td>53.00</td><td>7.27</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>D24:7839230&#x02013;7,844,650(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_A08G1158</td><td>GhSK34</td><td>471</td><td>53.06</td><td>8.2</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>A08:81021333&#x02013;81,025,764(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_A11G0778</td><td>GhSK35</td><td>470</td><td>52.87</td><td>6.81</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>A11:7649123&#x02013;7,654,545(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_D08G0378</td><td>GhSK36</td><td>494</td><td>55.85</td><td>8.99</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>D21:3871236&#x02013;3,880,133(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga08G0389</td><td>GaSK31</td><td>469</td><td>52.95</td><td>8.2</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Ga08:4054818&#x02013;4,060,304(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga11G3164</td><td>GaSK32</td><td>470</td><td>52.88</td><td>7</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Ga11:116299523&#x02013;116,304,934(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga08G1552</td><td>GaSK33</td><td>471</td><td>53.10</td><td>8.2</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Ga08:103960877&#x02013;103,965,308(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.004G042400.1</td><td>GrSK31</td><td>469</td><td>52.97</td><td>8.86</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr04:3659148&#x02013;3,665,477(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.007G096100.1</td><td>GrSK32</td><td>470</td><td>53.04</td><td>7.6</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr07:7076952&#x02013;7,083,244(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.004G156700.2</td><td>GrSK33</td><td>415</td><td>47.04</td><td>8.21</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr04:44445510&#x02013;44,453,846(+)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10">Clade IV</td><td>Gh_A01G1558</td><td>GhSK41</td><td>422</td><td>47.85</td><td>8.63</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>A01:92410497&#x02013;92,413,873(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_D01G1809</td><td>GhSK42</td><td>422</td><td>47.85</td><td>8.63</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>D14:55472543&#x02013;55,475,936(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_D12G0407</td><td>GhSK43</td><td>422</td><td>47.90</td><td>8.49</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>D25:6533937&#x02013;6,537,332(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gh_A12G0411</td><td>GhSK44</td><td>422</td><td>47.87</td><td>8.49</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>A12:8244999&#x02013;8,248,430(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga02G1328</td><td>GaSK41</td><td>422</td><td>47.84</td><td>8.63</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Ga02:91572951&#x02013;91,576,357(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Ga12G2665</td><td>GaSK42</td><td>439</td><td>50.02</td><td>8.68</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Ga12:98904726&#x02013;98,909,799(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.002G218100.1</td><td>GrSK41</td><td>422</td><td>47.85</td><td>8.63</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr02:56980865&#x02013;56,985,951(+)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.008G045800.6</td><td>GrSK42</td><td>422</td><td>47.89</td><td>8.49</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr08:6198704&#x02013;6,202,924(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.008G045800.3</td><td>GrSK42&#x02013;1</td><td>422</td><td>47.89</td><td>8.49</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr08:6198649&#x02013;6,203,828(&#x02212;)</td></tr><tr><td>Gorai.008G045800.2</td><td>GrSK42&#x02013;2</td><td>422</td><td>47.89</td><td>8.49</td><td>Cyto_Nucl_Memb</td><td>Gr08:6198649&#x02013;6,203,828(&#x02212;)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par39">The biophysical characteristics of the identified cotton GSKs are provided in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The number of amino acids of putative GhSK, GaSK, and GrSK proteins varied from 376 (GhSK25 and GaSK22) to 494 (GhSK36), and the associated molecular weights ranged from 42.59 to 53.14&#x02009;kDa respectively. All pIs of the GSKs were higher than 7, except GhSK35 (6.81). Interestingly, the predicted subcellular localization revealed that almost all of the proteins were localized to multiple compartments including the cytoplasm, nucleus, and membrane, excepting for GaSK23 (only cytoplasmic). The localization results for the cotton GSKs were not the same as those that have been reported for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GSKs which might be because the cotton GSKs are much less well studied and their functions remain largely unknown.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Phylogenetic analysis amongst the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, rice and cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes</title><p id="Par40">To reveal the phylogenetic relationships among the <italic>GSK</italic> genes, full-length <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, rice, and cotton protein sequences were aligned. The aligned GSKs were highly similar and the conserved GSK protein kinase region is presented in detail in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S1. Additionally, the kinase domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and the tyrosine residue essential for kinase activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] were conserved among all the cotton GSKs.</p><p id="Par41">A phylogenetic tree was generated using the neighbor-joining (NJ) <bold>(</bold>Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a<bold>)</bold> as well as minimum-evolution (ME) (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S2) method of MEGA6.0. As shown in Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, all sequences were divided into four subgroups (I, II, III, and IV), similar to previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. The phylogenetic tree indicated that <italic>GhSK</italic>, <italic>GaSK</italic>, and <italic>GrSK</italic> genes clustered together within each sub-group suggesting a close evolutionary affinity amongst the three cotton species and providing further support for the origins of the tetraploid species from a relatively recent hybridisation between an A-genome progenitor similar to <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and a D-genome progenitor similar to <italic>G. raimondii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of GSK3 proteins in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, rice, and species of cotton. 10 AtSKs, 15 OsSKs, 20 GhSKs, 10 GaSKs, and 10 GrSKs are divided into four clades. The four clades are respectively colored in cyan, reddish brown, violet, and green</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Chromosomal locations, gene structures, and conserved motifs analysis</title><p id="Par42">Chromosomal locations of the cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes using sequencing information for <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, <italic>G. raimondii</italic>, and <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> TM-1 revealed that the genes were unevenly distributed among chromosomes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Out of the total of 45 cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes, four <italic>GhSKs</italic> (<italic>GhSK12</italic>, <italic>GhSK23</italic>, <italic>GhSK24</italic>, and <italic>GhSK26</italic>) were assigned to scaffolds not connected to chromosomes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The other 16 <italic>GhSK</italic> genes were distributed to chromosomes A08, A09 (two genes on each), A12 (two genes), D21 (two genes), D24, D25 (two genes on each), A01, A11, D14 and D19 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). The <italic>GaSK</italic> genes were localized to chromosomes Ga02, Ga06, and Ga08, Ga11, Ga09 as well as Ga12 (two genes on each) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b), while <italic>GrSK</italic> genes were positioned on chromosomes Gr02 (one gene), Gr04 and Gr10 (two genes on each), Gr06 as well as Gr07 (three genes on each) and Gr08 (four genes) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Chromosomal assignment of <italic>GhSKs</italic> (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>GaSKs</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic>GrSKs</italic> (<bold>c</bold>). The relative chromosomal sizes (unit, Mb) of <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> were calculated from the published genome data of the kinds of cotton</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par43">To further clarify the evolutionary relationships (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>) among cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes, genomic information corresponding to 40 (excluding the five different transcripts of <italic>GrSKs</italic>) cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes extracted from Generic Feature Format (gff3) files were used to examine the structural diversity associated with the <italic>GhSK</italic>, <italic>GaSK</italic>, and <italic>GrSK</italic> genes. The structural analysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>) indicated that the coding regions of all the cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes were interrupted by 11&#x02013;13 introns. The UTR regions of <italic>GhSK34</italic>, <italic>35</italic>, and <italic>36</italic> and <italic>GaSK23</italic> as well as <italic>GaSK33</italic> are undetermined, while other cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes had UTR region information in the genomic annotation files. In most cases, <italic>GSK</italic> genes within the same sub-family had similar gene structures in regard to the number and length of exons.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic relationships between the cotton GSKs constructed using the Neighbor-Joining algorithm and Poisson model (<bold>a</bold>), gene structure predictions (<bold>b</bold>) and conversed protein motifs (<bold>c</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par44">Using the MEME online server, 16 conserved domains and protein motifs were observed among 40 cotton GSKs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>), and the respective motif logos are presented in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S3. Members of the same subfamily mostly contained the same motif components, suggesting they might have identical functions. Motifs 1&#x02013;4 were found in all 40 analyzed GSKs, and constituted the kinase domain of GSK3. Additionally, motif 8 and 10 were present in all proteins of subfamily I and III. Motif 6 was observed in the members of subfamily III and IV. Furthermore, motif 13 was mainly present in subfamily II and IV members (except for GaSK22, GhSK25, and GrSK33), while motif 11 was identified in the proteins of subfamily I and IV. Motif 9 was mainly present in subfamily III members (except for GrSK33). Motif 14, 15, and 16 were present only in some members of subfamily III. The variations in the distribution of motifs indicate that cotton GSKs experienced functional diversification during their evolution.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Duplicated cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes and syntenic blocks</title><p id="Par45">During evolution, the two major mechanisms that generate novel genes and contribute to the complexity of the genomes of higher plants are small-scale tandem and large segmental duplications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. In this study, 25 pairs of paralogous <italic>GSK</italic> genes resulting from gene duplication events were identified in <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In contrast, <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> consisted of 10 and 22 pairs of paralogs, respectively. Among the 25 pairs of duplicated <italic>GhSK</italic> genes, 14 were observed between different chromosomes, from which 8 pairs were identified between the At and Dt subgenomes. Further, 6 out of the 8 duplicated gene pairs were located between the homologous chromosomes of <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. <italic>GhSK24</italic>, <italic>GhSK25</italic>, and their paralogs were localized to chromosome A09. Other gene pairs were duplicated either between At to At, or Dt to Dt subgenomes, which might have resulted from the whole genome duplication (WGD) during plant genome evolution.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Duplicated <italic>GSK</italic> gene pairs identified in <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, and <italic>G. raimondii</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="6">Duplicates</th></tr><tr><th>Clade</th><th>Gene ID</th><th>Gene name</th><th>Position</th><th>Gene ID</th><th>Gene name</th><th>Position</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>II</td><td>Ga09G0899</td><td>GaSK22</td><td>Ga09: 59971361&#x02013;59,974,663</td><td/><td/><td>Ga09: 59971879&#x02013;59,974,663</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Ga09G0899</td><td>GaSK22</td><td>Ga09: 59971361&#x02013;59,974,663</td><td/><td/><td>Ga09: 59989139&#x02013;59,991,790</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Ga09G0899</td><td>GaSK22</td><td>Ga09: 59971361&#x02013;59,974,663</td><td/><td/><td>Ga06: 130211141&#x02013;130,213,614</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Ga09G0900</td><td>GaSK23</td><td>Ga09: 59988594&#x02013;59,991,790</td><td/><td/><td>Ga09: 59989139&#x02013;59,991,790</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Ga09G0900</td><td>GaSK23</td><td>Ga09: 59988594&#x02013;59,991,790</td><td/><td/><td>Ga09: 59971879&#x02013;59,974,663</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Ga09G0900</td><td>GaSK23</td><td>Ga09: 59988594&#x02013;59,991,790</td><td/><td/><td>Ga06: 130211141&#x02013;130,213,614</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Ga02G1328</td><td>GaSK41</td><td>Ga02:91572951&#x02013;91,576,357</td><td/><td/><td>Ga12: 98906373&#x02013;98,909,799</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Ga06G2433</td><td>GaSK21</td><td>Ga06:130210718&#x02013;130,213,627</td><td/><td/><td>Ga09: 59989139&#x02013;59,991,777</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Ga06G2433</td><td>GaSK21</td><td>Ga06:130210718&#x02013;130,213,627</td><td/><td/><td>Ga09: 59971879&#x02013;59,974,650</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Ga12G2665</td><td>GaSK42</td><td>Ga12:98904726&#x02013;98,909,799</td><td/><td/><td>Ga02: 91572950&#x02013;91,576,342</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gorai.010G241600.3</td><td>GrSK21</td><td>Gr10: 61087060&#x02013;61,090,705</td><td/><td/><td>Gr10: 61087549&#x02013;61,090,443</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gorai.010G241600.2</td><td>GrSK21&#x02013;1</td><td>Gr10: 61085419&#x02013;61,090,069</td><td/><td/><td>Gr10: 61087549&#x02013;61,090,014</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Gorai.004G042400.1</td><td>GrSK31</td><td>Gr04: 3659148&#x02013;3,665,477</td><td/><td/><td>Gr04: 3659643&#x02013;3,665,066</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Gorai.004G156700.2</td><td>GrSK33</td><td>Gr04: 44445510&#x02013;44,453,846</td><td/><td/><td>Gr04: 44449136&#x02013;44,452,709</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Gorai.007G096100.1</td><td>GrSK32</td><td>Gr07: 7076952&#x02013;7,083,244</td><td/><td/><td>Gr07: 7077235&#x02013;7,082,655</td></tr><tr><td>I</td><td>Gorai.007G308500.3</td><td>GrSK11&#x02013;1</td><td>Gr07: 52192786&#x02013;52,196,322</td><td/><td/><td>Gr07: 52193148&#x02013;52,195,963</td></tr><tr><td>I</td><td>Gorai.007G308500.1</td><td>GrSK11</td><td>Gr07: 52192786&#x02013;52,197,103</td><td/><td/><td>Gr07: 52193148&#x02013;52,195,963</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gorai.002G218100.1</td><td>GrSK41</td><td>Gr02: 56980865&#x02013;56,985,951</td><td/><td/><td>Gr02: 56982189&#x02013;56,985,586</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gorai.002G218100.1</td><td>GrSK41</td><td>Gr02: 56980865&#x02013;56,985,951</td><td/><td/><td>Gr08: 6199127&#x02013;6,202,516</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gorai.008G045800.2</td><td>GrSK42&#x02013;2</td><td>Gr08: 6198649&#x02013;6,203,828</td><td/><td/><td>Gr02: 56982189&#x02013;56,985,579</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gorai.008G045800.2</td><td>GrSK42&#x02013;2</td><td>Gr08: 6198649&#x02013;6,203,828</td><td/><td/><td>Gr08: 6199120&#x02013;6,202,516</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gorai.008G045800.3</td><td>GrSK42&#x02013;1</td><td>Gr08: 6198649&#x02013;6,203,828</td><td/><td/><td>Gr02: 56982189&#x02013;56,985,579</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gorai.008G045800.3</td><td>GrSK42&#x02013;1</td><td>Gr08: 6198649&#x02013;6,203,828</td><td/><td/><td>Gr08: 6199120&#x02013;6,202,516</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gorai.008G045800.6</td><td>GrSK42</td><td>Gr08: 6198704&#x02013;6,203,828</td><td/><td/><td>Gr02: 56982189&#x02013;56,985,579</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gorai.008G045800.6</td><td>GrSK42</td><td>Gr08: 6198704&#x02013;6,203,828</td><td/><td/><td>Gr08: 6199120&#x02013;6,202,516</td></tr><tr><td>I</td><td>Gorai.008G136600.1</td><td>GrSK12</td><td>Gr08: 38585110&#x02013;38,589,107</td><td/><td/><td>Gr08: 38585874&#x02013;38,588,662</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gorai.006G089300.1</td><td>GrSK22</td><td>Gr06: 32530678&#x02013;32,535,037</td><td/><td/><td>Gr06: 32531407&#x02013;32,534,186</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gorai.006G089300.1</td><td>GrSK22</td><td>Gr06: 32530678&#x02013;32,535,037</td><td/><td/><td>Gr06: 32547582&#x02013;32,550,218</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gorai.006G089300.2</td><td>GrSK22&#x02013;1</td><td>Gr06: 32530521&#x02013;32,535,037</td><td/><td/><td>Gr06: 32531410&#x02013;32,534,186</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gorai.006G089300.2</td><td>GrSK22&#x02013;1</td><td>Gr06: 32530521&#x02013;32,535,037</td><td/><td/><td>Gr06: 32547583&#x02013;32,550,218</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gorai.006G089400.1</td><td>GrSK23</td><td>Gr06: 32546669&#x02013;32,551,023</td><td/><td/><td>Gr06: 32531410&#x02013;32,534,186</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gorai.006G089400.1</td><td>GrSK23</td><td>Gr06: 32546669&#x02013;32,551,023</td><td/><td/><td>Gr10: 61087562&#x02013;61,089,975</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_A12G0411</td><td>GhSK44</td><td>A12: 8244999&#x02013;8,248,430</td><td>Gh_D01G1809</td><td>GhSK42</td><td>D14: 55472542&#x02013;55,475,929</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_A12G0411</td><td>GhSK44</td><td>A12: 8244999&#x02013;8,248,430</td><td>Gh_A01G1558</td><td>GhSK41</td><td>A01: 92410496&#x02013;92,413,866</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_A12G0411</td><td>GhSK44</td><td>A12: 8244999&#x02013;8,248,430</td><td>Gh_D12G0407</td><td>GhSK43</td><td>D25: 6533936&#x02013;6,537,332</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_D06G2142</td><td>GhSK21</td><td>D19: 63261021&#x02013;63,263,915</td><td>Gh_A06G2020</td><td>GhSK26</td><td>Scaf1340_A06: 43051&#x02013;45,948</td></tr><tr><td>I</td><td>Gh_D11G2830</td><td>GhSK11</td><td>D24: 58071261&#x02013;58,074,075</td><td>Gh_A11G3270</td><td>GhSK12</td><td>Scaf3045_A11: 160891&#x02013;163,705</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Gh_A08G0285</td><td>GhSK31</td><td>A08: 3329052&#x02013;3,334,479</td><td>Gh_D08G0378</td><td>GhSK36</td><td>D21: 3871235&#x02013;3,880,133</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_D12G0407</td><td>GhSK43</td><td>D25: 6533937&#x02013;6,537,332</td><td>Gh_D01G1809</td><td>GhSK42</td><td>D14: 55472542&#x02013;55,475,929</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_D12G0407</td><td>GhSK43</td><td>D25: 6533937&#x02013;6,537,332</td><td>Gh_A01G1558</td><td>GhSK41</td><td>A01: 92410496&#x02013;92,413,866</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_D12G0407</td><td>GhSK43</td><td>D25: 6533937&#x02013;6,537,332</td><td>Gh_A12G0411</td><td>GhSK44</td><td>A12: 8244998&#x02013;8,248,430</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Gh_D08G0378</td><td>GhSK36</td><td>D21: 3871236&#x02013;3,880,133</td><td>Gh_A08G0285</td><td>GhSK31</td><td>A08: 3329051&#x02013;3,334,479</td></tr><tr><td>I</td><td>Gh_D12G1230</td><td>GhSK14</td><td>D25: 40170076&#x02013;40,172,846</td><td>Gh_A12G1106</td><td>GhSK13</td><td>A12: 64114145&#x02013;64,116,909</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_D01G1809</td><td>GhSK42</td><td>D14: 55472543&#x02013;55,475,936</td><td>Gh_A01G1558</td><td>GhSK41</td><td>A01: 92410496&#x02013;92,413,873</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_D01G1809</td><td>GhSK42</td><td>D14: 55472543&#x02013;55,475,936</td><td>Gh_D12G0407</td><td>GhSK43</td><td>D25: 6533943&#x02013;6,537,332</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_A09G0712</td><td>GhSK25</td><td>A09: 52841598&#x02013;52,844,894</td><td/><td/><td>A09: 52842113&#x02013;52,844,894</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_A09G0712</td><td>GhSK25</td><td>A09: 52841598&#x02013;52,844,894</td><td>Gh_A09G0713</td><td>GhSK24</td><td>A09: 52861923&#x02013;52,864,569</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_A09G0712</td><td>GhSK25</td><td>A09: 52841598&#x02013;52,844,894</td><td>Gh_D09G2469</td><td>GhSK22</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 137948&#x02013;140,717</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_A09G0712</td><td>GhSK25</td><td>A09: 52841598&#x02013;52,844,894</td><td>Gh_D09G2468</td><td>GhSK23</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 123123&#x02013;125,754</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_A09G0713</td><td>GhSK24</td><td>A09: 52861382&#x02013;52,864,569</td><td/><td/><td>A09: 52842113&#x02013;52,844,894</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_A09G0713</td><td>GhSK24</td><td>A09: 52861382&#x02013;52,864,569</td><td/><td/><td>A09: 52861923&#x02013;52,864,569</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_A09G0713</td><td>GhSK24</td><td>A09: 52861382&#x02013;52,864,569</td><td>Gh_D09G2469</td><td>GhSK22</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 137948&#x02013;140,717</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_A09G0713</td><td>GhSK24</td><td>A09: 52861382&#x02013;52,864,569</td><td>Gh_D09G2468</td><td>GhSK23</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 123123&#x02013;125,754</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Gh_D11G0907</td><td>GhSK33</td><td>D24: 7839230&#x02013;7,844,650</td><td>Gh_A11G0778</td><td>GhSK35</td><td>A11: 7649122&#x02013;7,654,545</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Gh_A08G1158</td><td>GhSK34</td><td>A08: 81021333&#x02013;81,025,764</td><td>Gh_D08G1440</td><td>GhSK32</td><td>D21: 47361119&#x02013;47,366,590</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_A01G1558</td><td>GhSK41</td><td>A01: 92410497&#x02013;92,413,873</td><td>Gh_D01G1809</td><td>GhSK42</td><td>D14: 55472542&#x02013;55,475,936</td></tr><tr><td>IV</td><td>Gh_A01G1558</td><td>GhSK41</td><td>A01: 92410497&#x02013;92,413,873</td><td>Gh_D12G0407</td><td>GhSK43</td><td>D25: 6533943&#x02013;6,537,332</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Gh_A11G0778</td><td>GhSK35</td><td>A11: 7649123&#x02013;7,654,545</td><td>Gh_D11G0907</td><td>GhSK33</td><td>D24: 7839229&#x02013;7,844,650</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Gh_D08G1440</td><td>GhSK32</td><td>D21: 47361120&#x02013;47,366,590</td><td>Gh_A08G1158</td><td>GhSK34</td><td>A08: 81021332&#x02013;81,025,764</td></tr><tr><td>I</td><td>Gh_A12G1106</td><td>GhSK13</td><td>A12: 64114146&#x02013;64,116,909</td><td>Gh_D12G1230</td><td>GhSK14</td><td>D25: 40170075&#x02013;40,172,846</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_A06G2020</td><td>GhSK26</td><td>Scaf1340_A06: 43052&#x02013;45,877</td><td>Gh_D06G2142</td><td>GhSK21</td><td>D19: 63261091&#x02013;63,263,915</td></tr><tr><td>I</td><td>Gh_A11G3270</td><td>GhSK12</td><td>Scaf3045_A11: 160892&#x02013;163,705</td><td>Gh_D11G2830</td><td>GhSK11</td><td>D24: 58071260&#x02013;58,074,075</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_D09G2468</td><td>GhSK23</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 123124&#x02013;126,295</td><td/><td/><td>A09: 52861923&#x02013;52,864,569</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_D09G2468</td><td>GhSK23</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 123124&#x02013;126,295</td><td/><td/><td>A09: 52842113&#x02013;52,844,894</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_D09G2468</td><td>GhSK23</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 123124&#x02013;126,295</td><td>Gh_D09G2469</td><td>GhSK22</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 137948&#x02013;140,717</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_D09G2469</td><td>GhSK22</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 137949&#x02013;141,233</td><td/><td/><td>A09: 52861923&#x02013;52,864,569</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_D09G2469</td><td>GhSK22</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 137949&#x02013;141,233</td><td/><td/><td>A09: 52842113&#x02013;52,844,894</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Gh_D09G2469</td><td>GhSK22</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 137949&#x02013;141,233</td><td>Gh_D09G2468</td><td>GhSK23</td><td>Scaf4332_D22: 123123&#x02013;125,754</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par46">Syntenic blocks consist of conserved genes arranged similarly in chromosomes of different species. In this study, 26, 28 and 13 conserved non-nested syntenic blocks around GSK genes were predicted between the genomes of <italic>G.hirsutum</italic> and <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic>, and <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic>, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The detailed information regarding each syntenic block is provided in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Table S3. The <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> genes on chromosomes A01, A08, A09, A11, A12, D14, D19, D21, D24, and D25 as well as scaffold 1340_A06, 3045_A11, and 4332_D22 were likely derived from conserved blocks on <italic>G. arboreum</italic> chromosome Ga02, Ga06, Ga08, Ga09, Ga11, and Ga12. Meanwhile, genes on <italic>G. raimondii</italic> chromosome Gr02, Gr04, Gr06, Gr07, Gr08, and Gr10 were predicted to possess ortholog genes on <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> chromosomes as well as orthologs of <italic>GaSKs</italic>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Orthologous <italic>GSK</italic> genes identified in <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic>. Links between <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> and <italic>G. arboreum</italic> are colored in cyan, <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> in orange, <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> in light purple. Chromosomes of <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>arboreum</italic> and <italic>raimondii</italic> were respectively colored in orange-red, green and blue</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><italic>GhSK</italic> expression profiles in various tissues and organs</title><p id="Par47">Different tissue- and organ-specific gene expression patterns might be an indicator of distinct biological functions. Heat maps of transcriptomic data from the NCBI database revealed that most of the genes assigned to the same subfamily were clustered together and had similar expression profiles (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). For example, most of <italic>GhSK</italic> genes were expressed at relatively low levels in 25, 35 dpa ovules and fiber tissues. The exception being subfamily IV members, as well as <italic>GhSK33</italic> and <italic>GhSK35</italic> in 10 and 20 dpa ovule, <italic>GhSK34</italic> in early stage fiber and <italic>GhSK32</italic> in 5, 10, and 20 dpa fiber tissues where their expression was often significant. Most of <italic>GhSK</italic> genes had relatively high expression levels in &#x02212;&#x02009;1~&#x02009;20 dpa ovules. Additionally, <italic>GhSK32</italic>, <italic>GhSK33</italic>, <italic>GhSK34</italic>, and <italic>GhSK35</italic> were highly expressed in petal and stamen tissues. Apart from subfamily IV members, other <italic>GhSKs</italic> had relatively high, but uneven expression patterns in various floral organs. Most of the <italic>GhSK</italic> members showed poor expressions in the dry seed, while some exhibited slightly higher expression in the calycle (epicalyx). Nearly all the <italic>GhSKs</italic> had relatively high expression levels in leaf and stem, excluding <italic>GhSK31</italic>, <italic>GhSK33</italic>, <italic>GhSK35</italic>, <italic>GhSK36</italic> and members of subfamily IV. Furthermore, only <italic>GhSK14</italic>, <italic>GhSK21</italic>, <italic>GhSK25</italic>, <italic>GhSK42</italic>, <italic>GhSK43</italic> exhibited relatively high expression levels in root tissue.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Hierarchical clustering of gene expression profiles of all <italic>GhSK</italic> members in 23 diverse organs/tissues (dry seed, root, stem, leaf, torus (receptacle), petal, stamen, pistil, calycle (epicalyx), 10 stages of ovule and 4 stages of fiber). The FPKM values, log10-transformed, were utilized to generate the heat map. The blue colors indicate low expression levels, while yellow represents high expression levels</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par48">The different members of the same gene family can exhibit diverse expression patterns in various tissues/organs and play different physiological functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. To further validate the transcriptomic data, the expression levels of 20 <italic>GhSK</italic> genes were analyzed in 10 different tissues/organs, including flower, ovule (1, 3, and 5 dpa), and fiber (7, 10, 15, and 20 dpa) by Q-PCR (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Here, 13 of the 20 genes (<italic>GhSK12</italic>, <italic>13</italic>, <italic>14</italic>, <italic>22</italic>, <italic>23</italic>, <italic>24</italic>, <italic>25</italic>, <italic>32</italic>, <italic>35</italic>, <italic>41</italic>, <italic>42</italic>, <italic>43</italic>, and <italic>44</italic>) were preferentially or relatively highly expressed in different fiber development stages. The <italic>GSK</italic> gene expression was lower in whole flower tissues than in the isolated growing fibers.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Validation by qRT-PCR of tissues/organ-specific expression patterns of <italic>GhSK</italic> genes (flower, ovules of 1, 3, and 5 dpa, fibers of 7, 10, 15 and 20 dpa samples of CCRI24 were used). Data are the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three independent experiments</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Analysis of <italic>GSK</italic> promoter regions</title><p id="Par49">Abundant hormone- and stress-related <italic>cis</italic>-elements, including <italic>cis</italic>-elements that confer high transcript levels and MYB-binding sites were detected in the regions 2&#x02009;kb upstream of the transcription start site of different GhSK genes (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Figure S4 and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: Table S4). The phylogenetically similar genes shared identical <italic>cis</italic>-elements. All of the <italic>GhSK</italic> promoter regions contained more than one <italic>cis</italic>-element that confers high transcript level. Additionally, heat-, defense-, stress-, salicylic acid-, and auxin-responsive <italic>cis</italic>-elements were identified in the promoter regions of almost all <italic>GhSK</italic> genes, except for <italic>GhSK44</italic> (no heat-responsive element), <italic>GhSK13</italic> and <italic>32</italic> (no defense- and stress-responsive elements), <italic>GhSK13</italic>, <italic>14</italic> and <italic>43</italic> (no salicylic acid-responsive element), and <italic>GhSK11, 12, 43,</italic> and <italic>44</italic> (no auxin-responsive element). Furthermore, wound-responsive elements were detected only in the promoter regions of <italic>GhSK21, GhSK26</italic>, and <italic>GhSK32</italic>, while only <italic>GhSK23 and 33</italic> contained an ABA-responsive element. Moreover, 9 and 13 out of 20 <italic>GhSK</italic> genes contained low temperature- and GA-responsive elements respectively, while methyl jasmonate- and fungal elicitor-responsive <italic>cis</italic>-element were observed in 8 and 9 genes respectively. MYB-binding site or MYB binding site involved in regulating flavonoid gene expression was observed in 4 <italic>GhSKs</italic> promoter regions, while elements of drought-inducible MYB binding site were observed in 13 <italic>GhSKs</italic> promoter regions. Additionally, the ethylene-responsive element was identified in 8 <italic>GhSKs</italic> promoter regions. Furthermore, three kinds of tissue-specific (shoot, meristem, and seed) elements were found in the promoter regions of some of the <italic>GhSK</italic> genes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title><italic>GSK</italic> gene expression patterns in response to several abiotic stresses</title><p id="Par50">To explore the physiological and functional relevance of <italic>GhSK</italic> genes, we investigated the expression patterns of 20 <italic>GhSK</italic> genes under different environmental stresses [i.e., Cold (4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C), salinity, simulated drought (PEG), and heat (38&#x02009;&#x000b0;C)] (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Among the 20 genes, expression levels of six <italic>GhSK</italic> (i.e., <italic>GhSK14</italic>, <italic>22</italic>, <italic>35</italic>, <italic>41</italic>, <italic>43</italic>, and <italic>44</italic>) genes were down-regulated by all imposed stresses. Not all <italic>GhSK</italic> genes were induced or repressed by temperature stresses. Among them, <italic>GhSK21</italic>, <italic>24</italic>, <italic>26</italic>, and <italic>36</italic> were cold induced, <italic>GhSK21</italic>, <italic>24</italic> and <italic>42</italic> were up-regulated by heat stress, while the expression levels of <italic>GhSK31</italic>, <italic>33</italic>, and <italic>36</italic> were repressed under heat condition. Except for <italic>GhSK25</italic>, <italic>31</italic>, and <italic>33</italic>, the expression levels of the other 11 <italic>GhSK</italic> genes (excluded those six uniformly down-regulated genes mentioned above) were up-regulated on exposure to PEG. <italic>GhSK11</italic>, <italic>12</italic>, and <italic>13</italic> were slightly induced by PEG treatment during the first 3&#x02009;h. <italic>GhSK21</italic>, <italic>GhSK24</italic>, and <italic>GhSK26</italic> were highly responsive to PEG treatments, with 3-fold, 2-fold, and 4-fold increases, respectively, irrespective of different times after treatment. Unlike <italic>GhSK31</italic> and <italic>33</italic>, expression levels of the other <italic>GhSK3s</italic> exhibited more than 2-fold increases at 3&#x02009;h after PEG treatment excluding <italic>GhSK36</italic> that peaked at 1&#x02009;h with about 4-fold changes. The expression level of <italic>GhSK42</italic> was only slightly affected by PEG at 1&#x02009;h but was subsequently induced, reaching its peak level (approximately 2.5-fold increase) at 3&#x02009;h. For salinity stress, expression levels of <italic>GhSK11</italic>, <italic>25</italic>, and <italic>42</italic> were not significantly induced at any time point. However, <italic>GhSK12</italic>, <italic>24</italic>, and <italic>32</italic> expression levels increased during the first 3&#x02009;h and then decreased slightly. Additionally, the expression levels of <italic>GhSK13</italic>, <italic>23</italic>, <italic>31</italic>, <italic>33</italic> and <italic>36</italic> were up-regulated over the first 6&#x02009;h (approximately 3-fold, 3-fold, 3-fold, 2.2-fold, and 2.3-fold increases, respectively) and then decreased. Meanwhile, <italic>GhSK21</italic>, <italic>26</italic>, <italic>34</italic> as well as <italic>42</italic> expression levels were up-regulated gradually and finally peaked at 12&#x02009;h after salinity treatment.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>20 <italic>GhSKs</italic> relative expression patterns in response to cold, NaCl, PEG and heat stresses were analyzed by qRT-PCR. The relative expression levels of CK (0&#x02009;h) were normalized to 1. Data were the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three independent experiments</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Regulatory sub-networks involving <italic>GhSK</italic> and other <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> genes</title><p id="Par51">Co-expressed genes exhibit similar increases or decreases in transcription levels in different samples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. The <italic>GSKs</italic> are known to influence several developmental, signaling, and physiological processes in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The co-expression between <italic>GhSK</italic> and other <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> genes were analyzed using the R package (WGCNA), and the co-expressed genes linking to other <italic>GhSK</italic> genes (<italic>GhSKs</italic> linkers) were identified and annotated (Fig&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref><bold>,</bold> Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: Figure S5a, S5b, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">10</xref>: Figure S6 and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM11" ref-type="media">11</xref>: Table S5.1, S5.2 and S5.3). We detected five modules (blue, brown, green, turquoise and yellow), in which nine <italic>GhSK</italic> genes were co-expressed with other <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> genes. Surprisingly, the <italic>GhSK32</italic> (found in brown module) was co-expressed with 2781&#x02009;<italic>G. hirsutum</italic> genes across all the analyzed samples (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">10</xref>: Figure S6 and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM11" ref-type="media">11</xref>: Table S5.1, S5.2, and S5.3). The <italic>GhSK34</italic> (also present in the brown module) had 2142 co-expressed genes (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">10</xref>: Figure S6 and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM11" ref-type="media">11</xref>: Table S5.3). These genes in the brown module were enriched in 55 GO terms (<italic>FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</italic>) (i.e., 30, 20, and 5 related to molecular functions, biological processes, and cellular components, respectively). Additionally, <italic>GhSK13</italic> was co-expressed with 17 genes (including <italic>GhSK14</italic>) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>), similarly, <italic>GhSK31</italic> was co-expressed with 20 genes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8b</xref>). <italic>GhSK11</italic>, <italic>GhSK25</italic>, and <italic>GhSK24</italic> were co-expressed with 19, 1 (Gh_A04G1034), and 20 other <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> genes, respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8c</xref>), meanwhile, <italic>GhSK42</italic> and <italic>GhSK41</italic> were co-expressed with 6 and 11 genes, respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8d</xref>). Among these genes, <italic>GhSK11</italic> and <italic>GhSK24</italic> were indirectly co-expressed with each other, as were <italic>GhSK42</italic> and <italic>GhSK4</italic> (directly/indirectly). Similarly, <italic>GhSK32</italic> co-expressed with <italic>GhSK34</italic> both directly and indirectly (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">10</xref>: Figure S6 and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM11" ref-type="media">11</xref>: Table S5.3). The co-expressed genes in the brown module were mainly enriched (Top20 GO) for protein phosphorylation, protein kinase activity, integral component of membrane, Calcium ion binding, transmembrane transport, and enzyme inhibitor activity (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: Figure S5a). Further, these were also significantly enriched in pentose and glucoronate interconversion, plant-pathogen interaction, as well as starch and sucrose metabolism pathways (Top20 KEGG) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: Figure S5b). The GO (<italic>FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</italic>) and KEGG (<italic>p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</italic>) enrichment results for the other target genes are presented in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM11" ref-type="media">11</xref>: Table S5.1 and S5.2.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>The weighted gene co-expression analysis modules of <italic>GhSK</italic> genes visualized by Cytoscape software. <bold>a</bold> Co-expression sub-network for <italic>GhSK13</italic>. <bold>b</bold> Co-expression sub-network for <italic>GhSK31</italic>. <bold>c</bold> Co-expression sub-network for <italic>GhSK14</italic> and <italic>GhSK24</italic>. <bold>d</bold> Co-expression sub-network for <italic>GhSK42</italic> and <italic>GhSK41</italic>. Nodes are genes with node size related to the number of connections of that gene to other co-expressed genes. Nodes are connected by lines (edges) with the weight of the line determined by the size of the correlation coefficient with thicker lines having a higher correlation and hence higher certainty</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par52">Protein kinases form a large family of enzymes that mediate eukaryotic cell responses to external stimuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. To date, several protein kinase family members have been identified, including GSK3, MAPKKK, Pto-like protein kinase, and PP2C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Among these enzymes, GSK3 reportedly regulates different physiological and developmental processes in mammals and plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. However, the genome-wide characterization of GSK3-like kinases has been limited to model plants, even though these enzymes were first reported decades ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec25"><title>The cotton GSK gene family expanded but remained highly conserved during evolution</title><p id="Par53">The availability of high-quality whole draft genome sequences has enabled the characterization of <italic>G. aboreum</italic>, <italic>G. raimondii</italic>, and <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> genes. Interestingly, the number of <italic>G. hirsutum GSK</italic> genes almost equals to the sum of <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> genes, possibly because of its formation as an allotetraploid following hybridization of A and D genome progenitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Consistent with the names of corresponding <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and rice genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], we renamed the cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes as <italic>GhSKs</italic> (i.e., <italic>G. hirsutum Shaggy/GSK3-like kinases</italic>), <italic>GaSKs</italic> and <italic>GrSKs</italic> (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Additionally, the cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes were divided into four subfamilies in accordance with the <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and rice <italic>GSK</italic> genes. We observed that subfamily II was the largest containing 14 members, then subfamily III with 12 members, IV and I comprised of 10 and 9 members respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Moreover, the sub-cellular location of almost all GSKs was predicted to be in the nucleus, membrane and cytoplasm, except for GaSK23 (cytoplasmic) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Additionally, the kinase domains of AtSKs and OsSKs were 65&#x02013;72% similar to human GSK3&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Here, we aligned the peptide sequences of AtSKs, OsSKs, GaSKs, GrSKs, and GhSKs. All of these GSKs contain related conserved domains and residues, suggesting these enzymes are highly conserved across species and that of the GSK family existed before the separation of these different species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par54">Consistent with the AtSKs, cotton GSKs are clustered into four clades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The results of phylogenetic analysis and the presence of conversed domains suggested that the GSKs may have analogous biological functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. However, various bootstrap values in the phylogenetic tree were low, potentially because of a relatively low similarity in the protein sequences of different species. This implied there was considerable variability in the <italic>GSK</italic> gene sequences, even though the protein motifs were highly conserved (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Furthermore, the cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes clustered in the same subfamily were observed to encode proteins with similar motifs and protein architectures, suggesting the protein structures were conserved among members of the same subfamily. Nevertheless, there was significant diversity in the N-terminal domains of GSKs between different subfamilies, which was consistent with the findings of Forde and Dale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. Protein kinases are important for regulating protein phosphorylation in many cellular activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. Integrating the results of conserved protein motifs, multiple sequence alignment, and previously published research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], we speculate that a functional GSK kinase domain (motifs 1 to 4) was present in all cotton GSKs although we have not confirmed this enzymatically (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref><bold>:</bold> Figure S3). Additionally, most of these GSKs also contain serine and/or threonine kinase active sites and tyrosine residues, which could be phosphorylated by other kinases to modulate their enzymatic activity. This is believed to occur in all GSK3s and is required for the full kinase activity of human GSK3&#x003b2;. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Gene duplicates and synteny blocks were detected between cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes</title><p id="Par55">Allotetraploid cotton was generated from the fusion of two diploid cotton species, with chromosomes 1&#x02013;13 and 14&#x02013;26 derived from A and D genomes, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. In our study, <italic>GSK</italic> genes were unevenly distributed on the chromosomes of the three analyzed cotton species (diploid <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> as well as allotetraploid <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>). Thus, <italic>GSK</italic> gene duplication events might have occurred in these chromosomes during evolution, with neo- or sub-functionalization of these genes.</p><p id="Par56">Orthologs are genes in different genomes that were derived from the same ancestral gene; they encode proteins with similar biological functions, whereas paralogs are defined as genes derived from a single gene via a duplication event, encoding proteins with different functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. During evolutionary processes, new genes were generated as a result of large segmental and small-scale tandem duplications or polyploidization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. Duplicated genes are often found to be involved in the formation of paralogous genes present in gene families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. Tandem duplication usually results from unequal crossovers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>] and multiple occurrences of these can result in the expansion or reduction of different gene family members [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Here, <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, <italic>G. ramondii</italic>, and <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> contain more than one <italic>GSK</italic> gene clusters and genes within them with similar intron numbers suggesting that these duplicated genes might be the result of unequal crossovers. Additionally, recent studies demonstrated that the <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> genomes underwent at least two whole-genome duplication events [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Although the total number of <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> genes dramatically expanded after polyploidization and duplication, gene loss also occurred during the evolution of upland cotton [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. These might be the cause of the greater number of paralog gene pairs (25) in upland cotton compared to <italic>G. arboreum</italic> (10) and the uneven distribution of <italic>GSK</italic> genes on different chromosomes. Considering that orthologs might exhibit the same biological functions over the course of evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>], the syntenic blocks between <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> and <italic>G. arboreum</italic>, <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic>, and <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G.raimondii</italic> were identified. All <italic>GhSK</italic> genes had at least one syntenic gene in <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic>. Further, most of the highly similar gene pairs in regions around GSK genes found by comparing <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> (red), <italic>G. raimondii</italic> and <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> (blue), and <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> (orange) in our study coincided with previous synteny analyses of various published cotton genomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], marked in different colors mentioned above and detailed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Table. S3, suggesting that most of the cotton <italic>GSK</italic> loci were conserved during evolution.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title><italic>GhSKs</italic> are involved in fiber development and abiotic stresses response</title><p id="Par57">Variations in the expression patterns of <italic>GSK</italic> family members in various tissues/organs may be related to their functional differences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. To further characterize the potential regulatory functions of <italic>GhSKs</italic> affecting cotton growth and development, the expression patterns of 20 <italic>GhSK</italic> genes were analyzed using both transcriptomic data and qRT-PCR data. Similar tissue- and organ-specific expression patterns were observed for the same <italic>GhSK</italic> gene based on either transcriptome or qRT-PCR data. Furthermore, <italic>GhSK22</italic>, <italic>41</italic>, and <italic>GhSK44</italic> were preferentially expressed in fibers. The <italic>GhSK12</italic>, <italic>25</italic>, and <italic>32</italic> expression levels were also relatively high in different fiber tissues. <italic>GSK</italic> genes were previously reported to be involved in BR signaling in flowering plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. These kinases may help to control cell elongation in plants because BRs regulate cell elongation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. However, gene expression levels of most <italic>GhSKs</italic> were not induced or repressed by exogenous BL treatment (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM12" ref-type="media">12</xref>: Figure S7). Previous reports indicated that brassinolide treatment reduced in vivo phosphorylation of BIN2, a special GSK3 member, and inhibited its function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Similarly, BL treatment has been reported to lead to reductions in the protein accumulation and to inhibit the phosphorylation of AtSK12 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. The BR signal transduction pathway starts from a receptor kinase (BRI) to BR responsive transcription factors BZR1 and BES1, through a process of phosphorylation and dephosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. Last but not the least, we checked the differential expression levels of <italic>AtSKs</italic> in previously published transcriptome data of BL treated <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>], but similarly saw no evidence of transcriptional induction or repression of <italic>AtSKs</italic>. We speculate that BRs might affect GSKs at the protein and post-translational modification levels, rather than at the level of transcriptional regulation. Additionally, BIN2 functions in the crosstalk between BRs and auxin. <italic>AtSK21/BIN2</italic> expression accelerates lateral root formation via the activation of ARF7 and ARF19, which are two factors involved in auxin-mediated lateral root development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. Meanwhile, TGA elements described as auxin-responsive elements were found in almost all <italic>GhSK</italic> gene promoter regions, and previous research has demonstrated that NAA (a synthetic auxin) enhances fiber elongation by suppressing secondary wall cellulose synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]. Furthermore, the regulation of auxin biosynthesis in ovule epidermal cells of cotton can enhance fiber quality and yield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]. Additionally, ethylene was reported as playing a major role during fiber elongation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>], and ERE (ethylene responsive elements) were found in 8 <italic>GhSK</italic> promoter regions. The current evidence suggests that <italic>GhSKs</italic> may therefore mediate fiber development and elongation.</p><p id="Par58">Plant responses to abiotic and biotic stresses are found to be regulated by GSK3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], although not in a consistent fashion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Previous studies confirmed that <italic>GSK3</italic> expression is up-regulated by salt stress in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>], wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>], and sugarcane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Moreover, the expressions of <italic>AtSK13</italic>, <italic>31</italic>, and <italic>42</italic> are also up-regulated by osmotic stress, while <italic>OsGSK3</italic> expression is down-regulated under drought conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]. Consistent with these findings, we determined that the transcription of most <italic>GhSK</italic> genes were up-regulated in response to several abiotic stresses. The opposite trend was observed for six other <italic>GhSK</italic> genes. In contrast, <italic>GhSK25</italic> expression was rarely affected under abiotic stress conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Another study indicated that <italic>OsGSK3</italic> expression is up-regulated on exposures to salt, cold, and drought stresses, mechanical injury, and exogenous ABA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. These results imply the encoded kinase activates signal cascade during stress. Besides, over-expressing <italic>TaSK5</italic> cDNA in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> enhances the resistance of the transgenic plants to salinity and drought stresses, while their tolerance to freezing stress is retained [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. Coupled with these results, we may conclude that stress-responsive <italic>cis</italic>-elements in the <italic>GhSK</italic> promoter regions play crucial roles during plant responses to various abiotic stresses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Several fiber-related genes are co-expressed with <italic>GhSKs</italic></title><p id="Par59">Glycogen synthase kinase 3 is a serine/threonine kinase with several vital roles in animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. There are about 18 proteins verified as direct substrates of GSK3. This kinase is associated with multiple molecular and cellular mechanisms affecting glycogen metabolism, cell cytoskeleton stability, as well as the regulation of cell division, differentiation, and apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. In the current study, a coexpressed network analyzed by WGCNA indicated that 9 <italic>GhSK</italic> genes were co-expressed with one or more other <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> genes. Additionally, a KEGG enrichment analysis (<italic>p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</italic>) revealed that these 9 <italic>GhSK</italic> genes could be involved in stress responses, phytohormone signal transductions, and/or the Wnt signaling pathway. Moreover, the genes co-expressed in the brown module containing <italic>GhSK32</italic> and <italic>GhSK34</italic> were significantly enriched for protein phosphorylation (GO:0006468), protein kinase activity (GO:0004672), integral component of membrane (GO:0016021), Calcium ion binding (GO:0005509), transmembrane transport (GO:0055085) and enzyme inhibitor activity (GO:0004857). The genes co-expressed with <italic>GhSK41</italic> and <italic>GhSK42</italic> were enriched for functions related to cytoskeleton organization (GO:0007010) and microtubule binding (GO:0008017). Cortical microtubules and newly deposited cellulose microfibrils are transversely oriented relative to the growth axis of fiber cell, and are critical for longitudinal expansion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. In addition, the temporal and spatial Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration changes in the fiber tip are converted through calcium sensors, such as calmodulins, calcium-dependent protein kinases, and calcineurin B-like proteins that have been shown to be necessary for maintaining fast cell elongation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Furthermore, ethylene has also been shown to promote fiber elongation by activating genes involved in cytoskeleton organization and cell wall loosening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]. These findings may help to clarify the potential functions of GhSKs in fiber development and will lay the foundations for further molecular and functional analysis of <italic>GSK</italic> genes in cotton.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par60">Previous research has shown that <italic>GSK</italic> genes have significant functions in regulating plant growth and development, as well as responses to various abiotic stresses. In the present study, <italic>GSK</italic> genes were shown to be highly conserved among <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, rice and three cotton species (<italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. raimondii</italic>, and <italic>G. arboreum</italic>). Whole genome duplication was speculated as the major impetus for the expansion of the <italic>GSK</italic> gene family in cotton. Additionally, the duplicated <italic>GhSK</italic> genes might have experienced functional diversification as the duplicated gene pairs exhibited disparate expression patterns in different tissues and organs. Further, some <italic>GSK</italic> gene members were shown to be involved in fiber development as well as stress responses.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec30"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.1</bold> Gene accession numbers and sample information of transcriptome data used in our research. <bold>Table S1.2</bold> FPKM values of transcriptome data used in our research. (XLSX 16765 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S2.</bold> FPKM values of different tissues obtained from published transcriptome data. (XLSX 16 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM3_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> Multiple sequence alignments of the kinase domains of Arabidopsis, rice, and cotton. Amino acids are shaded in black, dark and light grey based on sequence similarity (high to low). The kinase-inactivating mutation <italic>bin2</italic> that suppresses gain of function are highlighted in light green. The conserved phosphate-binding residues are highlighted in orange. The conversed tyrosine phosphorylated residue is highlighted in red. The conserved TRRE box in which the three residues (T, E, and E) that lead to BIN2 gain of function are included are highlighted in green. (PDF 3258 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S2.</bold> Phylogenetic analysis of GSK3 proteins in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, rice, and species of cotton. 10 AtSKs, 15 OsSKs, 20 GhSKs, 10 GaSKs, and 10 GrSKs are divided into four clades. The four clades are respectively colored in cyan, reddish brown, violet, and green. The tree was constructed by Minimum-Evolution using Poisson model of MEGA 6.0. (PDF 301 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S3.</bold> Motif logos of 16 conserved motifs found in cotton GSK proteins. (PDF 817 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM6_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S3.</bold> Orthologous <italic>GSK</italic> genes identified in <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>, <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic>. Orthologous genes were highlighted on condition that they were coincident with the results analyzed by MCScanX software: orthologous gene pairs between <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> and <italic>G. arboreum</italic> were highlighted in red, <italic>G. hirsutum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> in blue, as well as <italic>G. arboreum</italic> and <italic>G. raimondii</italic> in orange. (XLSX 18 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM7_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 7:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S4.</bold> Cis-regulatory elements predicted in the promoter regions of cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes. (PDF 173 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM8_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 8:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S4.</bold> Cis-regulatory elements found in the promoter regions of cotton <italic>GSK</italic> genes. (XLSX 33 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM9_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 9:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S5.</bold> The GO (a) and KEGG (b) enrichment of weighted co-expressed genes of the brown module <italic>(GhSK32)</italic> as predicted by &#x0201c;WGCNA&#x0201d; R package with published transcriptomics data. (PDF 149 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM10"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM10_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 10:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S6.</bold> The weighted gene co-expression analysis sub-network of <italic>GhSK32</italic> and <italic>GhSK34</italic> were visualized by Cytoscape software. (PDF 7454 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM11"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM11_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 11:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S5.1</bold> GO annotations of the co-expressed genes involved in the weighted gene co-expression sub-network of <italic>GhSKs</italic>. <bold>Table S5.2</bold> KEGG annotations of the co-expressed genes involved in the weighted gene co-expression sub-network of <italic>GhSKs</italic>. <bold>Table S5.3</bold> Linkers co-expressed with <italic>GhSK32</italic> and <italic>GhSK34. (XLSX 201 kb)</italic></p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM12"><media xlink:href="12870_2018_1526_MOESM12_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 12:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S7.</bold> 20 <italic>GhSKs</italic> expression patterns in response to BL treatment were analyzed by qRT-PCR. The relative expression levels of CK (0&#x02009;h) were normalized to 1. Data are the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three independent experiments. (PDF 459 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term><italic>A. thaliana</italic></term><def><p id="Par4">
<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ABA</term><def><p id="Par5">Abscisic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BIN2</term><def><p id="Par6">Brassinosteroid-Insensitive 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BL</term><def><p id="Par7">Brassinolide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BLAT</term><def><p id="Par8">BLAST-Like Alignment Tool</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BR</term><def><p id="Par9">Brassinosteroid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Dpa</term><def><p id="Par10">Day post-anthesis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>G6PD</term><def><p id="Par11">Glc-6-phosphate dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GA</term><def><p id="Par12">Gibberellins</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GaSKs</term><def><p id="Par13"><italic>Gossypium arboreum</italic> Shaggy/GSK3-like kinases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GhSKs</term><def><p id="Par14"><italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> Shaggy/GSK3-like kinases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p id="Par15">Gene Ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GrSKs</term><def><p id="Par16"><italic>Gossypium raimondii</italic> Shaggy/GSK3-like kinases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSK3</term><def><p id="Par17">Glycogen synthase 3/shaggy-like kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p id="Par18">Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PEG</term><def><p id="Par19">Polyethylene glycol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qRT-PCR</term><def><p id="Par20">Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WGCNA</term><def><p id="Par21">Weighted gene co-expression network analysis</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><p>The authors would like to thank the previous researchers and communities (particularly Tianzhen Zhang et al., Nanjing Agricultural University) to submit the transcriptome data of the upland cotton TM-1 to NCBI SRA databases. Special thanks to Dr. Xiaoyang Ge for his insightful comments and suggestions that helped us to improve our manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par61">This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31501345) in writing the manuscript and Young Elite Scientist Sponsorship Program by CAST supported the funds for the research but was not involved in data collection and analysis, or the preparation or publication of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par62">The data generated or analyzed in this study are included in this article and its Additional materials. And the Genome sequence and annotation datasets that supported the findings of this study are available in: <italic>A. thaliana</italic>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org/">http://www.arabidopsis.org</ext-link>.</p><p id="Par63"><italic>O. sativa</italic>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plants.ensembl.org/index.html">http://plants.ensembl.org/index.html</ext-link>.</p><p id="Par64"><italic>G. hirsutum</italic>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cottongen.org">https://www.cottongen.org</ext-link></p><p id="Par65"><italic>G. arboreum</italic>: PacBio-Gar-Assembly-v1.0, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://bioinfo.ayit.edu.cn/downloads/">ftp://bioinfo.ayit.edu.cn/downloads/</ext-link></p><p id="Par66"><italic>G. raimondii</italic>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cottongen.org">https://www.cottongen.org</ext-link></p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>FGL and ZRY designed the experiments. LLW performed the data analysis and drafted the manuscript. ZEY provided and analyzed the transcriptome data. BZ, DQY, and QG conducted the abiotic stress experiments and provided the organs/tissues of CRI24. GQ and YJL contributed technical support in writing and editing the manuscript. LLL, YL, and JL prepared the cotton seedlings. All of the authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The plant materials (including seeds) were collected from Zhengzhou Research base, State key Laboratory of Cotton Biology, Institute of Cotton Research, CAAS. The experimental research on plants, including collection of plant material, was complied with the institutional, national, or international guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic diversification of glycogen synthase kinase 3/SHAGGY-like kinase genes in plants</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-6-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16504046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saidi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hearn</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Function and evolution of &#x02018;green&#x02019; GSK3/Shaggy-like kinases</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2011.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22051150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orena</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Torchia</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garofalo</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of glycogen-synthase kinase 3 stimulates glycogen synthase and glucose transport by distinct mechanisms in 3T3-L1 adipocytes</article-title><source>J Bio Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>15765</fpage><lpage>15772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M910002199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10748179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rylatt</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Condon</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Embi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycogen synthase from rabbit skeletal muscle. Amino acid sequence at the sites phosphorylated by glycogen synthase kinase-3, and extension of the N-terminal sequence containing the site phosphorylated by phosphorylase kinase</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><year>1980</year><volume>107</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1980.tb06060.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6772446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>ME</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>JMd</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stripes of positional homologies across the wing blade of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Development</source><year>1988</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>401</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OsGSK3 is a novel GSK3/SHAGGY-like gene from <italic>Oryza sativa L</italic>., involved in abiotic stress signaling</article-title><source>Pak J Bot</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>1496</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddien</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wnt signaling and the polarity of the primary body axis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>139</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2009.11.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20005801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Saint-Jeannet</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodgett</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Varmus</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawid</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycogen synthase kinase-3 and dorsoventral patterning in Xenopus embryos</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1995</year><volume>374</volume><issue>6523</issue><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/374617a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7715701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GSK3: a multifaceted kinase in Wnt signaling</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibs.2009.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19884009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodgett</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multisite phosphorylation of glycogen synthase. Molecular basis for the substrate specificity of glycogen synthase kinase-3 and casein kinase-II (glycogen synthase kinase-5)</article-title><source>Biochimica Biophys Acta</source><year>1984</year><volume>788</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0167-4838(84)90047-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dornelas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>van Lammeren</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis thaliana SHAGGY-related protein kinases (AtSK11 and AtSK12) function in perianth and gynoecium development</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.2000.00691.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10758494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charrier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Champion</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression profiling of the whole Arabidopsis shaggy-like kinase multigene family by real-time reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>130</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.009175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tavares</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Lammeren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AtSK&#x003b8;, a plant homologue of SGG_GSK-3 marks developing tissues in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1016009831678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12175018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claisse</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Charrier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> GSK3/Shaggy like kinase AtSK3&#x02013;2 modulates floral cell expansion</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>64</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-007-9138-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17427040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dal Santo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stampfl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasensky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kempa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Petutschnig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stress-induced GSK3 regulates the redox stress response by phosphorylating glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3380</fpage><lpage>3392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.101279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22885737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of Brassinosteroid Signaling by a GSK3/SHAGGY-Like Kianse</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>295</volume><fpage>1299</fpage><lpage>1301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11847343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronn</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyploidy and the evolutionary history of cotton</article-title><source>Adv Agron</source><year>2003</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2113(02)78004-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cotton (<italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic>) seed trichomes expand via diffuse growing mechanism</article-title><source>Can J Bot</source><year>1995</year><volume>73</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b95-081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gundlach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repeated polyploidization of Gossypium genomes and the evolution of spinnable cotton fibres</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>492</volume><issue>7429</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23257886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sze</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Accumulation of genome-specific transcripts, transcription factors and phytohormonal regulators during early stages of fiber cell development in allotetraploid cotton</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2006</year><volume>47</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02829.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16889650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Veerabomma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Mageed</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fokar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brassinosteroid regulates fiber development on cultured cotton ovules</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>46</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1384</fpage><lpage>1391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pci150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15958497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The calcium sensor GhCaM7 promotes cotton fiber elongation by modulating reactive oxygen species (ROS) production</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2014</year><volume>202</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24443839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How cotton fibers elongate: a tale of linear cell-growth mode</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2010.09.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20943428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PAG1, a cotton brassinosteroid catabolism gene, modulates fiber elongation</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2014</year><volume>203</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24786710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seagull</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Giavalis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pre- and Post-Anthesis Application of Exogenous Hormones Alters Finer Production in <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L. Cultivar Maxxa GTO</article-title><source>J Cotton Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>111</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nemhauser</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different plant hormones regulate similar processes through largely nonoverlapping transcriptional responses</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>126</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.05.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16901781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The primary signaling outputs of brassinosteroids are regulated by abscisic acid signaling</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>4543</fpage><lpage>4548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0900349106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19240210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaiwanon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatiotemporal brassinosteroid signaling and antagonism with auxin pattern stem cell dynamics in Arabidopsis roots</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2015.02.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25866388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hormonal crosstalk for root development: a combined experimental and modeling perspective</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>116</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24734037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandenbussche</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Callebert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zadnikova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Benkova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Straeten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brassinosteroid control of shoot gravitropism interacts with ethylene and depends on auxin signaling components</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2013</year><volume>100</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1200264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23152331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integration of brassinosteroid signal transduction with the transcription network for plant growth regulation in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>777</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2010.10.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21074725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aleman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-mageed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of cotton orthologs of GA signal transduction factors GID1 and SLR1</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>68</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-008-9347-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18506581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohel</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence of cultivated Upland cotton (<italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> TM-1) provides insights into genome evolution</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25893780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sequencing of allotetraploid cotton (<italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L. acc. TM-1) provides a resource for fiber improvement</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25893781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The draft genome of a diploid cotton Gossypium raimondii</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1098</fpage><lpage>1103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22922876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence of the cultivated cotton <italic>Gossypium arboreum</italic></article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2014</year><volume>46</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24836287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression changes and early events in cotton fibre development</article-title><source>Ann Bot</source><year>2007</year><volume>100</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1391</fpage><lpage>1401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcm232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17905721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of GRAS transcription factor gene family in <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>348</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-4722-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29743013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of WOX genes in upland cotton and their expression pattern under different stresses</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>113</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-017-1065-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28683794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(&#x02212;Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zerbino</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Achuthan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Akanni</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Amode</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ensembl 2018</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D754</fpage><lpage>D761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx1098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29155950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ficklin</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Percy</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Main</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CottonGen: a genomics, genetics and breeding database for cotton research</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D1229</fpage><lpage>D1236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24203703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resequencing of 243 diploid cotton accessions based on an updated A genome identifies the genetic basis of key agronomic traits</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2018</year><volume>50</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0116-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29736014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coggill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberhardt</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mistry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Pfam protein families database: towards a more sustainable future</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D279</fpage><lpage>D285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26673716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional insights of plant GSK3-like kinases: multi-taskers in diverse cellular signal transduction pathways</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2014.12.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25655825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA-CC: computing core of molecular evolutionary genetics analysis program for automated and iterative data analysis</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>2685</fpage><lpage>2686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22923298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sequence-based ultra-dense genetic and physical maps reveal structural variations of allopolyploid cotton genomes</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>108</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0678-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26003111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The value of prior knowledge in discovering motifs with MEME</article-title><source>Proc Int Conf Intell Syst Mol Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7584439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doerks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Copley</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic identification of novel protein domain families associated with nuclear functions</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.203201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11779830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krzywinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Birol</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Connors</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascoyne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Horsman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>1645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.092759.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19541911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lescot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehais</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thijs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Peer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rombauts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PlantCARE, a database of plant cis-acting regulatory elements and a portal to tools for in silico analysis of promoter sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.1.325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasteiger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gattiker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Duvaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein Identification and Analysis Tools on the ExPASy Server</article-title><source>The Proteomics Protocols Handbook</source><year>2005</year><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>607</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briesemeister</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahnenfuhrer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohlbacher</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>YLoc--an interpretable web server for predicting subcellular localization</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><issue>Web Server issue</issue><fpage>W497</fpage><lpage>W502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20507917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNAs and their proposed functions in fibre development of cotton (Gossypium spp.)</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2015</year><volume>207</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>1197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25919642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langfelder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WGCNA: an R package for weighted correlation network analysis</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>559</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-9-559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19114008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Markiel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozier</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Baliga</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramage</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwikowski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ideker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2498</fpage><lpage>2504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.1239303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide survey and expression analysis of the plant-specific NAC transcription factor family in soybean during development and dehydration stress</article-title><source>DNA Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsr015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21685489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dornelas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>von Recklinghausen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>van Lammeren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of three novel members of the Arabidopsis SHAGGY-related protein kinase (ASK) multigene family</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>39</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1006102812280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10080716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jonak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycogen synthase kinase 3/SHAGGY-like kinases in plants: an emerging family with novel functions</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(02)02331-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12399181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgarten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The roles of segmental and tandem gene duplication in the evolution of large gene families in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-4-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15171794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide analysis of the auxin/indole-3-acetic acid gene family in hexaploid bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>770</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26483801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oncotarget-Identification of breast cancer candidate genes using gene co-expression and protein-protein interaction information</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>36092</fpage><lpage>36100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27150055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Approaches for extracting practical information from gene co-expression networks in plant biology</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcm013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17251202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanks</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The protein kinase family: conserved features and deduced phylogeny of the catalytic domains</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1988</year><volume>241</volume><issue>4861</issue><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.3291115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3291115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-Wide Analysis and Evolution of the Pto-Like Protein Kinase (PLPK) Gene Family in Pepper</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e0161545</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0161545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27536870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and evolutionary analyses of the PP2C gene family with their expression profiling in response to multiple stresses in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>175</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-2526-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26935448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dornelas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lejeune</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis SHAGGY-related protein kinase (ASK) gene family: structure, organization and evolution</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1998</year><volume>212</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-1119(98)00147-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9611268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification, phylogeny and expressional profiles of mitogen activated protein kinase kinase kinase (MAPKKK) gene family in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>668</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-2993-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27549916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>FQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GSK3 signaling in neural development</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20648061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Double</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodgeet</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GSK-3: trick of the trade for multi-tasking kinase</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>1175</fpage><lpage>1186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.00384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12615961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohel</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic nomenclature in cotton</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1973</year><volume>64</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>291</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a108415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forde</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycogen synthase kinase 3: a key regulator of cellular fate</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>64</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>1930</fpage><lpage>1944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-007-7045-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17530463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide exploration of the molecular evolution and regulatory network of mitogen-activated protein kinase cascades upon multiple stresses in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>228</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1452-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25886731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lochhead</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinstrie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sibbet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawjee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrice</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleghon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A chaperone-dependent GSK3beta transitional intermediate mediates activation-loop autophosphorylation</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>24</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2006.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17188038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Frame</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goedert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Polakis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A GSK3-binding peptide from FRAT1 selectively inhibits the GSK3-catalysed phosphorylation of Axin and L-catenin</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><year>1999</year><volume>458</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(99)01161-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10481074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatusov</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genomic perspective on protein families</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>278</volume><issue>5338</issue><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.278.5338.631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9381173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heidelberg</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaidos</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence of the dissimilatory metal ion-reducing bacterium Shewanella oneidensis</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2002</year><volume>20</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1118</fpage><lpage>1123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution by gene duplication: an update</article-title><source>Trens Ecol Evol</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(03)00033-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achaz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Coissac</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Viari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Netter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of intrachromosomal duplications in yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>: a possible model for their origin</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1268</fpage><lpage>1275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a026410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10908647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altenhoff</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dessimoz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic and functional assessment of orthologs inference projects and methods</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e1000262</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19148271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Perez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponce</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Micol</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The UCU1 Arabidopsis gene encodes a SHAGGY/GSK3-like kinase required for cell expansion along the proximodistal axis</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>242</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/dbio.2001.0543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11820813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Burlingame</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brassinosteroid signal transduction from cell-surface receptor kinases to nuclear transcription factors</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1254</fpage><lpage>1260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb1970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19734888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pati</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Versatile roles of brassinosteroid in plants in the context of its homeostasis, signaling and crosstalks</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>950</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26583025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemhauser</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Geldner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of steroid hormone signaling in plants</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.21.090704.151241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16212492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belkhadir</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Brassinosteroid Signaling Pathway</article-title><source>Sci STKE</source><year>2006</year><volume>2006</volume><issue>364</issue><fpage>cm5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17148786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenhart</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell elongation is regulated through a central circuit of interacting transcription factors in the Arabidopsis hypocotyl</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e03031</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.03031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Audenaert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A secreted peptide acts on BIN2-mediated phosphorylation of ARFs to potentiate auxin response during lateral root development</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24362628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheek</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Haigler</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A synthetic auxin (NAA) suppresses secondary wall cellulose synthesis and enhances elongation in cultured cotton fiber</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep</source><year>2009</year><volume>28</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-009-0714-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19479259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatiotemporal manipulation of auxin biosynthesis in cotton ovule epidermal cells enhances fiber yield and quality</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21478877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome profiling, molecular biological, and physiological studies reveal a major role for ethylene in cotton fiber cell elongation</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.040303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16461577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T-DNA tagged knockout mutation of rice OsGSK1, an orthologue of Arabidopsis BIN2, with enhanced tolerance to various abiotic stresses</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>65</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-007-9213-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17690841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constitutive over-expression of AtGSK1 induces NaCl stress responses in the absence of NaCl stress and results in enhanced NaCl tolerance in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2001</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.2001.01099.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11532176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Paquet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Haudecoeur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Charrier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organization and expression of the GSK3/shaggy kinase gene family in the moss <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> suggest early gene multiplication in land plants and an ancestral response to osmotic stress</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>2005</year><volume>61</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00239-004-0302-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16007489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kempa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozhon</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Samaj</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Erban</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baluska</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A plastid-localized glycogen synthase kinase 3 modulates stress tolerance and carbohydrate metabolism</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2007</year><volume>49</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1076</fpage><lpage>1090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.03025.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17319843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patade</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Suprasanna</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression analysis of sugarcane shaggy-like kinase (SuSK) gene identified through cDNA subtractive hybridization in sugarcane (<italic>Saccharum officinarum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Protoplasma</source><year>2011</year><volume>248</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00709-010-0207-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20853012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of TaGSK1 involved in wheat salt tolerance</article-title><source>Plant Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>165</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9452(03)00365-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christov</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Christova</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TaSK5, an abiotic stress-inducible GSK3/shaggy-like kinase from wheat, confers salt and drought tolerance in transgenic Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source><year>2014</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2014.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25306528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frame</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GSK3 takes centre stage more than 20 years after its discovery</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2001</year><volume>359</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/bj3590001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11563964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seagull</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of microtubule and microfilament disrupting agents on cytoskeletal arrays and wall deposition in developing cotton fibers</article-title><source>Protoplasma</source><year>1990</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01326634</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>