<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Food Sci Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Food Sci Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2048-7177</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">FSN3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Food Science &#x00026; Nutrition</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2048-7177</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5980175</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.590</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">FSN3590</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Physical, chemical, and sensory properties of biscuits prepared from flour blends of unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">ADEOLA and OHIZUA</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="fsn3590-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Adeola</surname><given-names>Abiodun A.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0761-3507</contrib-id><address><email>adeolaroni@yahoo.com</email><email>adeolaaa@funaab.edu.ng</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn3590-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn3590-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ohizua</surname><given-names>Ehimen R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn3590-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="fsn3590-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Food and Nutrition Research Programme</named-content>
<institution>Institute of Food Security, Environmental Resources and Agricultural Research</institution>
<institution>Federal University of Agriculture</institution>
<named-content content-type="city">Abeokuta</named-content>
<country country="NG">Nigeria</country>
</aff><aff id="fsn3590-aff-0002">
<label><sup>2</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Food Science and Technology</named-content>
<institution>Federal University of Agriculture</institution>
<named-content content-type="city">Abeokuta</named-content>
<country country="NG">Nigeria</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Abiodun A. Adeola, Food and Nutrition Research Programme, Institute of Food Security, Environmental Resources and Agricultural Research, Federal University of Agriculture, Abeokuta, Nigeria.<break/>
Emails: <email>adeolaroni@yahoo.com</email>; <email>adeolaaa@funaab.edu.ng</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.2018.6.issue-3</issue-id><fpage>532</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2018 Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2018 The Authors. <italic>Food Science &#x00026; Nutrition</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:FSN3-6-532.pdf"/><abstract id="fsn3590-abs-0001"><title>Abstract</title><p>Biscuits were produced from 14 flour blends of cooking banana (<styled-content style="fixed-case">UBF</styled-content>), pigeon pea (<styled-content style="fixed-case">PPF</styled-content>), and sweet potato (<styled-content style="fixed-case">SPF</styled-content>). The physical properties, nutrient composition, and sensory characteristics of the biscuits were evaluated using standard methods. Data obtained were subjected to analysis of variance, and mean values were separated using Duncan's multiple range test. The hardness of the biscuit samples decreased as <styled-content style="fixed-case">PPF</styled-content> increased, while the fracturability decreased with increase in <styled-content style="fixed-case">UBF</styled-content>. Biscuits were significantly (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05) different in their nutrient composition, with the crude protein, crude fiber, ash contents, and dietary fiber content increasing as the <styled-content style="fixed-case">PPF</styled-content> level increased. Cookies were rich in magnesium (576.54&#x02013;735.06&#x000a0;mg/100&#x000a0;g) with favorable Na/K ratio (&#x0003c;1.0). The antinutritional factors in the biscuit samples were within permissible levels. Biscuits prepared from flour blend of 21.67% unripe cooking banana, 21.67% pigeon pea, and 56.67% sweet potato were the most preferred in terms of shape, mouthfeel, taste, crunchiness, and overall acceptability. Flour blends of unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato could therefore be used as raw materials for the production of biscuits, with high protein, total dietary, and energy content.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="fsn3590-kwd-0001">biscuit</kwd><kwd id="fsn3590-kwd-0002">cooking banana</kwd><kwd id="fsn3590-kwd-0003">nutrient composition</kwd><kwd id="fsn3590-kwd-0004">pigeon pea</kwd><kwd id="fsn3590-kwd-0005">sweet potato</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>TefFund, Nigeria</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>Institute of Food Security, Environmental Resources and Agricultural Research</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>Federal University of Agriculture, Abeokuta, Nigeria</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="7860"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>fsn3590</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>May 2018</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:version=5.4.0 mode:remove_FC converted:31.05.2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-1001">
<string-name>
<surname>Adeola</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ohizua</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Physical, chemical, and sensory properties of biscuits prepared from flour blends of unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Sci Nutr</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>532</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>540</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.590">https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.590</ext-link>
</mixed-citation>
</p><fn-group id="fsn3590-ntgp-0001"><fn fn-type="funding" id="fsn3590-note-1001"><p>
<bold>Funding Information</bold>
</p><p>The authors acknowledge TefFund, Nigeria, and the Institute of Food Security, Environmental Resources and Agricultural Research, Federal University of Agriculture, Abeokuta, Nigeria, for providing financial assistance for this study.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Biscuits are prominent ready&#x02010;to&#x02010;eat baked snack among the people, globally. The association of wheat consumption with such health problems as celiac disease makes it pertinent to utilize composite flour in biscuit manufacture (Kiin&#x02010;Kabari &#x00026; Giami, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Composite flour is desirable in this regard because it improves the nutritional value of food products such as bakery products, especially when blended with legumes such as pigeon pea (Preedy, Watso, &#x00026; Patel, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). In fact, biscuits have been suggested as better use for composite flour than bread due to their ready&#x02010;to&#x02010;eat form, wide consumption, relatively long shelf life, and good eating quality (Bala, Gul, &#x00026; Riar, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Noorfarahzihah, Lee, Sharifudin, Mohd&#x02010;Fadzelly, &#x00026; Hasmadi, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).</p><p>The use of banana flour in biscuits is desirable due to its contents of indigestible carbohydrate, mineral, and antioxidant capacity (Ovando&#x02010;Martinez, S&#x000e1;yago&#x02010;Ayerdi, Agama&#x02010;Acevedo, Go&#x000f1;i, &#x00026; Bello&#x02010;P&#x000e9;rez, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Preedy et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Pigeon pea, though grows well in Nigeria and is a good source of protein, is underutilized due to its hard&#x02010;to&#x02010;cook phenomenon (Fasoyiro &#x00026; Arowora, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). The use of pigeon pea flour in the production of biscuits has been reported (Chinma et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Okpala &#x00026; Okoli, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Silky &#x00026; Tiwari, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Sweet potato flour is used in baking as a dough conditioner and as an alternative flour in the production of gluten&#x02010;free products. It has been reported to improve the nutrient composition and toasting properties, reduce staling, and provide a distinctive flavor to several baked products such as bread and biscuits (Adeyeye &#x00026; Akingbala, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Noorfarahzihah et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Onabanjo &#x00026; Ighere, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).</p><p>This study which is a continuation of our earlier work (Ohizua et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) therefore evaluated some quality attributes of biscuits from composite flour of unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato.</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Source of raw materials</title><p>Mature unripe cooking banana (<italic>Musa cardaba</italic> AAB) as earlier described by Ohizua et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>), cream flesh sweet potato root (<italic>Ipomea batatas</italic>), and pigeon pea (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic>) were obtained from local markets in Ibadan, Abeokuta, and Oshodi, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0004"><label>2.2</label><title>Preparation of flours from unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato</title><p>Unripe cooking banana flour (UBF), pigeon pea flour (PPF), and sweet potato flour (SPF) were prepared according to the methods described by Ohizua et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Banana fruits were washed, peeled under water treated with 0.05% (w/v) sodium metabisulphite, sliced to an average thickness of 1&#x000a0;mm, dried at 50&#x000b0;C for 24&#x000a0;hr in a Genlab Cabinet dryer (Model DC 500, Serial number 12B154), and milled using Fritsch hammer mill (Serial number: 15.302/982) equipped with a 250&#x02010;&#x003bc;m mesh sieve. Pigeon pea seeds were subjected to cleaning, boiling (20&#x000a0;min), dehulling, drying (60&#x000b0;C for 48&#x000a0;hr), cooling at room temperature, and milling using Fritsch hammer mill (Serial number: 15.302/982) equipped with a 250&#x02010;&#x003bc;m mesh sieve. Sweet potato roots were cleaned, cut into chips, soaked in 0.05% (w/v) sodium metabisulphite for 10&#x02013;20&#x000a0;min to prevent browning, drained, dried in at 60&#x000b0;C for 48&#x000a0;hr, and milled in a Fritsch hammer mill (Serial number: 15.302/982) equipped with a 250&#x02010;&#x003bc;m mesh sieve.</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0005"><label>2.3</label><title>Blending of flour</title><p>The method described by Ohizua et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) was used.</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0006"><label>2.4</label><title>Preparation of biscuit</title><p>The modified recipe of Onabanjo and Ighere (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) adopted after preliminary experimentation was as follows: flour (250&#x000a0;g), fat (63&#x000a0;g), sugar (63&#x000a0;g), salt (1&#x000a0;g), whole egg (20&#x000a0;ml), powdered milk (5&#x000a0;g), nutmeg (1.5&#x000a0;g), baking powder (1&#x000a0;g), and water (20&#x02013;60&#x000a0;ml).</p><p>Biscuit was prepared using the traditional creaming method described by Chinma et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>).The fat and sugar were mixed in a Kenwood mixer (HM 430) until the mixture was fluffy. Eggs and milk were added, while mixing continued. Baking powder, ground nutmeg, composite flour, and salt were introduced into the mixture to form a soft dough. The dough was removed from the bowl and kneaded on a flat surface to obtain a uniform mix. The kneaded dough was rolled out into sheets using a rolling pin and cut into the desired shape using a cutter. The cut mass was transferred to a greased baking tray. Baking was carried out at 180&#x000b0;C for 17&#x000a0;min. Biscuit made from 100% wheat flour served as the control sample.</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0007"><label>2.5</label><title>Determination of physical properties of biscuit</title><p>The method described by Bala et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) was used, with slight modification, to evaluate the biscuit for the following parameters:</p><p>
<list list-type="bullet" id="fsn3590-list-0001"><list-item><p>Thickness of biscuits was determined by measuring the diameter of four biscuit samples placed edge to edge with a digital vernier caliper. An average of six values was taken for each set of samples. Average value for thickness was reported in millimeter.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Diameter of biscuits was determined by placing four biscuit samples edge to edge and measuring with a digital vernier caliper. An average of six values was taken for each set of samples. Average value for diameter was reported in millimeter.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Weight of biscuits was measured as average values of six individual biscuits with the help of an analytical weighing balance. Average value for weight was reported in grams.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Spread ratio was calculated by dividing diameter by thickness.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Texture profile analysis of biscuit samples: Hardness and fracturability analysis of the biscuit samples were determined using the TA&#x02010;XT Plus texture analyzer (Stable Micro Systems Serial No. 5014 England) according to the method described by Ahmed and Hussein (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). The analyzer was set to perform single&#x02010;cycle measurements which were used for the determination of the first bite force of the product. The measurement speed of 2&#x000a0;mm/s and a distance of 5&#x000a0;mm were applied. The force&#x02013;time plots were analyzed for hardness or breaking force (g) and fracturability (mm) to reach the peak. Textural attributes were measured in six independent samples.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0008"><label>2.6</label><title>Determination of color attribute of biscuit</title><p>The color intensity of the top and down (the one in contact with the baking tray) surfaces of biscuit samples was measured using a Konica Minolta Colour Measuring System (Chroma Meter CR&#x02010;410, Minolta LTD Japan). The lightness (L*), redness (a*), and yellowness (b*) values were obtained after calibrating the instrument using a white tile. Six replicate readings were taken for each biscuit formulation sample and the average value reported. The results were expressed in accordance with the CIE LAB system where:</p><p>L * is known as the lightness [L&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0 (black), L&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;100 (white)],</p><p>a* (&#x02212;a&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;greenness, +a&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;redness)</p><p>b * (&#x02212;b* values&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;blueness, +b* value&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;yellowness)</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0009"><label>2.7</label><title>Determination of chemical properties of biscuit</title><p>The proximate composition of the biscuit sample was determined in triplicate using the standard procedures of Association of Official Analytical Chemists (AOAC, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>).</p><p>Total dietary fiber content was evaluated using the method of AOAC (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>).</p><p>The total carotenoid content of biscuit samples was determined by the method described by Ohizua et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Briefly, the method involved filtering a mixture of biscuit sample and 70% methanol and washing the residue with acetone&#x02013;petroleum ether. The extract was mixed with a solution of 10% KOH in methanol (v/v) in a separating funnel, which was allowed to stand for about 1&#x000a0;hr. In addition of petroleum ether and solution of sodium chloride to separating funnel, the lower layer was discarded and the upper layer treated with distilled water and anhydrous sodium sulfate. The filtrate was made up to 250&#x000a0;ml and the absorbance measured at 450&#x000a0;nm with a UV/Visible spectrophotometer (Model: CE 2021 2000 series, serial no 923&#x02010;41).</p><p>Calculation:
<disp-formula id="fsn3590-disp-0001"><mml:math id="nlm-math-1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Total carotenoids content</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Volume</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ml</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">cm</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Weight</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">of</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">sample</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p>where: <italic>A</italic> =Absorbance</p><p>Volume = total volume of extract</p><p>
<mml:math id="nlm-math-2"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">cm</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math>= Absorption coefficient of &#x003b2;&#x02010;carotene in petroleum ether (2,592).</p><p>The method described by Ohizua et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) was used to determine the mineral composition of biscuit. Sodium, potassium, and calcium were determined using the Jenway digital flame photometer, while the atomic absorption spectrophotometer (Thermo scientific S series Model GE Model No. 712354) was used to determine magnesium, iron, and manganese.</p><p>The method described by Ohizua et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) was used to determine the vitamin C content of the biscuit samples. Aqueous solution of ground biscuit sample was titrated with indophenol standard and the vitamin C calculated.</p><p>Calculation:
<disp-formula id="fsn3590-disp-0002"><mml:math id="nlm-math-3"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Vitamin C content</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.0000833</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">titre</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">value</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100000</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Weight</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">of</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">sample</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>20</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Tannin, oxalate, phytate, and trypsin inhibitor were determined as earlier described (Ohizua et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>).</p><p>The energy content was estimated by calculation from fat, carbohydrate, and protein contents, using the Atwater's conversion factor: 4.0&#x000a0;kcal/g for protein, 9.0&#x000a0;kcal/g for fat, and 4.0&#x000a0;kcal/g for carbohydrate content.</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0010"><label>2.8</label><title>Sensory evaluation of biscuit</title><p>Both the descriptive and discriminatory evaluation methods were used (Iwe, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). The organoleptic characteristics of the biscuit samples chosen by 15 trained judges were appearance (symmetry), color, aroma, mouthfeel, sweetness, hardness, crunchiness, and overall acceptability. Thereafter, a 50&#x02010;member panel evaluated coded biscuit samples based on the identified attributes using a 9&#x02010;point hedonic scale.</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0011"><label>2.9</label><title>Data analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed using SPSS 21.0 software. Means with significant difference were separated by applying Duncan's multiple range test at 95% confidence level.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0012"><label>3</label><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0013"><label>3.1</label><title>Physical properties of biscuits</title><p>There were significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05) differences in the thickness, diameter, height, spread ratio, weight, hardness, and fracturability of the biscuit samples (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn3590-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap">1</xref>). The thickness of the biscuits increased as the inclusion of SPF and UBF increased in the biscuit formulation. Values for height increased as the level of SPF increased, while the weight of the biscuit increased as level of PPF in the formulation increased. This may be due to the increasing protein content arising from incorporation of PPF. Spread ratio or diameter is used to determine the quality of flour used in preparing biscuits and the ability of the biscuit to rise (Bala et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). The higher the spread ratio of biscuit the more desirable it is (Chauhan, Saxena, &#x00026; Singh, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Hence, biscuit prepared from the flour blend containing 45% UBF, 10% PPF, and 45% SPF may be the most preferred based on spread ratio. This assertion is confirmed in Table <xref rid="fsn3590-tbl-0004" ref-type="table-wrap">4</xref> where there were no significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05) differences in the sensory attributes of this biscuit sample and the one adjudged to be the most acceptable. Biscuit sample prepared from 21.6:21.67:56.67 (UBF:PPF:SPF) flour blend had the highest overall acceptability. Similar findings with respect to the weight, diameter, and spread ratio were reported by other researchers (Mridula, Goyal, Bhargar, &#x00026; Manikantan, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Oluwamukomi, Oluwalana, &#x00026; Akinbowale, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Textural quality [hardness and fracturability] is a very important and desirable quality attribute for biscuit. Hardness, which is the peak force required to break the biscuit, decreased as the percentage inclusion of PPF in the formulation reduced. Fracturability measures the ability of a product to fight to regain its original status or form. Fracturability of the biscuit samples significantly (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05) reduced as the level of UBF increased. Apart from the baking conditions, the type, quantity of ingredients, and protein content of the flour used have been reported to influence its hardness and other textural attributes (Gaines, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>; Pyler, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">1982</xref>). The result suggests that blends having higher PPF and SPF levels would be suitable to maintain its shape during transportation and would fracture easily when chewed in the mouth name (Manley, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). Similar results for hardness of biscuit with increased incorporation of pigeon pea flour were reported by Silky and Tiwari (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="fsn3590-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Physical properties of biscuits prepared from flour blends of unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBF:PPF:SPF blend ratio</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thickness (mm)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diameter (mm)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (mm)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spread ratio</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (g)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hardness (g)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fracturability (mm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:80:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.46<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.83<sup>abcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.74<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.49<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,456.72<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:45:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.63<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.74<sup>abcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.92<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.85<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.35<sup>abcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,316.94<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72<sup>b</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:10:80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.20<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.30<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.23<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.42<sup>abcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,285.04<sup>m</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71<sup>j</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67:56.67:21.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.43<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.09<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.12<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.93<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,771.33&#x000a0;<sup>l</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.41<sup>g</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:10:45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.05<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.82<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.26<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,092.47<sup>k</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59<sup>i</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:45:45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.64<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.48<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.42<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.80<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.14<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,945.73<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84<sup>c</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:10:80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.96<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.24<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.23<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.44<sup>abcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,391.73<sup>n</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.148<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33:33.33:33.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.93<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.43<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.06<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,749.59<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72<sup>k</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.67:21.67:21.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.45<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.40<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.31<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.16<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.92<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,164.51<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84<sup>c</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:80:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.55<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.86<sup>abcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.77<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.49<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,550.59<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80:10:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.13<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.16<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.15<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,632.03<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51<sup>h</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:10:45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.05<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.81<sup>abcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.26<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,095.34<sup>k</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40<sup>f</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67:21.67:56.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.48<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.36<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.98<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,817.64<sup>n</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88&#x000a0;<sup>l</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80:10:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.16<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.16<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.15<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,759.61<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.31<sup>e</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fsn3590-note-0002"><p>Mean values with different superscripts within a column are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05); UBF, unripe cooking banana flour; PPF, pigeon pea flour; SPF, sweet potato flour.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0014"><label>3.2</label><title>Color attribute of biscuit</title><p>Color is an important attribute because it can arouse individual's appetite. It is one of the parameters used for process control during baking and roasting, because brown pigments appear as browning and caramelization reactions progress (Pereira, Correia, &#x00026; Guine, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). The L*, a*, and b* values of the biscuit samples were lower for the topside than downside (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn3590-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). The positive values of a* and b* values indicated the predominance of redness and yellowness in the biscuit samples. The color of the biscuits changed to dark brown from creamy yellow as the inclusion level of PPF and SPF increased. This may be due to the ingredient composition, air velocity in the oven, and red pigmentation resulting from the Maillard reaction or nonenzymatic browning which depends on the content of reducing sugars and amino acids or proteins on the surface, baking temperature, and time (Pereira et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). The current result is similar to the findings of other workers (Pereira et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="fsn3590-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Color attributes of biscuit prepared from flour blends of unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">UBF:PPF:SPF blend ratio</th><th align="left" colspan="3" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Color of biscuit (topside)</th><th align="left" colspan="3" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Color of biscuit (downside)</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L*</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a*</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b*</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L*</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a*</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:80:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.60<sup>cde</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.10<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.68<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.58<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.70<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.29<sup>i</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:45:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.06<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.94<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.82<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.86<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.53<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.45<sup>c</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:10:80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.76<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.56<sup>de</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.01<sup>de</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.23<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.57<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.38<sup>k</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67:56.67:21.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.59<sup>ef</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.28<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.86<sup>de</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.55<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.57<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.36<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:10:45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.29<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.14<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.12<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.58<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.68<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.60<sup>f</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:45:45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.76<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.06<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.24<sup>de</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.45<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.17<sup>ef</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.58&#x000a0;<sup>l</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:10:80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.60<sup>ef</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.23<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.51<sup>de</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.06<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.24<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.38<sup>k</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33:33.33:33.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.83<sup>def</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.71<sup>de</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.19<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.16<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.83<sup>def</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.30<sup>h</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.67:21.67:21.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.80<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.28<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.13<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.87<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.82<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.51<sup>b</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:80:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.10<sup>cde</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.93<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.71<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.42<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.03<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.79<sup>j</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80:10:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.77<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.74<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.53<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.04<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.10<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.42<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:10:45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.79<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.12<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.22<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.50<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.51<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.43<sup>e</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67:21.67:56.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.73<sup>ef</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.17<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.22<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.29<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.03<sup>g</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80:10:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.44<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.57<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.36<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.04<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.10<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.11<sup>m</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fsn3590-note-0003"><p>Means with different superscripts within a column are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05); UBF, unripe cooking banana flour; PPF, pigeon pea flour; SPF, sweet potato flour.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0015"><label>3.3</label><title>Chemical properties of biscuit</title><p>There was a significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05) in the proximate composition, energy content, total carotenoid, and vitamin C content of the biscuits (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn3590-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap">3</xref>). The moisture content of the biscuit samples increased as the inclusion levels of SPF and PPF increased. This may be attributed to the high water&#x02010;binding capacity of both flours which retained higher moisture content in the ultimate product (Anuonye, Jigam, &#x00026; Ndaceko, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). The protein content increased as PPF increased but decreased as UBF and SPF increased. Similar observations were observed by other authors (Anuonye et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Fasoyiro &#x00026; Arowora, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Silky &#x00026; Tiwari, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Tiwari, Brennan, Jaganmohan, Surabi, &#x00026; Alagusundaram, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Foods rich in protein content are of great nutritional importance in developing countries such as Nigeria where there is a prevalence of protein malnutrition (Anuonye et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Okpala &#x00026; Okoli, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Protein is required by children for growth, repair, and maintenance of the body. It also acts as enzymes and hormones and maintains fluid, electrolyte and acid&#x02013;base balance, and strong immune system (Mahan &#x00026; Escott&#x02010;Stump, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). Proteins act as carriers for other nutrients such as lipids, vitamin A, iron, sodium, and potassium (Mahan &#x00026; Escott&#x02010;Stump, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="fsn3590-tbl-0003" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Chemical properties of biscuits produced from flour blends of unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Chemical attributes</th><th align="left" colspan="14" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">UBF:PPF:SPF blend ratio</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:80:10</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:45:10</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:10:80</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67:56.67:21.67</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:10:45</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:45:45</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:10:80</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3:33.3:33.3</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.67:21.67:21.67</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:80:10</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80:10:10</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:10:45</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67:21.67:56.67</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80:10:10</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moisture (g/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.90<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.45<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.40<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.90<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.30<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.90<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.30<sup>b</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude protein (g/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.86<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.52<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.10<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.68<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.34<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.82<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.09<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.15<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.82<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.87<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.34<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.82<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.89<sup>c</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude fat (g/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.02<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.65<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.09<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.84<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.14<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.19<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.08<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.71<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.07<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.96<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.26<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.14<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.03<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.25<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude fiber (g/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51<sup>k</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.46<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total ash (g/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02<sup>e</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbohydrate (g/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.84<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.90<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.46<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.56<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.37<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.68<sup>k</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.53<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.28<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.18<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.94<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.69<sup>m</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.37<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.24<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.67&#x000a0;<sup>l</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total dietary fiber (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.05i</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.33<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.73<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.50<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.63<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.69<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.74<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.44<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.74<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.07<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.61<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.62<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.60<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.60<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total carotenoid (&#x003bc;g/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.00<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.00<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177.00<sup>ef</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.00<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.00<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172.00<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178.00<sup>ef</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195.00<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174.00<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.00<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.00<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.00<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.00<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.00<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mg (mg/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">670.22<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">702.74<sup>k</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">576.54<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">652.74<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">635.49<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">675.63<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">589.68<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">674.53<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">714.31<sup>m</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">700.67<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">710.52&#x000a0;<sup>l</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">684.86<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">657.22<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">735.06<sup>n</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tannin (mg/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.31<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.55<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.86<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.07<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.93<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.02<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.90<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.48<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.99<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.41<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.00<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.19<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.81<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.43<sup>h</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxalate (mg/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.96<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.92<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.91<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.91<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.60<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.96<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.59<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.50<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24<sup>ab</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phytate (mg/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50&#x000a0;<sup>l</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.55<sup>k</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trypsin inhibitor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.00<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.00<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.22<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.50<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.50<sup>h</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Energy (kcal/100&#x000a0;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">439.97<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">439.55<sup>e</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">437.07<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">454.48<sup>i</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">432.12<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">439.73<sup>g</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">437.31<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">439.89<sup>h</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">447.98<sup>k</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">439.71<sup>f</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444.53<sup>j</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">432.12<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">432.52<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444.50<sup>j</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fsn3590-note-0004"><p>Mean values with different superscripts within a row are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05); UBF, unripe cooking banana flour; PPF, pigeon pea flour; SPF, sweet potato flour.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>The fat contents of the biscuit samples were similar to those reported by other researchers (Giwa &#x00026; Ikujenlola, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Silky &#x00026; Tiwari, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) who used composite flours for biscuit manufacture. The fat content of the biscuits did not appear to vary much as the same quantities of fat were added. The variations observed in the fat contents of the biscuit samples, despite the same quantity of fat used in the recipe, may be due to variations in their moisture contents. The fat content of the biscuits was within the standard value (15%&#x02013;20%) for soft dough biscuits (Manley, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). Similar values (15.1%&#x02013;18.1%) were reported by other workers (Asif&#x02010;Ul&#x02010;Alam, Islam, Hoque, &#x00026; Monalis, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Chinma et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Eneche, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>; Silky &#x00026; Tiwari, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) for biscuits prepared from composite flours containing different proportions of UBF, PPF, SPF, millet, wheat, and tigernut.</p><p>Fiber is known to aid the digestive system of humans. It has been reported that UBF, PPF, and SPF are good sources of fiber (Daramola &#x00026; Osanyinlusi, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Tiwari et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), and this could justify the results obtained for the crude fiber and total dietary fiber contents of the biscuits. Similar observation was reported by Silky and Tiwari (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) and Chinma et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). The high ash contents of the biscuit samples attest to the nutritional report that PPF and SPF are good sources of calcium, sodium, magnesium, potassium, and iron (Torres, Frias, Grantito, &#x00026; Vidal&#x02010;Valverde, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). The carbohydrate contents decreased as the percentage of PPF increased but increased as the percentage inclusion of UBF and SPF increased. This observation may be due to the low amount of carbohydrate in PPF and the high sugar content in UBF and SPF (Ayo&#x02010;Omogie &#x00026; Ogunsakin, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Silky &#x00026; Tiwari, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). The two flour samples (UBF and SPF) are considered as starchy foods. The carbohydrate content of the biscuit samples was within the range (54.13%&#x02013;69.02%) reported by Chinma et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) and Tiwari et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>).</p><p>Dietary fiber is the indigestible part of plant material that helps increase roughage and bulk of stool, maintains a healthy intestine, and decreases the time waste material spends in the gastrointestinal tract (AACC, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Potter &#x00026; Hotchkiss, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>). The total dietary fiber content of the biscuits increased as percentage inclusion of UBF and PPF increased. According to Ovando&#x02010;Martinez et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), Trinidad, Mallillin, Loyola, Sagum, and Encabo (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), and Srikaeo, Sukanya, and Sopade (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), unripe banana and legumes such as cowpea and pigeon pea are good sources of dietary fiber (21&#x02013;41&#x000a0;g/100&#x000a0;g sample) and can be used in the preparation of functional foods. The recommended daily intake of dietary fiber for a healthy adult is 20&#x02013;25&#x000a0;g (Dhingra, Michael, Rajput, &#x00026; Patil, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). This implies that all the composite flour blends are good sources of dietary fiber. Food products high in dietary fiber are known as low glycemic index foods and have been shown to reduce postprandial blood glucose and insulin response and improve blood glucose and insulin concentration in subjects with diabetes mellitus (Trinidad et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). The total carotenoids content of the biscuit increased as the percentage of SPF increased in the formulation. Carotenoids are important micronutrients for human health. They function as a precursor of vitamin A. Some beneficial effects include enhancement of the immune system and decreased risk of degenerative diseases such as cancer, cardiovascular disease, age&#x02010;related muscular degeneration, and cataract formation (Kimura &#x00026; Rodriguez&#x02010;Amaya, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>).</p><p>There was a significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05) in the mineral composition of the biscuit samples. However, only magnesium was of significant value in the biscuit samples. The sodium, iron, potassium, and calcium contents of the biscuits ranged, respectively, from 0.019&#x02013;0.02, 0.25&#x02013;0.54, 0.31&#x02013;0.69, 0.06&#x02013;0.13, and 0.01&#x02013;0.03&#x000a0;mg/100&#x000a0;g. The biscuit samples had high content of magnesium as the flour blends are rich sources of magnesium (Anuonye et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Inyang &#x00026; Ekop, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Ohizua et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Magnesium is a cofactor in more than 300 enzyme systems that regulate diverse biochemical reactions in the body, including protein synthesis, muscle and nerve function, blood glucose control, and blood pressure regulation. Magnesium keeps bones strong and heart rhythm steady (Wardlaw &#x00026; Kessel, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). It is worthy of note that the sodium content of biscuits increased as the level of SPF increased, while the potassium content increased as the percentage inclusion level of UBF and SPF increased. The vitamin C content of the biscuit samples ranged from 0.12 to 0.21&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/100&#x000a0;g, maybe as a result of its low level in the flour blends and heat processing (Ahmed, Akter, &#x00026; Eun, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Ohizua et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>).</p><p>Antinutrients are substances that reduce the nutritional values of food by reducing the bioavailability, digestibility, and utilization of nutrients. There was a significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05) in the tannin, oxalate, phytate, and trypsin inhibitor contents of the biscuit samples. Tannins are polyhydric phenols which are present in virtually all parts of plants and have been found to inhibit trypsin, chymotrypsin, amylase, and lipase activities (Inyang &#x00026; Ekop, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). The low tannin content is desirable as tannin forms insoluble complexes with proteins to decrease the digestibility of proteins (Uzeochina, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Tannins can also provoke an astringent reaction in the mouth and decrease palatability of food, cause damage to intestinal tract, and enhance carcinogenesis (Onwuka, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). The low concentration of oxalate obtained in the study may be beneficial to man as low concentration of oxalate has been linked to reduction in blood cholesterol (Kaushal, Kumar, &#x00026; Sharma, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Oxalate is also known to form complexes with most essential trace elements including calcium thereby making them unavailable for enzymatic activities and other metabolic activities (Onwuka, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). The consumption of large dose of oxalic acid causes gastroenteritis, shock, convulsion, and renal damage. The lethal dose of oxalate has been reported to be between 2 and 5&#x000a0;g/kg for man. The biscuit samples are therefore safe, from the standpoint of oxalate level (Eneobong, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). Phytate level, though low, increased as the percentage inclusion of SPF and PPF increased. Pigeon pea and sweet potato are rich in phytate (Tiwari et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). It is known that phytate also forms complexes with protein at low and high pH and causes indigestion of food and flatulence. However, the low quantity of phytate in the biscuit samples should enhance the bioavailability of minerals such as iron, magnesium, and calcium (Anuonye, Onu, Egwin, &#x00026; Adeyemo, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). The recommended limit for phytate is 250&#x02013;500&#x000a0;mg/100&#x000a0;g (Ekop, Obot, &#x00026; Ikpatt, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). Okpala and Okoli (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) reported low phytic acid (0.56 to 0.70&#x000a0;mg/100&#x000a0;g) and tannin (0.36 to 0.51&#x000a0;mg/100&#x000a0;g) levels for cookies produced from pigeon pea, cocoyam, and sorghum flour blends. The trypsin inhibitor level increased as the percentage inclusion of UBF and PPF increased. Pigeon pea and banana are rich in trypsin inhibitors (Tiwari et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). It was generally observed in this study that the antinutritional content of the products was low and within the tolerable levels.</p><p>Energy content is the amount of calorie available from food through oxidation, and it is a function of the total protein, fat, and carbohydrates present in the food. The energy content of the biscuit samples increased as the protein content decreased. This was in conformity with reported trends (Iwe, Van Zauilichem, Ngoddy, &#x00026; Ariahu, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). Biscuits are energy&#x02010;giving foods which are consumed by both young and old (Manley, <xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). The energy content of the biscuit samples was within the range (397&#x02013;457&#x000a0;kcal/g) reported by Chinma et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) and Adeyeye and Akingbala (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0016"><label>3.4</label><title>Sensory properties of biscuit</title><p>The sensory attributes of the biscuit samples are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn3590-tbl-0004" ref-type="table-wrap">4</xref>. The biscuit samples varied significantly (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05) in terms of appearance, color, aroma, mouthfeel, taste, hardness, crunchiness, and overall acceptability. The appearance and color of the biscuit were strongly influenced by the SPF level. Biscuit samples with higher level of SPF had high scores in terms of appearance and color. Mouthfeel and aroma scores were more influenced by the PPF levels than other flours. Taste is an important attribute in acceptance of food product. The taste of the samples increased with the increasing inclusion of SPF. This finding confirms the report by Preedy et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="fsn3590-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) that SPF adds natural sweetness, color, and flavor to processed foods. Among the biscuit samples, biscuit sample produced from 21.67:21.67:56.67 (UBF:PPF:SPF) flour blends had the highest mean score (6.56) for hardness, while the one from 80:10:10 (5.80) had the least mean scores. Biscuit prepared from 21.67:56.67:21.67 (UBF:PPF:SPF) flour blend was least preferred in terms of color, aroma, mouthfeel, taste, and overall acceptability, while the one prepared from 21.67:21.67:56.67 (UBF:PPF:SPF) flour blend was the most preferred in terms of shape, mouthfeel, taste, crunchiness, and overall acceptability.</p><table-wrap id="fsn3590-tbl-0004" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Hedonic scores for the sensory attributes of biscuits produced from flour blends of unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UBF:PPF:SPF blend ratio</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symmetry (shape)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aroma</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouthfeel</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweetness</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hardness</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crunchiness</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall acceptability</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:80:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.63<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.82<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.14<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.80<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.06<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.80<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.41<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:45:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.16<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:10:80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.96<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.92<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.56<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67:56.67:21.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.32<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.68<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.40<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.92<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:10:45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.88<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.64<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:45:45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.92<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.80<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20<sup>ab</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:10:80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.96<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26<sup>abcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.56<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33:33.33:33.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.40<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.40<sup>abcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.96<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.84<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.67:21.67:21.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.12<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.88<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.52<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.92<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24<sup>ab</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:80:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.88<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.16<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.81<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.86<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80:10:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.38<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.22<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.14<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.94<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.58<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45:10:45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.88<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.64<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67:21.67:56.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.08<sup>d</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.56<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.92<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.56<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.04<sup>c</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80:10:10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.38<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32<sup>bcd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.18<sup>bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.16<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.96<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.28<sup>abc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50<sup>cd</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.58<sup>bc</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fsn3590-note-0005"><p>Mean values with different superscripts within a column are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05); UBF, unripe cooking banana flour; PPF, pigeon pea flour; SPF, sweet potato flour.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0017"><label>4</label><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>The physical, chemical, and sensory characteristics of biscuit produced from flour blends of unripe banana, pigeon pea, and sweet potato were studied. The thickness of biscuit samples increased as the level of sweet potato flour and unripe cooking banana flour increased, while the hardness decreased with increase in pigeon pea flour. There was a predominance of redness and yellowness in the biscuit samples. The crude protein, crude fiber, and total ash contents of biscuits increased as the PPF level increased. The biscuit samples had high energy content and were rich in magnesium with favorable Na/K ratio (&#x0003c;1.0) and with antinutritional contents within the tolerable levels.</p></sec><sec id="fsn3590-sec-0018"><title>CONFLICT OF INTERESTS</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="fsn3590-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="fsn3590-cit-0001">
<collab collab-type="authors">AACC</collab>
. (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Definition of dietary fibre: Report of the dietary fibre definition committee, CFW</article-title>. American Association of Cereal Chemist. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://Aaccnet.org/initiatives/definitions/page/dietaryfibre/aspx/">https://Aaccnet.org/initiatives/definitions/page/dietaryfibre/aspx/</ext-link> on June 8, 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Adeyeye</surname>, <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Akingbala</surname>, <given-names>J. O.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Physico&#x02010;chemical and functional properties of cookies produced from sweetpotato&#x02010;maize flour blends</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Science and Quality Management</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>48</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Akter</surname>, <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Eun</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Peeling, drying temperatures and sulphite&#x02010;treatment affect physicochemical properties and nutritional quality of sweet potato flour</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2009.12.015">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2009.12.015</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Ahmed</surname>, <given-names>Z. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hussein</surname>, <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Exploring the suitability of incorporating tiger nut flour as novel ingredient in gluten&#x02010;free biscuit</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Polish Journal of Food and Nutrition Sciences</source>, <volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Anuonye</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jigam</surname>, <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ndaceko</surname>, <given-names>G. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Effects of extrusion&#x02010;cooking on the nutrient and anti&#x02010;nutrient composition of pigeon pea and unripe plantain blends</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Applied Pharmaceutical Science</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>158</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Anuonye</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Onu</surname>, <given-names>J. O.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Egwin</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Adeyemo</surname>, <given-names>S. O.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Nutrient and anti&#x02010;nutrient composition of extruded acha and soybean blend</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Processing and Preservation</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>680</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>691</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0007">
<collab collab-type="authors">AOAC</collab>
(<year>2010</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Official methods of analysis</source>, <edition>25th edn</edition>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association of Official Analytical Chemist</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Asif&#x02010;Ul&#x02010;Alam</surname>, <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Islam</surname>, <given-names>M. Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hoque</surname>, <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Monalis</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Effect of drying on the physicochemical and functional properties of green banana (<italic>Musa sapientum</italic>) flour and development of baked product</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">American Journal of Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.12691/ajfst-2-4-4">https://doi.org/10.12691/ajfst-2-4-4</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Ayo&#x02010;Omogie</surname>, <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ogunsakin</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Assessment of chemical, rheological and sensory properties of fermented maize&#x02010;cardaba&#x02010;banana complementary food</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food and Nutrition Sciences</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>844</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>850</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.4236/fns.2013.48110">https://doi.org/10.4236/fns.2013.48110</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Bala</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gul</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Riar</surname>, <given-names>C. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Functional and sensory properties of cookies prepared from wheat flour supplemented with cassava and water chestnut flours</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Cogent Food and Agriculture</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>1019815</fpage>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/23311932.2015.1019815">https://doi.org/10.1080/23311932.2015.1019815</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Chauhan</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Saxena</surname>, <given-names>D. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Singh</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Physical, textural and sensory characteristics of wheat and amaranth flour blend cookies</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Cogent Food and Agriculture</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1125773</fpage>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/23311932.2015.1125773">https://doi.org/10.1080/23311932.2015.1125773</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Chinma</surname>, <given-names>C. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>James</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Imam</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ocheme</surname>, <given-names>O. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Anuonye</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Yakubu</surname>, <given-names>C. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Physicochemical and sensory properties and in&#x02010;vitro digestibility of biscuits made from blends of tigernut (<italic>Cyperus esculentus</italic>) and pigeon pea (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic>)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Nigerian Journal of Nutritional Sciences</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Daramola</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Osanyinlusi</surname>, <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Production, characterization and application of banana (<italic>Musa</italic> spp) flour in whole maize</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">African Journal of Biotechnology</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>992</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>995</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Dhingra</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Michael</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rajput</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Patil</surname>, <given-names>R. T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Dietary fibre in foods: A review</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>266</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197-011-0365-5">https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197-011-0365-5</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23729846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Ekop</surname>, <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Obot</surname>, <given-names>I. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ikpatt</surname>, <given-names>E. N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Anti&#x02010;nutritional factors and potassium bromate content in bread and flour samples in Uyo metropolis, Nigeria</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">European Journal of Chemistry</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>736</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>741</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1155/2008/530596">https://doi.org/10.1155/2008/530596</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Eneche</surname>, <given-names>E. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Biscuit&#x02010;making potential of millet/pigeon pea flour blends</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Plant Foods for Human Nutrition</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1008031618117">https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1008031618117</ext-link>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10646626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Eneobong</surname>, <given-names>H. N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Eating right (A nutrition guide)</source>. <publisher-loc>Nigeria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zoometer Print Communications Ltd</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Fasoyiro</surname>, <given-names>S. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Arowora</surname>, <given-names>K. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Chemical, pasting and sensory properties of whole fermented maize (ogi) fortified with pigeon pea flour</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Journal of Food, Agriculture and Veterinary and Agricultural Engineering</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Gaines</surname>, <given-names>C. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Collaborative studies on baking quality of cookies flour by wire&#x02010;cut formulation</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Cereal Foods World</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Giwa</surname>, <given-names>E. O.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ikujenlola</surname>, <given-names>A. V.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Quality characteristics of biscuits produced from composite flour of wheat and quality protein maize</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">African Journal of Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>116</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Inyang</surname>, <given-names>U. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ekop</surname>, <given-names>V. O.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Physico&#x02010;chemical properties and anti&#x02010;nutrient contents of unripe banana and African yam bean flour blends</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Journal of Food Sciences and Nutrition</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>554</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.11648/j.ijnfs.20150405.16">https://doi.org/10.11648/j.ijnfs.20150405.16</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Iwe</surname>, <given-names>M. O.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2002</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Handbook of sensory method and analysis</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Enugu, Nigeria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rejoint Communication Service Ltd Uwani</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Iwe</surname>, <given-names>M. O.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Van Zauilichem</surname>, <given-names>D. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ngoddy</surname>, <given-names>P. O.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ariahu</surname>, <given-names>C. C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Residence time distribution in a single screw extruder processing soybean &#x02010; sweet potato mixtures</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Lebensmittel&#x02010;Wissenschaft and Technologie</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1006/fstl.2000.0731">https://doi.org/10.1006/fstl.2000.0731</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Kaushal</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sharma</surname>, <given-names>H. K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Comparative study of physiochemical, functional, anti&#x02010;nutritional and pasting properties of taro, rice flour, pigeon pea flour and their blends</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Kiin&#x02010;Kabari</surname>, <given-names>D. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Giami</surname>, <given-names>S. Y.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Physicochemical properties and <italic>in&#x02010;vitro</italic> protein digestibility of non&#x02010;wheat cookies prepared from plantain flour and bambara groundnut protein concentrate</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Research</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5539/jfr.v4n2p78">https://doi.org/10.5539/jfr.v4n2p78</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Kimura</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Rodriguez&#x02010;Amaya</surname>, <given-names>D. B.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2004</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Harvestplus handbook for carotenoids analysis. 2004</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Food Policy Research Institute</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Mahan</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Escott&#x02010;Stump</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Krause's food and nutrition therapy</source>, <edition>12th edn</edition>
<publisher-loc>Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Saunders Elsevier</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Manley</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Biscuit, cracker and cookie recipes for the food industry</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Woodhead Publishing Limited</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Mridula</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Goyal</surname>, <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bhargar</surname>, <given-names>V. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Manikantan</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Effect of roasting on texture, colour, and acceptability of soybean for making sattu</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">American Journal of Food Technology</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Noorfarahzihah</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sharifudin</surname>, <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mohd&#x02010;Fadzelly</surname>, <given-names>A. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hasmadi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Application of composite flour in development of food products</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Food Research</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2061</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2074</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Ohizua</surname>, <given-names>E. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Adeola</surname>, <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Idowu</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sobukola</surname>, <given-names>O. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Afolabi</surname>, <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ishola</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Oyekale</surname>, <given-names>T. O.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Nutrient composition, functional and pasting properties of unripe cooking banana, pigeon pea and sweetpotato flour blends</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Sciences and Nutrition</source>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>750</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>762</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.455">https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.455</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Okpala</surname>, <given-names>L. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Okoli</surname>, <given-names>E. C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Nutritional evaluation of cookies produced from pigeon pea, cocoyam and sorghum flour blends</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">African Journal of Biotechnology</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>Oluwamukomi</surname>, <given-names>M. O.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Oluwalana</surname>, <given-names>I. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Akinbowale</surname>, <given-names>O. F.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Physicochemical and sensory properties of wheat&#x02010;cassava composite biscuit enriched with soy flour</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">African Journal of Food Science</source>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Onabanjo</surname>, <given-names>O. O.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ighere</surname>, <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Nutritional, functional and sensory properties of biscuit produced from wheat&#x02010;sweetpotato composite</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Technology Research</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<surname>Onwuka</surname>, <given-names>G. I.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Food analysis and instrumentation: Theory and practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Lagos</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Naphtali Prints</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<surname>Ovando&#x02010;Martinez</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>S&#x000e1;yago&#x02010;Ayerdi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Agama&#x02010;Acevedo</surname>, <given-names>E. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Go&#x000f1;i</surname>, <given-names>I. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Bello&#x02010;P&#x000e9;rez</surname>, <given-names>L. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Unripe banana flour as an ingredient to increase the undigestible carbohydrates of pasta</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>113</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>126</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.07.035">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.07.035</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0037">
<string-name>
<surname>Pereira</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Correia</surname>, <given-names>P. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Guine</surname>, <given-names>R. P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Analysis of the physical&#x02010;chemical and sensorial properties of maria type cookies</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Acta Chimica Slovaca</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<surname>Potter</surname>, <given-names>N. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hotchkiss</surname>, <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1995</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Food science</source>, <edition>5th edn</edition>
<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall Inc</publisher-name>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4615-4985-7">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4615-4985-7</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0039">
<string-name>
<surname>Preedy</surname>, <given-names>V. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Watso</surname>, <given-names>R. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Patel</surname>, <given-names>V. B.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Flour and breads and their fortification in health and disease prevention</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0040">
<string-name>
<surname>Pyler</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1982</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Baking science and technology. Miscellaneous flours</source> (pp. <fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>395</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Siebel</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0041">
<string-name>
<surname>Silky</surname>, <given-names>M. P. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Tiwari</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Development of high protein biscuits using pigeon pea broken flour</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Journal of Engineering and Innovative Technology</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0042">
<string-name>
<surname>Srikaeo</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sukanya</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sopade</surname>, <given-names>P. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Physicochemical properties, resistant starch content and enzymatic digestibility of unripe banana, edible canna, taro flours and their rice noodle products</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Journal of Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>2111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2117</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2621.2011.02724.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2621.2011.02724.x</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0043">
<string-name>
<surname>Tiwari</surname>, <given-names>B. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Brennan</surname>, <given-names>C. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jaganmohan</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Surabi</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Alagusundaram</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Utilization of pigeon pea (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> L.) byproducts in biscuit manufacture</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">LWT&#x02010; Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>1533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1537</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2011.01.018">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2011.01.018</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0044">
<string-name>
<surname>Torres</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Frias</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Grantito</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Vidal&#x02010;Valverde</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Germinated <italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> seeds as ingredients in pasta products: Chemical, biological and sensory evaluation</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>101</volume>, <fpage>202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2006.01.018">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2006.01.018</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0045">
<string-name>
<surname>Trinidad</surname>, <given-names>P. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mallillin</surname>, <given-names>A. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Loyola</surname>, <given-names>A. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sagum</surname>, <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Encabo</surname>, <given-names>R. R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The potential health benefits of legumes as a good source of dietary fibre</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">British Journal of Nutrition</source>, <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>574</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn3590-cit-0046">
<string-name>
<surname>Uzeochina</surname>, <given-names>O. B.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of the effect of processing techniques on the nutrient and anti&#x02010;nutrients contents of pigeon pea (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic>) seed flours</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Science</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn3590-bib-0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn3590-cit-0047">
<string-name>
<surname>Wardlaw</surname>, <given-names>G. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Kessel</surname>, <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2002</year>). <source xml:lang="en">Perspective in nutrition</source>, <edition>5th edn</edition>
<publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mcgraw&#x02010;Hill, Boston</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>