<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6136457</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.01217</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>OsCER1</italic> Plays a Pivotal Role in Very-Long-Chain Alkane Biosynthesis and Affects Plastid Development and Programmed Cell Death of Tapetum in Rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Erdong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/493365/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Lingyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/493540/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/493731/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Dagang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/493361/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Zhonghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/482773/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Shaoyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/494535/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Hua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/456429/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/493389/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Cimei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/493370/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Shi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/279063/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Zhenlan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/493366/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Hai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/493362/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Chuxiong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/484908/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory for Conservation and Utilization of Subtropical Agro-Bioresources &#x02013; Key Laboratory of Plant Functional Genomics and Biotechnology of Guangdong Provincial Higher Education Institutions, College of Life Sciences, South China Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Laboratory Center of Basic Biology and Biotechnology, Education Department of Guangdong Province, Zhongkai University of Agriculture and Engineering</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Crop Stress Biology for Arid Areas, College of Agronomy, Northwest A&#x00026;F University</institution>, <addr-line>Yangling</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Biocontrol and Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Plant Resources, School of Life Sciences, Sun Yat-sen University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Zhong-Nan Yang, Shanghai Normal University, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Jie Xu, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, China; Fang Chang, Fudan University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Hai Zhou, <email>hai_zhou127@126.com</email> Chuxiong Zhuang, <email>zhuangcx@scau.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Physiology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1217</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Ni, Zhou, Li, Jiang, Wang, Zheng, Qi, Zhou, Wang, Xiao, Liu, Zhou and Zhuang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ni, Zhou, Li, Jiang, Wang, Zheng, Qi, Zhou, Wang, Xiao, Liu, Zhou and Zhuang</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Cuticle waxes, which are primarily comprised of very-long-chain (VLC) alkanes, play an important role in plant reproductive development. <italic>ECERIFERUM1</italic> (<italic>CER1</italic>) is recognized as the core element for VLC alkane biosynthesis in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>). However, genes involved in the VLC alkane biosynthesis in rice remain unclear, and the alkane-form pathway in rice has still to be further explored. Here, we show that <italic>OsCER1</italic>, a homology of <italic>CER1</italic>, functions in VLC alkanes biosynthesis, which also could regulate anther development and plastids differentiation in rice. <italic>OsCER1</italic> was highly expressed in the tapetum (stage 10) and bicellular pollen cells (stage 11). The decreased content of VLC alkanes (C25 and C27) in the <italic>OsCER1</italic> knocked down plants as well as the increased content of C27 alkanes in the <italic>OsCER1</italic> overexpression plants indicates that <italic>OsCER1</italic> participates in VLC alkane biosynthesis. Downregulation of <italic>OsCER1</italic> in rice led to sterility, and fewer amyloplasts within the mature pollen grains. In addition, the downregulation of <italic>OsCER1</italic> in rice caused delayed tapetal programmed cell death and abnormal development of plastids in the tapetal cells. Furthermore, significantly altered levels of expression of genes involved in the pollen development were exhibited in the <italic>OsCER1</italic> knocked down plants. These results indicate that <italic>OsCER1</italic> is critical for VLC alkanes biosynthesis, plastids differentiation, and pollen development. This work provides insights into the VLC alkanes biosynthesis in anther development in rice.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.</kwd><kwd>male sterility</kwd><kwd>plastid development</kwd><kwd>tapetum degeneration</kwd><kwd>anther cuticle wax</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="9"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="74"/><page-count count="17"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>In flowering plants, successful male reproductive development within the anther includes critical developmental events such as meristem specification, sporogenous cell differentiation, meiosis, and mitosis (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Scott et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Blackmore et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Wilson and Zhang, 2009</xref>). Rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) is one of the most important food crops in the world. Abnormal reproductive development has significantly influenced rice production. Rice anthers have four lobes in which the primordial cells differentiate into reproductive pollen mother cells. Four somatic cell layers surround these cells: the tapetum, the middle layer, the endothecium, and the epidermis, which are arranged from the innermost to the outermost layer (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Goldberger et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Yang, 2014</xref>).</p><p>Covering the epidermal cells, the rice anther has a reticulate cuticle, which plays a protective role in pollen development (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Li and Zhang, 2010</xref>). The anther cuticle is a thin, continuous hydrophobic layer that coats the outermost surface of anthers and is mainly composed of epicuticular waxes and a cutin matrix (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Kunst and Samuels, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Nawrath, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Pollard et al., 2008</xref>). Cuticular waxes are mostly composed of very-long-chain fatty acids (VLCFAs) derivatives, including primary and secondary alcohols, aldehydes, alkanes, ketones, and esters (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Kunst and Samuels, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Buschhaus and Jetter, 2011</xref>). Abnormal cuticular waxes of anthers frequently accompany aborted pollen development (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Jessen et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Leide et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Smirnova et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Haslam et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>The biosynthesis of VLCFAs occurs in two stages. First, <italic>de novo</italic> fatty acids (FAs), such as C16 and C18 FAs, are synthesized in the plastid stroma and are catalyzed by the FA synthase complex using acetyl-CoA as the starting substrate. The majority of long-chain fatty acids (LCFAs) serve as central intermediates in catalytic steps, such as elongation and acyl editing (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Haslam and Kunst, 2013</xref>), and some LCFAs remain in plastids integrated into polar lipids, such as glycolipids and phospholipids (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Li-Beisson et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>The second stage of VLCFA biosynthesis is the elongation of C16 and C18 FAs into VLCFAs consisting of C20 to C34 chains. The synthesis of VLCFAs is catalyzed by fatty acyl-CoA elongase in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Hooker et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Efremova et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bach et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Joubes et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Beaudoin et al., 2009</xref>). Subsequently, extended VLCFAs are modified into diverse VLCFAs derivatives, the main components of wax, via two pathways, namely, the alcohol-forming (acyl reduction) pathway and the alkane-forming (decarbonylation) pathway. The alcohol-forming pathway is involved in the production of very-long-chain (VLC) primary alcohols catalyzed by a fatty acyl-CoA reductase. The alkane-forming pathway yields VLC alkanes, aldehydes, secondary alcohols, and ketones (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Jenks et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Rashotte et al., 2001</xref>). Among these metabolites, VLC alkanes predominate in the wax structure, and account for 50&#x02013;70% of the total wax content in numerous different plants species (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Kunst and Samuels, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Kosma et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Kunst and Samuels, 2009</xref>). The VLC alkanes play critical roles in various plant physiological processes, notably in plant fertility and resistance to drought stress (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Aarts et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Kosma et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bourdenx et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Recently, several genes function in the metabolism of VLCFAs and wax were discovered (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Kunst and Samuels, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Buschhaus and Jetter, 2011</xref>), and several <italic>eceriferum</italic> (<italic>cer</italic>) mutations in Arabidopsis affect wax composition, suggesting that CER proteins play important roles in wax biosynthesis (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Jenks et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Lai et al., 2007</xref>). For instance, CER1 and CER3, which are localized in the ER, may form a complex that catalyzes the synthesis of VLC alkanes from VLC acyl-CoAs via a two-step reaction (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bernard et al., 2012</xref>). The <italic>GLOSSY1 (GL1)</italic> gene in maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>), a homolog of <italic>CER3</italic>, affects the biosynthesis of epicuticular waxes on the surfaces of seedling leaves (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Sturaro et al., 2005</xref>). <italic>CsCER1</italic> and <italic>CsWAX2</italic> in <italic>Cucumis</italic> are involved in the biosynthesis of VLC alkanes and influence pollen fertility (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015a</xref>,<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). It is important to understand the VLC biosynthesis pathway in rice at the molecular level because rice is one of the most important food crops worldwide. Recent studies have reported that <italic>Wax Crystal-Sparse Leaf 2</italic> (<italic>WSL2</italic>), <italic>OsGL1-2, OsGL1-3, Wax-deficient Anther 1</italic> (<italic>WDA1</italic>), and <italic>OsGL1-6</italic> are homologs of <italic>CER</italic> involved in the wax biosynthesis in rice (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Mao et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, the alkane-form pathway in rice still needs to be explored, and whether other unreported <italic>CER</italic> homologs in rice are involved in VLC alkanes biosynthesis remains unclear.</p><p>Plastids where <italic>de novo</italic> fatty acids synthesis occurred play crucial roles in successful anther development. During anther development, proplastids in tapetal cells undergo division during the early stages of microsporogenesis and subsequently develop into elaioplasts that are associated with biosynthesis of the lipids that tapetum cells secrete into the anther locule to contribute to pollen wall formation (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cl&#x000e9;ment and Pacini, 2001</xref>). For instance, No Exine Formation 1 (NEF1) is a plastid integral membrane protein that plays an important role in tapetum degeneration, plastid development, and lipid accumulation, and effects fertility in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ariizumi et al., 2004</xref>). However, whether there are lipid signals from plastids that regulate anther development and how these pathways accomplish this regulatory role remain unclear.</p><p>In this article, we isolated a homologous protein of CER1, OsCER1, and characterized its function in rice. <italic>OsCER1</italic> is preferentially expressed in tapetum cells at stage 10 and in bicellular pollens at stage 11 of anther development. We obtained several independent <italic>OsCER1</italic> downregulated lines, and found that these plants displayed low fertility, including abnormal anther development with smaller and fewer amyloplasts within the mature pollens. We also observed abnormal plastids differentiation in the tapetum. Furthermore, we provide evidence for the pivotal role of <italic>OsCER1</italic> in the biosynthesis of VLC alkanes and in the tapetum degeneration during anther development in rice.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Plant Materials and Growth Conditions</title><p>The rice variety Zhonghua 11 (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. ssp. <italic>japonica</italic> cv. Zhonghua 11) was used for all experiments in this study. The wild-type (WT) and transgenic plants were grown in a paddy field at South China Agricultural University. The developmental stages of the spikelets were determined according to spikelet length and anther morphology as described by <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2011)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic Analysis</title><p>Sequence alignment of OsCER1 and its related proteins from rice and other species was performed using Clustal Omega from EMBL-EBI<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref></sup> to construct a phylogenetic tree, using default parameters. The phylogenetic tree was constructed using the neighbor-joining method as implemented in the MEGA program version 3.0 with 1,000 bootstrap replications<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn02">2</xref></sup>. CER1 and OsCER1 were aligned with ClustalW<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn03">3</xref></sup>, followed by manual alignment in conserved active His-rich motifs.</p></sec><sec><title>Generating <italic>OsCER1</italic> Antisense-RNA and Overexpression Transgenic Plants</title><p>The <italic>OsCER1</italic> antisense transgene driven by the <italic>OsCER1</italic> promoter was constructed as described by <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Li J. et al. (2011)</xref>. A 560-bp fragment of the <italic>OsCER1</italic> cDNA was amplified using reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) from Zhonghua 11 with gene-specific <italic>OsCER1</italic>-A F/R primers (<bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">4</xref></bold>). The PCR product was inserted in reverse orientation into the multiple cloning site of pCAMBIA1380. A 2,036-bp genomic fragment located upstream of the annotated ATG start codon of <italic>OsCER1</italic> was isolated from Zhonghua 11 genomic DNA using <italic>OsCER1</italic>-P F and <italic>OsCER1</italic>-P R primers (<bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">4</xref></bold>) and then inserted upstream of the antisense fragment. A 1,860-bp ORF of <italic>OsCER1</italic> cDNA was amplified using RT-PCR from Zhonghua 11 with gene-specific <italic>OsCER1</italic>-OE F/R primers (<bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">4</xref></bold>) and inserted into the multiple cloning site of pYLpox driven by <italic>Ubi</italic> promoter. Then constructs were transformed into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain EHA105. Transgenic plants were obtained as described by <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Li J. et al. (2011)</xref>. Two homozygous <italic>OsCER1</italic> antisense transgenic (<italic>OsCER1A</italic>) lines, <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1, and two homozygous <italic>OsCER1</italic> overexpression transgenic lines, <italic>OsCER1</italic> overexpression 3 (OV-3) and <italic>OsCER1</italic> overexpression 6 (OV-6) were obtained and used for relevant analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Southern Bolt and Quantitative Reverse Transcription-PCR (qRT-PCR) Analysis</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted with the plant genomic DNA miniprep Kit (Sigma, United States) from the 3&#x02013;5 g mature leaves of WT and the nine <italic>OsCER1</italic> antisense-RNA transgenic lines, respectively. To generate a <italic>Hpt</italic> gene-specific probe for the Southern bolt, a 651-bp <italic>Hpt</italic> fragment was amplified using the <italic>Hpt</italic> F and <italic>Hpt</italic> R primers (<bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">4</xref></bold>) and labeled with a PCR DIG labeling mix (Roche, Diagnostics). The Southern bolt procedures were performed as previously described by <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ariizumi et al. (2004)</xref>. Total RNA was isolated from rice tissues using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, United States), including shoots, roots, and spikelets with anthers at different stages. First-strand cDNA synthesis was performed using a Takara PrimeScript first-strand cDNA synthesis kit (Takara Bio Inc.), and the cDNA was then used for qRT-PCR, which was performed in triplicate using SsoFast EvaGreen Supermix (Bio-Rad, United States). All primers for qRT-PCR are listed in <bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">4</xref></bold>. <italic>OsActin1</italic> was used as reference for normalization of mRNA expression.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA <italic>in situ</italic> Hybridization</title><p>Rice anthers from stages 6 to 11 were collected. To generate gene-specific and control probes, a 613-bp <italic>OsCER1</italic> fragment was amplified using the <italic>OsCER1</italic> HIS F and <italic>OsCER1</italic> HIS R primers (<bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">4</xref></bold>) and inserted into a pEASY-Blunt vector (Transgen, Beijing, China). The probes were transcribed <italic>in vitro</italic> from the T7 promoter using RNA polymerase as provided in the DIG RNA labeling kit (Roche, Indianapolis, IN, United States). The following RNA <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization procedures were performed as previously described by <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Kouchi and Hata (1993)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Terminal Deoxynucleotidyl Transferase-Mediated dUTP Nick-End Labeling (TUNEL) Assay</title><p>For the TUNEL assay, 6-&#x003bc;m sections of anthers were prepared and the following procedures were performed using the TUNEL apoptosis detection kit (DeadEnd Fluorometric TUNEL System, Promega). Slides were stained with propidium iodide (PI). Green GFP signals (excitation wavelength: 488 nm) and the red PI signals (excitation wavelength: 543 nm) were assessed using a confocal laser-scanning microscope (LSM510 Mera; Carl Zeiss).</p></sec><sec><title>Microscopy Analysis</title><p>Anthers from mature flowers were dissected, and pollen grains were stained with iodine/potassium iodide (I<sub>2</sub>/KI) staining (0.2% iodine and 2% potassium iodide) and observed under a brightfield microscope (Zeiss, Axio Observer D1, Germany). To investigate pollen germination <italic>in vitro</italic>, mature pollen grains were germinated on a glass slide at 33&#x000b0;C for 30 min in a pollen germination medium composed of 2.0% (m/v) agar, 30% (m/v) sucrose, 50 mM KNO<sub>3</sub>, 400 mM H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3,</sub> and 400 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>&#x022c5;7H<sub>2</sub>O. The pollen grains were then observed under a brightfield microscope (Zeiss, Axio Observer D1).</p><p>Anthers of the WT and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants at different stages were fixed in 3.7% formaldehyde/acetic acid (v/v) and resin-embedded semi-thin sections (epoxy resin PolyBed 812, Polysciences) were made and observed as described by <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al. (2011)</xref>. For transmission electron microscopy (TEM), anthers were fixed in sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.2) containing 4% (w/v) paraformaldehyde and 2.5% (v/v) glutaraldehyde and sectioned as described by <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Schulz et al. (1993)</xref>. The sections were observed using an electron microscope (TECNAI G2 12, FEI) at 100&#x02013;120 kV. For scanning electron microscopy (SEM), anthers were fixed in sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.2) containing 4% (w/v) paraformaldehyde and 2.5% (v/v) glutaraldehyde. The following SEM procedures were performed as previously described by <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al. (2015)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Subcellular Localization</title><p>The <italic>CaMV35S</italic> promoter, <italic>eGFP</italic> fragments, and <italic>NOS</italic> terminator were successively cloned into pUC18 to construct the <italic>eGFP</italic> transient expression (<italic>GFP</italic>) vectors. The signal peptide fragment of <italic>OsCER1</italic> was amplified using the primer pair <italic>OsCER1-eGFP F, OsCER1-eGFP R</italic> (<bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">4</xref></bold>) and then subcloned into the <italic>GFP</italic> vector between the <italic>CaMV35</italic>S promoter and the <italic>eGFP</italic> gene, in-frame with the N-terminus of <italic>eGFP</italic> being driven by the <italic>CaMV35S</italic> promoter. Protoplasts from the leaf sheaths of 14-day-old rice seedlings were prepared, and transient expression was conducted following the protocol described by <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al. (2015)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>WAX Profiling</title><p>For the anthers wax composition studies, waxes were extracted from 10 to 20 mg of freeze-dried anthers and analyzed as described by <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al. (2015)</xref>. For the leaves wax composition analysis, 20&#x02013;50 mg of freeze-dried flag leaves were harvested in a Teflon-lined screw cap glass tube, extracted, and analyzed following the method of <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al. (2015)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Accession Numbers</title><p>The sequences used in this study were downloaded from GenBank with the following accession numbers: <italic>CER1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="D64155.1">D64155.1</ext-link>), <italic>CER3</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="X95962">X95962</ext-link>), <italic>BnCER1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KF724897.1">KF724897.1</ext-link>), <italic>CsCER1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KJ461885">KJ461885</ext-link>), <italic>CYP704B2</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Os03g07250">Os03g07250</ext-link>), <italic>Defective Pollen Wall</italic> (<italic>DPW</italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="EU971135">EU971135</ext-link>), <italic>GL1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="U37428.1">U37428.1</ext-link>), <italic>Rice ATP binding cassette subfamily G 15/ Post-meiotic deficient anther 1</italic> (<italic>OsABCG15/PDA1</italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Os06g40550">Os06g40550</ext-link>), <italic>OsC</italic>6 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Os11g37280">Os11g37280</ext-link>), <italic>OsNEF1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Os11g32470">Os11g32470</ext-link>), <italic>OsGL1-3</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AK070469">AK070469</ext-link>), <italic>WSL2</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AK060786">AK060786</ext-link>), <italic>OsGL1-2</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AK066569">AK066569</ext-link>), <italic>OsCER1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AK066386">AK066386</ext-link>), <italic>WDA1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AK100751">AK100751</ext-link>), <italic>OsGL1-6</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AK068166">AK068166</ext-link>), Os<italic>RAFTIN1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Os08g38810">Os08g38810</ext-link>), <italic>Tapetum Degeneration Retardation</italic> (<italic>TDR</italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Os02g02820">Os02g02820</ext-link>), and <italic>TDR Interacting Protein 2</italic> (<italic>TIP2</italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Os01g18870">Os01g18870</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title><italic>OsCER1</italic> Is Homologous to <italic>CER1</italic></title><p>Phylogenetic reconstruction indicated that CER1 and other 10 homologous proteins of CER1 could be classified into two clades; CER1 and CER3 belonging to clades I and II, respectively (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref></bold> and <bold>Supplementary Data Set <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">1</xref></bold>). The gene Os02g0621300 located on rice chromosome 2 is a homology of <italic>CER1</italic>, thus we named this gene <italic>OsCER1</italic>. The full-length 2,481-bp cDNA clone of <italic>OsCER1</italic> contains an open reading frame of 1,860 bp in length, which encodes a 619-amino acid protein (XP_015627618.1) with a molecular mass of 71 kD. Putative conserved domains include a fatty acid hydroxylase superfamily domain (amino acids 139&#x02013;253) and a WAX2 C-terminal domain (amino acids 453&#x02013;615) (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Islam et al., 2009</xref>). OsCER1 was grouped into clade I, and shared 57% sequence identity with CER1. Alignment of CER1 and OsCER1 showed that their predicted amino acid sequences contained the same three conserved histidine-rich (His-rich) motifs (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref></bold>) that are likely critical for alkane synthesis function (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bernard et al., 2012</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Phylogenic analysis and sequence alignment of OsCER1. <bold>(A)</bold> Phylogenetic analysis of the OsCER1 protein and 10 OsCER1 related proteins. Bootstrap values are shown on the branches. The scale bar represents the number of amino acid substitutions per site. The value of 0.01 on the scale bar indicates 1 amino acid substitution per 100 residues. The numbers near the branches refer to the bootstrap value of the neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree. The length of the branches is proportional to the amino acid variation rates. <bold>(B)</bold> Sequence alignment between CER1 and OsCER1. Identical and similar residues are shown on black and gray backgrounds, respectively. Green boxes indicate the three conserved active His-rich motifs; asterisks (<sup>&#x02217;</sup>) indicate the identical residues in all sequences, black dots (.) indicate the semi-conserved substitutions, and dashes (&#x02013;) indicate gaps in the alignment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01217-g001"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>OsCER1</italic> Is Mainly Expressed in Tapetum and Microspores</title><p>To further characterize the expression pattern of <italic>OsCER1</italic>, we measured its transcript levels in different tissues by qRT-PCR. In rice, anther development can be divided into 14 stages based on morphological characteristics (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2011</xref>). <italic>OsCER1</italic> was highly expressed in the panicles, particularly in the spikelets within anthers at stages 10 and 11, whereas its expression level was lower in the vegetative organs (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref></bold>). This finding indicates that <italic>OsCER1</italic> might be involved in panicle development in rice. To explore the spatiotemporal expression of <italic>OsCER1</italic> during anther development, RNA <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization of the WT anthers was performed. Rare <italic>OsCER1</italic> signals were detectable in anthers from stages 6 to 9 (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS1">1</xref></bold>), which refer to the stages from microspore mother cells generation to microspores generation. However, strong RNA <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization signals were detected in the tapetum cells with swollen structure at stage 10 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref></bold>). Also, a high <italic>OsCER1</italic> expression level was detected in bicellular pollens undergoing the first mitosis at stage 11 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref></bold>). In the negative control, hybridization with the <italic>OsCER1</italic> sense probe did not generate any detectable signals (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C,E</xref></bold>). These results demonstrate that <italic>OsCER1</italic> is highly expressed in tapetum cells and bicellular pollens of anthers at stages 10 and 11, respectively.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>The expression patterns of <italic>OsCER1</italic>. <bold>(A)</bold> Spatial and temporal expression analysis of <italic>OsCER1</italic> in spikelets at various anther developmental stages by qRT-PCR. S1-3, before stage 3; S4-5, from stages 4 to 5; S6, stage 6; S7, stage 7; S8, stage 8; S9, stage 9; S10, stage 10; S11, stage 11; S12, stage12; S13 stage13. <italic>OsActin1</italic> was used as an internal control. Each reaction had three biological repeats and error bars indicate the standard deviations (SD). <bold>(B&#x02013;E)</bold>
<italic>In situ</italic> hybridization of <italic>OsCER1</italic> in WT anthers. The anthers at stage 10 <bold>(B)</bold> and stage 11 <bold>(D)</bold> hybridized with an <italic>OsCER1</italic> antisense probe. The anthers at stage 10 <bold>(C)</bold> and stage 11 <bold>(E)</bold> hybridized with an <italic>OsCER1</italic> sense probe. Bp, bicellular pollen; Msp, microspore; T, tapetum. Bars = 50 &#x003bc;m in <bold>(B&#x02013;E)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01217-g002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Defects in Anther Development in Plants Expressing an <italic>OsCER1</italic> Antisense Construct</title><p>To analyze the biological function of <italic>OsCER1</italic>, we constructed an <italic>OsCER1</italic> antisense vector containing a gene-specific <italic>OsCER1</italic> fragment driven by the native promoter and transformed this construct into Zhonghua 11 calli (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Hiei et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Li J. et al., 2011</xref>). A total of nine independent <italic>OsCER1A</italic> lines were obtained and identified by Southern blotting (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS2">2</xref></bold>). Furthermore, we obtained two transgenic homozygous lines through genetic screening, lines <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1, which exhibited lower <italic>OsCER1</italic> transcript levels as determined by semi-quantitative RT-PCR (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS3">3</xref></bold>). These two lines were then used in the subsequent experiments, and the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 plants showed the lowest <italic>OsCER1</italic> expression.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of the WT plants and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> lines. <bold>(A&#x02013;C)</bold> Comparison of seed setting rate between the WT <bold>(A)</bold>, <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 <bold>(B)</bold>, and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 <bold>(C)</bold> plants showing low seed setting rate in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants. <bold>(D&#x02013;F)</bold> A WT spikelet <bold>(D)</bold>, an <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 spikelet <bold>(E)</bold>, and an <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 spikelet <bold>(F)</bold> after removing the lemma and palea showing no obvious difference in stamens with each other. <bold>(G)</bold> Mature pollen grains stained with 1% I<sub>2</sub>/KI solution in the WT plants. <bold>(H,I)</bold> Abnormal pollen grains stained with 1% I<sub>2</sub>/KI solution in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 <bold>(H)</bold> and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 <bold>(I)</bold> plants showing lightly stained pollen grains. <bold>(J&#x02013;L)</bold>
<italic>In vitro</italic> pollen germination of the WT <bold>(J)</bold>, <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 <bold>(K)</bold> and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 <bold>(L)</bold> plants. St, stamen. Bars = 10 cm in <bold>(A&#x02013;C)</bold>; 100 &#x003bc;m in <bold>(D&#x02013;F)</bold>; 50 &#x003bc;m in <bold>(G&#x02013;L)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01217-g003"/></fig><p>The plants of <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 at maturity stage were slightly smaller than the WT plants (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS4">4</xref></bold>). The most remarkable feature of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants was the lower seed setting. The seed setting of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 plants only 50.14%, which is lower than that of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 plants (54.79%) and significantly reduced compared to that of the WT plants (94.20%) (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">C</xref></bold> and <bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">1</xref></bold>). The anthers of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 plants also showed a normal stamen morphology (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">F</xref></bold>) and SEM showed slightly higher concentration of wax crystal in the surface of <italic>OsCER1A</italic> anthers and no obvious alteration in <italic>OsCER1A</italic> pollens morphology (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS5">5</xref></bold>). To explore the reason of sterility, we examined pollen viability and pollen tube growth by I<sub>2</sub>/KI staining and <italic>in vitro</italic> germination analysis, respectively. The pollen grains of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 showed lighter staining than that of the WT (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">I</xref></bold>), suggesting lower pollen viability in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants. Additionally, statistical analysis of the <italic>in vitro</italic> germination demonstrated that none of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 pollens were able to germinate normal pollen-tubes compared to the 42.33% normal pollen-tube rate of the WT pollens germination (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3J</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">L</xref></bold>). These results strongly indicate that a decrease in <italic>OsCER1</italic> expression affects pollen fertility and pollen germination.</p><p>To examine defects in anther development in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants, we evaluated transverse semi-thin sections of the WT and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> anthers by light microscopy. At stage 8, the dyad cells underwent normal meiosis and produced tetrads, and tapetum displayed shrunk and vacuolated cytoplasm of the WT anthers (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref></bold>). However, the tetrads became abnormally vacuolated in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4F,K</xref></bold>), and tapetal cells exhibit non-vacuoles of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 anthers (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4F</xref></bold>) and small vacuoles of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4K</xref></bold>). At stage 9, new microspores were generated and released from the tetrads, and the vacuoles in the tapetal cells were reabsorbed and the cytoplasm appeared highly condensed with intense staining of the WT anthers (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref></bold>). In contrast, the thicker tapetum was observed in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers at the same stage (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4G,L</xref></bold>). At stage 10, the microspores exhibited a round-shape within the enlarging vacuoles and the tapetum continued to degenerate, forming swollen and lighter stained tapetal cells in the WT anthers (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref></bold>), whereas darkly stained tapetal cells appeared in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers at this stage (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4H,M</xref></bold>). At stage 11, the microspores underwent the first mitosis, and the tapetal layer continued to degenerate and formed large, clear vacuoles in the WT anthers (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref></bold>); the small vacuoles could be observed in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 tapetal cells (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4N</xref></bold>), whereas the tapetal cells still showed intense staining cytoplasm in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 anthers (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4I</xref></bold>). Subsequently, the mature pollen grains of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 plants were abnormally deeply stained compared with that of the WT plants (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4E,J,O</xref></bold>). These results suggest that the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants underwent abnormal tapetum and pollen development.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of transverse semi-thin sections of anthers from the WT plants and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> lines. <bold>(A&#x02013;E)</bold> Transverse semi-thin sections of a single locule of the WT anthers at stage 8b (S8b) <bold>(A)</bold>, stage 9 (S9) <bold>(B)</bold>, stage 10 (S10) <bold>(C)</bold>, stage 11 (S11) <bold>(D)</bold>, and stage 12 (S12) <bold>(E)</bold>. <bold>(F&#x02013;J)</bold> Transverse semi-thin sections of a single locule of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 anthers at S8b <bold>(F)</bold>, S9 <bold>(G)</bold>, S10 <bold>(H)</bold>, S11 <bold>(I)</bold>, and S12 <bold>(J)</bold>. <bold>(K&#x02013;O)</bold> Transverse semi-thin sections of a single locule of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers at S8b <bold>(K)</bold>, S9 <bold>(L)</bold>, S10 <bold>(M)</bold>, S11 <bold>(N)</bold>, and S12 <bold>(O)</bold>. Bp, bicellular pollen; E, epidermis; En, endothecium; ML, middle layer; MP, mature pollen; Msp, microspore; T, tapetum; Tds, tetrads. Bars = 20 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01217-g004"/></fig><p>To further characterize the details of the defect in the tapetal cells of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants, the ultra-structural features of the tapetal cells were assessed by TEM. From stages 8b to 11, the tapetum of the WT plants showed signs of degeneration (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">D</xref></bold>). In contrast, the tapetal cells of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 plants showed the state of condensed cytoplasm had been maintained from stages 8b to 11 (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">L</xref></bold>). In particular, at stage 11, obviously large vacuoles and fragmented cytoplasm were observed in the tapetal cells of the WT anthers (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref></bold>). A densely stained cytoplasm full of the whole tapetal cells and a dense cytoplasm with small vacuoles within tapetal cells were observed in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 plants, respectively (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5H,L</xref></bold>). These findings suggest that the tapetal cells of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants underwent abnormal degeneration compared to that in the WT plants.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of transmission electron microscopy (TEM) of anthers from the WT plants and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> lines. <bold>(A&#x02013;D</bold>) TEM analysis of the WT anthers at stage 8b (S8b) <bold>(A)</bold>, stage 9 (S9) <bold>(B)</bold>, stage 10 (S10) <bold>(C)</bold>, and stage 11 (S11) <bold>(D)</bold>. <bold>(E&#x02013;H)</bold> TEM analysis of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 anthers at S8b <bold>(E)</bold>, S9 <bold>(F)</bold>, S10 <bold>(G)</bold>, and S11 <bold>(H)</bold>. <bold>(I&#x02013;L)</bold> TEM analysis of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers at S8b <bold>(I)</bold>, S9 <bold>(J)</bold>, S10 <bold>(K)</bold>, and S11 <bold>(L)</bold>. Bp, bicellular pollen; En, endothecium; ML, middle layer; Msp, microspore; Ne, nucleus; T, tapetum; Tds, tetrads. Bars = 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01217-g005"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Delayed Programmed Cell Death (PCD) in Tapetum of <italic>OsCER1A</italic> Plants</title><p>In rice, PCD is necessary for anther development, and abnormal PCD in tapetal cells may cause male sterility (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Parish and Li, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2012</xref>). The hallmarks of PCD include DNA fragmentation, mitochondrial, and cytoskeletal disintegration, cellular condensation, and nuclear condensation (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Parish and Li, 2010</xref>). The above TEM observations in the tapetum indicate that the tapetum degeneration in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants was affected during anther development. To determine the effect of <italic>OsCER1</italic> downregulation on tapetum degeneration and PCD during anther development, we examined DNA fragmentation of the WT, <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 tapetum using the TUNEL assay. In the WT tapetal cells, TUNEL-positive signals were first detected at stage 8a (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A,B</xref></bold>), and the signals were strongest at stage 8b (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref></bold>). Subsequently, the signals in the tapetal cells gradually weakened from stage 9 to stage 10 in the WT tapetal cells (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D,E</xref></bold>). However, in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants, no TUNEL signals were observed in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 tapetal cells at stages 7 (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6F,K</xref></bold>) and 8a (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6G,L</xref></bold>). At stage 8b, no apoptotic characteristics were detected in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 tapetal cells (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6H</xref></bold>), and weakly TUNEL signals were detected in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 tapetal cells (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6M</xref></bold>). Stronger but fewer TUNEL-positive signals and several intense TUNEL-positive signals were observed in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 tapetal cells at stage 9, respectively (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6I,N</xref></bold>). Until stage 10, signals in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 tapetal cells remained distinct (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6J,O</xref></bold>). These results suggest the initiation of tapetal PCD in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 tapetum was delayed from stage 8a to stage 9 and stage 8b, respectively. These results suggest that the abnormal non-vacuolization in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> tapetum during stage 8b was coupled with delayed tapetal PCD may result in male sterility.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p>Programmed cell death (PCD) defects in the tapetal cells of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> lines. <bold>(A&#x02013;E)</bold> TUNEL assay of the WT anthers at stage 7 (S7) <bold>(A)</bold>, stage 8a (S8a) <bold>(B)</bold>, stage 8b (S8b) <bold>(C)</bold>, stage 9 (S9) <bold>(D)</bold>, and stage 10 (S10) <bold>(E)</bold>. <bold>(F&#x02013;J)</bold> TUNEL assay of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 anthers at S7 <bold>(F)</bold>, S8a <bold>(G)</bold>, S8b <bold>(H)</bold>, S9 <bold>(I)</bold>, and S10 <bold>(J)</bold>. <bold>(K&#x02013;O)</bold> TUNEL assay of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers at S7 <bold>(K)</bold>, S8a <bold>(L)</bold>, S8b <bold>(M)</bold>, S9 <bold>(N)</bold>, and S10 <bold>(O)</bold>. The red fluorescence showed tissues stained with propidium iodide and the yellow fluorescence showed TUNEL-positive nuclei. Bp, bicellular pollen; Dy, dyad cell; E, epidermis; En, endothecium; MC, meiotic cell; ML, middle layer; Msp, microspore; Tds, tetrads; T, tapetum. Bars = 50 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01217-g006"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Defects in Plastids During Anther Development in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> Plants</title><p>Abnormal tapetal elaioplasts were also detected in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants at stage 11 (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5H,L</xref></bold>). TEM was used to observe tapetal cells and pollens at higher magnification, which exhibited significant differences in plastid structure in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> anthers relative to that in the WT anthers (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref></bold>). The proplastids in the WT tapetal cells at stage 10 were beginning to develop into larger elaioplasts (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref></bold>). In contrast, in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 tapetal cells the plastids were observed without elaioplast-like shape at this stage (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B,C</xref></bold>). At stage 11 in the WT anthers, the tapetal cells had generated into cellular debris and contained the large completely differentiated elaioplasts (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7D</xref></bold>). However, at this stage the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 tapetal cells remained filled with cytoplasm including plastids that lacked a distinct boundary and a typical elaioplast structure, and in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 plants, tapetal cytoplasm was still dense including elaioplasts with abnormal structure (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7E,F</xref></bold>). In the WT plants, mature pollens were filled with amyloplasts that differentiated from proplastids (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7G</xref></bold>). In contrast, in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 plants, fewer amyloplasts were observed within the mature pollen grains and most of them exhibited abnormal morphology (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7H,I</xref></bold>). Taken together, these results suggest that the downregulation of <italic>OsCER1</italic> disrupts the development of elaioplasts and amyloplasts within tapetal cells and in microspores, respectively.</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>FIGURE 7</label><caption><p>TEM of tapetum cells at stage 10 (S10), at stage 11 (S11) and mature pollen (MP) in the WT plants and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> lines. <bold>(A&#x02013;C)</bold> Tapetal regions at S10 of the WT <bold>(A)</bold>, <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 <bold>(B)</bold>, and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 <bold>(C)</bold> plants. <bold>(D&#x02013;F)</bold> Tapetum regions at S11 of the WT <bold>(D)</bold>, <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 <bold>(E)</bold>, and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 <bold>(F)</bold> plants. <bold>(G&#x02013;I)</bold> Pollen cross sections of the WT <bold>(G)</bold>, <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 <bold>(H)</bold>, and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 <bold>(I)</bold> plants. Amy, amyloplast; Ela, elaioplast; Pl, plastid; T, tapetum. Bars = 2 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01217-g007"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>OsCER1</italic> Is Involved in VLC Alkanes Biosynthesis</title><p>In Arabidopsis, CER1 is involved in VLC alkanes biosynthesis (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bourdenx et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bernard et al., 2012</xref>). Our bioinformatics analysis showed that <italic>OsCER1</italic> possesses three conserved His-rich motifs and shares high sequence identity with CER1. The subcellular localization of the signal peptide of OsCER1 showed that the ER localization of the GFP fusion protein was detected by the co-localization of GFP fluorescence and KDEL-MCherry (ER marker) fluorescence (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS6">6</xref></bold>) (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2015</xref>), which indicating that OsCER1 was localized in the ER. These results suggest that <italic>OsCER1</italic> may also be involved in the biosynthesis of VLC alkanes in rice. To investigate the alteration of wax profiles in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> anthers, we measured the composition of chloroform-extractable cuticular wax in the mature anthers using gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS). In the WT anthers, total wax content of dry, mature anthers was 999.63 &#x003bc;g/g, whereas in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> lines, total wax increased by 16.2% to 1,161.64 &#x003bc;g/g in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 anthers and by 13.6% to 1135.81 &#x003bc;g/g in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers (<bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>). Compared to the WT anthers, the alkene content in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers was increased by 34.54% and by 43.18%, respectively (<bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>). The primary alcohol content was increased by 813.62% and by 218.41% in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers, respectively (<bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>). However, alkane content decreased by 13.55% and 6.67% in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers, respectively (<bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>). A significant reduction of alkanes C25 (45.26% and 21.27%) and C27 (35.46% and 12.38%) and a dramatic increase in corresponding primary alcohols C26 (573.26% and 146.1%) and C28 (2,494.40% and 477.79%) were detected in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 anthers, respectively (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref></bold> and <bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">2</xref></bold>). These results indicate that <italic>OsCER1</italic> may function in alkane biosynthesis.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Epicuticular wax composition of anthers from WT and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> lines.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wax</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild-type (&#x003bc;g/g)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 (&#x003bc;g/g)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 (&#x003bc;g/g)</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#x000b1;<italic>SD</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#x000b1;<italic>SD</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#x000b1;<italic>SD</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatty acids</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.34 &#x000b1; 3.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.44 &#x000b1; 2.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113.42 &#x000b1; 0.10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary alcohols</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.90 &#x000b1; 0.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.04 &#x000b1; 0.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.97 &#x000b1; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aldehydes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56 &#x000b1; 0.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19 &#x000b1; 0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkanes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413.95 &#x000b1; 14.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">357.84 &#x000b1; 0.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386.32 &#x000b1; 0.31</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkenes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">420.01 &#x000b1; 14.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">565.10 &#x000b1; 4.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">563.57 &#x000b1; 0.49</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stigmasterol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.33 &#x000b1; 5.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.66 &#x000b1; 2.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.33 &#x000b1; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total wax</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">999.63 &#x000b1; 34.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1161.64 &#x000b1; 5.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1135.81 &#x000b1; 1.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>FIGURE 8</label><caption><p>Analysis of wax constituents. <bold>(A)</bold> Wax constituents in whole anthers at stage 12 in the WT (Black bars), <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 (slightly gray bars) and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 (darkly gray bars) plants. <bold>(B)</bold> Wax constituents in leaves in the WT (black bars), <italic>OsCER1</italic> overexpression 3 (OV-3) (slight gray bars) and <italic>OsCER1</italic> overexpression 6 (OV-6) (darkly gray bars) plants. Error bars indicate SD (<italic>n</italic> = 5). Statistical significance of differences between WT and transgenic plants means is indicated by <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 and <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01217-g008"/></fig><p>To confirm whether <italic>OsCER1</italic> is involved in VLC alkanes biosynthesis, we obtained 2 homozygous <italic>OsCER1</italic> overexpression lines, OV-3 and OV-6, which exhibited higher <italic>OsCER1</italic> transcript levels, as determined by qRT-PCR (<bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS7">7</xref></bold>). These two lines were then used in the subsequent wax composition analysis, and the <italic>OsCER1</italic> expression of OV-3 exhibited higher than that of OV-6. To avoid the effect of native <italic>OsCER1</italic>, we selected leaves that showed minimal native <italic>OsCER1</italic> expression for wax composition analysis. Compared to the WT leaves, the C27, C29, C31, C33 VLC alkanes increased in the OV-3 leaves, and C27 alkanes were increased in the OV-6 leaves (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref></bold>). The C27 alkanes were showed a significant increase (24.71% and 16.77%) in the OV-3 and OV-6 leaves, respectively (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref></bold> and <bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">3</xref></bold>). We also detected a significant reduction of the corresponding fatty acid C28 (34.17% and 51.54%) in the OV-3 and OV-6 leaves, respectively (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref></bold> and <bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">3</xref></bold>). The reduction in the content of VLC alkanes of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants and the increase in the content of VLC alkanes of <italic>OsCER1</italic> overexpression plants suggest that <italic>OsCER1</italic> functions in VLC alkanes biosynthesis.</p></sec><sec><title>Altered Gene Expression Affects Lipid Metabolism and Tapetum Development in <italic>OsCER1A</italic> Plants</title><p>The reduced fertility and altered lipid profiles of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants implied that some genes that were critical for anther development and lipid metabolism might be affected. Therefore, we used qRT-PCR to examine five genes involved in lipid metabolism and anther development, namely, <italic>WDA1</italic> (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Islam et al., 2009</xref>), <italic>OsABCG15/PDA1</italic> (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2013</xref>), <italic>OsC6</italic> (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2010</xref>), <italic>OsRAFTIN1</italic> (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2003</xref>), and <italic>CYP704B2</italic> (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2010</xref>) in the WT, <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6, and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 spikelets with anthers from stages 6 to 10. Among these genes, OsCER1 showed 63% identity with WDA1, which also belonged to the clade I (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref></bold>) in rice. The expression level of <italic>WDA1</italic>, which is essential for anther wall and pollen development, significantly increased in <italic>OsCER1A</italic> spikelets with anthers at stage 7 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref></bold>). An increase in the expression of <italic>OsABCG15/PDA1</italic>, which encodes a lipid-soluble precursor transporter, was observed at stage 9 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9B</xref></bold>), whereas an upregulation of <italic>OsC6</italic>, which is required for transport of lipophilic materials, was detected at stage 10 in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9C</xref></bold>). <italic>CYP7042B2</italic> and <italic>OsRAFTIN1</italic> are important for exine formation during pollen development. The expression pattern of <italic>CYP704B2</italic> was similar to that of WT plants from stages 6 to 8, but at stages 9 and 10, the expression levels of <italic>CYP704B2</italic> significantly decreased (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9D</xref></bold>). <italic>OsRAFTIN1</italic> expression increased at stages 9 and 10 in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9E</xref></bold>).</p><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>FIGURE 9</label><caption><p>Expression analysis of genes related to lipid metabolism and pollen wall biosynthesis in the WT and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> lines by qRT-PCR. <bold>(A&#x02013;I)</bold> Expression analysis of <italic>WDA1</italic>
<bold>(A)</bold>, <italic>OsABCG15/PDA1</italic>
<bold>(B)</bold>, <italic>OsC6</italic>
<bold>(C)</bold>, <italic>CYP704B2</italic>
<bold>(D)</bold>, <italic>OsRAFTIN1</italic>
<bold>(E)</bold>, <italic>TIP2</italic>
<bold>(F)</bold>, <italic>TDR</italic>
<bold>(G)</bold>, <italic>DPW</italic>
<bold>(H)</bold>, and <italic>OsNEF1</italic>
<bold>(I)</bold> in the WT, <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1 plants with anthers from stages 6 to 10. <italic>OsActin1</italic> was used as a control. Black bars represent the WT plants. Slightly gray bars represent the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 3-6 plants. Darkly gray bars represent the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> 9-1. Each reaction had three biological repeats. Error bars indicate SD (<italic>n</italic> = 4). Gene names are abbreviated as follows: <italic>DPW, Defective Pollen Wall</italic>; <italic>OsABCG15/PDA1, Rice ATP binding cassette subfamily G 15/ Post-meiotic deficient anther 1</italic>; <italic>OsNEF1, Rice No Exine Formation 1</italic>; <italic>TDR, Tapetum Degeneration Retardation</italic>; <italic>TIP2, TDR Interacting Protein 2</italic>; <italic>WDA1, Wax-deficient Anther 1</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01217-g009"/></fig><p>The abnormal differentiation of tapetal cells in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants implied that some genes critical for tapetum degeneration could be affected. We analyzed two basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) transcription factor genes, <italic>TIP2</italic> and <italic>TDR</italic> (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Yi et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Fu et al., 2014</xref>). <italic>TIP2</italic> functions in tapetum differentiation during early anther development, and <italic>TIP2</italic> transcript levels significantly decreased from stage 6 to stage 10 in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9F</xref></bold>). <italic>TDR</italic> functions downstream of <italic>TIP2</italic>, and unexpectedly, <italic>TDR</italic> transcript levels significantly increased from stages 7 to 8 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9G</xref></bold>). These results suggest that <italic>OsCER1</italic> is involved in the regulation of tapetum development probably not via the TIP2-TDR pathway.</p><p>Because plastids development in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants was blocked, we analyzed two plastidial genes, <italic>DPW</italic> and <italic>OsNEF1.</italic> DPW is a plastid-localized fatty acid reductase that is involved in primary fatty alcohol synthesis and pollen wall formation (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2011</xref>). The expression of <italic>DPW</italic> started to decrease at stage 9 in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants, suggesting that <italic>DPW</italic> is affected by the downregulation of <italic>OsCER1</italic> (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9H</xref></bold>). <italic>OsNEF1</italic> shares high identity (up to 60%) with Arabidopsis <italic>NEF1</italic>, which encodes a regulator of primexine formation that is localized in plastids (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ariizumi et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2011</xref>). The expression level of <italic>OsNEF1</italic> significantly decreased at stages 6, 7, and 8 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9I</xref></bold>), indicating that the downregulation of <italic>OsCER1</italic> also results in a decrease in <italic>OsNEF1</italic> expression.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title><italic>OsCER1</italic> Is Associated With VLC Alkanes Biosynthesis</title><p>Cuticular wax coats the surface of anthers, and the disruption of anther wax synthesis is frequently accompanied by abnormal pollen development (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Jessen et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Leide et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Smirnova et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Haslam et al., 2015</xref>). VLC alkanes and other VLCFA derivatives are produced via the alkane-formation pathway (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Greer et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bernard et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015b</xref>). There was strong evidence for the involvement of Arabidopsis CER1 in VLC alkanes biosynthesis (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Aarts et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bourdenx et al., 2011</xref>). Arabidopsis CER1 contains three His-rich motifs (HX<sub>3</sub>H, HX<sub>2</sub>HH, and HX<sub>2</sub>HH, in which X stands for any amino acid) that are critical for its function in alkane synthesis (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Aarts et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Shanklin and Cahoon, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bourdenx et al., 2011</xref>). CsCER1, a CER1 homolog in cucumber sharing 61% identity with CER1, also contains three His-rich motifs (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015b</xref>). Overexpression of <italic>CsCER1</italic> resulted in significant changes in VLC alkanes production, indicating that <italic>CsCER1</italic> also plays a role in VLC alkanes biosynthesis (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015b</xref>). However, genes involved in VLC alkane forming have not been reported in rice, and the VLC alkanes biosynthesis pathway has not been elucidated. The present study determined that full-length OsCER1 shares 57% sequence identity with CER1; OsCER1 also contains the three conserved His-rich motifs. Furthermore, the proportion of C25 and C27 alkanes decreased in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants. Accordingly, the concentration of C27 alkanes increased in the <italic>OsCER1</italic> overexpression plants. These results suggest that the synthesis of some species of VLC alkanes decreased when <italic>OsCER1</italic> was knocked down, and increased when <italic>OsCER1</italic> was overexpressed. Based on these findings, we suggest that <italic>OsCER1</italic> is involved in VLC alkanes biosynthesis and may be mainly involved in C27 alkanes in rice.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>OsCER1</italic> Is Involved in a Distinctive Wax Synthesis Pathway</title><p>In the present study <italic>OsCER1</italic> deficiency was also associated with an increase in the concentration of total waxes, alkenes, and primary alcohols, and with a decrease in the concentration of alkanes. Mutants of genes homologous to <italic>OsCER1</italic> in rice, including <italic>WSL2, OsGL1-2, OsGL1-3, WDA1</italic>, and <italic>OsGL1-6</italic>, exhibited decreased total waxes, alkenes, primary alcohols, and alkanes (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Mao et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Among these genes, WDA1 is sharing the highest identity (to 63%) with OsCER1. <italic>WDA1</italic> is involved in wax synthesis and pollen development in rice, and loss-of-function mutant <italic>wda1</italic> exhibits significant reduction in the contents of all wax components (fatty acids, alcohols, alkanes, and alkene) (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2006</xref>). However, in our <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants, only the contents of C25 and C27 alkane significantly decreased, whereas contents of C31 and C33 alkanes markedly increased. There is a possibility that the antisense construct intended for non-specifically targets <italic>OsCER1</italic> and <italic>WDA1</italic>. If this were the case, then the decrease in VLC alkane content in <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants could be an indirect effect of double knockdown of <italic>OsCER1</italic> and <italic>WDA1</italic>. To exclude such a possibility, qRT-PCR was performed using the spikelets with anthers from stages 6 to 10 of the WT and <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants. A significant increase in the expression of <italic>WDA1</italic> was observed at stage 7, whereas no distinct changes were observed at other anther development stages (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref></bold>). These findings suggest that <italic>OsCER1</italic> may participate in a different wax synthesis pathway other than <italic>WDA1</italic> and other reported homologies in rice.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>OsCER1</italic> Is Required for Plastid Development in Anthers</title><p>Plastids play crucial roles for successful anther development in angiosperms with different morphologies at different developmental stages. In rice tapetum plastids begin as proplastids and differentiate into elaioplasts, which are involved in the biosynthesis of tapetal lipids; in turn, these contribute to lipidic pollen wall formation (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000e9;vesque-Lemay et al., 2016</xref>). Amyloplasts are terminally differentiated plastids that serve as sites for starch synthesis and storage in mature pollen grains (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Matsushima et al., 2014</xref>). However, the mechanisms of plastid development during anther development are not well understood. In the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants, we observed abnormal plastids differentiation and alterations in the structure of the plastid in tapetal cells. These results reveal that decreased <italic>OsCER1</italic> could affect plastid development. Furthermore, a significant decrease in the number of amyloplasts was observed in mature pollen grains of the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants. A recent study showed that VLCFAs play an essential role in plastid division, and reduced levels of VLCFAs lead to a decrease in the number of plastids (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Nobusawa and Umeda, 2012</xref>). Wax analysis showed that <italic>OsCER1</italic> knockdown plants disrupt the homeostasis of VLCFAs and their derivatives, which in turn could cause alterations in plastid division and development, thereby affecting the quantity of amyloplasts in mature pollens, which in turn influences pollen viability.</p></sec><sec><title>Plastid Functions in Anther Development</title><p><italic>De novo</italic> FA synthesis occurs in plastids, and lipid metabolism also affects plastid development. Furthermore, plastid-related lipid metabolism in the tapetum can influence anther development through aliphatic compound synthesis and secretion. In Arabidopsis, fatty acid export 1 (FAX1) has been localized to the inner envelope of chloroplasts and is involved in the transport of plastid fatty acids; in addition, <italic>fax1</italic> mutants produced shorter siliques containing almost no seeds (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2015</xref>). In <italic>Brassica napus</italic>, Tic40 is a membrane-anchored co-chaperone homolog localized in the inner membrane of chloroplast that is mainly expressed in tapetum cells and microsporocytes. The <italic>tic40</italic> mutant exhibits delayed tapetum PCD and abnormal tapetal cell expansion and division (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dun et al., 2011</xref>). Plastid genes could also affect anther development through sugar signaling, such as glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPCp) was localized in plastid, and <italic>gapcp1gapcp2</italic> double mutant displayed the sterility in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Mu&#x000f1;oz-Bertomeu et al., 2010</xref>). However, the role of plastids in anther development remains elusive.</p><p>Tapetum PCD is a precise, genetically controlled cellular process that is regulated by several transcription factors. For instance, the altered expression of some bHLH transcription factors strongly influences tapetum PCD in rice; these bHLH transcription factors include <italic>Undeveloped Tapetum 1</italic> (<italic>UDT1/bHLH164</italic>), <italic>TDR1, TIP2</italic>, and <italic>Eternal Tapetum 1</italic> (<italic>EAT1</italic>/<italic>DTD1</italic>/<italic>bHLH141</italic>) (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Ji et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Niu et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Fu et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ko et al., 2014</xref>). In rice, several other genes independent of the ROS and bHLH pathways also regulate tapetum PCD, including <italic>Persistent Tapetal Cell 1</italic> (<italic>PTC1</italic>), <italic>Apoptosis inhibitor 5</italic> (<italic>API5</italic>), and <italic>Microspore and Tapetum Regulator1</italic> (<italic>MTR1</italic>) (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Li H. et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Li X. et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2015</xref>). In addition to the PCD-related genes, various other genes are involved in tapetum development and degeneration in rice such as <italic>Histone Monoubiquitination</italic> (<italic>OsHUB1</italic>/<italic>OsHUB2</italic>), <italic>Defective Tapetum and Meiocytes 1</italic> (<italic>DTM1</italic>), and <italic>Anther Development F-box</italic> (<italic>ADF</italic>) (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Aarts et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Yi et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2015</xref>). These genes form an extensive network that controls tapetum differentiation and PCD. The present studies had shown a delayed tapetum degeneration with a downregulation of <italic>TIP2</italic> but an upregulation of <italic>TDR</italic> in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants. However, our results showed the opposite alterations in the primary alcohols and alkenes in <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants compared to <italic>tdr</italic> mutants (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2006</xref>). These findings suggest that delayed tapetum degeneration in <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants may not via the TIP2-TDR pathway. However, whether plastids are involved in the delayed tapetum degeneration in <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants and the potential roles of plastids in the regulation of tapetum PCD remain elusive.</p><p>In the present study, the reduced fertility <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants exhibited abnormal plastid development, and delayed tapetum PCD during anther development. Alterations in the expression levels of genes involved in lipid metabolism, and plastidial genes were observed in the <italic>OsCER1A</italic> plants. This suggests that OsCER1, a protein involved in VLC alkanes biosynthesis, possibly generates some lipidic signals that impact genes involved in plastids development and tapetum PCD then affects anther development in rice.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>CZ and HZ designed the project and wrote the manuscript. EN, LZ, JL, DJ, ZW, SZ, HQ, YZ, CW, SX, and ZL performed the experiments and analyzed the data.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by grants from the National Basic Research Program of China (2016YFD0100405, 2013CB126905, and 2013CBA01401), Genetically Modified Breeding Major Projects (2016ZX08001-004-001-003), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31371225 and 31571255), and the Scientific Research Project of Guangzhou City (201504010004).</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn02"><label>2</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.megasoftware.net/index.html">http://www.megasoftware.net/index.html</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn03"><label>3</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/tools/clustalw/">http://www.genome.jp/tools/clustalw/</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01217/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01217/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS1"><media xlink:href="Table_1.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS1"><media xlink:href="Image_1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS2"><media xlink:href="Image_2.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS3"><media xlink:href="Image_3.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS4"><media xlink:href="Image_4.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS5"><media xlink:href="Image_5.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS6"><media xlink:href="Image_6.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS7"><media xlink:href="Image_7.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aarts</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keijzer</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiekema</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Molecular characterization of the CER1 gene of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> involved in epicuticular wax biosynthesis and pollen fertility.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>2115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2127</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.7.12.2115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8718622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ariizumi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinata</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inatsugi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Disruption of the novel plant protein NEF1 affects lipid accumulation in the plastids of the tapetum and exine formation of pollen resulting in male sterility in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02118.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15225283</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaelson</surname><given-names>L. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellec</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gissot</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The very-long-chain hydroxy fatty acyl-CoA dehydratase PASTICCINO2 is essential and limiting for plant development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>105</volume>
<fpage>14727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14731</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0805089105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18799749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaudoin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Markham</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Functional characterization of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> &#x003b2;-ketoacyl-coenzyme a reductase candidates of the fatty acid elongase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>150</volume>
<fpage>1174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.137497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Domergue</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jetter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renne</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Reconstitution of plant alkane biosynthesis in yeast demonstrates that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ECERIFERUM1 and ECERIFERUM3 are core components of a very-long-chain alkane synthesis complex.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>3106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3118</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.099796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22773744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blackmore</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortley</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skvarla</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Pollen wall development in flowering plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>174</volume>
<fpage>483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>498</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02060.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17447905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourdenx</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Domergue</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000e9;ger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roby</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Overexpression of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ECERIFERUM1 promotes wax very-long-chain alkane biosynthesis and influences plant response to biotic and abiotic stresses.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>156</volume>
<fpage>1532</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2548</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.172320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buschhaus</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jetter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Composition differences between epicuticular and intracuticular wax substructures: how do plants seal their epidermal surfaces?</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>853</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21193581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Histone H2B Monoubiquitination Mediated by HISTONE MONOUBIQUITINATION1 and HISTONE MONOUBIQUITINATION2 is involved in anther development by regulating tapetum degradation-related genes in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>168</volume>
<fpage>1389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1405</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.256578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26143250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cl&#x000e9;ment</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacini</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Anther plastids in angiosperms.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bot. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02857849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dun</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>BnaC.T<italic>ic</italic>40 a plastid inner membrane translocon originating from <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> is essential for tapetal function and microspore development in <italic>Brassica napus</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>532</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>545</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04708.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21756273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Efremova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heidmann</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellesen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Functional conservation and maintenance of expression pattern of FIDDLEHEAD-like genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and <italic>Antirrhinum</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>837</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-004-5576-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15803418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The rice basic helix-loop-helix transcription factor TDR INTERACTING PROTEIN2 is a central switch in early anther development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>1512</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1524</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.123745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24755456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldberger</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Damle</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadish</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Effect of increased drive-train stimulus intensity on dispersion of ventricular refractoriness.</article-title>
<source><italic>Circulation</italic></source>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>875</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>880</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.92.4.875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7641368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The cytochrome P450 enzyme CYP96A15 is the midchain alkane hydroxylase responsible for formation of secondary alcohols and ketones in stem cuticular wax of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>145</volume>
<fpage>653</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>667</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.107.107300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17905869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thoraval</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delude</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Domergue</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>ECERIFERUM2-LIKE proteins have unique biochemical and physiological functions in very-long-chain fatty acid elongation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>167</volume>
<fpage>682</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>692</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.253195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25596184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Extending the story of very-long-chain fatty acid elongation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>210</volume>
<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2013.05.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23849117</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Komari</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumashiro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Efficient transformation of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) mediated by <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> and sequence analysis of the boundaries of the T-DNA.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>282</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7920717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hooker</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Significance of the expression of the CER6 condensing enzyme for cuticular wax production in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>129</volume>
<fpage>1568</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1580</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.003707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Characterization of glossy1-homologous genes in rice involved in leaf wax accumulation and drought resistance.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>456</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-009-9483-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19322663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuttle</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eigenbrode</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Leaf epicuticular waxes of the eceriferum mutants in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>377</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.1.369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jessen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olbrich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knufer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoppert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Combined activity of LACS1 and LACS4 is required for proper pollen coat formation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>726</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21790813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A novel rice bHLH transcription factor, DTD, acts coordinately with TDR in controlling tapetum function and pollen development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Plant</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>1715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1718</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/sst046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23519457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joubes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raffaele</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourdenx</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laroche-Traineau</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The VLCFA elongase gene family in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: phylogenetic analysis 3D modelling and expression profiling.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>566</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-008-9339-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18465198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Wax-deficient anther1 is involved in cuticle and wax production in rice anther walls and is required for pollen development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>3015</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3032</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.042044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17138699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Rice undeveloped tapetum1 is a major regulator of early tapetum development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>2705</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2722</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.034090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16141453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun-Ben Ku</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The bHLH142 transcription factor coordinates with TDR1 to modulate the expression of EAT1 and regulate pollen development in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>2486</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2504</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.126292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24894043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosma</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourdenx</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joub&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The impact of water deficiency on leaf cuticle lipids of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>151</volume>
<fpage>1918</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1929</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.141911a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19819982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kouchi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of novel nodulin cDNAs representing genes expressed at early stages of soybean nodule development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Gen. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>238</volume>
<fpage>106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>119</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00279537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7683079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis and secretion of plant cuticular wax.</article-title>
<source><italic>Prog. Lipid Res.</italic></source>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12467638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Plant cuticles shine: advances in wax biosynthesis and export.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>727</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2009.09.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19864175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jetter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Composition of alkyl esters in the cuticular wax on inflorescence stems of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> cer mutants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17376164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leide</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hildebrandt</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riederer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The positional sterile (ps) mutation affects cuticular transpiration and wax biosynthesis of tomato fruits.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>168</volume>
<fpage>871</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>877</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2010.11.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21242016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e9;vesque-Lemay</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabot</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Tapetal oleosins play an essential role in tapetosome formation and protein relocation to the pollen coat.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>209</volume>
<fpage>691</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>704</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26305561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinot</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauveplane</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Werck-Reichhart</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Cytochrome P450 family member CYP704B2 catalyzes the &#x003c9;-hydroxylation of fatty acids and is required for anther cutin biosynthesis and pollen exine formation in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.070326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20086189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vizcay-Barrena</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>PERSISTENT TAPETAL CELL1 ecodes a PHD-Finger protein that is required for tapetal cell death and pollen development in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>156</volume>
<fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>630</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.175760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21515697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Expression of RNA-interference/antisense transgenes by the cognate promoters of target genes is a better gene-silencing strategy to study gene functions in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>e17444</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Rice APOPTOSIS INHIBITOR5 coupled with two DEAD-Box adenosine 5&#x02032;-triphosphate-dependent RNA helicases regulates tapetum degeneration.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>1416</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1434</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.110.082636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21467577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis of anther cuticle and pollen exine in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Signal. Behav.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>1121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1123</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.5.9.12562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20930527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;gel</surname><given-names>I. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giavalisco</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeisler</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname> Soll</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>FAX1, a novel membrane protein mediating plastid fatty acid export.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>:<issue>e1002053</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1002053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W. Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The rice tapetum degeneration retardation gene is required for tapetum degradation and anther development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>2999</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3014</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.044107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17138695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li-Beisson</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shorrosh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beisson</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>M. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arondel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Acyl-lipid metabolism.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arabidopsis Book.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<issue>e0161</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1199/tab.0161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Wax crystal-sparse leaf2 a rice homologue of WAX2/GL1 is involved in synthesis of leaf cuticular wax.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>235</volume>
<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-011-1481-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21809091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsushima</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawagoe</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>amyloplast-localized SUBSTANDARD STARCH GRAIN4 protein influences the size of starch grains in rice endosperm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>164</volume>
<fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>636</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.229591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24335509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz-Bertomeu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cascales-Mi&#x000f1;ana</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Irles-Segura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mateu</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunes-Nesi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The plastidial glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase is critical for viable pollen development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>152</volume>
<fpage>1830</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1841</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.150458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20107025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawrath</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Unraveling the complex network of cuticular structure and function.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>287</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2006.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16580871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Z. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>EAT1 promotes tapetal cell death by regulating aspartic proteases during male reproductive development in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>:<issue>1445</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms2396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nobusawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Umeda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Very-long-chain fatty acids have an essential role in plastid division by controlling Z-ring formation in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genes Cells</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>719</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2443.2012.01619.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22734690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parish</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Death of a tapetum: a programme of developmental altruism.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>178</volume>
<fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2009.11.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beisson</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Building lipid barriers: biosynthesis of cutin and suberin.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trends Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2008.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18440267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>B. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Rice OsGL1-1 is involved in leaf cuticular wax and cuticle membrane.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Plant.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>985</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>995</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21511810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luchang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quilichini</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>ABCG15 encodes an ABC transporter protein and is essential for post-meiotic anther and pollen exine development in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>138</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>154</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcs162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23220695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rashotte</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Cuticular waxes on eceriferum mutants of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(00)00513-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11336252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Chemical agents that inhibit pollen development: effects of the phenyl-cinnoline carboxylates SC-1058 and SC-1271 on the ultrastructure of developing wheat anthers (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L. var Yecora roj&#x000f2;).</article-title>
<source><italic>Sex Plant Reprod.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00227655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spielman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Stamen structure and function.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>S46</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.017012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15131249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shanklin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahoon</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Desaturation and related modifications of fatty acids.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annu. Rev. Plant Physiol. Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>641</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.49.1.611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranathunge</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Defective pollen wall is required for anther and microspore development in rice and encodes a fatty acyl carrier protein reductase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>2225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2246</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.087528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21705642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smirnova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leide</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riederer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Deficiency in a very-long-chain fatty acid &#x003b2;-Ketoacyl-Coenzyme a synthase of tomato impairs microgametogenesis and causes floral organ fusion.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>161</volume>
<fpage>196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.206656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23144186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sturaro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartings</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmelzer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Motto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Cloning and characterization of GLOSSY1 a maize gene involved in cuticle membrane and wax production.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>138</volume>
<fpage>478</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>489</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.058164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15849306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>MTR1 encodes a secretory fasciclin glycoprotein required for male reproductive development in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Dev. Cell</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>1127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1137</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2012.04.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22698279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Datla</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The classical Ubisch bodies carry a sporophytically produced structural protein (RAFTIN) that is essential for pollen development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>14487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2231254100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14612572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015a</year>). <article-title><italic>Cucumis sativus</italic> L. <italic>WAX</italic>2 plays a pivotal role in wax biosynthesis influencing pollen fertility and plant biotic and abiotic stress responses.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>1339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1354</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcv052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26023108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015b</year>). <article-title>Cucumber ECERIFERUM1 (CsCER1) which influences the cuticle properties and drought tolerance of cucumber plays a key role in VLC alkanes biosynthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>233</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-014-0271-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25539982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Z. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>From <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> to rice: pathways in pollen development.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>1479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19321648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The rice gene DEFECTIVE TAPETUM AND MEIOCYTES 1 (DTM1) is required for early tapetum development and meiosis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>256</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>270</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04864.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22111585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Defective tapetum cell death 1 (DTC1) regulates ROS levels by binding to metallothionein during tapetum degeneration.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>170</volume>
<fpage>1611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1623</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.01561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26697896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>OsC6 encoding a lipid transfer protein is required for postmeiotic anther development in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>154</volume>
<fpage>149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.158865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20610705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Cytological analysis and genetic control of rice anther development.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Genet. Genom.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>390</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgg.2011.08.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Specification of tapetum and microsporocyte cells within the anther.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2013.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24507494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.-Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Tapetum degeneration retardation is critical for aliphatic metabolism and gene regulation during rice pollen development.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Plant</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>599</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>610</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssn028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19825565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Rice OsGL1-6 is involved in leaf cuticular wax accumulation and drought resistance.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>e65139</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>OsGL1-3 is involved in cuticular wax biosynthesis and tolerance to water deficit in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>e116676</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0116676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title><italic>Post-meiotic deficient anther1 (PDA1)</italic> encodes an ABC transporter required for the development of anther cuticle and pollen exine in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12374-013-0902-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A genetic pathway for tapetum development and function in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Integr. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>892</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>900</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2011.01078.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21957980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>