<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6349027</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6311</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biochemistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecosystem Science</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Soil Science</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Environmental Impacts</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impact assessment of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> on plant growth and soil environment: a greenhouse study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Wenmei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>Gayoung</given-names></name><email>gayoo@khu.ac.kr</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moonis</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Youjin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xuanlin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/></contrib><aff id="aff-1">
<institution>Department of Applied Environmental Science, Kyung Hee University</institution>, <city>Yongin-si</city>, <country>South Korea</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Abiven</surname><given-names>Samuel</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2019-01-25"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e6311</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-10-11"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-12-19"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2019 He et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>He et al.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6311"/><abstract><p>To ensure the safety of carbon capture and storage (CCS) technology, insight into the potential impacts of CO<sub>2</sub> leakage on the ecosystem is necessary. We conducted a greenhouse experiment to investigate the effects of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> on plant growth and the soil environment. Treatments comprised 99.99% CO<sub>2</sub> injection (CG), 99.99% N<sub>2</sub>injection (NG), and no injection (BG). NG treatment was employed to differentiate the effects of O<sub>2</sub> depletion from those of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment. Soil CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> concentrations were maintained at an average of 53% and 11%, respectively, under CG treatment. We verified that high soil CO<sub>2</sub> had negative effects on root water absorption, chlorophyll, starch content and total biomass. Soil microbial acid phosphatase activity was affected by CG treatment. These negative effects were attributed to high soil CO<sub>2</sub> instead of low O<sub>2</sub> or low pH. Our results indicate that high soil CO<sub>2</sub> affected the root system, which in turn triggered further changes in aboveground plant tissues and rhizospheric soil water conditions. A conceptual diagram of CO<sub>2</sub> toxicity to plants and soil is suggested to act as a useful guideline for impact assessment of CCS technology.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>CO<sub>2</sub> stress</kwd><kwd>High soil CO<sub>2</sub></kwd><kwd>Carbon capture and storage</kwd><kwd>Root water absorption activity</kwd><kwd>Plant response</kwd><kwd>Impact assessment</kwd><kwd>O<sub>2</sub> depletion</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Korea Ministry of Environment</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Korea-CO<sub>2</sub> Storage Environmental Management (K-COSEM) Research Program</funding-source><award-id>2014001810002</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This work is supported by the Korea Ministry of Environment (MOE) as the Korea-CO<sub>2</sub> Storage Environmental Management (K-COSEM) Research Program (Project No. 2014001810002). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Carbon capture and storage (CCS) technology is considered an important strategy for mitigating climate change (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">IPCC, 2014</xref>). To ensure safe and successful CCS projects, the European Union has published guidance documents for its CCS Directive that include general CO<sub>2</sub> leakage scenarios (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">European&#x000a0;Communities, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Pearce et al., 2014</xref>). The most relevant CO<sub>2</sub>leakage could occur in storage reservoirs via faults, fractures or boreholes (<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Pearce et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Vr&#x000e5;lstad et al., 2018</xref>). As CO<sub>2</sub> would likely be transported to storage sites through long pipelines, leakage could also occur via corrosion and connection failures of shallow pipes (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">European&#x000a0;Communities, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Fu &#x00026; Gundersen, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Pearce et al., 2014</xref>). The leaked CO<sub>2</sub> would diffuse from deep soil layers toward the surface. As a result, soil could experience high CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations between 40% and 95% for a period of time (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Beaubien et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Al-Traboulsi et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Paulley et al., 2013</xref>). Surrounding plants and soil microbes could be influenced by high concentration of soil CO<sub>2</sub> and the concomitant low pH and reduced proportions of O<sub>2</sub> andN<sub>2</sub>.</p><p>Plant responses to a high-CO<sub>2</sub> soil environment have been widely investigated in natural analogues and at artificial CO<sub>2</sub> release sites (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Pfanz et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Beaubien et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Male et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Kr&#x000fc;ger et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Patil, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">West et al., 2015</xref>). Chlorosis and discoloration were observed in natural vegetation after 4 days of CO<sub>2</sub> exposure at the Zero Emission Research and Technology Center in the US (<xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Lakkaraju et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2014</xref>). Plant physiological indicators such as chlorophyll content, photosynthesis rate, stomata conductance and transpiration rate were lower in soils with a high CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Spangler et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2014</xref>). Morphological indicators such as plant height, root length, leaf number, leaf area, seed number and pod number were also reduced after the soil was exposed to high levels of CO<sub>2</sub> compared with non-gassed controls. Plant biomass also decreased on CO<sub>2</sub> gassing (<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Al-Traboulsi et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Al-Traboulsi et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al.,&#x000a0;2014</xref>).</p><p>Although previous studies consistently reported that plants exposed to high soil CO<sub>2</sub> showed inhibited growth (<xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Patil, Colls &#x00026; Steven, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Al-Traboulsi et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2017</xref>), few clearly identified the main driving factor of these negative impacts (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Pfanz et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Pfanz &#x00026; Sa&#x000df;mannshausen, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2016</xref>). <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Beaubien et al. (2008)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Stephens &#x00026; Hering (2002)</xref> observed that water absorption of plants was lower, but they did not distinguish the effects of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> (&#x0223c;100% at 20&#x000a0;cm depth) from those of low O<sub>2</sub> or other trace gases such as H<sub>2</sub>S and CH<sub>4</sub>. <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Al-Traboulsi et al. (2012)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2016)</xref> explained that reduced bean and maize metabolism in CO<sub>2</sub> gassing plots might be due to reduced O<sub>2</sub> level rather than pH changes induced by high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (50&#x02013;70% at 15&#x02013;30&#x000a0;cm depth). <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al. (2016a)</xref> sought to distinguish the effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> (42.3%) from those of O<sub>2</sub> depletion (11.1%) on the growth of wheat and beetroot by employing an N<sub>2</sub> gassing treatment. They suggested that high soil CO<sub>2</sub> might explain the biomass reduction of beetroots better than O<sub>2</sub> deficiency. Similar results were found in earlier studies by <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Chang &#x00026; Loomis (1945)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Kramer (1940)</xref>. In their studies, transpiration and root water absorption of wheat, maize, rice, sunflowers and tomatoes were close to normal under O<sub>2</sub>-free nitrogen-bubbling treatment, while they were severely affected by 100% CO<sub>2</sub> bubbling. <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Chang &#x00026; Loomis (1945)</xref> also compared the effects of low pH solution and high CO<sub>2</sub> exposure on root function and observed that toxic effects were more evident under high CO<sub>2</sub> conditions than under acidic solutions. They suggested that CO<sub>2</sub> toxicity is a more important factor in plant growth than O<sub>2</sub> deficiency. Previous studies have implied that high concentration of soil CO<sub>2</sub> itself might be toxic to plant growth in a variety of plant species. However, compared with the intensive studies of CO<sub>2</sub> effects on plants in hydroponic system, the assumption of CO<sub>2</sub> toxicity on plant growth under high soil CO<sub>2</sub> condition has not been sufficiently proved.</p><p>To identify the main factor in soil CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment that influences plant growth and soil, we conducted a greenhouse experiment using a specially designed pot in which soil CO<sub>2</sub> was enriched without a buildup of ambient atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>. We separated the effects of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> and those of low soil O<sub>2</sub> by employing an N<sub>2</sub> gassing treatment. The pot was large enough to grow woody plants, and the injection time covered the main growing period. The objective of this study was to investigate the effects of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> on plant physiological reactions and their interactions with the soil environment. A conceptual diagram of the effects of CO<sub>2</sub> toxicity on plant metabolism is proposed for further insight into the impacts of high soil CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials &#x00026; Methods</title><sec><title>Soil and plant preparation</title><p>Soils used for incubation included commercial potting soil (Korea Association of Seedbed Media, Seoul, South Korea) and mineral soil procured from a construction company (Seung Hwa Construction, South Korea). Basic soil physicochemical properties and components are summarized in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Soil pH was measured using a 1:5 dilution method (<xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Thomas, 1996</xref>). Total carbon (TC) and total nitrogen (TN) contents were analyzed using combustion analysis with a Carlo Erba NS 1500 C/N analyzer (Carlo Erba, Milan, Italy). A two-year-old crimson glory vine (<italic>Vitis coignetiae</italic>) was selected for this experiment and bought locally (West Suwon Agricultural Products Inc., South Korea). This plant grows well in neutral to alkaline soils and is native to East Asian countries such as Japan and South Korea.</p><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Physicochemical properties of the soil.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Soil</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>pH</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TN</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TC</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Composition (%)</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">(g kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> soil)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Zeolite</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pearlite</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Vermiculite</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Coco peat</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Peat moss</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Other</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Potting</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">390.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Clay</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Silt</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sand</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mineral</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Experimental design</title><p>Gas treatments were applied in a greenhouse on the campus of Kyung Hee University (Yongin-si, South Korea) for 32 days from August 20 to September 23, 2015. Mean temperature was 28&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C during the day and 18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C at night. An acrylic container including three pots (30&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;20&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;20 cm; height &#x000d7; length &#x000d7; width) and an empty chamber (20&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;20&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;60 cm; height &#x000d7; length &#x000d7; width) were specially designed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1A</xref>). At the bottom of each pot, nine drainage holes were covered with mesh for optimal gas diffusion. An empty chamber was connected to a gas tank through a valve. Each pot was filled with 7 kg of mineral soil up to 15 cm from the bottom, and then another 15 cm of potting soil was added. Grape saplings were transplanted on July 15 and adjusted to a new environment for 36 days until August 20. Soil water content in all treatments was adjusted to 20&#x02013;30% (v/v) and maintained by manual watering every 4 days. In the CG treatment, 99.99% CO<sub>2</sub> gas was supplied at a rate of 400 mL/min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The NG treatment was set up using 99.99% N<sub>2</sub> gas at the same injection rate to investigate the effects of O<sub>2</sub> depletion without CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment. The BG treatment was prepared as a control with no injection. Three silicon tubes (2 mm in diameter) with one end connected to a copper fitting covered with mesh (100 &#x000b5;m) were buried in the soil at depths of 5, 10 and 20 cm to measure the CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> concentrations. Although the pot was not large enough to permit lateral heterogeneity of the gases, the tubes at each depth in the replicated pots were located randomly to ensure measurements were representative. Nine replicates were set up for each treatment. The greenhouse remained open and two fans were used to prevent ambient CO<sub>2</sub> accumulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Injection box (A) and treatment layout in the greenhouse (B).</title><p>Photo credit: Wenmei He.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Soil measurements</title><p>Daily measurements of soil CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> (% of total 100% by volume) at three depths (5, 10, and 20 cm) were performed using a portable gas detector (COMBI-R, Status Scientific Controls Ltd., Mansfield, Nottinghamshire, UK). The detection range of CO<sub>2</sub> was from 0 to 100% with an accuracy of&#x000a0;&#x000b1;1% and that of O<sub>2</sub> was from 0 to 25% with an accuracy of&#x000a0;&#x000b1;0.1%. Soil pH and temperature were measured directly using a pH meter (Field Scout pH 600; Spectrum Technologies, Inc. Plainfield, IL, USA). Soil volumetric water content was measured using a moisture sensor (GS1, Decagon Devices, Inc., Washington D.C., USA) at 5 cm depth. Plant root water absorption activity (RWAA) was measured indirectly by monitoring changes in soil water content in each pot. Soil with active root metabolism tends to lose more water when soil water change occurs only through plant transpiration (<xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Stephens &#x00026; Hering, 2002</xref>). We assumed an equal amount of water drainage from pots and surface soil evaporation among the different treatment pots (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al., 1998</xref>). Hence, we defined RWAA as the daily amount of water loss during the no watering period. A larger RWAA indicated greater root activity.</p><p>Samples (200g) of potting and mineral soils were removed from each pot at the end of the injection period and stored at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0; C before analysis. Enzyme analysis was conducted within one week of sampling. Five enzyme activities were determined by fluorometric assays using methylumbelliferone linked substrates, including acid phosphatase (AP), cellobiohydrolase (BC), 1,4-&#x003b2;-glucosidase (BGC), xylosidase (BX) and 1,4-&#x003b2;-N-acetyl glucosaminidase (NAG), which are enzymes that mediate key functions during microbial degradation of soil litter (<xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Chung et al., 2011</xref>). AP cleaves phosphoester bonds; BC and BGC decompose cellulose; BX breaks down hemicellulose and NAG degrades chitin (<xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Saiya-Cork, Sinsabaugh &#x00026; Zak, 2002</xref>). The TC and TN contents of air-dried soils were analyzed with a Carlo Erba NS 1500 C/N analyzer (Carlo Erba, Milan, Italy). The hot water extractable carbon (HWC) of the potting and mineral soils, which is a proxy for the amount of labile carbon, was determined following the method described in <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Nelissen et al. (2012)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Plant measurements</title><p>Photographs were produced every week to record visible changes in plants, and chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> content was measured to monitor physiological changes. To measure chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>, leaves were sampled twice a week from August 20 to September 3 and once a week from September 4 to September 23. The leaves were homogenized by grinding with a mortar and pestle and chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> was extracted using 90% acetone overnight at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in the dark. A UV/Vis spectrophotometer (Optizen POP, Mecasys Co., Ltd, Daejeon, South Korea) was used to measure chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> concentration (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Arnon, 1949</xref>).</p><p>When the CO<sub>2</sub> injection period was completed, the plant was carefully dug out and separated into roots and shoots (leaves and stems). Root samples were washed with water and dried at 60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 3 days to obtain dry weights. The fresh weight of the shoots was recorded, and a subsample of fresh shoots was dried to determine water content. To monitor movement and distribution of nutrients, TC, TN and total phosphorus (TP) contents of the plants were measured. The TC and TN contents of the roots and leaves were subjected to combustion analysis with a Carlo Erba NS 1500 C/N analyzer. TP content of leaves was measured using a modified molybdenum blue technique (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Murphy &#x00026; Riley, 1962</xref>). The starch content of plant roots was measured using a starch assay kit (K-TSTA, Megazyme International Ireland Co. Ltd., Wicklow, Ireland) as a stress indicator that decreases when plants are under stress (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al., 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Analysis of variance was performed using the MIXED procedure in SAS 9.1 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA) and included concentrations of soil CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub>, pH, chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> content, and RWAA, while an additional GLM procedure was used to analyze plant parameters (biomass, starch, TC, TN, TP and water content) and soil parameters (TC, TN, HWC contents and enzyme activities). Least square means were used to test for significant differences among treatments at a 5% probability level.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Soil gases and pH</title><p>Soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations were significantly higher in the CG treatment than in the NG and BG treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Due to gas exchange with the atmosphere, we observed a CO<sub>2</sub> gradient at depths in the CG treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2A</xref> and <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The gas concentrations from locations of nine replicates had small deviations at each depth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>), indicating that lateral heterogeneity of gases could be ignored in our small pots. Constant CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations were maintained throughout the injection period indicating that our incubation system was sufficiently stable to investigate the effects of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> on plant growth. In the BG and NG treatments, soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations were lower than 1%, which is below the detection threshold (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). These concentrations were comparable with those of field studies that reported &#x0003c;1% CO<sub>2</sub> in the non-injection plots (0.7&#x02013;0.9%) measured by high-accuracy gas analyzers (GA5000 and Vaisala 221 GMT probe) (<xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al., 2016a</xref>). Soil O<sub>2</sub> concentrations in the BG treatment were similar at all depths and the same as that at the ambient condition (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). In the NG and CG treatments, soil N<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> injections significantly reduced O<sub>2</sub> concentrations, which were maintained at 7.4&#x02013;14.3% throughout the injection period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2C</xref> and <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Soil CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> concentrations were negatively correlated in the CG treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2D</xref>). Soil pH was slightly increased at the end of the injection period compared with the initial pH (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), and the CG treatment significantly reduced soil pH compared with pH in the BG and NG treatments (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Mean soil CO<sub>2</sub> (A) and O<sub>2</sub> (B) concentrations in CG treatment. Mean soil O<sub>2</sub> concentration in NG treatment (C). The relationship between soil CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> concentrations in CG at each depth (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;256) (D)</title><p>Bars with the same letters are not significantly different at a 5% level (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Mean soil CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> concentrations in different depths and soil pH at each treatment.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatments</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (%)</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">O<sub>2</sub> concentration (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depth (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.8<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1"><label>a,b</label><p>Different letters indicate significant differences among treatments at a 5% level (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;261).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Analysis of variance examining the effects of CO<sub>2</sub> injection on soil parameters.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g008"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Source</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CO</bold><sub><bold>2</bold></sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>O</bold><sub><bold>2</bold></sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>pH</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chlorophyll <italic>a</italic></bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RWAA</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Date</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depth</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Date &#x000d7; Depth</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Date &#x000d7; Treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9941</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depth &#x000d7; Treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Date &#x000d7; Depth &#x000d7; Treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Source</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="11" rowspan="1"><bold>Soil</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Potting</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Mineral</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Microbial enzyme activities</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TC</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TN</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HWC</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TC</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TN</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HWC</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AP</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BC</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BGC</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BX</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NAG</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6421</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2532</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.983</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8781</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0298</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2503</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0174</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-3fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-3fn1"><label>a</label><p>No data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Plant parameters during injection</title><p>Temporal changes in leaf color and vitality varied by treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>). In the BG treatment, plant leaves remained healthy and green until the end of the experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig.&#x000a0;3A</xref>). In the NG treatment, plant leaves appeared healthy until September 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig.&#x000a0;3B</xref>); after that, a few leaves at the bottom of the plant turned yellow. In the CG treatment, plant leaves appeared healthy until September 8 and then turned yellow and red. At the end of experiment, the leaves in the CG treatments appeared very dry and showed low vitality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3C</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Morphological changes of plants during the experimental period.</title><p>(A) The photographs of grape in BG (no injection) from left to right were taken on August 21, September 8 and September 22; (B) The photographs of grape in NG (N<sub>2</sub> injection) from left to right were taken on August 21, September 8 and September 22; (C) The photographs of grape in CG (CO<sub>2</sub> injection) from left to right were taken on August 21, September 8 and September 22. Photo credit: Wenmei He.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g003"/></fig><p>In all treatments, chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> content increased quickly until August 25 and decreased slowly thereafter, following the seasonal night temperature drop in all the treatments (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Treatment effects varied by date and became apparent after the one-week injection. On August 28, September 8, and September 16, the chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> content of leaves in the CG treatment was significantly lower than that in the BG treatment. However, chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> in the NG was not significantly lower than in the BG on any date of measurement.</p><fig id="fig-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Leaf chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> content (A) and root water absorption activity (RWAA) (B).</title><p>Each date was compared and results with the same letter are not significantly different at a 5% level (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g004"/></fig><p>An overall decreasing pattern in RWAA was observed in all the treatments (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4B</xref>). This could be due to seasonal temperature drop, which leads to slower plant metabolism. Treatment effects became apparent from August 24, when RWAA in the CG treatment was significantly lower than in the BG and NG treatments. This effect continued until the end of the experiment. RWAA was not significantly different between the NG and BG treatments. The effects of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> on RWAA were observed 4 days earlier than those on chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> content.</p></sec><sec><title>Plant parameters after harvest</title><p>After injection, shoot and root biomass were reduced by 19.2% and 59.2%, respectively, in the CG treatment compared with the BG treatment (<xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Shoot and root biomass, however, were not changed in the NG compared to the BG. Water content of the shoots (leaves and stems) and starch content of the roots were also significantly lower in the CG treatment, but they were not significantly different between BG and NG treatments. TC content in leaves and roots was similar between BG and CG treatments. TN content was higher in leaves and roots in the CG treatment compared with the BG and NG treatments. The TP content of leaves was lower in the NG and CG treatments than in the BG treatment (<xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/table-4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Total shoot and root biomass, shoot water, root starch, TC and TN contents in leaves and roots.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g009"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total biomass</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Shoot biomass</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Root biomass</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Shoot water content</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Root starch</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>TC</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>TN</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TP</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Leaf</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Root</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Leaf</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Root</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Leaf</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">(g plant<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">(%)</th><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">(g kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BG</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.22<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.36<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.87<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.37<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.75<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">435.78<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">473.89<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.94<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.26<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NG</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.50<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.88<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.62<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.57<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.55<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">435.82<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">464.78<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.83<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CG</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.48<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.75<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.73<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.68<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">436.42<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">482.22<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.62<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.89<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0754</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9739</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0970</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0238</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-4fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-4fn1"><label>a,b</label><p>Different letters indicate significant differences among treatments at a 5% level (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Soil parameters after experiments had finished</title><p>Soil TC and TN contents did not vary among treatments, while HWC contents in mineral soil were lower in CG than in the BG (<xref rid="table-5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). On the other hand, enzyme activities in potting soil were different among treatments. The activity of AP was lower in the CG and NG than in the BG, while activities of NAG and BX were higher in the NG than in the BG and CG (<xref rid="table-5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). In mineral soils, enzyme activities were too low to be detected.</p><table-wrap id="table-5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/table-5</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>TC, TN and HWC contents and microbial enzyme activities in soil.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g010"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Parameters</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Soils</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>BG</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>NG</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>CG</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potting</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potting</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potting</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Chemical parameters</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TC</bold></td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">(g kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.96<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">224.74<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">257.76<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TN</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.01<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HWC</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.62<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.73<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.67<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1"><bold>Microbial enzyme activities</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AP<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn2"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">(nmol h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200.56<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn3"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.40<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.98<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BC</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BGC</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.75<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.16<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.12<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BX</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.32<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.20<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.38<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NAG</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.30<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.22<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.63<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-5fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-5fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-5fn1"><label>a, b</label><p>Different letters indicate significant differences among treatments at a 5% level (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9).</p></fn><fn id="table-5fn2"><label>c</label><p>AP, BC, BGC, BX and NAG stand for: acid phosphatase, cellobiohydrolase, 1,4-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-glucosidase, xylosidase, and 1,4-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-N-acetyl glucosaminidase, respectively.</p></fn><fn id="table-5fn3"><label>d</label><p>No data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The results clearly indicated that injected gases migrated upwards through all the gassed pots. A clear depth gradient of soil CO<sub>2</sub> was observed in these pots, while lateral heterogeneity in CO<sub>2</sub> was negligible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). High soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration lowered soil O<sub>2</sub> and pH, consistent with the previous results. The negative relationship between soil CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> concentrations in the CG could be due to O<sub>2</sub> displacement by injected CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Patil, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al., 2016a</xref>). The steeper slope in the linear negative relationship between CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> at 5 cm depth than those at 10 cm and 20 cm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2D</xref>) implied that, in the shallow surface layer, diffused CO<sub>2</sub> gas was mixed with atmospheric air (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2A</xref>). These vertical gradients in soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration were also observed in other greenhouse and field studies (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Kr&#x000fc;ger et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">West et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2018</xref>). In addition, our range of CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations of 41.3&#x02013;65.3% at 5&#x02013;20 cm depths (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) was comparable to the levels in previous studies (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Beaubien et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Al-Traboulsi et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al., 2016a</xref>), and this the possible level of CO<sub>2</sub> concentration at which CO<sub>2</sub> from the CCS site would leak and be transported via faults or failure.</p><p>The reductions in chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> content, RWAA and total biomass seen with CG treatment and not in the NG treatment indicate that plants were influenced by high soil CO<sub>2</sub> but not by low O<sub>2</sub> concentration. Although CO<sub>2</sub>-induced reduction in soil pH in the CG treatment could affect plants, we put little emphasis on the effect of lowered pH. In this experiment, soil pH in the CG treatment (7.0) was lower than in BG and NG (pH = 7.4 on average) (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), but the difference was only 0.4, which is within the optimal range for grape growth. The possible reason for such a slight change in soil pH despite CO<sub>2</sub> gassing, which could lead to formation of weak acid (H<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>) and release of H<sup>+</sup> (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Wei, Maroto-Valer &#x00026; Steven, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Moonis et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2017</xref>), could be the high buffering capacity of the potting soil and plants&#x02019; indirect effects. Our results were consistent with those of <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al. (2013)</xref>, who reported that beetroots were not significantly affected by N<sub>2</sub> gas treatment at O<sub>2</sub> concentration of 8.7%. Even in an O<sub>2</sub>-free hydroponic solution, <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Boru et al. (2003)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Chang &#x00026; Loomis (1945)</xref> did not observe inhibited root growth or function, implying that plants could be resistant to low O<sub>2</sub> condition (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Geigenberger, 2003</xref>). <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Nikolopoulou et al. (2012)</xref> reported clear results that grass (<italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic>) root length and biomass were greatly reduced (&#x0003e;50%) under treatment with 40% CO<sub>2</sub> combined with 20% O<sub>2</sub>, and a similar reduction was observed under treatment with 40% CO<sub>2</sub> combined with 10% or 2.5% O<sub>2</sub>. We therefore suggest that high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration has negative effects on overall plant metabolism.</p><p>We observed the effects of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration on plants with regard to root function. The reduction in RWAA in the CG treatment was apparent on August 24, 4 days after the start of injection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4B</xref>). On August 28th, lower chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> content was first observed in the CG treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Leaf color change became apparent as late as September 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3C</xref>). The series of changes in the CG treatment imply that high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration affected the root system first, which triggered other aboveground changes in the plant. Color changes in the leaves are related to changes in nutrient transport (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Chang &#x00026; Loomis, 1945</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Cook, Ward &#x00026; Wicks, 1983</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Boru et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Geigenberger, 2003</xref>). In our study, the TN content of the roots was higher in the CG than in the BG treatment, while there were similar TN and lower TP contents in the CG plant leaves compared with the BG leaves (<xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). These results indicated that nitrogen transport from the roots to the leaves was inhibited by high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration.</p><p>CO<sub>2</sub> injection also induced changes in soil HWC content and microbial enzyme activities. Reduced HWC in mineral soil of the CG treatment could be related to the high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<xref rid="table-5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Moonis et al. (2017)</xref> reported that soil CO<sub>2</sub> injection increased exchangeable Al<sup>3+</sup> of mineral soil, which would be strong bound with dissolved C molecules. The resulting Al<sup>3+</sup>-C complexes could be absorbed on the soil surface, producing reduced water-extractable C. Reduced soil microbial enzyme activity of AP in the CG and NG (<xref rid="table-5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), which is involved in cleaving phosphoester bonds, could be related to the decreased TP contents of the leaves in those treatments (<xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The increased enzyme activities of NAG and BX in the NG treatment (<xref rid="table-5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), which are involved in decomposition of hemicellulose and chitin, respectively, might be related to lower soil O<sub>2</sub> concentration. In a low O<sub>2</sub> environment, the activity of N<sub>2</sub>-fixation organisms could be enhanced, resulting in increased soil-available N. This change could be beneficial to microbial decomposition processes that are usually limited by the low N content of residues in soil (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Rice &#x00026; Paul, 1972</xref>; <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Halsall &#x00026; Gibson, 1985</xref>; <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2011</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/fig-5</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Conceptual model of the response to high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in plant: involvement of hydraulic reaction and compensational mechanism.</title><p>Photo credit: Wenmei He.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-g005"/></fig><p>A mechanism for CO<sub>2</sub> toxicity to plant root tissue was suggested by earlier studies (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Chang &#x00026; Loomis, 1945</xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Bown, 1985</xref>). High soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations could dramatically change the pH level of root tissues, which could undermine membrane function and osmoregulation of root cells. Damaged root cells would not absorb water sufficiently, and plant stomata would close to prevent water loss (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Davies, Kudoyarova &#x00026; Hartung, 2005</xref>). Similarly, <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Lake et al. (2016b)</xref> suggested a signaling mechanism from the root to the leaf: when plant roots suffer CO<sub>2</sub> stress, they produce hormones such as abscisic acid and send this signal to the leaves to close stomata. As a compensatory mechanism, the plant hydrolyzes starch in the roots and stems into soluble sugars and changes the osmotic potential to increase water absorption (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Mohammadkhani &#x00026; Heidari, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Naser et al., 2010</xref>). In our study, the reduced starch content of roots in the CG treatment (<xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) could be associated with this compensation response to high soil CO<sub>2</sub> stress (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Nikolopoulou et al., 2012</xref>). Based on our observations and extensive literature review, we propose a conceptual diagram of plant response to high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5</xref>). The effects of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> on plants start from the root cells where intercellular pH is reduced, leading to activation of signaling to the leaf to close the stomata. Due to stomata closure, water and nutrients are not transported from the soil to the leaves, resulting in low photosynthesis. Although plants try to compensate for lower photosynthates by solubilizing starch, they eventually consume stored resources, lose vitally and die.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Plants can be a useful tool for assessing the potential risk of CO<sub>2</sub> leakage from CCS sites. We verified that high soil CO<sub>2</sub> (41.3&#x02013;65.0%) had negative effects on overall plant metabolism. These negative effects were attributed to high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and not to low soil O<sub>2</sub> concentration or to reduced soil pH. Negative effects on root water absorption were observed after CO<sub>2</sub> injection, and the effects extended to aboveground plant tissues, leading to decreased chlorophyll content and chlorosis.</p><p>Results from our study suggest two sensitive indicators for CO<sub>2</sub> leakage in ecosystem. The first indicator is chlorophyll content which showed a reduction 8 days after CO<sub>2</sub> injection. Another sensitive indicator was RWAA, which showed reduction 4 days earlier than chlorophyll content. However, as RWAA is difficult to measure in the field, soil water content could be used as an indirect parameter for detecting CO<sub>2</sub> leak. The inherent heterogeneity of soil water content in space and time could be overcome by establishing long-term baseline data in a given site. Suggested indicators could be utilized to develop a guideline for environmental management of CCS and the surrounding environment. Further research should focus on the responses of different plant species to high soil CO<sub>2</sub> and the interactions between plants and soil.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title> Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentration</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-s001.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>Soil O<sub>2</sub> concentration</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-s002.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/supp-3</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 3</label><caption><title>Chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> contents</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-s003.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/supp-4</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 4</label><caption><title>Soil moisture</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-s004.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6311/supp-5</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 5</label><caption><title>Soil pH</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-6311-s005.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to acknowledge Konkuk University for its supports of analysis of enzyme activities in this study. We would also like to thank all participants for their full cooperation during the experimental period.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Wenmei He</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Gayoung Yoo</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Mohammad Moonis</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-4" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-4">Youjin Kim</xref> and <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-5">Xuanlin Chen</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The raw measurements are available in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplemental-information">Supplemental Files</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Al-Traboulsi et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Traboulsi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;gersten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Colls</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Potential impact of CO<sub>2</sub> leakage from carbon capture and storage systems on field bean (Vicia faba)</article-title><source>Physiologia Plantarum</source><volume>146</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.2012.01620.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22443472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Al-Traboulsi et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Traboulsi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;gersten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Colls</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Potential impact of CO<sub>2</sub> leakage from Carbon Capture and Storage (CCS) systems on growth and yield in maize</article-title><source>Plant and Soil</source><volume>365</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-012-1390-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Allen et&#x000a0;al. (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Raes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Crop evapotranspiration&#x02014;guidelines for computing crop water requirements</article-title><source>FAO Irrigation and drainage paper 56</source><publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Arnon (1949)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnon</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><year>1949</year><article-title>Copper enzymes in isolated chloroplasts. Polyphenoloxidase in Beta vulgaris</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.24.1.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16654194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Beaubien et&#x000a0;al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaubien</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciotoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dictor</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>The impact of a naturally occurring CO<sub>2</sub> gas vent on the shallow ecosystem and soil chemistry of a Mediterranean pasture (Latera, Italy)</article-title><source>International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijggc.2008.03.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Boru et&#x000a0;al. (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boru</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vantoai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Knee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Responses of soybean to oxygen deficiency and elevated root-zone carbon dioxide concentration</article-title><source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcg040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12588724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Bown (1985)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bown</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>CO<sub>2</sub> and intracellular pH</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.1985.tb01681.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Chang &#x00026; Loomis (1945)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1945</year><article-title>Effect of carbon dioxide on absorption of water and nutrients by roots</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.20.2.221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16653979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Chen et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Marti</surname><given-names>MdeH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Falen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>The Composting Process</article-title><source>Dairy Manure Compost Production and Use in Idaho</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9780470666883.ch34</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Chung et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>The effect of multi-walled carbon nanotubes on soil microbial activity</article-title><source>Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2011.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21310485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Cook, Ward &#x00026; Wicks (1983)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wicks</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>Phosphorus deficiency in California vineyards</article-title><source>California Agriculture</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Davies, Kudoyarova &#x00026; Hartung (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudoyarova</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartung</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Long-distance ABA signaling and its relation to other signaling pathways in the detection of soil drying and the mediation of the plant&#x02019;s response to drought</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Growth Regulation</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00344-005-0103-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>European&#x000a0;Communities (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European&#x000a0;Communities</collab></person-group><year>2011</year><source>Implementation of directive 2009/31/EC on the geological storage of carbon dioxide Guidance document 2, characterisation of the storage complex, CO<sub>2</sub> stream composition, monitoring and corrective measures</source><publisher-name>EU Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Luxembourg</publisher-loc><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.egypro.2013.06.240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Fu &#x00026; Gundersen (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gundersen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Carbon capture and storage in the power industry: challenges and opportunities</article-title><source>Energy Procedia</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1806</fpage><lpage>1812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.egypro.2012.01.278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Geigenberger (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geigenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Response of plant metabolism to too little oxygen</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(03)00038-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Halsall &#x00026; Gibson (1985)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halsall</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>Cellulose decomposition and associated nitrogen fixation by mixed cultures of cellulomonas gelida and azospirillum species or bacillus macerans downloaded from</article-title><source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16346898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>He et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Moonis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Effects of high soil CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations on seed germination and soil microbial activities</article-title><source>International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijggc.2016.07.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>IPCC (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IPCC</collab></person-group><year>2014</year><source>Intergovernmental panel on climate change (2014)</source><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pachauri</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>151</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Kim et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Characterizing the spatial distribution of CO<sub>2</sub> leakage from the shallow CO<sub>2</sub> release experiment in South Korea</article-title><source>International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijggc.2018.03.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Kramer (1940)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1940</year><article-title>Causes of decreased absorption of water by plants in poorly aerated media</article-title><source>American Journal of Botany</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2436882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Kr&#x000fc;ger et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Frerichs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppermann</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Strutt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations on the vegetation and microbial populations at a terrestrial CO<sub>2</sub> vent at Laacher See, Germany</article-title><source>International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>1093</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijggc.2011.05.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Lake et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomax</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>COOLTRANS&#x02014;environmental impacts of CO<sub>2</sub> leakage into the soil environment</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 4th international forum on the transportation of CO<sub>2</sub> by pipeline</source><publisher-loc>Gateshead</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Lake et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomax</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Environmental impact of a hypothetical catastrophic leakage of CO<sub>2</sub> onto the ground surface</article-title><source>Journal of Pipeline Engineering</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>248</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Lake et&#x000a0;al. (2016a)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomax</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016a</year><article-title>Plant responses to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> levels in soils: distinct CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub>-depletion effects</article-title><source>International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijggc.2016.07.042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Lake et&#x000a0;al. (2016b)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomax</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016b</year><article-title>A novel root-to-shoot stomatal response to very high CO<sub>2</sub> levels in the soil: electrical, hydraulic and biochemical signalling</article-title><source>Physiologia Plantarum</source><volume>159</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppl.12525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27779760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Lakkaraju et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lakkaraju</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Apple</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobeck</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gullickson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Spangler</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Studying the vegetation response to simulated leakage of sequestered CO<sub>2</sub> using spectral vegetation indices</article-title><source>Ecological Informatics</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoinf.2010.05.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Male et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Male</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickles</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>EA</surname><given-names>Silver</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewicki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Apple</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Repasky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Using hyperspectral plant signatures for CO<sub>2</sub> leak detection during the 2008 ZERT CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration field experiment in Bozeman, Montana</article-title><source>Environmental Earth Sciences</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12665-009-0372-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Mohammadkhani &#x00026; Heidari (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammadkhani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Heidari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Drought-induced accumulation of soluble sugars and proline in two maize varieties</article-title><source>World Applied Sciences Journal</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>453</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Moonis et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moonis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Effect of potential CO<sub>2</sub> leakage from carbon capture and storage sites on soil and leachate chemistry</article-title><source>KSCE Journal of Civil Engineering</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>1640</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12205-016-1867-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Murphy &#x00026; Riley (1962)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1962</year><article-title>A single solution method for the determination of phosphate in in natural waters</article-title><source>Analytica Chimica Acta</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-2670(00)88444-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Naser et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourosh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Reza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Soluble sugars and proline accumulation play a role as effective indices for drought tolerance screening in Persian walnut (Juglans regia L.) during germination</article-title><source>Fruits</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/fruits/20010005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Nelissen et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelissen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000fc;tting</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huygens</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Staelens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruysschaert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeckx</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Maize biochars accelerate short-term soil nitrogen dynamics in a loamy sand soil</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2012.05.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Nikolopoulou et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikolopoulou</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nektarios</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aivalakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Volterrani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chronopoulos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Effects of rootzone CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> levels on seed germination and stolon growth of Cynodon dactylon</article-title><source>Acta Agriculturae Scandinavica, Section B&#x02014;Soil &#x00026; Plant Science</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09064710.2012.681058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Patil (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Impacts of carbon dioxide gas leaks from geological storage sites on soil ecology and above ground vegetation</article-title><source>Diversity of ecosystems</source><publisher-name>In Tech</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rijeka</publisher-loc><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Mahamane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Patil, Colls &#x00026; Steven (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Colls</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Effects of CO<sub>2</sub> gas as leaks from geological storage sites on agro-ecosystems</article-title><source>Energy</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>4587</fpage><lpage>4591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.energy.2010.01.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Paulley et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paulley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Limer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimstad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><collab>RISCS Project Team&#x000a0;T</collab></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Hypothetical impact scenarios for CO<sub>2</sub> leakage from storage sites</article-title><source>Energy Procedia</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>3495</fpage><lpage>3502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.egypro.2013.06.240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Pearce et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaubien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Foekema</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gemeni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lions</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziogou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>A guide for assessing the potential impacts on ecosystems of leakage from CO<sub>2</sub> storage sites</article-title><source>Energy Procedia</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>3242</fpage><lpage>3252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.egypro.2014.11.351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>Pfanz &#x00026; Sa&#x000df;mannshausen (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfanz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sa&#x000df;mannshausen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Geogenic CO<sub>2</sub>-Exhalations and Vegetation: its possible use to predict volcanic eruptions</article-title><source>Geophysical Research Abstracts</source><volume>10</volume><comment>EGU2008-A-12108</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Pfanz et&#x000a0;al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfanz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vodnik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Aschan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Raschi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Plants and geothermal CO<sub>2</sub> exhalations&#x02014;survival in and adaptation to a high CO<sub>2</sub> environment</article-title><source>Progress in botany</source><publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer Science &#x00026; Business Media</publisher-name><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;ttge</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyschlag</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>628</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Rice &#x00026; Paul (1972)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year><article-title>The organisms and biological processes involved in asymbiotic nitrogen fixation in waterlogged soil amended with straw</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Microbiology</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/m72-114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4556097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Saiya-Cork, Sinsabaugh &#x00026; Zak (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saiya-Cork</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinsabaugh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The effects of long term nitrogen deposition on extracellular enzyme activity in an Acer saccharum forest soil</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>1309</fpage><lpage>1315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0038-0717(02)00074-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Sharma et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Apple</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorshorst</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobeck</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Spangler</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Physiological responses of dandelion and orchard grass leaves to experimentally released upwelling soil CO<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijggc.2014.03.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Spangler et&#x000a0;al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spangler</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobeck</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Repasky</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nehrir</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>JLJL</given-names></name><name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouse</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewicki</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Strazisar</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fessenden</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahn</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amonette</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>JLJL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickles</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>EA</surname><given-names>Silver</given-names></name><name><surname>Male</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gullickson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kharaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Birkholzer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wielopolski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>A shallow subsurface controlled release facility in Bozeman, Montana, USA, for testing near surface CO<sub>2</sub> detection techniques and transport models</article-title><source>Environmental Earth Sciences</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12665-009-0400-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Stephens &#x00026; Hering (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hering</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Comparative characterization of volcanic ash soils exposed to decade-long elevated carbon dioxide concentrations at Mammoth Mountain, California</article-title><source>Chemical Geology</source><volume>186</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-2541(02)00007-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Thomas (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Soil pH and soil acidity</article-title><source>Methods of soil analysis: chemical methods</source><publisher-name>Soil Science Society of America Inc</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Madison</publisher-loc><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmke</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Loeppert</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltanpour</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabatabai</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumner</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>490</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Vr&#x000e5;lstad et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vr&#x000e5;lstad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Todorovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollenweber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdollahi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Karas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Buddensiek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><source>Description of leakage scenarios for consideration in the work in SP3</source><institution>Trondheim: SINTEF</institution><uri xlink:href="https://www.mirecol-co2.eu/download/D08.1%20-%20Description%20of%20leakage%20scenarios.pdf">https://www.mirecol-co2.eu/download/D08.1%20-%20Description%20of%20leakage%20scenarios.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Wei, Maroto-Valer &#x00026; Steven (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Maroto-Valer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Environmental consequences of potential leaks of CO2 in soil</article-title><source>Energy Procedia</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>3224</fpage><lpage>3230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.egypro.2011.02.239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>West et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Annunziatellis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaubien</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Breward</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>de&#x000a0;Angelis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gemeni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Graziani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwosdz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koukouzas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Libertini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thatcher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziogou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Comparison of the impacts of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> soil gas concentrations on selected European terrestrial environments</article-title><source>International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijggc.2015.07.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Wu et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>The impacts of introduced CO<sub>2</sub> flux on maize/alfalfa and soil</article-title><source>International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijggc.2014.02.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Yang et&#x000a0;al. (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Activities of starch hydrolytic enzymes and sucrose-phosphate synthase in the stems of rice subjected to water stress during grain filling</article-title><source>Journal of experimental botany</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>2169</fpage><lpage>2179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jexbot/52.364.2169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11604456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Zhang et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>CO<sub>2</sub> leakage-induced vegetation decline is primarily driven by decreased soil O<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>Journal of Environmental Management</source><volume>171</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2016.02.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26899305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Zhao et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Impact of naturally leaking carbon dioxide on soil properties and ecosystems in the Qinghai-Tibet plateau</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-02500-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127051</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>