<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">abd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5726681</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20176373</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Eosinophilic annular erythema in adults: report of two cases and
review of the literature<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heras</surname><given-names>Marta Oliv&#x000e9;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>Noelia P&#x000e9;rez</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sancho</surname><given-names>Maribel Iglesias</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>Pablo Umbert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label> Department of Dermatology, Hospital Sagrat Cor - Barcelona,
Spain.</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label> Department of Pathological Anatomy, Hospital General de Catalunya -
Barcelona, Spain.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Mailing address: Marta Oliv&#x000e9; Heras, Hospital Universitari
Sagrat Cor C/ Viladomat 288 08029 Barcelona, Spain. Email:
<email>marta_olive_1987@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><season>Sep-Oct</season><year>2017</year></pub-date><!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Sep-Oct</season><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>92</volume><issue>5 Suppl 1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2017 by Anais Brasileiros de
Dermatologia</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any
medium provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We herein report two cases of eosinophilic annular erythema in adults, which is
rare. In both patients, lesions developed rapidly in few days and were located
mainly on the trunk, buttocks, and extremities. Diagnosis was histopathological,
with typical features including acute dermal inflammatory infiltrate with
abundant eosinophils. One of the patients recurred after treatment on three
occasions and finally cured spontaneously. The second patient recurred once and
was then successfully treated with topical clobetasol. Clinical and
histopathological features of eosinophilic annular erythema in adults have
rarely been reported. A review of the literature and discussion of relationship
with Wells syndrome are also included.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cellulitis</kwd><kwd>Clobetasol</kwd><kwd>Eosinophils</kwd><kwd>Erythema</kwd><kwd>Steroids</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Eosinophilic annular erythema (EAE) is an uncommon benign acute eosinophilic
dermatosis of unknown etiology, originally described in children.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> EAE is clinically characterized by recurrent annular,
erythematous-edematous, pruritic lesions with a centrifugal growth pattern. A
limited number of EAE cases in adolescents and adults have been reported to date.
<sup><xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> We herein add two new adult cases of this rare entity, which
shared clinical and histopathologic features that enabled this diagnosis. We also
provide insight in the understanding of its possible relationship with Wells
syndrome.</p></sec><sec><title>CASE REPORT</title><p><bold>Case 1.</bold> A 74-year-old man presented with an annular lesion, on the
lateral aspect of the thorax, which appeared two weeks prior to the consultation.
Its growth was centrifugal with erythematous-edematous margins, and a minimally
scaly center (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). At the moment, a
punch-biopsy was performed. Histopathological examination showed a perivascular and
interstitial mixed infiltrate with abundant eosinophils, but without evidence of
flame figures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). Direct
immunofluorescence test was negative. With the suspicion of Lyme disease, treatment
with doxycycline was initiated. Laboratory tests including complete blood count,
C-reactive protein, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, renal and liver function and
<italic>Borrelia burgdorferi&#x02019;s</italic> serology were unrevealing.</p><p>
<fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>An annular lesion on one side of the thorax with erythematous-edematous
margins, and a minimally scaly center</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="abd-92-05-s1-0065-g01"/></fig>
</p><p>
<fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>A:</bold> Hyperplasia of the epidermis. Perivascular and
interstitial (arrow) mixed infiltrate with abundant eosinophils. Absence
of flame figures and vasculitis (Hematoxylin &#x00026; eosin, X10).
<bold>B:</bold> A cluster of eosinophils (circle), more abundant
around the central vessel (Hematoxylin &#x00026; eosin, X40)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="abd-92-05-s1-0065-g02"/></fig>
</p><p>The patient underwent three recurrences that were treated with topical clobetasol
propionate cream. Three months later, a further recurrence healed spontaneously.</p><p><bold>Case 2. A</bold> 75-year-old man presented with migrating, minimally scaly,
annular lesions located on the trunk, buttocks, and limbs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>). Routine laboratory tests did not disclose any
abnormality and included complete blood count, C-reactive protein, erythrocyte
sedimentation rate, renal and liver function. A biopsy was taken and the
histopathological examination revealed a chronic perivascular and interstitial
inflammatory infiltrate with moderate amount of eosinophils in the superficial as
well as in the deep dermis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>). Flame
figures were absent. Direct immunofluorescence test was negative. The patient, with
the clinical orientation of eosinophilic dermatosis, was treated with oral
corticosteroids. Six months later, there was a recurrence, which was successfully
treated with topical clobetasol, with complete clearance of the plaques.</p><p>
<fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Minimally scaly, annular, erythematous plaques on the buttocks and
trunk</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="abd-92-05-s1-0065-g03"/></fig>
</p><p>
<fig id="f4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>A:</bold> Superficial and deep dermatitis, perivascular and
extending to the interstitium with presence of lymphocytes and plasma
cells, as well as eosinophils. (Hematoxylin &#x00026; eosin, X8).
<bold>B:</bold> Presence of eosinophils (arrow) in the interstitium
and inside a blood vessel (Hematoxylin &#x00026; eosin, X40)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="abd-92-05-s1-0065-g04"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>EAE is a benign eosinophilic dermatosis with excellent prognosis. The first
description by Peterson and Jarratt in 1981 included only pediatric
patients.<sup><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Thus, it was
initially named annular erythema of infancy. Children fulfilling the author&#x02019;s
diagnostic criteria of EAE, usually healthy, showed slowly expanding arcuate or
urticaria-like lesions. Skin manifestations were cyclic and persisted for some days
up to weeks or months. Histologically, the authors described a perivascular
lymphohistiocytic infiltrate with a prominent eosinophilic component and no
alteration at the epidermic level. <sup><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p><p>The first adult case of EAE was described by Kahofer <italic>et al.</italic> in 2000.
<sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> They found similarities
with the previously described EAE in children. Therefore, they decided to treat the
patient with hydroxychloroquine, with optimal response.</p><p>In further published cases in following years, a possible association of EAE with
autoimmune thyroid disease, chronic borreliosis, and renal cell carcinoma has been
suggested. <sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> In most adult patients, regarding clinical
manifestations, EAE presents as recurrent annular papules that evolve into palpable
erythematous arches or rings.</p><p>Microscopic findings of the reviewed literature are identical for adult and pediatric
patients. Proposed clinical differential diagnoses included: Wells syndrome,
erythema chronicum migrans, erythema annulare centrifugum, erythema gyratum repens,
and pemphigoid. After hematoxylin and eosin staining, histopathological pattern was
only compatible with Wells syndrome or eosinophilic cellulitis, but a final
diagnosis of EAE was achieved. Wells syndrome is histologically defined by an
interstitial infiltrate of eosinophils, with lymphocytes and histiocytes. The
infiltrate is usually more impressive in the deep dermis. Eosinophilic-staining
flame figures consisting of collagen fibers coated with eosinophil granule proteins
are a hallmark of this entity. In our patients diffuse inflammatory infiltrate in
the dermis with abundant eosinophils was observed, but neither the so-called flame
figures nor the vesicular change were present.</p><p>The major series of EAE cases, to our knowledge, corresponds to a multicentric study
including 10 patients that was published in 2013 by El-Khalawany et al.<sup><xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> The authors described typical
clinical presentation very similar to ours, and also included histopathological
study. In the article some histopathological differential features seemed to
correlate with the age of the lesions. Presence of flame figures and mucin
deposition was observed in some instances. Those patients had a chronic course and
were resistant to treatment with systemic corticosteroids alone or in combination
with hydroxychloroquine and cyclosporine. The authors, therefore, concluded that EAE
was a peculiar clinical variant in the spectrum of Wells syndrome. It is our
understanding that maybe the worse response to the treatment in some of these
patients corresponded to underdiagnosed Wells syndrome and not EAE with well-defined
criteria.</p><p>Regarding biochemical tests, blood eosinophilia and high serum levels of interleukin
5 can be found in patients with Wells syndrome.<sup><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> As we already stated, no blood eosinophilia was found in our
two patients. Some authors defend that peripheral blood eosinophilia and absence of
response to antimalarial drugs would be two distinctive aspects of Wells syndrome
when compared with EAE.<sup><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Finally,
EAE as well as Wells syndrome can present recurrences and spontaneous resolution
after some months or years.</p><p>Regarding the clinical course, rapid disappearance of lesions of EAE with systemic
corticoids is expected in most cases, although other authors have failed to find
such a good response. <sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> In one of our patients, lesions
recurred after discontinuation of corticosteroids but clobetasol cream was used for
the treatment of recurrences with good response. In some cases reported in the
literature, lesions cleared with antimalarial drugs. <sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Other
authors have also suggested the combination of oral prednisone and chloroquine or
cyclosporine as possible alternatives. <sup><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p><p>In summary, although some authors regard EAE as a variant of Wells syndrome, we
believe that some subtle differences allow this differential diagnosis. Despite the
clinical similarity of both diseases, in EAE the inflammatory infiltrate is mainly
perivascular and no flame figures are observed. Peripheral eosinophilia is absent,
better pharmacological response might be expected and full recovery is obtained.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflict of Interests: None.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1"><label>*</label><p>Study conducted at the Hospital Universitari Sagrat Cor - Barcelona, Spain.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>Financial Support: None.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>AO Jr</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarratt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Annular erythema of infancy</article-title><source>Arch Dermatol</source><year>1981</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7212726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eosinophilic annular erythema: successful response to ultraviolet
B therapy</article-title><source>Clin Exp Dermatol</source><year>2015</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>883</fpage><lpage>886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25958878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sempau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Larralde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Staiger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eosinophilic anular erythema</article-title><source>Dermatol Online J</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Girgis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kossard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eosinophilic annular erythema: a subset of Wells' syndrome or a
distinct entity?</article-title><source>Australas J Dermatol</source><year>2008</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18638225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Pesta&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuneu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zubizarreta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eritema anular eosinof&#x000ed;lico</article-title><source>Actas Dermosifilogr</source><year>2004</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>304</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kahofer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabmaier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aberer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of eosinophilic annular erythema with
chloroquine</article-title><source>Acta Derm Venereol</source><year>2000</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10721850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mebazaa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghariani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Denguezli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sriha</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Belajouza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Eosinophilic annular erythema responsive to
chloroquin</article-title><source>Eur J Dermatol</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Khalawany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Mutairi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaaban</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eosinophilic annular erythema is a peculiar subtype in the
spectrum of Wells syndrome: a multicentre long-term follow-up
study</article-title><source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>979</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22731886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Espa&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Sola</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wells' syndrome (eosinophilic cellulitis): correlation between
clinical activity, eosinophil levels, eosinophil cation protein and
interleukin-5</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>1999</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10215782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Izadpanah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Borsuk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Watters</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and management of eosinophilic cellulitis (Wells'
syndrome): A case series and literature review</article-title><source>Can J Plast Surg</source><year>2012</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23730155</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>