<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6305194</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ery341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ery341</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Plant&#x02014;Environment Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Relationship between fluorescence yield and photochemical yield under water stress and intermediate light conditions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xuejuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>Xingguo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>moxg@igsnrr.ac.cn</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Shi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Suxia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Key Laboratory of Water Cycle and Related Land Surface Processes, Institute of Geographic Sciences and Natural Resources Research, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Chaoyang District, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shijingshan District, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>College of Resources and Environment/Sino-Danish Center, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shijingshan District, Beijing, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence: <email>moxg@igsnrr.ac.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-10-08"><day>08</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>08</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>70</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ery341.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Under intermediate and low light conditions, the relationship between fluorescence yield and photochemical yield in water-stressed C<sub>4</sub> leaves is non-linear. Non-photochemical quenching yield regulates this relationship.</p></abstract><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The dynamics between fluorescence (F<sub>s</sub>) yield and photochemical (P) yield in a changing environment are essential for understanding the relationship between photosynthesis and fluorescence. The ratio of F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield tends to be constant under high light intensity, but the relationship between these two yields, and its response to environmental conditions, need to be explored further under intermediate and low light. In this study, we performed leaf-scale measurements of fluorescence parameters by pulse-amplitude modulation (PAM) technology in summer maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) plants grown under intermediate light conditions in a climate chamber. Plants were treated as moderately water stressed and non-water stressed. Results showed that a decrease in P yield was accompanied by increases in F<sub>s</sub> yield and non-photochemical quenching (NPQ) yield in response to moderate water stress under intermediate and low light conditions. F<sub>s</sub> yield was negatively correlated with P yield under intermediate and low light conditions when there was sufficient soil water in the root zone. Under water stress, the correlation between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield was negative in low light, but became positive under higher light levels. F<sub>s</sub> yield was negatively related to P yield when NPQ yield was low; however, they were synergistically and positively associated when excessive light dissipation was dominated by NPQ.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Chlorophyll fluorescence</kwd><kwd>intermediate light</kwd><kwd>leaf scale</kwd><kwd>pulse-amplitude modulation</kwd><kwd>photochemistry</kwd><kwd>summer maize</kwd><kwd>water stress</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Natural Science Foundation of China</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source><award-id>41471026</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Chlorophyll fluorescence is red and far-red light (650&#x02013;800 nm) emitted by chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> pigments a few nanoseconds after light absorption (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Verrelst <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). It is sensitive to short-term environmental stresses such as drought or nutrient deficiency, among others. (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Souza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Dobrowski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Zarco-Tejada <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Tubuxin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). Chlorophyll fluorescence has been used as a non-destructive and non-intrusive probe in studies of plant photochemistry, physiology, and ecology (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Remotely sensed chlorophyll fluorescence from satellite imaging is providing new data sources to characterize the dynamics of gross photosynthesis at regional scale, increasing our ability to monitor and assess the effects of environmental stresses on the productivity of vegetation (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>).</p><p>Studies have shown that solar-induced fluorescence (SIF) is closely related to gross primary production (GPP) at regional or ecosystem scale (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>a</italic></xref>), especially when there is water stress (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). It has been reported that SIF and GPP are consistent in terms of spatial patterns and seasonal dynamics (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). SIF traces the variations of GPP much better than the enhanced vegetation index, normalized difference vegetation index, and land surface water index do (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Wagle <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). For example, during the 2012 drought event in the Great Plains of the USA, it was found that variations of SIF and GPP were consistent, and SIF declined more significantly than the normalized difference vegetation index (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Sun <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). As SIF is more sensitive to changes in vegetation photosynthesis and water status than greenness indices, it is a better indicator of photosynthesis (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). So far, some empirical linear relationships between SIF and GPP have been developed to directly estimate the productivity of vegetation using remote sensing of SIF (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Wagle <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p><p>Although some studies have demonstrated close associations between chlorophyll fluorescence and GPP (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>a</italic></xref>), the quantitative relationship and inherent mechanisms of the links between them are still not clear. In photosystem II (PSII), chlorophyll fluorescence, photochemical reactions, and non-photochemical quenching (NPQ) are three pathways that consume all of the light energy absorbed by the leaf (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). These three pathways are closely associated, and the sum of fluorescence (F<sub>s</sub>) yield, photochemical (P) yield, and NPQ yield is considered to equal 1 (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Hmimina <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>b</italic></xref>). F<sub>s</sub> yield is the fraction of absorbed light energy re-emitted as fluorescence, and represents the light use efficiency of fluorescence (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). The P yield of PSII, which is the fraction of absorbed photons used for photochemical reactions, provides an estimation of photochemical light use efficiency (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). The surplus part of the absorbed light energy is dissipated as heat (i.e. NPQ), including the constitutive thermal dissipation and variable energy-dependent heat dissipation. A simple competition model has been proposed for these three processes (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Butler, 1978</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>). <italic>In situ</italic> measurements or mechanistic model simulations have revealed that the relationship between fluorescence yield and photochemical yield is not perfectly linear (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cui <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>) and is influenced by the absorbed photosynthetically active radiation (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cui <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). At present, our understanding of the non-linear relationship between the fluorescence and photochemical yields is still insufficient. It has been observed that the ratio of the F<sub>s</sub> yield to the P yield tends to be constant under high light condition, that is, in the imaging time of satellite SIF (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). However, under intermediate and low light conditions (i.e. the early morning and late afternoon), the relationship between these two yields is not clear, and needs to be further investigated.</p><p>Fluorescence and photochemical processes are sensitive to environmental stresses (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). In the context of climate change, droughts have become more frequent and severe around the world in recent decades (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Spinoni <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Drought has been reported to induce significant decreases of P yield and F<sub>s</sub>, and increases of NPQ (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Souza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Faraloni <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). However, few studies have explored the effects of water stress on the relationships between these parameters (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>).</p><p>This study explored the fluorescence and photochemical physiology in response to water stress under intermediate and low light conditions. It is hypothesized that the relationship between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield is not perfectly linear, and depends on water status and light intensity. As summer maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) is one of the most important and widely planted C<sub>4</sub> crops (in which photorespiration is negligible) in the world, we conducted an experiment with summer maize in a climate chamber with two soil moisture treatments (moderate water stress and no water stress). The fluorescence parameters were measured in leaves by using a pulse-amplitude modulation (PAM) fluorometer. This study aimed to explore (i) the relationship between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield under intermediate and low light conditions, and (ii) the effects of water stress on F<sub>s</sub> yield, P yield, and the relationship between them. The results provide new knowledge about the interaction between leaf photochemistry and fluorescence, which is crucial for improving the estimation of vegetation productivity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Description of the experiment</title><p>This experiment was conducted between 12 October 2016 and 24 February 2017 using the Water Transformation Dynamical Processes Experimental Device (WATDPED; <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) established in the Institute of Geographic Sciences and Natural Resources Research, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China. The WATDPED consists of a climate chamber with two 3 &#x000d7; 2 &#x000d7; 3 m (length &#x000d7; width &#x000d7; height) lysimeters. The lysimeters contain alluvial soil taken from farmlands in the North China Plain, which is composed of 60.22% sand, 39.09% silt, and 0.70% clay. The field capacity is 25.12% and residual moisture is 2.66%. The climate chamber has an artificial light source composed of metal halide lamps and sodium lamps with a maximum illumination of 30000 lx. There are two centrifugal humidifiers to control the humidity and an air conditioning system to control the air temperature.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of the WATDPED (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Tan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34101"/></fig><p>Seeds of summer maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L., cultivar JD68) were sown in soil with an intra-row space of 40 cm and inter-row space of 30 cm; there were 36 plants in each lysimeter. According to the photosynthetic light response curve of summer maize (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Stirling <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), when photosynthetically active radiation (PAR) is greater than ~700 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, the photosynthetic rate increases slowly with increasing PAR, while when PAR is lower than ~450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, the photosynthetic rate increases rapidly with PAR. Thus, PAR in the range of 450&#x02013;700 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> was taken as the intermediate light condition and PAR lower than 450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> was taken as the low light condition for the summer maize in this study. In order to explore the relationship between P yield and F<sub>s</sub> yield under intermediate and low light conditions, the light intensity above the canopy was kept at 700 &#x000b5;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> during the whole growth period by adjusting the distance between the canopy top and the lamps. The light source was turned on at 06.00 h and off at 18.00 h automatically, so that the plants were exposed to a 12 h photoperiod. In the climate chamber, variations of 3 h averaged air temperature and daily humidity were set according to records made at the Beijing climatological station (116&#x000b0;28&#x02032;E, 39&#x000b0;48&#x02032;N) during the period 16 June to 29 October 2010, to represent normal climate conditions (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Chemical fertilizers were applied at the seedling, early jointing, and tasseling stages (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Records of the growing stages of summer maize and the use of fertilizer during the experiment</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growing stage</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAS<break/>(NS)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAS<break/>(WS)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fertilizer</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amount of fertilizer (g m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seedling</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#x02013;29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#x02013;34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound fertilizer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jointing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x02013;59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#x02013;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tasseling</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60&#x02013;74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65&#x02013;82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filling</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75&#x02013;105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83&#x02013;115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maturity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106&#x02013;130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116&#x02013;135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0001"><p>DAS, days after sowing; NS, non-water stress; WS, water stress.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Variations in 3 h averaged air temperature (Ta) and daily relative humidity (RH) during the summer maize growth period. These values were used as the inputs for the climate conditions, controlled by an air conditioner and centrifugal humidifiers, in the climate chamber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34102"/></fig><p>Plants in the two lysimeters were subjected to two treatments, moderate water stress (WS) and non-water stress (NS). The soil water contents (% by volume) of the root layer (25 cm depth) were monitored automatically by 5TE soil water sensors (Decagon, Pullman, WA, USA) and were maintained at 45&#x02013;50% of field capacity for the WS treatment and no less than 80% of field capacity for the NS treatment by irrigation. The weight of each lysimeter was recorded automatically at 30-min intervals with a precision of 180 g, and the weights were used to estimate the changes in evapotranspiration (ET). A water stress index (WSI) was calculated as</p><disp-formula><mml:math id="m1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>WSI</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(1)</label></disp-formula><p>where <italic>&#x003b8;</italic> is the measured soil water content of the root layer, <inline-formula><mml:math id="n100"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the residual moisture content, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="n101"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the field capacity. The range of values of WSI is 0&#x02013;1. When <italic>&#x003b8;</italic> &#x0003e; <inline-formula><mml:math id="n102"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, WSI is taken as 1.</p><p>For the measurements of growth indicators and fluorescence parameters, five plants in each treatment were randomly selected as biological replicates. Three fully expanded top leaves from each plant were sampled to measure chlorophyll content, and the chlorophyll content was calculated as the mean value of the three measurements. Fluorescence parameters were measured using the third fully expanded top leaf of each selected plant. During the growth period, measurements were made on the same plants, but the top expanded leaves may be updated in different growing stages. The chlorophyll content and fluorescence parameters of summer maize plants were measured in the middle of the leaf at 5-day intervals during the growth period. As we focused on photochemical yield in PSII rather than CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation, photosynthesis in terms of gas exchange was not measured in this experiment.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Measurement of growth indicators</title><p>Basic growth indicators including plant height, leaf area index (LAI), and relative leaf chlorophyll content were measured. TheSPAD-502 Plus chlorophyll meter (Konica Minolta Sensing Inc., Japan) was used to measure the relative chlorophyll content. The relative amount is an indexed estimation of chlorophyll content with the value of 0&#x02013;99, which is determined by measuring leaf transmittance coefficients at 650 nm and 940 nm. The length and width of each leaf were measured to estimate the leaf area (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Tan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), and LAI was calculated as the total leaf area divided by the projected land surface area of the canopy.</p><p>After harvest, the fresh weight of each corncob in the two treatments was measured. The dry matter and the mass of 100 randomly selected seeds (the 100-seed mass) were determined after corncobs had been oven-dried for 1 hour at 105 &#x000b0;C and 48 hours at 85 &#x000b0;C. The weights of oven-dried leaves, stems, and roots of three randomly selected plants in each treatment were also measured to explore the biomass allocation strategies of plants in response to water stress.</p><p>To explore the effects of leaf water levels on fluorescence parameters, in the early tasseling stage (65 days after sowing), after measurements of fluorescence parameters had been made on five fully expanded leaves of one randomly selected plant in each treatment, leaves were sampled and oven-dried for 1 hour at 105 &#x000b0;C and 48 hours at 85 &#x000b0;C. Leaf water content (LWC) was estimated as follows:</p><disp-formula><mml:math id="m2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mi>%</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(2)</label></disp-formula><p>where <italic>FW</italic> and <italic>DW</italic> are the fresh weight and dry weight, respectively, of each leaf.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Measurement of chlorophyll fluorescence parameters</title><p>Chlorophyll fluorescence parameters (described in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) were measured using an OS5P+ PAM fluorometer (Opti-Sciences Inc., Tyngsboro, MA, USA). Before measuring dark-adapted parameters, leaves were adapted to dark by applying leaf clips for 30 minutes (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Dobranszki and Mendler-Drienyovszki, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Then, the minimum and maximum fluorescence of dark-adapted leaves (F<sub>o</sub> and F<sub>m</sub>, respectively) were measured with leaves exposed to modulated light [660 nm light-emitting diode (LED) light source with a 690 nm short pass filter, 0.5 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>] and saturated flash light (white LED with 690 nm short pass filter, 11250 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> with a duration of 0.8 s), respectively. The maximum quantum yield of PSII of dark-adapted leaf (F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub>) was then calculated by using the software in the fluorometer.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Fluorescence parameters measured by the OS5P+ fluorometer</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>m</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximal fluorescence after dark adaptation</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum photochemical quantum yield under dark adaptation: F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub>=(F<sub>m</sub>&#x02013;F<sub>o</sub>)/F<sub>m</sub> (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), where F<sub>o</sub> is the minimal fluorescence after dark adaptation</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>m</sub>&#x002b9;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximal fluorescence under the light condition</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>s</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steady-state fluorescence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P yield</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actual quantum yield of PSII photochemistry, which indicates the proportion of light energy used in photochemistry by PSII under steady-state photosynthetic light conditions. P yield=(F<sub>m</sub>&#x002b9;-F<sub>s</sub>)/F<sub>m</sub>&#x002b9; (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Genty <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPQ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-photochemical quenching, a process in which excess absorbed light energy is dissipated as heat. NPQ=(F<sub>m</sub>-F<sub>m</sub>&#x002b9;)/F<sub>m</sub>&#x002b9; (<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Tietz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>After the measurement of dark-adapted parameters, the leaf clips were removed and the leaves were exposed to ambient light condition for 30 minutes. Then, light-adapted parameters were measured using the Yield protocol of the fluorometer. After leaves had been adapted in actinic light (white LED, 100 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) for 5 minutes, fluorescence reached steady state (F<sub>s</sub>). Then, the maximum fluorescence of light-adapted leaves (F<sub>m</sub>&#x002b9;) was measured by illumination with saturated flash light (the same as described above for dark-adapted leaves). The actual quantum yield of PSII (P yield) was then calculated from F<sub>s</sub> and F<sub>m</sub>&#x002b9;. Next, the light-adapted parameters under actinic light intensity of 500 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> were measured.</p><p>Finally, rapid light response curves (RLCs) of F<sub>s</sub> and F<sub>m</sub>&#x002b9; were determined by the RLC protocol of the fluorometer with incident PAR programmed at values of 100, 150, 200, 250, 300, 350, 400, 450, 500, 600, and 700 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, which took 2 minutes for each leaf. Parameters under dark and light conditions were measured at the same position for each leaf sample.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Calculation of fluorescence yield and NPQ yield</title><p>A fluorometer was used to measure the P yield and the pulse signal intensity of F<sub>s</sub>, but it cannot directly determine the F<sub>s</sub> yield. In order to explore the relationship between the two light-use efficiencies (i.e. F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield), the method proposed in the Soil-Canopy Observation of Photosynthesis and Energy model (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>b</italic></xref>) was used to calculate the F<sub>s</sub> yield. As heat dissipation is one of the three pathways that consumes the absorbed photons in the photosynthetic apparatus, the NPQ yield is achieved simultaneously as an auxiliary. In this method, heat dissipation is partitioned as the constitutive dark-adapted thermal dissipation (<italic>d</italic>) and the energy-dependent heat dissipation (<italic>n</italic>) under the light condition. The yields are calculated as follows, using the method described by <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, (2015)</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., (2014)</xref>, and <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> (2016<italic>b</italic></xref>):</p><disp-formula><mml:math id="m3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(3)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><mml:math id="m4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(4)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><mml:math id="m5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(5)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><mml:math id="m6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(6)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><mml:math id="m7"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(7)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><mml:math id="m8"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.03</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0773</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0.87</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(8)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><mml:math id="m9"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(9)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><mml:math id="m10"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(10)</label></disp-formula><p>where &#x003a6; is the probability of the fate of absorbed photons with subscripts <italic>f</italic> for fluorescence, <italic>p</italic> for photochemical reactions, and <italic>n</italic> and <italic>d</italic> for heat dissipation (the sum of <inline-formula><mml:math id="m11"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="n103"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the NPQ yield), respectively; <inline-formula><mml:math id="m12"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the rate constant for fluorescence, taken as 0.05 (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>); <inline-formula><mml:math id="m13"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the rate coefficient of dark-adapted thermal dissipation, which is a function of temperature (<italic>T</italic>) (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>); <inline-formula><mml:math id="m14"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="m15"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the rate coefficients of energy-dependent heat dissipation and photochemistry, respectively (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>); <inline-formula><mml:math id="m16"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the maximal fluorescence after dark adaptation; <inline-formula><mml:math id="m17"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the maximal fluorescence under the light condition; and <inline-formula><mml:math id="m18"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the steady-state fluorescence. <inline-formula><mml:math id="m19"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="m190"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="m20"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="m21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can all be measured directly by the OS5P+ fluorometer.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Differences in measurements between the two water treatments, and the correlations between F<sub>s</sub> yield, P yield, and NPQ yield, were analyzed. The <italic>t</italic>-test was used for comparisons between the mean values of measurements under the WS and NS conditions. As the time-series samples or variables changing with light intensity were not normally distributed and were paired across the two water treatments, the pairwise Wilcoxon non-parametric method was used to test differences in these parameters between the two treatments. To evaluate the relationship between two variables, regression analysis was performed with the coefficient of determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) to describe its level of significance. Pearson and Spearman correlation coefficients were used for the linear and non-linear correlation analysis, respectively. Statistical significance was accepted when <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Results</title><sec id="s9"><title>Effects of water stress on growth of summer maize</title><p>During the growth period, water stress indices for the NS treatment exceeded 0.77, whereas those for the WS treatment were lower, ranging from 0.38 to 0.48 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). The irrigation amounts during the whole growth period were 246 mm for the NS treatment and 39 mm for the WS treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). ET was significantly different between the two treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>); total ET during the whole growth period was 259 mm for the NS treatment and 109 mm for the WS treatment.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Variations in (A) water stress index and (B) evapotranspiration (ET); (C) total amount of irrigation (Irr) and ET during the whole growth period for the water stress (WS) and non-water stress (NS) treatments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34103"/></fig><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, there were significant differences between WS and NS plants in terms of plant height, LAI, and leaf chlorophyll content during the growth period (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 for height and LAI, <italic>P</italic>=0.001 for chlorophyll content). The maximum stalk heights of NS plants were significantly higher than those in the WS treatment (<italic>P</italic>=0.047), with mean values of 186.7 cm and 171.3 cm, respectively. The maximum LAI of plants in the NS treatment was significantly higher than that for the WS treatment (<italic>P</italic>=0.031).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Mean height, (B) leaf area index (LAI), and (C) relative chlorophyll content of water-stressed (WS) and non-water stressed (NS) summer maize. Data points are mean values obtained from a set of five plant samples; error bars represent &#x000b1;1 SD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34104"/></fig><p>Significant differences between WS and NS treatments were also observed for indicators of crop yield (<italic>P</italic>=0.017 for dry matter, <italic>P</italic>=0.047 for fresh weight, and <italic>P</italic>=0.045 for 100-seed mass). Relative to the NS treatment, the mean dry matter of corncobs and the 100-seed mass in plants subjected to WS were reduced by 28.6% and 20.4%, respectively (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A</xref>). The water use efficiency (defined here as crop yield divided by ET) of summer maize was 3.12 kg m<sup>&#x02013;3</sup> in the WS treatment and 1.95 kg m<sup>&#x02013;3</sup> in the NS treatment. The proportions of dry mass in the roots, stems, and leaves were 23.4%, 51.0%, and 25.6%, respectively, for plants in the WS treatment, and 16.2%, 54.9% and 28.9%, respectively, for plants in the NS treatment (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5B</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>(A) Dry matter, fresh weight, and 100-seed mass per corncob (<italic>n</italic>=33; error bars represent &#x000b1;1 SD); (B) mean proportions of biomass in the roots, stems, and leaves for the water stress (WS) and non-water stress (NS) treatments (<italic>n</italic>=3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34105"/></fig></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Effects of water stress on fluorescence, photochemistry, and NPQ</title><p>In PSII, the absorbed light has three fates: the photochemical reaction, heat dissipation, and fluorescence emissions by chlorophyll (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). There are trade-offs between these three yields when plants acclimate to a changing environment (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>). Fluorescence parameters measured in plants subjected to different water treatments and light conditions in two critical growth stages (the jointing and filling stages) are shown in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>. Significant differences in F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub> measurements between the two treatments were observed in the filling stage (<italic>P</italic>=0.013) but not in the jointing stage (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6G</xref>). This difference may be related to the smaller water deficit in the jointing stage than in the filling stage (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). Nevertheless, in both stages, the F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub> of WS leaves was lower than that of NS leaves, revealing the negative effects of water stress on the potential photon quantum yield. The actual P yields were also lower in the WS condition (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6C</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">D</xref>), whereas F<sub>s</sub> yields increased under WS (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">B</xref>), indicating that more absorbed light was emitted as fluorescence. The NPQ yields in the two water treatments were consistent with those of F<sub>s</sub> yields (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6E</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">F</xref>), because under the WS condition a higher proportion of energy was dissipated as heat to avoid damage resulting from excess light. The differences in P yields and NPQ yields between the two water treatments were significant in both the jointing and filling stages under the low light condition (PAR=100 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 and <italic>P</italic>=0.023 for P yield in the jointing and filling stages, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 and <italic>P</italic>=0.023 for NPQ yield in the jointing and filling stages, respectively), but were significant only in the filling stage under the intermediate light condition (PAR=500 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>; <italic>P</italic>=0.008 and <italic>P</italic>=0.009 for P yield and NPQ yield, respectively). The F<sub>s</sub> yields of the two water treatments showed significant differences in the jointing stage under the low light condition (<italic>P</italic>=0.033), and in both stages under the intermediate light condition (<italic>P</italic>=0.026 in the jointing stage and <italic>P</italic>=0.015 in the filling stage). Light intensity also affected the three yields. F<sub>s</sub> yields and NPQ yields were significantly higher, while P yields were significantly lower, under the intermediate light condition (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">D</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">F</xref>) compared with the low light condition (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">E</xref>) (all <italic>P</italic> values &#x0003c;0.001).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Comparisons of F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub>, F<sub>s</sub> yield, P yield, and NPQ yield in leaves of summer maize between the water stress (WS) and non-water stress (NS) treatments at the jointing stage (45 days after sowing) and filling stage (90 days after sowing) under (A, C, E) low light (PAR=100 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) and (B, D, F) intermediate light (PAR=500 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) conditions. Data are based on measurements made on five plants in each treatment. The top and bottom of the box represent the quartiles; the horizontal line in the box represents the median value; the whiskers represent &#x000b1;1 SD. Mean values in the two treatments were compared by the <italic>t</italic>-test; different letters indicate significant differences: *<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34106"/></fig><p>In the early tasseling stage, five fully expanded leaves from plants subjected to each treatment were oven-dried to estimate LWC after measuring the fluorescence parameters. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>, the differences in leaf water statuses between the two treatments were significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001), with LWC being 75.7% for WS leaves and 79.3% for NS leaves. The rapid light response curves of F<sub>s</sub> yield, P yield, and NPQ yield also showed significant differences between the WS and NS conditions (<italic>P</italic>=0.003 for all three yields). Under the WS condition, P yield was lower and NPQ yield and F<sub>s</sub> yield were higher than the respective yields in the NS treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B&#x02013;D</xref>). The P yield decreased with increasing PAR, indicating higher light use efficiency under low light levels. The increase of NPQ yield with increasing PAR indicated that more absorbed light was dissipated under higher light levels. The response of F<sub>s</sub> yield to light intensity was not linear: F<sub>s</sub> yield increased with PAR when PAR was &#x0003c;400 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, and then decreased as PAR increased from 450 to 700 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>Leaf water contents and rapid light response curves of (B) F<sub>s</sub> yield, (C) P yield, and (D) NPQ yield in the water stress (WS) and non-water stress (NS) treatments measured in the early tasseling stage (65 days after sowing). Data are based on measurements made on five fully expanded leaves on one plant in each treatment. Error bars represent &#x000b1;1 SD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34107"/></fig></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Effects of water stress on the relationship between photochemical and fluorescence yields</title><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>, there is a tipping point for the light response curve of F<sub>s</sub> yield at light intensity ~450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>. In view of this finding, we explored the relationships between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield at light intensities lower and higher than 450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). We found that the correlation of F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield was negative under the low light condition (PAR &#x0003c;450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) for both the WS (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.400, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01) and NS (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.490, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01) treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). When PAR exceeded 450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, the relationships were different. P yield and F<sub>s</sub> yield were still negatively related in the NS condition (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.109, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01), although the correlation was weaker. By contrast, for the WS treatment, the relationship was now positive (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.071, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01). Generally, under intermediate and low light conditions, higher light intensity causes the closure of photosynthetic reaction centers by reducing the primary quinone acceptor of PSII (Q<sub>A</sub>); consequently, photochemical quenching is reduced while fluorescence intensifies (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Thus, F<sub>s</sub> yield is negatively related to P yield. However, for the WS treatment, due to the dominant role of NPQ in dissipating excessive light (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield both decreased with increases of PAR above 450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>), leading to a positive relationship between the two yields. Therefore, light intensity and water status are critical factors that comprehensively regulate the relationship between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p>Relationships between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield at PAR levels lower or higher than 450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> for the (A) water stress and (B) non-water stress treatments. The fit line and the corresponding equation are shown in the same colour.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34108"/></fig><p>The relationships between the yields of the three energy consumption pathways under low light conditions (PAR at 100 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) were further explored. For the WS treatment, the NPQ yield was negatively and linearly related to the P yield (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.9997, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) and non-linearly related to the F<sub>s</sub> yield (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.317, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01) (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9A</xref>), resulting in a non-linear relationship between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.304, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01) (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9C</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9C</xref>, the F<sub>s</sub> yield increased and then decreased as the P yield increased, along with the declining NPQ yield. When the P yield was below 0.40, NPQ played a dominant role in consuming light energy (NPQ yield &#x0003e;0.58), and the relationship between the F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield was positive. As the NPQ yield decreased (&#x0003c;0.58) and P yield increased (&#x0003e; 0.40), however, the F<sub>s</sub> yield decreased and was negatively correlated with the P yield (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9C</xref>). Under the NS condition (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9B</xref>, <xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">D</xref>), the F<sub>s</sub> yield and NPQ yield changed synergistically, and the P yield was negatively related to both the NPQ yield (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.9995, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) and the F<sub>s</sub> yield (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.269, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 9.</label><caption><p>Relationships between F<sub>s</sub> yield, P yield, and NPQ yield under low light conditions (PAR=100 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>). Blue symbols in (A) and (B) correspond to the right axis, and black symbols correspond to the left axis. The fit line and the corresponding equation are shown in the same color. Gradient colors in (C, D) denote the changes of NPQ yield.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery34109"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s13"><title>Effects of water stress on plant growth and photosynthetic physiology</title><p>Our study revealed that water stress reduced the proportion of dry matter contributed by stems and leaves, and increased that of roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). Plants under water stress transferred more biomass to roots in order to take up water from deeper soil to relieve the stress (<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Yin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Ge <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The lower proportion of the biomass attributable to leaves (or decreased LAI, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>) may also help the stressed plants adapt to the water-limited environment by reducing transpiration (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Craufurd <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). We also found that water use efficiency increased under the WS condition, as has also been reported in previous studies (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Craufurd <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Yin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p><p>Water stress has a significant influence on plant photochemical and fluorescence characteristics (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Faraloni <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The three fluorescence parameters (F<sub>s</sub>, P yield, and NPQ) can effectively identify water stress, as suggested by previous studies (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Souza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Mishra <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In this experiment, summer maize grown under intermediate light conditions and subjected to moderate water stress and non-water stress treatments showed significant differences in their photosynthetic physiology: the P yield decreased and the F<sub>s</sub> yield and NPQ yield increased in response to water stress.</p><p>P yield is directly related to photosynthesis since it quantifies the light-use efficiency of PSII. It is sensitive to stress and decreases under drought conditions (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Lu and Zhang, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Mishra <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The reduction of P yield associated with water stress has been reported in tomato (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Mishra <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), maize (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), cowpea (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Souza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), wheat (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Lu and Zhang, 1999</xref>), grapevine (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>), and aloe (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Hazrati <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). In these studies, the decrease of P yield was accompanied by an increase in NPQ. We found similar results in the present study. The physiological mechanism for the decreased P yield and the increased NPQ yield of C<sub>4</sub> plants under water stress can be explained as follows. Water stress induces stomatal closure (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Rosales <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Mathobo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Ouyang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>); as a consequence, the intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> concentration decreases, inducing a decline in the rate of carboxylation (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Baker and Rosenqvist, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Souza <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). This results in feedback on the photoreaction to reduce electron use efficiency and retard electron transport (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Then, more photosynthetic reaction centers are closed because reduced Q<sub>A</sub> cannot be reoxidized in time, resulting in the inhibition of photochemical quenching and an increase in fluorescence (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>). In addition, when the electron transport chain is saturated, protons accumulate and the thylakoid lumen pH decreases, which may amplify NPQ (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). In this case, electron and light energy are excessive (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), and fluorescence and NPQ are utilized to consume the excessive light. This explains the observed increase of F<sub>s</sub> yield in summer maize (a C<sub>4</sub> crop) under moderate water stress in this study.</p><p>The response of F<sub>s</sub> to water stress in C<sub>3</sub> plants can also help us understand the results observed in this study. Decreased fluorescence in C<sub>3</sub> plants in response to water stress has been reported (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>, 2002; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). For example, <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al</italic>. (1999</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) reported that F<sub>s</sub> or F<sub>s</sub>/F<sub>o</sub> of grapevines decreased under water stress, which may result from photorespiration (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Flexas and Medrano, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Photorespiration increases as the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration reduces due to stomatal closure under water stress (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Photorespiration consumes NADPH (triphosphopyridine nucleotide) (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>), which promotes electron transfer from reduced Q<sub>A</sub> to the secondary electron acceptor and thus quenches fluorescence (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>). Therefore, the fluorescence of C<sub>3</sub> plants decreases under water stress. However, when the photorespiration of C<sub>3</sub> plants was inhibited by exposing leaves to high CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations in the absence of O<sub>2</sub>, the decrease of F<sub>s</sub>/F<sub>o</sub> under water stress was suppressed and an increase of F<sub>s</sub>/F<sub>o</sub> in response to water stress was observed with PAR &#x0003c;600 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). This observation indicates that fluorescence may increase under water stress in intermediate and low light conditions when there is no photorespiration. This is consistent with observations made in this study. In addition, <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic> (2015)</xref> showed that the F<sub>s</sub> yield of C<sub>3</sub> plants under water stress decreased significantly at PAR of 300 or 500 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, but it increased (albeit not significantly) when PAR was &#x0003c;300 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>. In the present study, the increase of F<sub>s</sub> yield in response to moderate water stress was also observed for summer maize grown under intermediate and low light conditions (0&#x02013;700 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>).</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Relationships between photochemistry, fluorescence, and heat dissipation</title><p>Chlorophyll fluorescence is an effective indicator for accurately estimating gross photosynthesis (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Baker and Rosenqvist, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Some studies have found that fluorescence and photosynthesis are positively related (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). For example, the CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rate is positively related to F<sub>s</sub> measured by PAM in leaves of <italic>Camelina sativa</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Guanter <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> used a positive linear relationship to directly estimate global GPP by solar-induced fluorescence. However, a negative relationship between fluorescence and photosynthetic light use efficiency or P yield has also been reported (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Cheng, 2010</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Cheng (2010)</xref> stated that photosynthetic light use efficiency is negatively related to chlorophyll fluorescence due to their competition for light energy. In PSII, light energy is partitioned between photochemistry, heat dissipation, and chlorophyll fluorescence (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Guo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Under non-stress conditions, most light energy is channeled into photochemistry, with smaller amounts of energy destined for heat dissipation and fluorescence emission (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). In the presence of stress, more energy is dissipated to relieve the stress, but the trade-off between, and changes in, the three pathways are still unclear.</p><p>Recently, studies have reported that the relationship between GPP and fluorescence is affected by physiological and ecological factors, such as vegetation type (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Guan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), land surface temperature (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cui <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), irradiation (<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cui <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), LAI, and chlorophyll content (<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cui <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). This study revealed the relationship between fluorescence and photochemistry and the changes in this relationship depending on water status and light intensity. Light intensity is a crucial factor regulating the photosynthetic physiological processes (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Flexas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Cendrero-Mateo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cui <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Under low light conditions (PAR&#x0003c;450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>), NPQ was inhibited by the proton gradient (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Losciale <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) and F<sub>s</sub> yield increased, while P yield decreased with increasing light intensity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>); in this case, F<sub>s</sub> was negatively related to photochemistry. However, under water stress and intermediate light conditions of 450&#x02013;700 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, as the light intensity increased, the electron transport chain became saturated (as mentioned above). NPQ increased as protons accumulated and the thylakoid lumen pH decreased (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). In this case, fluorescence and photochemistry were both inhibited (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), resulting in a positive relationship between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Similar results have been reported in previous studies based on model simulations (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>).</p><p>We found that light energy used for photochemical reactions was negatively related to that emitted as fluorescence in the NS condition (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>). For leaves under the WS condition, we inferred that when NPQ took up a large proportion of the absorbed light energy, fluorescence and photochemistry were concurrently inhibited, resulting in a positive relationship between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield. By contrast, when NPQ was not the primary light consumption pathway, the output between fluorescence and photochemistry changed. Together, these factors mean that the relationship between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield for water-stressed plants was non-linear. Similar phenomena have been observed in previous research (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Cheng, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). For example, <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Porcar-Castell <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> reported that F<sub>s</sub> yield is negatively related to P yield when NPQ is low, but the relationship becomes positive with increasing NPQ. <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> illustrated that F<sub>s</sub> yield may be positively or negatively related to photosynthetic light use efficiency, and that the slope of their relation function changes across different growing stages. <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Cheng (2010)</xref> also illustrated that fluorescence and photosynthesis have a competitive relationship only when NPQ is not operating. <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Baker (2008)</xref> and <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Damm <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> suggested that the principal inverse relationship between the energy used for fluorescence and that used for primary photosynthesis is usually lost due to the dominant role of NPQ in dissipating the excess light. Thus, it can be concluded that when NPQ is low, fluorescence emission is one of the processes that dissipate the excess light. In this case, F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield are inversely correlated. However, when NPQ plays a dominant role in dissipating the excess energy, F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield are both suppressed by NPQ yield; as a consequence, they are synergistic and positively related. Owing to complex relationships between fluorescence and photochemistry under changing environmental conditions, an increase in fluorescence may be associated with either an increase or a decrease in photochemistry. Thus, knowledge of the ambient environment is a prerequisite for assessing photochemistry by fluorescence (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">van der Tol <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Chlorophyll fluorescence is closely related to photosynthesis. To explore the relationship between photochemical yield and fluorescence yield, and the response of the relationship to water stress under intermediate light conditions, we conducted an experiment in a climate chamber. Summer maize grown under an above-canopy light intensity of 700 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> was subjected to moderate water stress, with soil water content being 45&#x02013;50% of the field capacity, and non-water stress, with soil water content of &#x0003e;80% of the field capacity.</p><p>Water stress has a significant influence on plant photosynthetic physiology. For plants grown in intermediate light conditions, the F<sub>s</sub> yield and NPQ yield increase and the P yield decreases in response to water stress. Light intensity and water status affect the apportioning of light energy between heat dissipation, fluorescence, and photochemistry. Specifically, in the absence of water stress, F<sub>s</sub> yield is negatively related to P yield in intermediate and low light conditions, regardless of the changes in NPQ yield. However, under water stress, the relationship between F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield is negative in low light conditions (PAR &#x0003c;450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) but positive in intermediate light conditions (PAR &#x02265;450 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> and &#x02264;700 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>); F<sub>s</sub> yield is negatively related to P yield when NPQ is &#x0003c;0.58, but when NPQ is &#x0003e;0.58, F<sub>s</sub> yield and P yield are synergistically and positively associated.</p><p>These results reveal that in intermediate and low light conditions there are no single positive or negative relationships between P yield and F<sub>s</sub> yield; the relationship between these yields may depend on light intensity and water status, and these factors should be considered when using measurements of chlorophyll fluorescence to estimate plant production.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant no.41471026). We thank Dr Liping Tan and Enmin Liu for the instrumentation in the WATDPED. We are grateful to doctoral students Lihong He and Yi Zou for their help with the experiment, and thank Associate Professor Monica Garcia for her suggestions on the manuscript. We also would like to thank the editors and reviewers for their careful corrections and constructive comments and suggestions, which helped to improve this paper.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Chlorophyll fluorescence: a probe of photosynthesis in vivo</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><volume>59</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenqvist</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Applications of chlorophyll fluorescence can improve crop production strategies: an examination of future possibilities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>55</volume>, <fpage>1607</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1621</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15258166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year>
<article-title>Energy distribution in the photochemical apparatus of photosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology</source><volume>29</volume>, <fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cendrero-Mateo</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carmo-Silva</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porcar-Castell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamerlynck</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papuga</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Dynamic response of plant chlorophyll fluorescence to light, water and nutrient availability</article-title>. <source>Functional Plant Biology</source><volume>42</volume>, <fpage>746</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>757</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cendrero-Mateo</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papuga</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorp</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ponce-Campos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rascher</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Plant chlorophyll fluorescence: active and passive measurements at canopy and leaf scales with different nitrogen treatments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>67</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>286</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26482242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qiang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Classification and characteristics of heat tolerance in <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic> populations using fast chlorophyll a fluorescence rise O-J-I-P</article-title>. <source>Environmental and Experimental Botany</source><volume>122</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Craufurd</surname><given-names>PQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Summerfield</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Effect of temperature and water deficit on water-use efficiency, carbon isotope discrimination, and specific leaf area in peanut</article-title>. <source>Crop Science</source><volume>39</volume>, <fpage>136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Analyzing the relationship between solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence and gross primary production using remotely sensed data and model simulation</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Earth &#x00026; Environmental Sciences</source><volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Damm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elbers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Remote sensing of sun-induced fluorescence to improve modeling of diurnal courses of gross primary production (GPP)</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biology</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Damm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guanter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paul-Limoges</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Tol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hueni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eugster</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ammann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaepman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Far-red sun-induced chlorophyll fluorescence shows ecosystem-specific relationships to gross primary production: an assessment based on observational and modeling approaches</article-title>. <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source><volume>166</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobr&#x000e1;nszki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mendler-Drienyovszki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Cytokinin-induced changes in the chlorophyll content and fluorescence of <italic>in vitro</italic> apple leaves</article-title>. <source>Journal of Plant Physiology</source><volume>171</volume>, <fpage>1472</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1478</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25108261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrowski</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pushnik</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zarco-Tejada</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ustin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Simple reflectance indices track heat and water stress-induced changes in steady-state chlorophyll fluorescence at the canopy scale</article-title>. <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source><volume>97</volume>, <fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>414</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faraloni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cutino</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petruccelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leva</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lazzeri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torzillo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Chlorophyll fluorescence technique as a rapid tool for <italic>in vitro</italic> screening of olive cultivars (<italic>Olea europaea</italic> L.) tolerant to drought stress</article-title>. <source>Environmental and Experimental Botany</source><volume>73</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flexas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briantais</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cerovic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Steady-state and maximum chlorophyll fluorescence responses to water stress in grapevine leaves: a new remote sensing system</article-title>. <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source><volume>73</volume>, <fpage>283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flexas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Escalona</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gul&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osmond</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Steady-state chlorophyll fluorescence (Fs) measurements as a tool to follow variations of net CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation and stomatal conductance during water-stress in C<sub>3</sub> plants</article-title>. <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source><volume>114</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11903970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flexas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Escalona</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Water stress induces different levels of photosynthesis and electron transport rate regulation in grapevines</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell and Environment</source><volume>22</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flexas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Energy dissipation in C<sub>3</sub> plants under drought</article-title>. <source>Functional Plant Biology</source><volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1215</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Effects of water stress on growth, biomass partitioning, and water-use efficiency in summer maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) throughout the growth cycle</article-title>. <source>Acta Physiologiae Plantarum</source><volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1053</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Genty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briantais</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>The Relationship between the quantum yield of photosynthetic electron-transport and quenching of chlorophyll fluorescence</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source><volume>990</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guanter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Badgley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lobell</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Improving the monitoring of crop productivity using spaceborne solar-induced fluorescence</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biology</source><volume>22</volume>, <fpage>716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>726</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26490834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guanter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Global and time-resolved monitoring of crop photosynthesis with chlorophyll fluorescence</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>111</volume>, <fpage>E1327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E1333</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Wavelet analysis of pulse-amplitude-modulated chlorophyll fluorescence for differentiation of plant samples</article-title>. <source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source><volume>370</volume>, <fpage>116</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25665719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hazrati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tahmasebi-Sarvestani</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Modarres-Sanavy</surname><given-names>SAM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mokhtassi-Bidgoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Effects of water stress and light intensity on chlorophyll fluorescence parameters and pigments of <italic>Aloe vera</italic> L</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</source><volume>106</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27161580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hmimina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufr&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soudani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Relationship between photochemical reflectance index and leaf ecophysiological and biochemical parameters under two different water statuses: towards a rapid and efficient correction method using real-time measurements</article-title>. <source>Plant, Cell &#x00026; Environment</source><volume>37</volume>, <fpage>473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>487</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Tol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guanter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Damm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frankenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Simulations of chlorophyll fluorescence incorporated into the Community Land Model version 4</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biology</source><volume>21</volume>, <fpage>3469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3477</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25881891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frankenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Tol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Forest productivity and water stress in Amazonia: observations from GOSAT chlorophyll fluorescence</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B-Biological Sciences</source><volume>280</volume>, <fpage>20130171</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Detection of vegetation light-use efficiency based on solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence separated from canopy radiance spectrum</article-title>. <source>IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing</source><volume>3</volume>, <fpage>306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Directly estimating diurnal changes in GPP for C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> crops using far-red sun-induced chlorophyll fluorescence</article-title>. <source>Agricultural and Forest Meteorology</source><volume>232</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Response of photosynthesis and chlorophyll fluorescence to drought stress in two maize cultivars</article-title>. <source>African Journal of Agricultural Research</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>4751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4760</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Losciale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grappadelli</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Quenching partitioning through light-modulated chlorophyll fluorescence: a quantitative analysis to assess the fate of the absorbed light in the field</article-title>. <source>Environmental and Experimental Botany</source><volume>73</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Effects of water stress on photosystem II photochemistry and its thermostability in wheat plants</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1206</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathobo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steyn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>The effect of drought stress on yield, leaf gaseous exchange and chlorophyll fluorescence of dry beans (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Agricultural Water Management</source><volume>180</volume>, <fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iannacone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petrozza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armentano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>La Vecchia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trt&#x000ed;lek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cellini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nedbal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Engineered drought tolerance in tomato plants is reflected in chlorophyll fluorescence emission</article-title>. <source>Plant Science</source><volume>182</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22118618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Struik</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Stomatal conductance, mesophyll conductance, and transpiration efficiency in relation to leaf anatomy in rice and wheat genotypes under drought</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>68</volume>, <fpage>5191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28992130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porcar-Castell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyystj&#x000e4;rvi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atherton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Tol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flexas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pf&#x000fc;ndel</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frankenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Linking chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> fluorescence to photosynthesis for remote sensing applications: mechanisms and challenges</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>65</volume>, <fpage>4065</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4095</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24868038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosales</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ocampo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Valent&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olvera-Carrillo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Acosta-Gallegos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Covarrubias</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Physiological analysis of common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.) cultivars uncovers characteristics related to terminal drought resistance</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</source><volume>56</volume>, <fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22579941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JAB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lagoa</surname><given-names>AMMA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>JAG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Photosynthetic gas exchange, chlorophyll fluorescence and some associated metabolic changes in cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic>) during water stress and recovery</article-title>. <source>Environmental and Experimental Botany</source><volume>51</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spinoni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naumann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carrao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>World drought frequency, duration, and severity for 1951&#x02013;2010</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Climatology</source><volume>34</volume>, <fpage>2792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2804</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stirling</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Changes in the photosynthetic light response curve during leaf development of field grown maize with implications for modelling canopy photosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Photosynthesis Research</source><volume>42</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24306563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frankenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernando</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Drought onset mechanisms revealed by satellite solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence: Insights from two contrasting extreme events</article-title>. <source>Journal of Geophysical Research-Biogeosciences</source><volume>120</volume>, <fpage>2427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2440</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Responses of maize ecosystem to warming based on WATDPED experiment under near-field condition</article-title>. <source>Ecological Indicators</source><volume>81</volume>, <fpage>390</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>400</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tietz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>NPQ(T): a chlorophyll fluorescence parameter for rapid estimation and imaging of non-photochemical quenching of excitons in photosystem-II-associated antenna complexes</article-title>. <source>Plant, Cell &#x00026; Environment</source><volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1255</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tubuxin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimzadeh-Bajgiran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ginnan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosoi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Omasa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Estimating chlorophyll content and photochemical yield of photosystem II (&#x003a6;PSII) using solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence measurements at different growing stages of attached leaves</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>66</volume>, <fpage>5595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5603</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26071530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Tol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rascher</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Models of fluorescence and photosynthesis for interpreting measurements of solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Geophysical Research. Biogeosciences</source><volume>119</volume>, <fpage>2312</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2327</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27398266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Tol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosema</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>A model for chlorophyll fluorescence and photosynthesis at leaf scale</article-title>. <source>Agricultural and Forest Meteorology</source><volume>149</volume>, <fpage>96</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verrelst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Tol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magnani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabater</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Evaluating the predictive power of sun-induced chlorophyll fluorescence to estimate net photosynthesis of vegetation canopies: A SCOPE modeling study</article-title>. <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source><volume>176</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>151</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Comparison of solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence, light-use efficiency, and process-based GPP models in maize</article-title>. <source>Ecological Applications</source><volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1222</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27509759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TX</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Monitoring and assessing the 2012 drought in the Great Plains: analyzing satellite-retrieved solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence, drought indices, and gross primary production</article-title>. <source>Remote Sensing</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mustard</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munger</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kornfeld</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence that correlates with canopy photosynthesis on diurnal and seasonal scales in a temperate deciduous forest</article-title>. <source>Geophysical Research Letters</source><volume>42</volume>, <fpage>2977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2987</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heskel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munger</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Chlorophyll fluorescence tracks seasonal variations of photosynthesis from leaf to canopy in a temperate forest</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biology</source><volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2874</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2886</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27976474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Early growth, dry matter allocation and water use efficiency of two sympatric <italic>Populus</italic> species as affected by water stress</article-title>. <source>Environmental and Experimental Botany</source><volume>53</volume>, <fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarco-Tejada</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catalina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Relationships between net photosynthesis and steady-state chlorophyll fluorescence retrieved from airborne hyperspectral imagery</article-title>. <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source><volume>136</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>258</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guanter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Tol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016b</year>
<article-title>Model-based analysis of the relationship between sun-induced chlorophyll fluorescence and gross primary production for remote sensing applications</article-title>. <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source><volume>187</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>155</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<year>2016a</year>
<article-title>Consistency between sun-induced chlorophyll fluorescence and gross primary production of vegetation in North America</article-title>. <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source><volume>183</volume>, <fpage>154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>169</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>