<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6216105</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.01565</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Detection of <italic>T. urartu</italic> Introgressions in Wheat and Development of a Panel of Interspecific Introgression Lines</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>Surbhi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/497917/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hubbart-Edwards</surname><given-names>Stella</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/610965/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Caiyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/617255/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scholefield</surname><given-names>Duncan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/628658/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ashling</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/628617/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burridge</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/610961/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>Paul Anthony</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/611031/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>Ian P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/607359/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>Julie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/607318/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Nottingham BBSRC Wheat Research Centre, Plant and Crop Sciences, School of Biosciences, The University of Nottingham</institution>, <addr-line>Loughborough</addr-line>, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Cereal Genomics Lab, Life Sciences Building, School of Biological Sciences, University of Bristol</institution>, <addr-line>Bristol</addr-line>, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Soren K. Rasmussen, University of Copenhagen, Denmark</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Luke Douglas Ramsay, The James Hutton Institute, United Kingdom; Istv&#x000e1;n Moln&#x000e1;r, Centre for Agricultural Research (MTA), Hungary</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Surbhi Grewal, <email>surbhi.grewal@nottingham.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Breeding, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1565</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Grewal, Hubbart-Edwards, Yang, Scholefield, Ashling, Burridge, Wilkinson, King and King.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Grewal, Hubbart-Edwards, Yang, Scholefield, Ashling, Burridge, Wilkinson, King and King</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Tritcum urartu</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 14, A<sup>u</sup>A<sup>u</sup>), the A genome donor of wheat, is an important source for new genetic variation for wheat improvement due to its high photosynthetic rate and disease resistance. By facilitating the generation of genome-wide introgressions leading to a variety of different wheat&#x02013;<italic>T. urartu</italic> translocation lines, <italic>T. urartu</italic> can be practically utilized in wheat improvement. Previous studies that have generated such introgression lines have been unable to successfully use cytological methods to detect the presence of <italic>T. urartu</italic> in these lines. Many have, thus, used a variety of molecular markers with limited success due to the low-density coverage of these markers and time-consuming nature of the techniques rendering them unsuitable for large-scale breeding programs. In this study, we report the generation of a resource of single nucleotide polymorphic (SNP) markers, present on a high-throughput SNP genotyping array, that can detect the presence of <italic>T. urartu</italic> in a hexaploid wheat background making it a potentially valuable tool in wheat pre-breeding programs. A whole genome introgression approach has resulted in the transfer of different chromosome segments from <italic>T. urartu</italic> into wheat which have then been detected and characterized using these SNP markers. The molecular analysis of these wheat-<italic>T. urartu</italic> recombinant lines has resulted in the generation of a genetic map of <italic>T. urartu</italic> containing 368 SNP markers, spread across all seven chromosomes of <italic>T. urartu</italic>. Comparative analysis of the genetic map of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and the physical map of the hexaploid wheat genome showed that synteny between the two species is highly conserved at the macro-level and confirmed the presence of the 4/5 translocation in <italic>T. urartu</italic> also present in the A genome of wheat. A panel of 17 wheat-<italic>T. urartu</italic> recombinant lines, which consisted of introgressed segments that covered the whole genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic>, were also selected for self-fertilization to provide a germplasm resource for future trait analysis. This valuable resource of high-density molecular markers specifically designed for detecting wild relative chromosomes and a panel of stable interspecific introgression lines will greatly enhance the efficiency of wheat improvement through wild relative introgressions.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>wheat</kwd><kwd><italic>T. urartu</italic></kwd><kwd>introgression</kwd><kwd>interspecific hybrid</kwd><kwd>SNP</kwd><kwd>genetic mapping</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100000268</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="42"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Common wheat has a narrow worldwide gene pool, descended from a very small number of spontaneous interspecific hybrids that originated from two natural amphiploidisation events. Domestication of wheat has further reduced its genetic variation. However, interspecific crossing with wheat&#x02019;s distant wild relatives has recently been employed to overcome this genetic bottleneck (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Gill et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Grewal et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, wheat&#x02019;s progenitors are being regarded as useful sources of genetic variation for many biotic and abiotic traits (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cox, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000f6;rner et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cox et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p><italic>Triticum urartu</italic> Thum. ex Gandil. (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 14; genome A<sup>u</sup>A<sup>u</sup>) is the A-genome donor of tetraploid wheat <italic>T. turgidum</italic> subsp. <italic>durum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 42; genome AABB) and hexaploid wheat <italic>T. aestivum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 42; genome AABBDD) (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Dvorak et al., 1993</xref>) and its chromosomes are homologous to chromosomes of the A genome of bread wheat (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Chapman et al., 1976</xref>). Thus, interspecific crossing between <italic>T. urartu</italic> and bread wheat would potentially enable transfer of desirable traits from the chromosomes of the wild diploid wheat into cultivated hexaploid wheat through direct hybridization. Previous research has shown that <italic>T. urartu</italic> carries many agronomically important traits, such as high net photosynthetic rate (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Austin et al., 1982</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>; <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Morgan and Austin, 1986</xref>) and disease resistance (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Rouse and Jin, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Sheedy et al., 2012</xref>), which can be exploited for improving wheat&#x02019;s narrow gene pool (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mart&#x000ed;n et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>For a successful interspecific crossing program, it is vital to be able to detect the presence of and distinguish between the parental chromosomes/alleles in the hybrids. Since <italic>T. urartu</italic> is the donor of wheat&#x02019;s A genome, traditional cytogenetic methods, such as genomic <italic>in situ</italic> hybridisation (GISH) and fluorescent <italic>in situ</italic> hybridisation (FISH), are unable to clearly distinguish between the A genome chromosomes of wheat and those of <italic>T. urartu</italic> in the interspecific hybrid. It also does not help that there are currently very few cytogenetic markers used for the analysis of A genome chromosomes (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Adonina et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>Previous attempts have been made at crossing <italic>T. urartu</italic> with other diploid wheat (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Johnson and Dhaliwal, 1976</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Fricano et al., 2014</xref>), tetraploid wheat (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Johnson and Dhaliwal, 1976</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Valkoun, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Alvarez et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Su&#x000e1;rez et al., 2011</xref>), and hexaploid wheat (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Dvo&#x00159;&#x000e1;k, 1976</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">1978</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et al., 2005</xref>). However, due to the lack of efficient cytogenetic methods for the detection of <italic>T. urartu</italic> chromatin in the hybrids, some studies have resorted to the use of microsatellite markers for detecting the presence of <italic>T. urartu</italic> alleles in wheat (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Su&#x000e1;rez et al., 2011</xref>). However, these markers do not provide a high-density coverage of the <italic>T. urartu</italic> genome. In addition, these techniques are low throughput and have limited success and are thus, not suitable for use in large-scale pre-breeding programs. Next-generation sequencing technologies and high-throughput single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) marker development and corresponding SNP-arrays allow faster and more accurate detection of introgressions from wild relatives into wheat (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Tiwari et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Grewal et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we present a resource of SNP markers, spread across all seven chromosomes of <italic>T. urartu</italic>, which were used to identify <italic>T. urartu</italic> chromatin in the hexaploid wheat background. The aim of the research was to attempt to transfer chromosome segments from <italic>T. urartu</italic> into hexaploid wheat using a whole-genome introgression approach i.e., to exploit genetic variation from the entire genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic> rather than concentrate on a single introgression for a single trait, and characterize the population with a custom-designed SNP genotyping array (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Winfield et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 2017</xref>). Using these SNP markers, we were able to detect and characterize wheat-<italic>T. urartu</italic> recombinants which allowed us to generate a genetic map for <italic>T. urartu</italic> consisting of 368 SNP markers. A panel of 17 wheat-<italic>T. urartu</italic> recombinant lines were then selected for self-fertilization to provide a germplasm resource consisting of the whole genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic> introgressed into hexaploid wheat. Development of such high-density molecular markers specific for wild relative chromosomes and a panel of stable interspecific introgression lines will greatly enhance the efficiency of wheat improvement through wild relative introgressions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Plant Materials</title><p>Hexaploid wheat <italic>T. aestivum</italic> cv. Paragon <italic>ph1/ph1</italic> mutant (2<italic>n</italic> = 6<italic>x</italic> = 42) was pollinated with <italic>T. urartu</italic> (accessions 1010001, 1010002, 1010006, and 1010020 obtained from Germplasm Resource Unit, JIC; 2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 14) to produce F<sub>1</sub> interspecific hybrids (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The origin, according to the GRU database Seedstor, of accessions 1010001, 1010002, and 1010006 is from Armenia and that of accession 1010020 is unknown. There is no trait data available for these accessions in particular and were thus, chosen at random.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>A summary of the crossing program followed to obtain interspecific wheat-<italic>Tritcum urartu</italic> introgression lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01565-g001"/></fig><p>In the F<sub>1</sub> hybrids, it was expected that recombination between chromosomes of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and wheat would occur, during gametogenesis, in absence of the <italic>Ph1</italic> pairing locus resulting in the production of wheat-<italic>T. urartu</italic> recombinants. These recombinant chromosomes would subsequently be transmitted to the progeny of these hybrid lines to generate <italic>T. urartu</italic> introgressions. After being grown to maturity, the F<sub>1</sub> hybrids were used as the female and backcrossed with Paragon wheat, carrying the wild-type <italic>Ph1</italic> locus intact, to generate a BC<sub>1</sub> population. The BC<sub>1</sub> individuals were then recurrently pollinated with Paragon <italic>Ph1/Ph1</italic> to produce BC<sub>2</sub>, BC<sub>3</sub>, and BC<sub>4</sub> populations (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Three heads from each plant in each backcross population were bagged to allow self-fertilization. Cross fertility was calculated as the number of crosses setting seed.</p></sec><sec><title>Genotyping via an Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> SNP Array</title><p>To detect introgressed chromosomes and chromosome segments from <italic>T. urartu</italic> into wheat, an array of circa 35 K SNPs, known as the Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Wheat-Relative Genotyping Array (available via Thermo Fisher Scientific), was used (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 2017</xref>). In summary, the array is composed of SNPs each showing polymorphisms for the ten wild relatives relative to the wheat genotypes under study. All the SNPs incorporated in this array formed part of the Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> 820 K SNP array (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Winfield et al., 2016</xref>). Detailed methods and protocols of the construction of the arrays is reported by <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Burridge et al. (2017)</xref>. The data set for the Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> 820 K array is available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cerealsdb.uk.net">www.cerealsdb.uk.net</ext-link> (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Winfield et al., 2012</xref>a). This array is facilitating cost-effective, high-throughput and high resolution screening of wheat-wild relative introgressions. Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the number of putative SNPs, for each linkage group (LG), between <italic>T. urartu</italic> and wheat included on the array.</p><p>The Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Wheat-Relative Genotyping Array was used to genotype 264 samples in total. Control samples included three replicates of each of parental lines, i.e., wheat cv. Paragon and <italic>T. urartu</italic> (all accessions were pooled into one sample). It should be noted that all the SNPs used on the array were also selected to be polymorphic between Paragon and all accessions of <italic>T. urartu</italic> used in this program. Call rate for a sample was calculated as the percentage of the number of SNP probes on the array that resulted in a definitive genotype call (AA, AB, and BB) for that sample. The equipment, software, procedures, and criteria used for this genotyping are as described by <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">King et al. (2017)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Genetic Mapping of <italic>T. urartu</italic> Chromosomes</title><p>Along with triplicates of the two parental lines, 258 lines comprising BC<sub>1</sub>, BC<sub>2</sub>, and BC<sub>3</sub> populations of <italic>T. urartu</italic> were genotyped altogether (different generations were combined in order to have sufficient numbers of individuals) using the Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Wheat-Relative Genotyping Array. As described by <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">King et al. (2017)</xref>, only the Poly High Resolution (PHR) SNP markers were used for further marker analysis. PHR markers were co-dominant, polymorphic and generated minor allele calls for at least two of the three replicates of <italic>T. urartu.</italic> Flapjack<sup>TM</sup> was used to disregard SNP markers which showed (i) heterozygous calls for either parent(s), (ii) no polymorphism between the wheat parents and <italic>T. urartu</italic> and/or, (iii) no calls for either parent(s) (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Milne et al., 2010</xref>; v.1.14.09.24). The remaining markers were sorted into LGs in JoinMap<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> 4.0 (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Van Ooijen, 2011</xref>) with a LOD score of 30 using the genotype classification code &#x0201c;(a,h)&#x0201d;, where &#x0201c;a&#x0201d; is the genotype of the first parent and &#x0201c;h&#x0201d; is the genotype of the F<sub>1</sub> hybrid. &#x0201c;BCpxFy&#x0201d; was used as the population code for each dataset which donates an advanced backcross inbred line family, where the backcross parent p had genotype &#x0201c;a&#x0201d;, x is the number of backcrosses including the one for creating the BC<sub>1</sub> and y is the number of selfings, i.e., BCa1F0 is equivalent to BC<sub>1</sub>. The seven highest-ranking LGs were selected for downstream analysis. These were exported and assigned to chromosomes using information from the Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Wheat HD Genotyping Array (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Winfield et al., 2012</xref>b). Erroneous markers that had more than 20% missing genotype calls were removed. LG data was used to produce a genetic map using MapChart 2.3 (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Voorrips, 2002</xref>). In some cases, physical map information was employed to order loci. Graphical genotype visualization was performed using Graphical GenoTypes 2.0 (GGT; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">van Berloo, 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Selection of Panel Lines</title><p>After genotyping, all backcrossed lines with three or less segments introgressed from <italic>T. urartu</italic> were considered for construction of a panel of plants with various homozygous segments. For that purpose, a set of lines that potentially had overlapping, different sized introgressions from <italic>T. urartu</italic> spanning the length of each LG were selected for self-fertilization to eventually produce a panel of homozygous single segment lines that covered the entire genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Comparative Analysis</title><p>Synteny analysis was carried out using sequence information of the markers located on the genetic map of <italic>T. urartu</italic>. The sequences of the mapped markers were used in BLAST (<italic>e</italic>-value cut-off of 1<italic>e</italic>-05) against the wheat genome IWGSC RefSeq v1.0 (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Alaux et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">International Wheat Genome Sequencing Consortium [IWGSC] et al., 2018</xref>) to obtain the corresponding physical positions of the top hit in A, B, and D genomes of wheat. The sequences were also used in BLAST against the <italic>T. urartu</italic> reference genome sequence (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2018</xref>) to obtain the top hit on the Tu chromosomes. To generate the figures, map positions of the loci on the genetic map of <italic>T. urartu</italic> were scaled up by a factor of 100,000 to match the corresponding physical positions of the loci on the wheat A genome and the <italic>T. urartu</italic> (Tu) genome. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> was visualized using Circos plots (v. 0.69; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Krzywinski et al., 2009</xref>) to observe (a) correlation between the markers on the genetic map of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and their physical positions on the Tu genome sequence and (b) synteny between the markers mapped on the A<sup>u</sup> genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and the A genome of wheat. Corresponding genetic and physical positions of the markers on <italic>T. urartu</italic> and wheat, respectively, are shown in Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Generating Introgressions From <italic>T. urartu</italic> Into Hexaploid Wheat</title><p>A crossing program was initiated to generate gene introgressions from <italic>T. urartu</italic> into wheat cv. Paragon (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) using the <italic>ph1</italic> mutant method (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Grewal et al., 2018</xref>). A total of 1902 crosses were made between wheat and <italic>T. urartu</italic> and their derivatives leading to the generation of 18441 crossed seed and 14193 self-fertilized seed. The number of seeds sown, germination rate, cross fertility and seed set, etc., are summarized in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Number of seeds produced and germinated in relation to the number of crosses carried out, cross fertility and the number of self-fertilized seed produced for each generation of the introgression program for <italic>Tritcum urartu</italic> into wheat.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seeds sown</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germination rate (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crosses made</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross fertility (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossed seeds produced</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seeds/Cross</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-fertilized seeds produced</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat &#x000d7; <italic>T. urartu</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>1</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">478</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2089</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC<sub>2</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">754</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11186</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3163</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC<sub>3</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3411</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8952</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC<sub>4</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1609</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2068</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">657</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1902</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18441</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14193</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Hexaploid bread wheat was used as the female parent to avoid problems with exotic cytoplasm. Sufficient viable F<sub>1</sub> seeds were achieved without embryo rescue (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The F<sub>1</sub> hybrids were backcrossed with Paragon wheat with the <italic>Ph1</italic> gene intact to generate the backcross populations. F<sub>1</sub> hybrids exhibited the highest levels of infertility since they had a cross fertility of only 21% as compared to 78, 97, 97, and 100% from the crossed ears of the BC<sub>1</sub>, BC<sub>2</sub>, BC<sub>3</sub>, and BC<sub>4</sub> generations. A further indication of the infertility of the F<sub>1</sub> was shown by the fact that this generation set no self-seed in contrast to the other generations. Since the ABDA<sup>u</sup> tetraploids were sterile, they were pollinated without emasculation. 478 crosses between the F<sub>1</sub> hybrids and Paragon wheat resulted in 146 BC<sub>1</sub> seeds. Approximately half of these BC<sub>1</sub> seeds were germinated of which 43 adult plants were obtained. These BC<sub>1</sub> plants also had low fertility with 24 out of 34 self-fertilized heads producing no seed. However, fertility was restored in the subsequent backcross generations.</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular Marker Analysis of Wheat-<italic>T. urartu</italic> Introgression Lines</title><p>There are 18,287 SNPs between <italic>T. urartu</italic> and wheat on the Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Wheat-Relative Genotyping Array which were evenly spread over all seven LGs (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). This array was used to screen genomic DNA prepared from 258 backcross lines between wheat and <italic>T. urartu</italic> along with control samples. Genotype calls were generated, and the sample call rate ranged from 83.2 to 99.9% with an average of 98.9% for the 264 samples. The lowest call rates were obtained for the three <italic>T. urartu</italic> samples with an average of 86.8%. Even though the Affymetrix software classified the scores for each of the probes into six cluster patterns, only those calls classified as PHR (3168) were used for genotyping as these are optimum quality.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Number of SNP markers polymorphic between wheat and <italic>T. urartu</italic> on the Affymetrix Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Wheat-Relative Genotyping Array for each linkage group of the A<sup>u</sup> genome and final number of SNP markers mapped onto the genetic map of the A<sup>u</sup> genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic> obtained through Poly High Resolution (PHR) calling.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short Arm</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long Arm</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both Arms</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of Total SNP markers</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHR calls on genetic map</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of Total PHR calls on genetic map</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cM length on genetic map</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linkage Group 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">908</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1439</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2347</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linkage Group 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1287</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3284</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linkage Group 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1092</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1673</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2765</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linkage Group 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">874</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1294</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2168</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linkage Group 5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">686</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2300</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2986</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linkage Group 6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">833</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1211</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2044</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linkage Group 7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1320</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1373</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2693</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11287</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18287</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">772.1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>After filtering out 2509 good quality PHR SNPs using Flapjack<sup>TM</sup>, JoinMap<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> was used to genetically map the markers by analyzing the corresponding genotypes of all lines. In order to get strongly linked loci a high LOD score was used which led to the establishment of seven LGs that were composed of 368 SNPs and represented the seven chromosomes of <italic>T. urartu</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Within the mapped PHR SNPS, LG 5 had the highest number of SNPs (22%) while LG 1 had the lowest (9.8%). A genetic map was constructed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) with a total map length of 772.1 cM (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) and an average chromosome length of 110.3 cM. It should be noted that the germplasm used to generate these linkage maps did not constitute proper mapping populations and in fact we combined different generations in order to have sufficient numbers. Therefore, the cM distances in the map generated should be treated with considerable caution. However, the map did allow the ordering of the markers and hence, the identification and tracking of segments through backcross generations.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Genetic linkage map of <italic>T. urartu</italic> showing 368 SNP markers spread across seven linkage groups (LGs).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01565-g002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Detection of Introgressions and Panel Selection</title><p>In Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, an example of how the genetic map allowed the tracking of <italic>T. urartu</italic> introgressions, through the backcrossed populations, is shown. Presence of <italic>T. urartu</italic>, shown in colored segments, could be visualized through GGT bar diagrams which allowed the graphical representation of the genotyping data for each line, i.e., the markers on the genetic map. The dark blue region of the GGT bars represent the wheat allele for a marker. Introgressions could be tracked from the BC<sub>1</sub> plant (BC<sub>1</sub>-293), which carried <italic>T. urartu</italic> segments from each of the seven LGs, through to the single segment BC<sub>4</sub> lines (BC<sub>4</sub>-112B and BC<sub>4</sub>-112C). Of the two BC<sub>2</sub> plants (BC<sub>2</sub>-218A and BC<sub>2</sub>-218B) originating from the BC<sub>1</sub> plant, both carrying segments from six <italic>T. urartu</italic> LGs, BC<sub>2</sub>-218B was propagated further to produce two BC<sub>3</sub> plants, BC<sub>3</sub>-134A and BC<sub>3</sub>-134C. The former was further backcrossed to produce two BC<sub>4</sub> plants, each with a different <italic>T. urartu</italic> segment.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>A graphical representation of SNP characterisation of <italic>T. urartu</italic> introgressions into a hexaploid wheat background in four consecutive generations, i.e., BC<sub>1</sub>, BC<sub>2</sub>, BC<sub>3</sub>, and BC<sub>4</sub>, through GGT bar diagrams. Wheat genotype is represented in dark blue and <italic>T. urartu</italic> genotype is represented in a different color for each LG.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01565-g003"/></fig><p>Furthermore, all lines with 3 or less segments from <italic>T. urartu</italic> were considered for self-fertilization. From these, 17 lines were selected which had a combination of introgressed segments that would overlap to cover the entire genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic> as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>. In lines with multiple segments, each segment is color-coded with the same color, i.e., <italic>T. urartu</italic> segments in different LGs of the same color in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> belong to one introgression line. This panel of <italic>T. urartu</italic> introgression lines, where each line contained between 1 and 3 segments, are currently being self-fertilized for downstream trait analysis.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>A graphical representation of various sized segments of <italic>T. urartu</italic>, along its linkage map, in introgression lines involved in panel selection. For each of the seven LGs, the map positions of the corresponding molecular markers are reported. Black bars represent single chromosome segments of <italic>T. urartu</italic> detected in the introgression lines, while bars with the same color indicate multiple chromosome segments of <italic>T. urartu</italic> detected in a single introgression line. In total, 17 lines with overlapping segments that covered the entire genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic> were selected for a panel of lines that would undergo self-fertilization for downstream trait analysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01565-g004"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Comparative Analysis of Wheat and <italic>T. urartu</italic> Genomes</title><p>A BLAST analysis of the 368 marker sequences on the A<sup>u</sup> genome map against their physical positions on the <italic>T. urartu</italic> genome (Tu chromosomes) indicated that the order of markers on the genetic map correlates well with their physical order on the Tu chromosomes. 341 markers resulted in a BLAST hit against the Tu genome sequence. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> shows that the seven LGs of mapped markers on the A<sup>u</sup> genome also map back to their corresponding Tu chromosome group, i.e., markers in LG 1 had a BLAST top hit on chromosome Tu1, and the markers are well distributed on each of the seven Tu chromosomes.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Comparative analysis between the A<sup>u</sup> genome loci on the genetic map of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and their physical positions on <bold>(A)</bold> the Tu chromosomes and <bold>(B)</bold> the A genome of wheat. Homeologous chromosomes from 7 LGs between <italic>T. urartu</italic> and wheat are displayed as ideograms of the same color. Lines connect genetic map positions of markers in the A<sup>u</sup> genome (left of plot) to their physical map positions (right of plot) on the <bold>(A)</bold> Tu chromosomes and <bold>(B)</bold> the A genome of wheat. Lines joining A<sup>u</sup> and wheat A chromosomes with the same color as the ideograms indicate synteny through mapping in homeologous LGs. Lines between the A<sup>u</sup> and the wheat A genome that end in a different colored ideogram in the wheat genome point to mapping in non-homoeologous LGs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01565-g005"/></fig><p>A macro-colinearity analysis was carried out to determine any occurrences of major chromosome rearrangements in the A genome during or after the formation of hexaploid wheat. Marker sequences on the genetic map of <italic>T. urartu</italic> were also used in BLAST analysis against the wheat Chinese Spring genome assembly. Physical position for the top hit from the A genome of wheat, where available, and for the overall top hit (maximum sequence identity match) for either of the 3 wheat genomes was obtained (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>). The BLAST results showed that 92.4, 74.7, and 76.4% of the markers had a significant BLAST hit on the A, B, and D genomes of wheat, respectively. Of these BLAST hits, 73.9, 13.6, and 19.8% of the markers had an overall top hit on the A, B, and D genomes of wheat, respectively, with some showing the same score for the top hit for more than one genome.</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref> shows the syntenic relationship between the seven LGs of the A<sup>u</sup> genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and the A genome of wheat with colored lines showing significant synteny and collinearity. Some gene rearrangements are indicated where single markers cross map to positions on non-homeologous wheat chromosomes. The only major disruption in collinearity between the two species is that the wheat chromosome 4A has an inversion compared to <italic>T. urartu</italic> chromosome 4A<sup>u</sup>. The latter has the 4/5 translocation like wheat but does not carry the 4/7 translocation observed for chromosomes 4A and 7B of wheat (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Devos et al., 1995</xref>). This data demonstrates the close syntenic relationship between the A genome of wheat and <italic>T. urartu</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p><italic>Tritcum urartu</italic> is a potentially important source of genetic variation for a wide variety of agronomically important traits (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Austin et al., 1982</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mart&#x000ed;n et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Rouse and Jin, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Sheedy et al., 2012</xref>). Using the <italic>ph1</italic> mutant approach, wheat-<italic>T. urartu</italic> recombinant lines have been generated in this study (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) suggesting that recombination can occur between hexaploid wheat and <italic>T. urartu</italic> chromosomes. Similar crossing strategies have been used previously to generate wheat-wild relative recombination (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Grewal et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, a high rate of recombination allowed generation of a genetic map for <italic>T. urartu</italic> indicating that the chromosomes of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and the A genome of bread wheat have high homology.</p><p>Cross fertility is lowest in the F<sub>1</sub> hybrids at 21% but increases substantially in the back-cross generations reaching 100% in the BC<sub>4</sub> population (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This was expected since the inter-specific F<sub>1</sub> hybrids were haploid for the A, B, D, and A<sup>u</sup> genomes and the frequency of recombination between chromosomes from different genomes is likely to be very low leading to unviable gametes. However, cross fertility and seeds set per cross increase remarkably in the backcross generations and self-fertility is restored after only two backcrosses.</p><p>Traditional cytogenetic methods such as GISH are not helpful in detecting the presence of <italic>T. urartu</italic> chromatin in the wheat background in an interspecific hybrid since <italic>T. urartu</italic> is the A genome donor of common wheat (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Dvorak et al., 1993</xref>). In addition to traditional FISH probes such as pSc119.2 and pAs1, probe pTm30, essentially a (GAA)n microsatellite marker, has been shown to produce major hybridization sites on the A genome chromosomes of diploid wheats including <italic>T. urartu</italic> (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Adonina et al., 2015</xref>). However, these FISH probes are still not able to distinguish between all A genome chromosomes and they demonstrate polymorphisms between accessions of different diploid and hexaploid wheats (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Adonina et al., 2015</xref>). Moreover the (GAA)n microsatellite marker has been shown to distinguish between A genome chromosomes of diploid wheats such as <italic>T. urartu</italic>, <italic>T. boeticum</italic>, and <italic>T. monococcum</italic> but not between the A genome chromosomes of <italic>T. urartu</italic> and hexaploid wheat (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Megyeri et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Adonina et al., 2015</xref>). This makes detection of chromosomes originating from wild diploid A genome species, such as <italic>T. urartu</italic>, difficult in the presence of the A genome chromosomes of hexaploid wheat.</p><p>In the absence of clear cytogenetic characterisation of wheat-<italic>T. urartu</italic> introgression lines, SNP markers prove vital in enabling the detection of <italic>T. urartu</italic> chromosomes in a wheat background. The Axiom<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Wheat-Relative Genotyping Array has been successfully validated as a high throughput genotyping platform consisting of SNP markers that are able to detect the presence of various wheat wild relatives in a hybrid line (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Grewal et al., 2018</xref>). In previous studies that have used this array, the introgressions detected by the SNP markers were also validated by GISH studies thereby indicating that the array was successful at detecting the presence of various sized segments of wild relatives in a wheat background. In this study using the same array, 368 SNPs were mapped into seven LGs that represented the genetic map of <italic>T. urartu</italic> with a total map length of 772.1 cM (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The average chromosome length was found to be 110.3 cM, however, for chromosome 4A<sup>u</sup> it was calculated to be 31 cM (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) due to the least number of recombination events in this LG as compared to the others. This was possibly due to the rearrangement of wheat chromosome 4A (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Devos et al., 1995</xref>) which impacted the recombination between chromosomes 4A and 4A<sup>u</sup>. This result is supported by the comparative analysis of the markers on the genetic map of textitT. urartu and their orthologous sequences on the Tu chromosomes and the wheat A genome (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). The comparison of the chromosomes showed high levels of collinearity and synteny between the two species, including the presence of the 4A/5A translocation in <italic>T. urartu</italic> which has been previously reported (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 1994</xref>), except in LG 4 where the wheat chromosome 4A showed an inversion as compared to chromosome 4A<sup>u</sup>. However, it should be noted that the SNP markers described in this paper are not able to distinguish which of the genomes of wheat the <italic>T. urartu</italic> introgressions have recombined with. The introgressions were produced using the <italic>ph1</italic> system and therefore it is possible that recombination has taken place between the <italic>T. urartu</italic> and the B or D genomes of wheat as well as the A genome. It is possible to use multi-color GISH to distinguish the A, B and D genomes of wheat (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Grewal et al., 2018</xref>) and thus, visualize an A-B or A-D recombinant. However, because of the <italic>ph1</italic> system used in this work, it is possible that recombination could have also occurred between the three genomes of wheat. It would therefore be impossible to determine which A genome (A or A<sup>u</sup>) was involved in any recombination event with the B or D genomes of wheat. We are currently developing a set of wheat genome specific markers which will enable the identification of the wheat genome involved in the recombination once the introgression lines are homozygous and stable, i.e., these markers would be able to detect which of the wheat genome regions had been replaced by the <italic>T. urartu</italic> introgressions.</p><p>Through marker assisted selection, the <italic>T. urartu</italic> segments were tracked in the backcross populations (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) leading to identification of lines with three or fewer segments that were eventually self-fertilized. From these lines, a panel of 17 interspecific lines, having various sized introgressions that potentially span the entire genome of <italic>T. urartu</italic>, is also described in this study (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). These lines aim to provide a valuable germplasm resource for phenotyping program, with the aim of transferring a wide variety of traits from <italic>T. urartu</italic> into all regions of the wheat genome for the introduction of genetic variation.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Availability</title><p>The raw genotyping data supporting the conclusions of this manuscript will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation, to any qualified researcher.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>JK, SG, CY, SH-E, DS, SA, and IK carried out the crossing program. SH-E, DS, SA, and CY prepared the samples for genotyping. AB ran the samples on the array. SG analyzed the genotyping data and constructed the genetic map. SG and PW worked on the comparative studies. IK and JK conceived and designed the experiments. SG wrote the manuscript with assistance from JK. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council (Grant No. BB/J004596/1) as part of the Wheat Improvement Strategic Programme (WISP). The funding body played no role in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank Prof. Keith Edwards and Dr. Sacha Allen at Bristol University for their technical assistance in the genotyping.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01565/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01565/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Table_1.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Table_2.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adonina</surname><given-names>I. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncharov</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Badaeva</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sergeeva</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrash</surname><given-names>N. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salina</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>(GAA)n microsatellite as an indicator of the A genome reorganization during wheat evolution and domestication.</article-title>
<source><italic>Comp. Cytogenet.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>547</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/CompCytogen.v9i4.5120</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26753073?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26753073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alaux</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Letellier</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfama</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pommier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Linking the international wheat genome sequencing consortium bread wheat reference genome sequence to wheat genetic and phenomic data.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>:<issue>111</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-018-1491-4</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30115101?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30115101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caballero</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Development and gluten strength evaluation of introgression lines of triticum urartu in durum wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cereal Res. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>248</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/CRC.37.2009.2.11</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Dry matter yields and photosynthetic rates of diploid and hexaploid triticum species.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>857</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aob.a087169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhagwat</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Flag leaf photosynthesis of <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> and related diploid and tetraploid species.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>189</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aob.a086238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;rner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogbonnaya</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;der</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Periyannan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagudah</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;<italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> introgressions in wheat,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Alien Introgression in Wheat</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Moln&#x000e1;r-L&#x000e1;ng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceoloni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dole&#x0017e;el</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burridge</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>G. L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coghill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;High-density SNP genotyping array for hexaploid wheat and its relatives,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Wheat Biotechnology: Methods and Protocols</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>Equivalence of the a genome of bread wheat and that of <italic>Triticum urartu.</italic></article-title>
<source><italic>Genet. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0016672300016244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Deepening the wheat gene pool.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Crop Prod.</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1300/J144v01n01-01</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Comparing two approaches for introgression of germplasm from <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> into common wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop J.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cj.2017.05.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devos</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubcovsky</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinoy</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Structural evolution of wheat chromosomes 4A, 5A, and 7B and its impact on recombination.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>91</volume>
<fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf00220890</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24169776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24169776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dvo&#x00159;&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>The relationship between the genome of <italic>Triticum urartu</italic> and the A and B genomes of <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Can. J. Genet. Cytol.</italic></source>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>377</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g76-045</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 3209062?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3209062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dvo&#x00159;&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Effect of the removal of genes promoting homoeologous chromosome pairing on chromosome pairing in <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> x <italic>Triticum urartu Amphiploids</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Can. J. Genet. Cytol.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>544</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g78-063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terlizzi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Resta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The evolution of polyploid wheats: identification of the A genome donor species.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g93-004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fricano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandolini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sourdille</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunder</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Effgen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Crossability of <italic>Triticum urartu</italic> and <italic>Triticum monococcum</italic> wheats, homoeologous recombination, and description of a panel of interspecific introgression lines.</article-title>
<source><italic>G3</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>1931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1941</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.114.013623</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25147190?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25147190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friebe</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>F. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Alien introgressions represent a rich source of genes for crop improvement.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>7657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7658</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1104845108</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21527718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21527718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholefield</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashling</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burridge</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Characterisation of <italic>Thinopyrum bessarabicum</italic> chromosomes through genome-wide introgressions into wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>131</volume>
<fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>406</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-017-3009-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29101420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29101420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>International Wheat Genome Sequencing Consortium [IWGSC]</collab>, <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Appels</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eversole</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuillet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Shifting the limits in wheat research and breeding using a fully annotated reference genome.</article-title>
<source><italic>Science</italic></source>
<volume>361</volume>:<issue>eaar7191</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aar7191</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30115783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30115783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhaliwal</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>Reproductive Isolation of <italic>Triticum boeoticum</italic> and <italic>Triticum urartu</italic> and the origin of the tetraploid wheats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. J. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>1088</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1094</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2441653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>I. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Purdie</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reader</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittaway</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orford</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Detection of interchromosomal translocations within the Triticeae by RFLP analysis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>882</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>887</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g94-125</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18470131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18470131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholefield</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashling</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>A step change in the transfer of interspecific variation into wheat from <italic>Amblyopyrum muticum</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Biotechnol. J.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12606</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27459228?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27459228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbart Edwards</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholefield</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashling</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Introgression of <italic>Aegilops speltoides</italic> segments in <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> and the effect of the gametocidal genes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>121</volume>
<fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcx149</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29216335?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29216335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krzywinski</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Birol</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connors</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascoyne</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horsman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome Res.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1645</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.092759.109</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19541911?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19541911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>H.-Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Genome sequence of the progenitor of wheat a subgenome <italic>Triticum urartu</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>557</volume>
<fpage>424</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0108-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29743678?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29743678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinoy</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devos</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Nonhomoeologous translocations between group 4, 5 and 7 chromosomes within wheat and rye.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>312</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf00224276</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24202512?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24202512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Polymorphisms at the Gli-A u 1 and Gli-A u 2 loci in wild diploid wheat (<italic>Triticum urartu</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>163</volume>
<fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-008-9656-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Megyeri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kov&#x000e1;cs</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moln&#x000e1;r-L&#x000e1;ng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moln&#x000e1;r</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Karyotypic analysis of <italic>Triticum monococcum</italic> using standard repetitive DNA probes and simple sequence repeats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Acta Agronomica Hungarica</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/AAgr.60.2012.2.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardle</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>W. T. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Flapjack &#x02013; graphical genotype visualization.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>3133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3134</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq580</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20956241?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20956241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Analysis of fluorescence transients of DCMU-treated leaves of Triticum species to provide estimates of the densities of photosystem II reaction centres.</article-title>
<source><italic>Photosynth. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf00014675</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24443118?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24443118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Microsatellite mapping of a <italic>Triticum urartu</italic> Tum. derived powdery mildew resistance gene transferred to common wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>111</volume>
<fpage>1524</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1531</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-005-0081-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16177900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16177900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Su&#x000e1;rez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Applicability of chromosome-specific SSR wheat markers for the introgression of <italic>Triticum urartu</italic> in durum wheat breeding programmes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Genet. Resour.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>444</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S147926211100061X</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouse</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Stem rust resistance in a-genome diploid relatives of wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Dis.</italic></source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>941</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>944</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-04-10-0260</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22070278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22070278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheedy</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Diploid and tetraploid progenitors of wheat are valuable sources of resistance to the root lesion nematode <italic>Pratylenchus thornei</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>186</volume>
<fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>391</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-011-0617-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>V. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danilova</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrana</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubalakova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Exploring the tertiary gene pool of bread wheat: sequence assembly and analysis of chromosome 5M(g) of <italic>Aegilops geniculata.</italic></article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>84</volume>
<fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>746</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13036</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26408103?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26408103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>V. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vr&#x000e1;na</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friebe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubal&#x000e1;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>SNP discovery for mapping alien introgressions in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Genomics</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>:<issue>273</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-273</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24716476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24716476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valkoun</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Wheat pre-breeding using wild progenitors.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>119</volume>
<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1017562909881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Berloo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>GGT 2.0: versatile software for visualization and analysis of genetic data.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Hered.</italic></source>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>232</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>236</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/esm109</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18222930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18222930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Ooijen</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Multipoint maximum likelihood mapping in a full-sib family of an outbreeding species.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genet. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0016672311000279</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21878144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21878144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voorrips</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>MapChart: software for the graphical presentation of linkage maps and QTLs.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Hered.</italic></source>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/93.1.77</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12011185?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burridge</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>G. L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benbow</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>High-density SNP genotyping array for hexaploid wheat and its secondary and tertiary gene pool.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Biotechnol. J.</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>1195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1206</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12485</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26466852?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26466852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coghill</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burridge</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Targeted re-sequencing of the allohexaploid wheat exome.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Biotechnol. J.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>742</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-7652.2012.00713.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22703335?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22703335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leamy</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barazani</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B.-H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Back into the wild&#x02014;apply untapped genetic diversity of wild relatives for crop improvement.</article-title>
<source><italic>Evol. Appl.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eva.12434</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28035232?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28035232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>