<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rice (N Y)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rice (N Y)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Rice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1939-8425</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1939-8433</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5943206</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12284-018-0225-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Outgrowth of Rice Tillers Requires Availability of Glutamine in the Basal Portions of Shoots</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3862-3073</contrib-id><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>Miwa</given-names></name><address><phone>+81-52-789-5511</phone><email>ohashi@agr.nagoya-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>Keiki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>Soichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>Noriyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>Kazuhiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miyao</surname><given-names>Mitsue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>Toshihiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>Tomoyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2248 6943</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.69566.3a</institution-id><institution>Graduate School of Agricultural Science, Tohoku University, </institution></institution-wrap>468-1 Aoba, Aramaki-Aza, Aoba-ku, Sendai, 980-8572 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2151 536X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.26999.3d</institution-id><institution>The University of Tokyo, Graduate School of Agricultural and Life Sciences, Institute of Sustainable Agro-ecosystem Services (ISAS), </institution></institution-wrap>1-1-1 Midori-cho, Nishitokyo, Tokyo, 188-0002 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0943 978X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27476.30</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Graduate School of Bioagricultural Sciences, Nagoya University, </institution></institution-wrap>Furo-cho, Chikusa-ku, Nagoya, 464-8601 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1302 4472</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.261356.5</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Institute of Plant Science and Resources, Okayama University, </institution></institution-wrap>2-20-1 Chuo, Kurashiki, 710-0046 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2248 6943</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.69566.3a</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Division for Interdisciplinary Advanced Research and Education, </institution><institution>Tohoku University, </institution></institution-wrap>6-3 Aoba, Aramaki-Aza, Aoba-ku, Sendai, 980-0845 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>31</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Our previous studies concluded that metabolic disorder in the basal portions of rice shoots caused by a lack of cytosolic glutamine synthetase1;2 (GS1;2) resulted in a severe reduction in the outgrowth of tillers. Rice mutants lacking GS1;2 (<italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants) showed a remarkable reduction in the contents of both glutamine and asparagine in the basal portions of shoots. In the current study, we attempted to reveal the mechanisms for this decrease in asparagine content using rice mutants lacking either GS1;2 or asparagine synthetase 1 (AS1). The contributions of the availability of glutamine and asparagine to the outgrowth of rice tillers were investigated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">Rice has two <italic>AS</italic> genes, and the enzymes catalyse asparagine synthesis from glutamine. In the basal portions of rice shoots, expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic>, the major species in this tissue, was reduced in <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants, whereas <italic>OsAS2</italic> expression was relatively constant. <italic>OsAS1</italic> was expressed in phloem companion cells of the nodal vascular anastomoses connected to the axillary bud vasculatures in the basal portions of wild-type shoots, whereas cell-specific expression was markedly reduced in <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants. <italic>OsAS1</italic> was up-regulated significantly by NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply in the wild type but not in <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants. When GS reactions were inhibited by methionine sulfoximine, <italic>OsAS1</italic> was up-regulated by glutamine but not by NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>. The rice mutants lacking AS1 (<italic>as1</italic> mutants) showed a decrease in asparagine content in the basal portions of shoots. However, glutamine content and tiller number were less affected by the lack of AS1.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">These results indicate that in phloem companion cells of the nodal vascular anastomoses, asparagine synthesis is largely dependent on glutamine or its related metabolite-responsive AS1. Thus, the decrease in glutamine content caused by a lack of GS1;2 is suggested to result in low expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic>, decreasing asparagine content. However, the availability of asparagine generated from AS1 reactions is apparently less effective for the outgrowth of tillers. With respect to the tiller number and the contents of glutamine and asparagine in <italic>gs1;2</italic> and <italic>as1</italic> mutants, the availability of glutamine rather than asparagine in basal portions of rice shoots may be required for the outgrowth of rice tillers.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12284-018-0225-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Asparagine</kwd><kwd>Asparagine synthetase</kwd><kwd>Cytosolic glutamine synthetase</kwd><kwd>Glutamine</kwd><kwd>Tiller</kwd><kwd>Rice</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan</institution></funding-source><award-id>22119003</award-id><award-id>GRENE NC-CARP project</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>Tomoyuki</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001691</institution-id><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>15K14674</award-id><award-id>15H04468</award-id><award-id>26450073</award-id><award-id>16J01799</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>Miwa</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>Soichi</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>Toshihiko</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Division for International Advanced Research and Education (DIARE), Tohoku University</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par12">Glutamine and asparagine play crucial roles in plant growth and development as the major nitrogen forms for transport via vasculatures from source to sink tissues within various plants (Urquhart and Joy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1981</xref>; Ireland and Lea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">1999</xref>; Lea et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2007</xref>; Gaufichon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2010</xref>). In rice plants, these amides are major nitrogen forms in both phloem (Hayashi and Chino <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1990</xref>) and xylem sap (Fukumorita and Chino <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1982</xref>; Funayama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2013</xref>; Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). In higher plants, including rice, glutamine is synthesized by glutamine synthetase (GS) (Lea and Miflin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1974</xref>; Yamaya and Oaks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2004</xref>), and asparagine is synthesized from glutamine by asparagine synthetase (AS) (Lea et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2007</xref>; Gaufichon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2010</xref>; Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). Asparagine is catabolized by asparaginase into aspartate as the common precursor of the essential amino acids (Azevedo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2006</xref>; Lea et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2007</xref>; Yabuki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2017</xref>).</p><p id="Par13">Rice has three cytosolic GS isoenzymes (GS1, <italic>OsGS1;1</italic> &#x02013; <italic>OsGS1;3</italic>) and one chloroplastic GS (GS2) (Tabuchi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2007</xref>). The occurrence of two AS isoenzymes (<italic>OsAS1</italic> and <italic>OsAS2</italic>) was recently confirmed (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). Both GS1;2 and AS1 are important in the primary assimilation of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> taken up by rice roots (Funayama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2013</xref>; Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). <italic>OsGS1;2</italic> and <italic>OsAS1</italic> were specifically accumulated in three cell layers of root surfaces (epidermis, exodermis and sclerenchyma) after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply to rice roots (Ishiyama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2004</xref>; Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). In both roots and xylem sap after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply, rice mutants lacking GS1;2 showed a decrease in glutamine and asparagine content, while mutants lacking AS1 showed a decrease in asparagine content (Funayama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2013</xref>; Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>).</p><p id="Par14">Tiller number is a critical agronomic trait defining grain yields in rice and is influenced by the availability of nitrogen (Mae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1997</xref>; Sakamoto and Matsuoka <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2008</xref>; Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2011</xref>). We found that the lack of GS1;2 suppressed the outgrowth of the tiller axillary bud and hence a substantial decrease in active tiller number and yields (Funayama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2013</xref>; Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015b</xref>). The outgrowth of tiller axillary buds has been proposed to be related to metabolite use efficiency and hormone signalling networks (Domagalska and Leyser <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2011</xref>; Evers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2011</xref>). We recently showed that metabolic disorder in the basal portions of rice shoots lacking GS1;2 caused a severe reduction in the outgrowth of tiller axillary buds, and this reduction was independent of the content of strigolactone (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015b</xref>), a phytohormone inhibiting tiller development (Umehara et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2008</xref>). The basal portions of rice shoots are important organs for the circulation of metabolites because of vascular networks (Hoshikawa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1989</xref>). These organs consist of axillary buds, internodes, and shoot apical meristems (SAMs) (Hoshikawa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1989</xref>; Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015b</xref>). In the basal portions of rice shoots, GS1;2 protein localizes in phloem companion cells of the nodal vascular anastomoses connecting to the axillary bud vasculatures (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015b</xref>). The lack of GS1;2 caused a large decrease in both glutamine and asparagine contents in roots and the basal portions of shoots (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>). This decrease in glutamine content in the basal portions of shoots caused a deficiency of active cytokinin, which is required for the outgrowth of rice tillers, via the down-regulation of glutamine or its related metabolite-dependent cytokinin synthesis (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>). Thus, the availability of glutamine and/or asparagine is required for the outgrowth of rice tillers (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>).</p><p id="Par15">In the present study, we focused on the reduction of asparagine content in the basal portions of rice mutants lacking GS1;2 (<italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants). Using rice mutants lacking either GS1;2 or AS1 (<italic>as1</italic> mutants), we investigated (1) the molecular mechanisms involved in the decrease in asparagine content in the basal portions of <italic>gs1;2</italic> shoots and (2) the relation between low availability of asparagine and the reduction in tiller number.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Reduced Expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic> in Phloem Companion Cells of the Nodal Vascular Anastomoses in the Basal Portions of Shoots Lacking GS1;2</title><p id="Par16">Expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic> in the basal portions of shoots of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-fed <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutant seedlings at the fourth-leaf stage showed an approximately 60% reduction compared with the level in the wild-type rice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However, the expression of <italic>OsAS2</italic> in the <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants was less affected in the basal portions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). <italic>OsAS1</italic> was expressed at twice the level of <italic>OsAS2</italic> in the basal portions of wild-type shoots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>qPCR analysis of <italic>OsASs</italic> in the basal portions of wild-type and <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutant shoots. qPCR analysis of <italic>OsAS1</italic> and <italic>OsAS2</italic> genes (<bold>a</bold>) and a control <italic>Actin1</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) in the basal portions of shoots of wild-type plants (WT: black column) and <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants (<italic>gs1;2</italic>: grey column) were performed. Rice seedlings were grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl until the fourth-leaf stage. Mean values with SE of four independent samples are shown. An asterisk denotes a statistically significant difference between wild type and <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants (*, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 by Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_225_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">In situ hybridization revealed strong signals for the <italic>OsAS1</italic> transcript in phloem companion cells of the nodal vascular anastomoses in the basal portion of wild-type shoots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d, e</xref>). However, the signal intensity for <italic>OsAS1</italic> in phloem companion cells of the nodal vascular anastomoses in the <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants was much lower than in the wild-type rice. Weak signals for <italic>OsAS1</italic> were also detected in the SAMs and immature leaves in both the <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants and wild-type rice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b, g, h</xref>). Signals for the <italic>OsAS2</italic> transcript were also detected in phloem companion cells of the nodal vascular anastomoses, and weak signals were detected in the SAM and immature leaves in both the <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants and wild-type rice. Unlike <italic>OsAS1,</italic> the signal intensity of the <italic>OsAS2</italic> transcript was not significantly different between <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants and wild-type rice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a, b, d, e, g, h</xref>). These results fit well with the results obtained from quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). When the control sense probes were used, only background levels of the <italic>OsAS1</italic> and <italic>OsAS2</italic> transcript were detected (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c, f, i</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c, f, i</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>In situ hybridization for <italic>OsAS1</italic> in the basal portions of wild-type and <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutant shoots. Longitudinal sections of basal portions of shoots were prepared from the wild-type rice (WT) (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>, <bold>f</bold>, <bold>g</bold>, <bold>i</bold>) and from <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants (<italic>gs1;2</italic>) (<bold>b</bold>, <bold>e</bold>, <bold>h</bold>) grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl until the fourth-leaf stage. A sense probe was hybridized to WT sections (<bold>c</bold>, <bold>f</bold>, <bold>i</bold>) as a negative control. Red arrowheads indicate hybridization signals for <italic>OsAS1</italic> transcripts in the shoot apical meristem (SAM) (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>), phloem companion cell of the nodal vascular anastomoses (cc) (<bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold>), an immature leaf (IML) area (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>, <bold>g</bold>, <bold>h</bold>), and the tiller containing the axillary bud meristem (AM) (<bold>g</bold>, <bold>h</bold>). Note that the signal intensity in <italic>gs1;2</italic> (<bold>e</bold>) was far weaker than in the WT (<bold>d</bold>). Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>a</bold> - <bold>c</bold>, <bold>g</bold> - <bold>i</bold>) and 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>d</bold> - <bold>f</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_225_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>In situ hybridization for <italic>OsAS2</italic> in the basal portions of wild-type and <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutant shoots. Longitudinal sections of basal portions of shoots were prepared from the wild-type rice (WT) (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>, <bold>f</bold>, <bold>g</bold>, <bold>i</bold>) and the <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants (<italic>gs1;2</italic>) (<bold>b</bold>, <bold>e</bold>, <bold>h</bold>) grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl until the fourth-leaf stage. A sense probe was hybridized to WT sections (<bold>c</bold>, <bold>f</bold>, <bold>i</bold>) as a negative control. Red arrowheads indicate hybridization signals for <italic>OsAS2</italic> transcripts in the shoot apical meristem (SAM) (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>), phloem companion cell of the nodal vascular anastomoses (cc) (<bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold>), an immature leaf (IML) area (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>, <bold>g</bold>, <bold>h</bold>), and the tiller containing the axillary bud meristem (AM) (<bold>g</bold>, <bold>h</bold>). Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>a</bold> - <bold>c</bold>, <bold>g</bold> - <bold>i</bold>) and 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m (<bold>d</bold> - <bold>f</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_225_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Reduction in <italic>OsAS1</italic> Expression and Asparagine Content after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> Supply to the <italic>gs1;2</italic> Mutants</title><p id="Par18">In rice roots, up-regulation of <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression and accumulation of asparagine content were observed after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). In the current study, <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression and asparagine content after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply were determined in the basal portions of shoots using <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutant and wild-type plants. <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression was increased over twofold at 8&#x000a0;h after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply in the shoot basal portions of the wild type, whereas it was less changed in the <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). In contrast, there were no significant differences in the expression of <italic>OsAS2</italic> and <italic>Actin1</italic> between the shoot basal portions of wild type and <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants treated with or without NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b, c</xref>). Asparagine was accumulated remarkably at 24&#x000a0;h after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply in the shoot basal portions of the wild type, whereas it was relatively constant in the <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>). NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> was highly accumulated in these tissues in <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e</xref>), indicating impairment of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> assimilation. Under the same conditions, glutamine content was less affected 24&#x000a0;h after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply in the shoot basal portions of <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>), as in the case of asparagine content in the current study (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Expression levels of <italic>OsASs</italic> and contents of asparagine and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> in the basal portions. <bold>a</bold> - <bold>c</bold> Transcript contents of the <italic>OsAS1</italic> (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>OsAS2</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and a control <italic>Actin1</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) in the basal portions of shoots of wild-type plants (WT: black column) and <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants (<italic>gs1;2</italic>: grey column) at the seventh-leaf stage for seedlings grown in water for 3 d followed by treatments with (+NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) or without (-N) 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl for 8&#x000a0;h. (<bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold>) Contents of asparagine (<bold>d</bold>) and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (<bold>e</bold>) in the basal portions of shoots of WT (black column) and <italic>gs1;2</italic> (grey column) at the fourth-leaf stage for seedlings grown in water for 3 d followed by treatments with or without 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl for 24&#x000a0;h. Mean values with SE of four independent samples are shown. Asterisks denote statistically significant differences between samples treated with and without 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl (*, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 by Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_225_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">Further qPCR analysis was carried out in the presence or absence of 1&#x000a0;mM methionine sulfoximine (MSX), an inhibitor of GS reactions. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>, a substantial increase in <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression was observed at 8&#x000a0;h after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply in the basal portions of shoots, but this increase was not observed when MSX was treated prior to NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). Over a three-fold increase in <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression was observed after glutamine supply with or without MSX pre-treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). As in <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression, the significant increase in <italic>OsGS1;2</italic> expression was observed after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> or glutamine supply, but an increase in <italic>OsGS1;2</italic> expression was not observed for the MSX treatment (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1b). The expression of <italic>OsAS2</italic> was stable after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply, while glutamine supply caused a decrease in its expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). There were slight fluctuations in the expression of <italic>OsGS1;1</italic> and <italic>Actin1</italic> used as a control treated with or without NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1a).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>qPCR analysis of <italic>OsASs</italic> in the basal portions of wild-type shoots using MSX. Wild-type rice seedlings were grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl until the fourth-leaf stage and then transferred into water for 3 d. After pre-treatment with 1&#x000a0;mM MSX for 2&#x000a0;h, the seedlings were treated for 8&#x000a0;h with 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (MSX&#x02009;+&#x02009;NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) or 5&#x000a0;mM glutamine (MSX&#x02009;+&#x02009;Gln). The seedlings without MSX pre-treatment were also treated for 8&#x000a0;h with 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (+NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>), 5&#x000a0;mM glutamine (Gln) or without nitrogen nutrients (-N). qPCR analyses of <italic>OsAS1</italic> (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>OsAS2</italic> (<bold>b</bold>), and <italic>actin1</italic> transcripts (<bold>c</bold>) were performed in the shoot basal parts. Fold changes of transcript levels in each treatment relative to those in &#x02013;N were calculated, and mean values with SE of four independent samples are shown. Asterisks denote statistically significant differences between the samples treated without nitrogen nutrients (-N) and each treated sample (*, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 by Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_225_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">In the roots, <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression was increased significantly after NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply, but this increase was not observed in the MSX treatment (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S2a). Increases in <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression were observed after glutamine supply with or without MSX treatment (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S2a).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Lack of AS1 Caused a Reduction in Asparagine Content in the Basal Portions of Rice Shoots but not in Tiller Number</title><p id="Par21">To examine the contribution of availability of asparagine generated from AS1 reactions in the basal portions of shoots to the outgrowth of rice tillers, reverse genetics studies were carried out using homozygous rice mutants lacking <italic>OsAS1</italic> (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). Our previous study showed that the lack of AS1 did not affect the expression of other genes related to nitrogen metabolism in roots (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). In the basal portions of shoots growing with NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>, the <italic>as1</italic> mutants exhibited no significant difference in <italic>OsAS2</italic> expression, but an approximately 80% decrease in asparagine content was observed compared with the content in the wild type (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a, c</xref>). In addition, transient NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply for 24&#x000a0;h to nitrogen-depleted <italic>as1</italic> mutants caused an approximately 60% decrease in asparagine content in the shoot basal portions (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S3a). There were slight fluctuations in the content of glutamine and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> between the basal portions of shoots of <italic>as1</italic> mutants and the wild type when plants were grown with NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6d, c</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S3b, d).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>qPCR and amino acid analysis in the basal portions of wild-type and <italic>as1</italic> mutant shoots. qPCR analysis of <italic>OsAS2</italic> (<bold>a</bold>) and <italic>Actin1</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and analyses of asparagine (<bold>c</bold>), glutamine (<bold>d</bold>) and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> contents (<bold>e</bold>) were performed in the basal portions of shoots of the wild type (WT: black column) and two lines of <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>as1-m1</italic> and <italic>as1-m2</italic>: dark and light grey column, respectively). Seedlings were grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl until the fourth-leaf stage. Mean values with SE of four independent samples are shown. One-way ANOVAs followed by Bonferroni tests were used to identify significant differences between the wild type and <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_225_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">No significant differences between <italic>as1</italic> mutants and the wild type were observed with respect to tiller number and leaf stage under 1&#x000a0;mM and 2&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The outgrowth of primary tiller was little affected in <italic>as1</italic> mutants grown with 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> until fifth leaf stage (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S4). The same is true when those plants were grown in the paddy field under normal fertilization (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). There were also no significant differences in shoot length, dry weight, or panicle number between <italic>as1</italic> mutants and wild-type plants grown in the paddy field (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In our experiments in the paddy field, the lodging phenotype was not observed in <italic>as1</italic> mutants (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S5).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Comparison of leaf stage and tiller number between the wild type and <italic>as1</italic> mutants. Wild-type (WT: black diamond) plants and two lines of <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>as1-m1</italic> and <italic>as1-m2</italic>: black square and grey triangle, respectively) were grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold>) or 2&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl (<bold>b</bold>, <bold>d</bold>) until 50&#x000a0;days after germination. Time course studies on measurements of leaf stage and tiller number were conducted. Mean values with SE of four independent samples are shown. One-way ANOVAs followed by Bonferroni tests were used to identify significant differences between the wild type and <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12284_2018_225_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Tiller number, panicle number and parameters of growth of plants growing in the paddy field</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>wild type</th><th>
<italic>as1-m1</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>as1-m2</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">Tiller number per plant</td><td align="center">25.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.83</td><td align="center">25.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.01</td><td align="center">22.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="center">a</td><td align="center">a</td><td align="center">a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Panicle number per plant</td><td align="center">20.32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.19</td><td align="center">20.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.71</td><td align="center">18.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98</td></tr><tr><td align="center">a</td><td align="center">a</td><td align="center">a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Shoot length (cm)</td><td align="center">100.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.23</td><td align="center">100.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.62</td><td align="center">94.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.99</td></tr><tr><td align="center">a</td><td align="center">a</td><td align="center">a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Shoot dry weight per plant (g)</td><td align="center">57.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.47</td><td align="center">65.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.79</td><td align="center">50.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.13</td></tr><tr><td align="center">ab</td><td align="center">a</td><td align="center">b</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">Wild-type plants and two lines of <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>as1-m1</italic> and <italic>as1-m2</italic>) were grown in the paddy field under normal fertilization. Tiller number was measured at the panicle initiation stage. After panicle ripening, rice plants were harvested and shoot length, shoot dry weight without panicle and panicle number were measured. Mean values with SE of four independent plots (five average plants selected from each plot) are shown. One-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni tests were used to identify significant differences between the wild type and <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24">A lack of GS1;2 caused a reduction in asparagine content in the basal portions of shoots (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>). The current study showed that the expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic>, the major species in the basal portions of shoots, was decreased by the lack of GS1;2, whereas <italic>OsAS2</italic>, which is dominant in rice leaves, was less affected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). In fact, the lack of AS1 severely decreased the asparagine content in the basal portions of shoots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref>). These results indicate that the low expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic> caused a decrease in asparagine content in the shoot basal portions of <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants. In the basal portions of shoots, GS1;2 and AS1 are suggested to be important in the biosynthesis of asparagine, whereas the contribution of AS2 to this process may be limited (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">Gene expression analyses clearly showed that the expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic>, but not <italic>OsAS2</italic>, in both roots and shoot basal portions was enhanced by NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and glutamine (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S2) (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). The NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-induced <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression was inhibited when GS1;2 was missing or GS activity was inhibited by MSX treatment (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S2). In addition, <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression was enhanced by glutamine when GS activity was inhibited by MSX treatment. These results are in close agreement with a previous study by Kawachi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2002</xref>), which showed that the NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>-induced accumulation of AS protein in rice roots was completely inhibited by MSX treatment. These results indicate that glutamine or its related metabolite, but not NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> itself, acts as a signal molecule for the stimulation of <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression in both roots and shoot basal portions, where AS1 is the major isoform (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S2) (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). In addition, the expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic> in phloem companion cells of nodal vascular anastomoses, overlapping with <italic>OsGS1;2</italic> expression (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015b</xref>), was reduced by the lack of GS1;2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d, e</xref>). These results possibly allow glutamine, which is produced by GS1;2, to directly induce the expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic> and to be used for asparagine synthesis within these cells. We conclude that the low availability of glutamine caused reduced expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic>, decreasing asparagine synthesis, in phloem companion cells of the nodal vascular anastomoses in the basal portions of shoots in the <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants.</p><p id="Par26">There are also several genes reported to be up-regulated by glutamine or related metabolites in rice and other plants, i.e., in rice, <italic>ammonium transporter1;1</italic> (<italic>OsAMT1;1</italic>) and <italic>OsAMT1;2</italic> (Sonoda et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2003</xref>), <italic>NADH-glutamate synthase1</italic> (Hirose et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1997</xref>), and <italic>adenosine phosphate-isopentenyltransferases4</italic> (<italic>IPT4</italic>) and <italic>IPT5</italic> (Kamada-Nobusada et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2013</xref>); in Arabidopsis, <italic>glutamine symtnetase1</italic> (Oliveira and Coruzzi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1999</xref>), <italic>AtAMT1;1</italic> (Rawat et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1999</xref>), and <italic>AtAS</italic> (Lam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1994</xref>); and nitrate reductase in tobacco leaves (Vincentz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1993</xref>). The signalling mechanism in response to glutamine apparently contributes to modulating plant growth. However, few details are known regarding glutamine signalling, unlike the case of nitrate signalling (Sakakibara et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2006</xref>). It is worth examining the glutamine responsive induction of <italic>OsAS1</italic> to understand the mechanism of glutamine signalling in response to NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>.</p><p id="Par27">As discussed previously (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015b</xref>), GS1;2 has a role in the re-assimilation of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> released from the phenylalanine ammonia-lyase (PAL) reaction during lignification in the basal portions of shoots. In fact, the biosynthesis of lignin accounts for 10&#x02013;23% in rice internodes (Ookawa and Ishihara <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1993</xref>; Ookawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1993</xref>), and PAL activity in the basal portions of rice shoots was approximately 20-fold higher than in leaf blade at the seedling stage (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Figure S6). Thus, in the basal portions of rice shoots, NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> released during lignification must be re-assimilated immediately to avoid the potential toxicity of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and the loss of nitrogen (Sakurai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2001</xref>). In the basal portions of shoots, AS1 and GS1;2 could contribute to the re-assimilation of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> during lignification. Considering its cellular localization in phloem companion cells of the nodal vascular anastomoses, the asparagine from AS1 reactions in these cells is apparently transported to sink organs, such as axillary buds, for its outgrowth and development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Asparagine is catabolized by asparaginase into aspartate as the common precursor of the essential amino acids (Azevedo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2006</xref>; Lea et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2007</xref>; Yabuki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2017</xref>).</p><p id="Par28">The lack of GS1;2 caused decreases in tiller number, rice yields and glutamine and asparagine content in the basal portions of shoots (Funayama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2013</xref>; Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>), while a lack of AS1 caused a decrease in only asparagine content and had less of an effect on tiller number and glutamine content (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). These results indicate that the availability of asparagine generated from AS1 reactions apparently contributes less to the outgrowth of tillers in rice plants under conditions of sufficient glutamine. Thus, we conclude that the reduction in tiller number in <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants is independent of the low availability of asparagine in the basal portions of shoots. Previous research has revealed that glutamine generated from GS1;2 reactions contributes to the outgrowth of tillers via glutamine-dependent cytokinin synthesis (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>). Compared to that of glutamine, the contribution of asparagine to the outgrowth of rice tillers is suggested to be limited.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par29">Our results demonstrated that the expression of <italic>OsAS1</italic> could be induced by glutamine or its related metabolite in both roots and the basal portions of rice shoots. Especially in phloem companion cells of the nodal vascular anastomoses, asparagine synthesis is largely dependent on glutamine-responsive AS1. Thus, we conclude that the low availability of asparagine in <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutants was caused by the reduction in glutamine content, which is required for the up-regulation of <italic>OsAS1</italic> expression. Availability of glutamine is suggested to be more important than that of asparagine for the outgrowth of rice tillers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Plant Materials</title><p id="Par30">This study utilized the rice (<italic>Oryza. sativa</italic> L.) cultivar &#x02018;Nipponbare&#x02019; as the wild-type plants as well as a retrotransposon <italic>Tos17</italic>-inserted line of the <italic>gs1;2</italic> mutant and two lines of <italic>as1</italic> mutants (Funayama et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2013</xref>; Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). The seeds of these rice plants were germinated and grown hydroponically until either the fourth- or seventh-leaf stage in an outdoor greenhouse. The temperature was controlled at 26&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C during the day with supplemental light for 13&#x000a0;h. The hydroponic culture solution was renewed once per week with 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl as described in Ohashi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>). Longitudinal sections (5&#x000a0;mm) of basal portions of shoots including axillary buds, internodes and a SAMs were prepared by removing the primary and secondary leaves, seeds and roots as described in Ohashi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>). The basal portions of shoots at the fourth-leaf stage or seventh-leaf stage were used for the determination of the amino acid and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> content, in situ hybridization, and qPCR analyses.</p><p id="Par31">When the short-term effects of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> supply to roots on gene expression and determination of the free amino acid and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> content were tested, the seedlings at the fourth-leaf stage or seventh-leaf stage were further grown in water for 3 d to deplete nitrogen and were then treated with or without 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl for 8&#x000a0;h or 24&#x000a0;h (Ohashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>). In MSX-treatment experiments, the seedlings at the fourth-leaf stage grown in water for 3 d were pretreated with or without 1&#x000a0;mM MSX (Sigma-Aldrich Japan, Tokyo, Japan) for 2&#x000a0;h and then transferred to media containing no nitrogen, 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>C1 or 5&#x000a0;mM glutamine for 8&#x000a0;h according to Kamada-Nobusada et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2013</xref>) with slight modifications.</p><p id="Par32">For measuring the tiller number, panicle number, shoot length and shoot dry weight at a paddy field, rice plants were grown in the paddy field of the Institute for Sustainable Agro-ecosystem Services in University of Tokyo, Japan (35&#x000b0;44&#x02019; N, 139&#x000b0;32&#x02032; E, 60&#x000a0;m altitude), during the summer (May to October) in 2015 under normal fertilizer, light irradiance and temperature. A germinated seed was sown into each cell of a cell tray and grown in a greenhouse under natural light conditions for four weeks. One seedling was then transplanted into each hill at 18&#x000a0;cm between hills and 30&#x000a0;cm between rows. Each plot was composed of four rows with ten hills with four replicates. Commercial compound fertilizer including N, P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and K<sub>2</sub>O was used to fertilize at 60, 90, and 80&#x02009;kg&#x02009;ha<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> as a basal fertilizer before transplanting. At the panicle initiation stage, tiller numbers of five average plants selected from each plot were measured. After panicle ripening, ten plants in each plot were harvested and shoot length, shoot dry weight without panicle, and panicle number were measured.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>qPCR Analysis</title><p id="Par33">The qPCR analysis was performed according to Konishi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2014</xref>). The nucleotide sequences for <italic>OsAS1</italic>, <italic>OsAS2</italic>, <italic>OsGS1;1</italic>, <italic>OsGS1;2</italic> and <italic>Actin1</italic> are registered in the Rice Annotation Project Database (RAP-DB; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rapdb.dna.affrc.go.jp">http://rapdb.dna.affrc.go.jp</ext-link>/) with accession numbers Os03g0291500, Os06g0265000, Os02g0735200, Os03g0223400 and Os03g0718100, respectively. Each gene-specific primer for qPCR analyses is shown in Tabuchi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2007</xref>) and Ohashi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>). The PCR products were amplified from the single-stranded cDNA as the template and quantified using a Light Cycler 480 (Roche Diagnostics K.K., Tokyo, Japan) according to the following program: 10&#x000a0;s at 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, followed by 50&#x000a0;cycles of 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;s and 60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 34&#x000a0;s. The transcript contents were quantitatively determined using each purified cDNA clone as a calibration standard.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>In situ Hybridization of <italic>OsAS</italic> Genes</title><p id="Par34">Preparation of RNA probes for <italic>OsAS1</italic> and <italic>OsAS2</italic> and in situ hybridization analysis for the basal portions of shoots were performed as described in Ohashi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2015a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Determination of Glutamine, Asparagine and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> Contents</title><p id="Par35">Free amino acids and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> contents in the basal portions of shoots at the fourth-leaf stage were determined as described in Konishi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2014</xref>). Derivatization of amino acids and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> was carried out using the AccQ-Tag Ultra Derivatization Kit (Nihon Waters K.K., Tokyo, Japan). AccQ-Tag-labelled derivatives were separated and quantified using an ACQUITY UPLC H-Class with a tunable UV detector (Nihon Waters K.K.).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Analysis of Phenylalanine Ammonia-lyase Activity</title><p id="Par36">The assay for PAL activity was conducted according to Olsen et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2008</xref>) with slight modifications. Shoot basal portion tissues (80&#x02013;170&#x000a0;mg fresh weight) were pre-chilled in liquid nitrogen and then milled with a Tissue Lyser II (Qiagen, K. K., Tokyo, Japan) at 20&#x000a0;Hz for 2&#x000a0;min. Powdered samples were resolved in 5 volumes of extraction buffer (100&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH&#x000a0;8.8) with 12&#x000a0;mM &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol) of sample weight, mixed in Tissue Lyser II at 20&#x000a0;Hz for 2&#x000a0;min, and centrifuged at 16,000&#x000a0;g for 15&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was passed through a MicroSpin S-200 HR Column (GE Healthcare Japan, Tokyo, Japan), and the elution as enzyme solution was used for the PAL activity assay. The PAL activity assay was performed at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 60&#x000a0;min in an assay mixture containing 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l enzyme extract, 450&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l 100&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH&#x000a0;8.8) and 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l 100&#x000a0;mM&#x000a0;L-phenylalanine. The reaction was terminated by adding 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of 5&#x000a0;M HCl, and absorbance was recorded at 290&#x000a0;nm against blanks made in the same way as the assays but with 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of 5&#x000a0;M HCl added before L-phenylalanine. The amount of product formed was calculated from the increase in absorbance using an extinction coefficient for cinnamate of 10,000&#x000a0;L/cm/mole (Zimmerman and Hahlbrock <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1975</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Statistics</title><p id="Par37">All data sets were analysed using Microsoft Excel add-in software (Social Survey Research Information Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec15"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_225_MOESM1_ESM.eps"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> qPCR analysis of <italic>OsGS1;1</italic> and <italic>OsGS1;2</italic> in the basal portions of wild-type shoots using MSX. Wild-type rice seedlings were grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl until the fourth-leaf stage and then in water for 3 d. After pre-treatment with 1&#x000a0;mM MSX for 2&#x000a0;h, the seedlings were treated for 8&#x000a0;h with 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (MSX&#x02009;+&#x02009;NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) or 5&#x000a0;mM glutamine (MSX&#x02009;+&#x02009;Gln). The seedlings without MSX pre-treatment were also treated for 8&#x000a0;h with 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (+NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>), 5&#x000a0;mM glutamine (Gln) or without nitrogen nutrients (-N). qPCR analysis of <italic>OsGS1;1</italic> (a) and <italic>OsGS1;2</italic> (b) were performed in the shoot basal parts. Fold changes of transcript levels in each treatment relative to those in &#x02013;N were calculated, and mean values with SE of four independent samples are shown. Asterisks denote statistically significant differences between samples treated without 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and each treated sample (*, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 by Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test). (EPS 1807 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_225_MOESM2_ESM.eps"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S2.</bold> qPCR analysis of <italic>OsAS1</italic> and <italic>OsAS2</italic> in roots of wild-type rice using MSX. Wild-type rice seedlings were grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl until the fourth-leaf stage and then transferred into water for 3 d. After pre-treatment with 1&#x000a0;mM MSX for 2&#x000a0;h, the seedlings were treated for 8&#x000a0;h with 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (MSX&#x02009;+&#x02009;NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) or 5&#x000a0;mM glutamine (MSX&#x02009;+&#x02009;Gln). The seedlings without MSX pre-treatment were also treated for 8&#x000a0;h with 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> (+NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>), 5&#x000a0;mM glutamine (Gln) or without nitrogen nutrients (-N). qPCR analyses of <italic>OsAS1</italic> (a), <italic>OsAS2</italic> (b), and <italic>actin1</italic> transcripts (c) were performed in roots. Fold changes of transcript levels in each treatment relative to those in &#x02013;N were calculated, and mean values with SE of four independent samples are shown. Asterisks denote statistically significant differences between samples treated without 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and each treated sample (*, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 by Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test). (EPS 1890 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_225_MOESM3_ESM.eps"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S3.</bold> Amino acid analysis in the basal portions of shoots supplied with transient NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>. Seedlings of the wild type (WT: black column) and two lines of <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>as1-m1</italic> and <italic>as1-m2</italic>: dark and light grey column, respectively) at the fourth-leaf stage were grown in water for 3 d, then treated with (+NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) or without (-N) 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl for 24&#x000a0;h. Mean values with SE of four independent samples are shown. One-way ANOVAs followed by Bonferroni tests were used to identify significant differences between the WT and <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). (EPS 1925 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_225_MOESM4_ESM.jpg"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S4.</bold> Stereoscopic microscope observation of the primary tiller at fifth leaf stage. Seedlings of the wild type (WT) (a) and two lines of <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>as1-m1</italic> and <italic>as1-m2</italic>) (b, c) were grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> until the fifth leaf stage. The primary tiller was observed by microscope. Scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;2&#x000a0;mm. (JPG 1217 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_225_MOESM5_ESM.jpg"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S5.</bold> Photos of wild type and <italic>as1</italic> mutants at heading stage. Wild-type plants (WT) (a) and two lines of <italic>as1</italic> mutants (<italic>as1-m1</italic> and <italic>as1-m2</italic>) (b, c) were grown in the paddy field under normal fertilization. Each two plants were shown. (JPG 1956 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12284_2018_225_MOESM6_ESM.eps"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S6.</bold> Comparison of the PAL activity between basal portions of shoots and the third-leaf blade. Rice seedlings were grown hydroponically in the presence of 1&#x000a0;mM NH<sub>4</sub>Cl until the fourth-leaf stage, and the basal portions of shoots (black column) and third-leaf blades (grey column) were harvested. Mean values with SE of five independent samples are shown. Asterisks denote statistically significant differences between each organ (*, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 by Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test). (EPS 1857 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AMT</term><def><p id="Par4">Ammonium transporter</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AS</term><def><p id="Par5">Asparagine synthetase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GS</term><def><p id="Par6">Glutamine synthetase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPT</term><def><p id="Par7">Adenosine phosphate-isopentenyltransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSX</term><def><p id="Par8">Methionine sulfoximine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PAL</term><def><p id="Par9">Phenylalanine ammonia-lyase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qPCR</term><def><p id="Par10">Quantitative real-time PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAM</term><def><p id="Par11">Shoot apical meristem</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12284-018-0225-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to express our deep gratitude to the technical support staff of the Institute for Sustainable Agro-ecosystem Services (ISAS) at the University of Tokyo for their help in the cultivation and management of rice. We thank Drs. Hirohiko Hirochika and Akio Miyao, The Project for Rice Genome Research, and The National Institute of Agrobiological Sciences, Tsukuba, Japan, for providing seeds of <italic>Tos17</italic>-inserted rice mutants. We would like to thank American Journal Experts (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aje.com">www.aje.com</ext-link>) for English language editing.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par38">This work was supported by the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan [a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research on Innovative Area (22119003 to TY) and a GRENE NC-CARP project]; the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) KAKENHI [Grant No. 15&#x000a0;K14674 and 15H04468 to TH, 26450073 to SK, and 16&#x000a0;J01799 to MO]; and the Division for International Advanced Research and Education (DIARE), Tohoku University.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of Data and Materials</title><p id="Par39">The datasets supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the article and its additional files.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; Contributions</title><p>MO and KI designed this study, performed most of the experiments and wrote the manuscript. NK operated UPLC for amino acid analysis. KS conducted the paddy field trials. SK, MM, TH and TY advised and assisted in the design of this study and in writing the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title><p id="Par40">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par41">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par42">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lancien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The aspartic acid metabolic pathway, an exciting and essential pathway in plants</article-title><source>Amino Acids</source><year>2006</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00726-005-0245-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16525757?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16525757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domagalska</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signal integration in the control of shoot branching</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm3088</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21427763?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21427763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evers</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Krol</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Struik</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding shoot branching by modelling form and function</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2011.05.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21658989?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21658989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukumorita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sugar, amino-acid, and inorganic contents in rice phloem sap</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>1982</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>283</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funayama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabuchi-Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytosolic glutamine synthetase1;2 is responsible for the primary assimilation of ammonium in rice roots</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pct046</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23509111?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23509111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaufichon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Reisdorf-Cren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chardon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological functions of asparagine synthetase in plants</article-title><source>Plant Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2010.04.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of phloem sap from the upper most internode of the rice plant</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>251</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inducible accumulation of mRNA for NADH-dependent glutamate synthase in rice roots in response to ammonium ions</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1295</fpage><lpage>1297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.pcp.a029120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoshikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>The growing Rice Plant</source><year>1989</year><publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Nosan Gyoson Bunka Kyokai</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The enzymes of glutamine, glutamate, asparagine, and aspartate metabolism</article-title><source>In plant amino acids: biochemistry and biotechnology</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Marcel Dekker, Inc</publisher-name><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>109</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical background and compartmentalized functions of cytosolic glutamine synthetase for active ammonium assimilation in rice roots</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1640</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pch190</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15574840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15574840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamada-Nobusada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Makita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen-dependent regulation of de novo cytokinin biosynthesis in rice: the role of glutamine metabolism as an additional signal</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1881</fpage><lpage>1893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pct127</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24058148?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24058148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawachi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sueyoshi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamagata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of asparagine synthetase in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) roots in response to nitrogen</article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><year>2002</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1399-3054.2002.1140107.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11982933?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11982933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maru</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NADH-dependent glutamate synthase plays a crucial role in assimilating ammonium in the Arabidopsis root</article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><year>2014</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppl.12177</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24576214?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24576214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Coruzzi</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic regulation of the gene encoding glutamine-dependent asparagine synthetase in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>1347</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.4.1347</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7846154?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7846154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miflin</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative route for nitrogen assimilation in higher plants</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1974</year><volume>251</volume><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/251614a0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 4423889?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4423889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sodek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>MAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Halford</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asparagine in plants</article-title><source>Ann Appl Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7348.2006.00104.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between nitrogen, auxin and cytokinin in the growth regulation of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) tiller buds</article-title><source>Aust J Crop Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>1026</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mae</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological nitrogen efficiency in rice: nitrogen utilization, photosynthesis, and yield potential</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><year>1997</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1004293706242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of cytosolic glutamine synthetase1;2 activity reduces nitrogen-dependent biosynthesis of cytokinin required for axillary bud outgrowth in rice seedlings</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcx022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28186255?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28186255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asparagine synthetase1, but not asparagine synthetase2, is responsible for the biosynthesis of asparagine following the supply of ammonium to rice roots</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcv005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25634963?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25634963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyozuka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of cytosolic glutamine synthetase1;2 in vascular tissues of axillary buds caused severe reduction in their outgrowth and disorder of metabolic balance in rice seedlings</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2015</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12731</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25429996?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25429996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Coruzzi</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbon and amino acids reciprocally modulate the expression of glutamine synthetase in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.121.1.301</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10482686?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10482686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name><name><surname>Slimestad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Verheul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lillo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of four Arabidopsis PAL genes; PAL1 and PAL2 have functional specialization in abiotic environmental-triggered flavonoid synthesis</article-title><source>J Plant Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>1499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2007.11.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18242769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18242769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ookawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Varietal difference of the cell wall components affecting the bending stress of the culm in relation to the loading resistance in paddy rice</article-title><source>Jpn J Crop Sci</source><year>1993</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1626/jcs.62.378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ookawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Todokoro</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in physical and chemical characteristics of culm associated with lodging resistance in paddy rice under different growth conditions and varietal difference of their changes</article-title><source>Jpn J Crop Sci</source><year>1993</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1626/jcs.62.525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Silim</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronzucker</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqi</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>AtAMT1</italic> gene expression and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> uptake in roots of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: evidence for regulation by erroot glutamine levels</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1999.00505.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10476061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10476061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between nitrogen and cytokinin in the regulation of metabolism and development</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2006.07.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16899391?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16899391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying and exploiting grain yield genes in rice</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2008.01.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18343712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18343712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overlapping expression of cytosolic glutamine synthetase and phenylalanine ammonia-lyase in immature leaf blades of rice</article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><year>2001</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1399-3054.2001.1130314.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12060286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12060286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonoda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saiki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>von Wir&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct expression and function of three ammonium transporter genes (<italic>OsAMT1;1&#x02013;1;3</italic>) in rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>726</fpage><lpage>734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcg083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12881500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12881500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abiko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assimilation of ammonium ions and reutilization of nitrogen in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2007</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>2319</fpage><lpage>2327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erm016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17350935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17350935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umehara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Arite</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda-Kamiya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Magome</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyozuka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of shoot branching by new terpenoid plant hormomes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>455</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07272</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18690207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18690207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urquhart</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Joy</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of phloem exudate technique in the study of amino acid transport in pea plants</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1981</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.68.3.750</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16661993?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16661993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vincentz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moureaux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Leydecker</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaucheret</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Caboche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of nitrate and nitrite reductase expression in <italic>Nicotiana plumbaginifolia</italic> leaves by nitrogen and carbon metabolites</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>1993</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.1993.tb00183.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8220446?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8220446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yabuki Y, Ohashi M, Imagawa F, Ishiyama K, Beier MP, Konishi N, Umetsu-Ohashi T, Hayakawa T, Yamaya T, Kojima S (2017) A temporal and spatial contribution of asparaginase to asparagine catabolism during development of rice grains. Rice 10. 10.1186/s12284-017-0143-8</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oaks</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Am&#x000e2;ncio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stulen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic regulation of ammonium uptake and assimilation</article-title><source>In nitrogen acquisition and assimilation in higher plants</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahlbrock</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light induced changes in enzyme activities in parsley cell suspension. Purification and some properties of phenylalanine ammonia lyase</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>1975</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-9861(75)90364-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1122145</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>