<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Intercult Ethnopharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Intercult Ethnopharmacol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Intercultural Ethnopharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2146-8397</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGEYA</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Turkey</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5061480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JIE-5-372</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/jice.20160723124347</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of the synergistic effect of <italic>Allium sativum, Eugenia jambolana, Momordica charantia, Ocimum sanctum</italic>, and <italic>Psidium guajava</italic> on hepatic and intestinal drug metabolizing enzymes in rats</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Devendra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>Neerja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>Rakesh K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, King George&#x02019;s Medical University, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Biotechnology, Dr. A.P.J. Abdul Kalam Technical University, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Center of Biomedical Research, Sanjay Gandhi Postgraduate Institute of Medical Sciences Campus, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for Correspondence:</bold> Devendra Kumar, Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, King George&#x02019;s Medical University, Uttar Pradesh, Lucknow, India. Email: <email xlink:href="kumardevendradubey@gmail.com">kumardevendradubey@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Sep-Dec</season><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; SAGEYA</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted, noncommercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Aims/Background:</title><p>This study was to investigated the synergistic effect of polyherbal formulations (PHF) of <italic>Allium sativum L</italic>., <italic>Eugenia jambolana</italic> Lam., <italic>Momordica charantia</italic> L., <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> Linn., and <italic>Psidium guajava</italic> L. in the inhibition/induction of hepatic and intestinal cytochrome P450 (CYPs) and Phase-II conjugated drug metabolizing enzymes (DMEs). Consumption of these herbal remedy has been extensively documented for diabetes treatment in Ayurveda.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Methodology:</title><p>PHF of these five herbs was prepared, and different doses were orally administered to Sprague&#x02013;Dawley rats of different groups except control group. Expression of mRNA and activity of DMEs were examined by real-time polymerase chain reaction and high performance liquid chromatography in isolated liver and intestine microsomes in PHF pretreated rats.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>The activities of hepatic and intestinal Phase-II enzyme levels increased along with mRNA levels except CYP3A mRNA level. PHF administration increases the activity of hepatic and intestinal UDP-glucuronyltransferase and glutathione S-transferase in response to dose and time; however, the activity of hepatic sulfotransferase increased at higher doses.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>CYPs and Phase-II conjugated enzymes levels can be modulated in dose and time dependent manner. Observations suggest that polyherbal formulation might be a possible cause of herb-drug interaction, due to changes in pharmacokinetic of crucial CYPs and Phase-II substrate drug.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEY WORDS</title><kwd>Cytochrome P450</kwd><kwd>herb-drug interaction</kwd><kwd>microsomes</kwd><kwd>sulfotransferase</kwd><kwd>UDP-glucuronyltransferase</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Diabetes is a chronic endocrine disorder, characterized by absolute or relative insulin deficiency. The peoples of the world especially in India are facing major health problem such as diabetes. There were 366 million people with diabetes in 2011, a number projected to rise to 552 million by 2030 [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Herbal remedies remain one of the major approaches as complementary alternatives in the management of diabetes mellitus. This is because their benefits are well documented from a historical perspective in diabetic populated areas [<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. A huge proportion of Indian population relies on the use of traditional medicines for the use of their primary health care [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. A major problem resulting from a combination of Ayurvedic medicine in present medical practices is a lack of clinical and scientific data to provide evidence for their efficacy and safety. It is a requirement to carry out research on herbal mixtures, to develop simple bioassays for biological standardization and pharmacological evaluation.</p><p>However, polyherbal formulations (PHF) are well documented to have the potential of inducing or inhibiting enzyme expression and their activities [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>-<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Several native products have been studied for the activity on drug metabolizing enzymes (DMEs) by several researchers [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and North American botanicals [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Furthermore, most of the studies on herb-drug interactions deal with induction or inhibition of enzymes, and less attention has been paid toward the recovery of these modulated enzymes back to normal levels following the discontinuation of respective herbal drug [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The major DMEs, the cytochrome P450 (CYP), consist of hemeproteins superfamily that catalyzes the oxidative metabolism of a wide variety of exogenous and indigenous chemicals. Several isoforms such as CYP1A1, CYP1A2, CYP2C9, CYP2B1, CYP2C1, CYP2D6, CY2E1, and CYP3A4 appear to be most relevant isozymes participated in the metabolism of clinically significant drugs [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Five plants, all native in India were used in PHF. <italic>Eugenia jambolana</italic> Lam. is known for its anti-diabetic activity [<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Fruit of <italic>Momordica</italic>
<italic>charantia</italic> L. is a known for anti-diabetic activity [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. <italic>Psidium</italic>
<italic>guajava</italic> L. and <italic>Allium sativum</italic> L. are known for their anti-diabetic activity [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. <italic>Ocimum</italic> sanctum Linn. (Holy basil) has been mentioned in Indian system of traditional medicine to be of value in the treatment of diabetes mellitus [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. To achieve the aim, the effect of PHF administration on the transcriptional level as well as the functional activity of Phase-I and II DME&#x02019;s in dose and time dependent manner. The effect of PHF treatment discontinuation after multiple weeks on Phase-I and II DMEs was evaluated to assess the time required for the recovery of PHF modulated enzymes back to control levels. With this aim, the present work was designed to study the effect of PHF administration on Phase-I and II DMEs of liver and intestine to assess its drug interaction potential.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Chemicals and Reagents</title><p>Acetaminophen, bufurolol, 1&#x02019;-hydroxybufurolol, caffeine, dexamethasone, ethoxyresorufin, glutathione (reduced), mephenytoin, 4-hydroxymephenytoin, pentoxyresorufin, resorufin, phenacetin, warfarin, 7-hydroxywarfarin, phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride, p-nitrophenol (PNP), UDP-glucuronic acid (ammonium salt) (UDPGA), 1-chloro-2, 4-dinitrobenzene (CDNB), 2-mercaptoethanol, 3&#x02019;-Phosphoadenosine-5&#x02019;-phosphosulfate (PAPS), flavin adenine dinucleotide, dicoumarol, 2,6 dichlorophenolindophenol, 2-naphthylsulfate, high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) grade acetonitrile, and methanol were purchased from Sigma&#x02013;Aldrich (St. Louis, MI, USA). Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH) and dimethyl sulfoxide were purchased from SRL Pvt. Ltd (Mumbai, Maharashtra, India). Testosterone, 6b-hydroxytestosterone, chlorzoxazone, and 6-hydroxychlorzoxazone were purchased from Cayman chemical company (USA). Ultrapure water (18.2 M/&#x003a9; cm) was obtained from Milli-Q PLUS PF water. All other chemicals were commercially available or HPLC grade.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Preparation of PHF</title><p>Five herbs <italic>E. jambolana</italic> Lam. (Jamun) seeds, <italic>M. charantia</italic> L. (Bitter gourd) fruits, <italic>O. sanctum</italic> Linn. (Holy Basil) leaves, <italic>A. sativum</italic> L. (garlic), and <italic>P. guajava</italic> L. (guava) were obtained from the local vegetable market in the city of Lucknow, India. The selected herbal materials were shade dried and grinded by mixer grinder. The prepared hydroalcohol extracts were concentrated using rotary evaporator at 40&#x000b0;C temperature. The concentrated extracts were freeze-dried at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C for 12 h then lyophilized using lyophilizer. The lyophilized extracted powders were stored in an airtight glass box and kept in the desiccator until used. PHF was prepared by mixing 200 mg powder of each herb in a single formulation.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Animals</title><p>Male Sprague&#x02013;Dawley rats of weight between 220 &#x000b1; 20 g were provided by CSIR-IITR (India). Animals were maintained at 25&#x000b0;C temperature in steel cages with alternate 12 h of light and dark cycles and given a pallet diet and water. Before start of experiment, rats were acclimatized for 7 days then divided into two groups, PHF pre-treated (<italic>n</italic> = 5) and vehicle treated control (<italic>n</italic> = 5). Rats in pretreated group were gavaged (16-gauge gavage needle) with PHF (50, 100, and 200 mg/kg/day) for 7 days and multiples of weeks. The PHF suspension was made in 0.5% sodium carboxymethyl cellulose for oral administration. The control group was administered the same volume of vehicle for 7 days. Animals were allowed free access to food and water but before euthanasia, rats were overnight fasted to decrease the intestinal content. At the end of the experiment, rats were sacrificed by anesthetic ether inhalation. Experiments were carried out in accordance with current legislation on animal experiments as per Institutional Animal Ethical Committee at King George&#x02019;s Medical University Lucknow (IAEC approval no IAEC/2013/44).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Assessment of PHF Pretreatment on Hepatic and Intestinal Phase-I DMEs</title><p>The effect of PHF administration of Phase-I enzymes (CYPs) was evaluated at transcriptional and assessment of functional activity level was performed by various enzyme assays.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>RNA Isolation, Primer Designing and Real-Time Polymerase Chain Reaction (RT-PCR) for CYPs</title><p>Rats were pretreated with PHF and vehicle for 7 days than rats were sacrificed with inhalation of anesthetic ether. A part of liver and intestine (10-50 mg) was homogenized with TRIzol (Invitrogen Life Technologies, USA) and RNA was isolated. Quantitation and purity check were accomplished using Nano drop (Thermo 6000, USA). Isolated RNA was instantly used for cyclic deoxyribose nucleic acid (cDNA) synthesis [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The cDNA sequences for various rat CYPs were obtained from Gene bank (gene bank as session number and sequences in [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>]. To make sure the specificity of primer sequences to target mRNA, each sequence was searched for homology with NCBI BLAST.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Oligonucleotide primer used for RT-PCR</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g001"/></table-wrap><p>Effect of PHF pretreatment on the mRNA expression of CYPs was evaluated using RT-PCR. For quantitative RT-PCR, cDNA was amplified using Light Cycler 480 (Roche Molecular Biochemicals, USA) using SYBR green kit (Fermentas, USA). The reaction was performed in 96-well PCR plate. The reaction mixture was consisted of 1X SYBR green, 200-300 nM primers, and 2 &#x000b5;l of cDNA in final reaction volume of 20 &#x000b5;l. The thermal cycle condition was 95&#x000b0;C for 15 min to activate Amplitaq Gold DNA polymerase, 95&#x000b0;C for 15 s and anneal/extension at 60&#x000b0;C for 1 min (40 cycles). Glyceraldihyde-3-phasphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was used as internal loading control. Fold changes in mRNA level were resultant after normalizing with GAPDH mRNA levels [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Evaluation of PHF Treatment on Function Activity of CYPs</title><p>To evaluate the effect of PHF pretreatment on CYPs functional activity various enzyme assays were performed with specific CYP probe substrates using microsomes structured from PHF treated and control animals.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Preparation of Microsome and Cytosolic Fractions</title><p>Liver and intestine were quickly excised, snap frozen, and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until used after perfusion with ice-cold normal saline. Microsome and cytosolic fractions were prepared [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Microsomal protein and cytosolic protein were determined using Lowry method of protein assessment using BSA as standard [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. CYP concentrations in rat liver microsomes (RLM) and rat intestine microsomes were quantified [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Assessment of CYPs Mediated Phase-I Enzymatic Activity</title><p>Microsomes prepared from PHF pre-treated, recovery and control groups were used for assessing the effect of PHF pretreatment and discontinuation on the enzymatic activity of hepatic Phase-I DMEs. CYP-mediated Phase-I DMEs were analyzed with following enzymatic assays.</p><sec id="sec3-1"><title>CYP1A1-dependent ethoxyresorufin O-deethylase (EROD) and CYP2B-dependent pentoxyresorufin O-dealkylase (PROD) assay</title><p>EROD and PROD assays [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] were performed with slight modifications. In brief, the reaction mixture consisted of a 100 mM Tris-HCl buffer (pH 7.4), 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mg/ml microsomal protein with a final reaction volume of 0.2 ml. Ethoxyresorufin (5 &#x000b5;M) and pentoxyresorufin (10 &#x000b5;M) were used as probe substrate for CYP1A1 and CYP2B, respectively. The reaction mixture was pre-incubated for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C. After pre-incubation, the reaction was initiated with addition of NADPH (2 mM), followed by incubation at 37&#x000b0;C for 15 min. An equal amount of buffer was added to the blank reaction. The reaction was terminated by addition of 300 &#x000b5;l ice cold methanol. The reaction was mixed and centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was used as HPLC sample. The amount of formed metabolite (resorufin) was determined using HPLC with fluorescence detector. The activity was expressed as pMol of product formed/min/mg.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>CYP1A2-dependent phenacetin O-deethylase (POD) assay</title><p>POD assay [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] was performed with slight modifications. Phenacetin (50 &#x000b5;M) was incubated with RLM (1 mg/ml), 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, in a total volume of 0.2 ml of potassium phosphate buffer (100 mM, pH 7.4). Reaction mixture was pre-incubated for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C. Reaction was initiated with adding of NADPH (2 mM). After 20 min incubation at 37&#x000b0;C reaction was terminated by adding up equal volume of ice-cold acetonitrile (containing internal standard caffeine). The blank reaction consisted of equal amount of buffer. The mixture was vortexed and centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C. The supernatant obtained was used as HPLC sample. Quantification of product (acetaminophen) was done from standard curve using HPLC-UV. Activity was expressed as nMol of product formed/min/mg.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>CYP2C19-dependent mephenytoin 4-hydroxylation assay</title><p>Mephenytoin 4-hydroxylation assay [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] was carried out with slight modifications. Mephenytoin (50 &#x000b5;M) was incubated with RLM (1 mg/ml), 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, in a total volume of 0.2 ml of 100 mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 7.4). Reaction mixture was pre-incubated for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C. The reaction was started with the addition of NADPH (2 mM) and terminated by adding up the equal volume of ice-cold acetonitrile (containing internal standard beta-naphthol) after 40 min incubation at 37&#x000b0;C. The blank reaction consisted equal amount of buffer. The mixture was vortexed and centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was used as HPLC sample. Quantification of product (4-hydroxymephenytoin) formed was done using standard curve of metabolite using HPLC. Activity was expressed as nMol of product formed/min/mg.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>CYP2D-dependent bufurolol 1-hydroxylation assay</title><p>Bufurolol (20 &#x000b5;M) was incubated with RLM (1 mg/ml), 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, in a total volume of 0.2 ml of potassium phosphate buffer (100 mM, pH 7.4). Reaction mixture was pre-incubated for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C. The reaction was started with the addition of NADPH (2 mM) and reaction was terminated by adding equal volume of ice cold acetonitrile after 20 min incubation at 37&#x000b0;C. The blank reaction contained equal amount of buffer. The mixture was then sturdily mixed, chilled on ice for 15 min, and centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C. Supernatant obtained was used as HPLC sample. Quantification of product (1-hydroxybufurolol) formed was done from standard curve of metabolite using HPLC. Activity was expressed as nMol of product formed/min/mg.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>CYP2E1-dependent chlorzoxazone 6-hydroxylation assay</title><p>Chlorzoxazone 6-hydroxylation assay [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] was performed with slight modifications. Chlorzoxazone (50 &#x000b5;M) was incubated with RLM (1 mg/ml), 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, in a total volume of 0.2 ml of potassium phosphate buffer (100 mM, pH 7.4). Reaction mixture was pre-incubated for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C. The reaction was started with the addition of NADPH (2 mM) and reaction was terminated by adding equal volume of ice cold acetonitrile (containing internal standard phenacetin) after 20 min incubation at 37&#x000b0;C. Blank reaction contained equal amount of buffer. The mixture was then vigorously mixed and centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C. Supernatant obtained was used as HPLC sample. Quantification of product (6-hydroxychlorzoxazone) formed was done from standard curve of metabolite using HPLC. Activity was expressed as nMol of product formed/min/mg.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-6"><title>CYP3A-dependent testosterone 6b-hydroxylation assay</title><p>Testosterone 6b-hydroxylation assay was performed [<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Testosterone (100 &#x000b5;M) was incubated with RLM (1 mg/ml), 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, in a total volume of 0.2 ml of 100 mM potassium phosphate buffer, pH 7.4. Reaction mixture was pre-incubated for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C. The reaction was started with addition of NADPH (2 mM) and reaction was terminated by adding of equal volume of ice-cold acetonitrile (containing internal standard dexamethasone) after 20 min of incubation at 37&#x000b0;C. Blank contains equal amount of buffer. The mixture was vigorously mixed and centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C. Supernatant obtained was used as HPLC sample. Quantification of product (6b-hydroxytestosterone) formed was done from standard curve of metabolite using HPLC. Activity was expressed as nMol of product formed/min/mg.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Assessment of PHF Pretreatment on Hepatic and Intestinal Phase-II DMEs</title><p>To examine the effect of PHF pretreatment on hepatic and intestinal Phase-II DMEs, microsomal and cytosolic conjugation enzyme activities were evaluated. Animals experiment and microsomal and cytosolic fractions were prepared as described. Phase-II DME&#x02019;s were analyzed with following enzymatic assays.</p><sec id="sec3-7"><title>UDP-glucuronyltransferase (UDPGT) assay</title><p>UDPGT activity was measured by determining the PNP conjugation with UDPGA [<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Activity was performed by determining amount of PNP consumed. The reaction mixture was consisted of 0.5 mM PNP, 4 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 mM TrisHCl (pH 7.4) and 1 mg/ml microsomal protein. The samples were preincubated in shaking water bath for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C and the reaction was initiated with addition of UDPGA (2 mM). Blank samples were performed in the absence of UDPGA, but the equal volume of buffer was added. After taking 15 min for incubation, reactions were broken by the addition of trichloroacetic acid (5% final concentration). Samples were then centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 15 min; supernatant was collected and NaOH was added to the reaction mixture to achieve final concentration of 0.5 M. Consumed PNP was calculated by subtracting value from blank. PNP concentration was determined at 410 nm using standard curve of PNP. Activity was expressed as nMol of conjugate/min/mg.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-8"><title>Glutathione S-transferase (GST) assay</title><p>Cytosolic GST activity to conjugate CDNB with reduced glutathione (GSH) was estimated [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Reaction mixture contained potassium phosphate buffer (0.3 M, pH 6.5) GSH (30 mM) and CDNB (30 mM) in 96 well plate. Reaction was initiated with addition of cytosolic enzyme. Blank contained an equal volume of buffer. The reaction was continuously monitored at 37&#x000b0;C in plate reader at 340 nm immediately after addition of cytosolic protein. Activity was expressed as nMol conjugate/min/mg.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-9"><title>Sulfotransferase (SULT) assay</title><p>SULT activity in cytosolic fraction was measured using methylene blue extraction assay [<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In brief, reaction mixture contains sodium acetate buffer pH 5.5, 7.5 &#x000b5;Mol 2-mercaptoethanol, 65 &#x000b5;Mol PAPS, 215 &#x000b5;Mol of 2-naphthol. After pre-incubation for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C, reaction was initiated with addition of cytosolic enzyme. Control reaction also contained equal volume of enzymes solution but the reaction was instantly stopped by addition of equal volume of methylene blue reagent. Chloroform (2.0 ml) was added, and the reaction mixture was vortex vigorously. Mixture was centrifuged at 1000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 15 min. Sodium sulfate was added to collected organic phase. The absorbance of organic phase was measured at 651 nm and specific activity (nMol product/min/mg protein) was calculated (10 nMol of 2-naphthylsulfate yields 0.3 absorbance at 651 nm). Activity was expressed as nMol of product formed/min/mg.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical analyses were performed with help of Prism version 5.1. Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test (non-parametric) and one-way analysis of variance followed by the Student&#x02019;s Newman-Keuls multiple range tests were used as applicable. Data are obtained as mean with standard errors. The level of significance was set prior at <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Effect of PHF Administration on Hepatic Phase-I and Phase-II DMEs</title><p>To evaluate the effect of PHF administration on hepatic DMEs, dose and time dependent study was conducted. Similarly, the effect of PHF discontinuation after 1 week pretreatment was also evaluated to determine whether the modulated DMEs recovered back to normal level or not, when PHF administration was discontinued.</p><p>The treatment with PHF at lower dose (50 mg/kg/day) for 7 days only change mRNA expression of CYP1A1 (two-fold up-regulation) and CYP3A2 (1.9 fold down-regulation) as compared to vehicle treated control. However, the treatment with PHF (100 and 200 mg/kg/day dose) for 7 days significantly up-regulated the mRNA expression of CYP1A1 (5.1 and 5.9 fold), CYP1A2 (1.9 fold), CYP2D1 (2.2 and 2.7 fold), and CYP2D2 (3.5 and 3.9 fold), respectively compared to vehicle treated control. However, treatment with PHF (100 and 200 mg/kg/day dose), significantly down-regulation was found in the mRNA expression of CYP3A1 (1.9 fold) and CYP3A2 (2.6 and 2.4 fold), respectively compared to control. Interestingly, treatment with PHF (50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day dose) for 7 days did not alter the mRNA expression level of CYP2B1, CYP2B2, CYP2C11 and CYP2E1 compared to vehicle-treated control [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>].</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Dose response of polyherbal formulation (PHF) pretreatment on hepatic cytochrome P450 mRNA level. Rats were given 50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day of PHF for 1 week. Control rats received same volume of blank formulation for same time duration. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g002"/></fig><p>Similarly, to validate the mRNA data, functional activity of CYPs were assessed after PHF treatment. The pretreatment with PHF (50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day dose) for 7 days significantly increased the functional/catalytic activity of EROD (1.6, 3.7 and 5.4 fold), POD (1.5 fold), PROD (1.2, 1.4 and 1.5 fold) and bufurolol hydroxylase (2.9 fold), respectively, compared to control. However, pretreatment with PHF did not alter the enzymatic activity of, mephenytoin and chlorzoxazone hydroxylase enzymes. In addition, treatment with PHF (50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day dose) for 7 days decreased the enzymatic activity of testosterone hydroxylase (2 fold), respectively, compared to control [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>].</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Dose response of polyherbal formulation (PHF) pretreatment on hepatic cytochrome P450 functional activity. Rats were given 50, 100, and 200 mg/kg/day of PHF for 1 week. Control rats received same volume of blank formulation for same time period of time. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g003"/></fig><p>Likewise, when Phase-II conjugation activity was assessed in dose-response study, no alteration in UDPGT, GST and SULT was observed at lowest dose study (50 mg/kg/day for 1 week). However, increase in catalytic activity of UDPGT (1.6 and 2.3 fold) and GST (1.6 and 2.1 fold) was observed at 100 and 200 mg/kg/day, respectively, in comparison to control. Modulation in SULT functional activity (1.8 fold) was obtained at 200 mg/kg/day of PHF dose compared to control [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>].</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Dose response of polyherbal formulation (PHF) pretreatment on hepatic Phase II conjugation enzymes functional activity. Rats were given 50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day of PHF for 1 week. Control rats received same volume of blank formulation for same period of time. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 and **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-12"><title>Time Dependent Response of PHF Administration on Hepatic Phase-I and II DMEs</title><p>To assess the time-dependent response of DMEs rats were administered with PHF (100 mg/kg/day) up to 4 weeks and activity was analyzed after every week. PHF pretreatment for 1, 2, 3 and 4 weeks increased the mRNA level of CYP1A1 (5.4, 5.5, 4.7 and 4.1 fold), CYP1A2 (1.7, 2, 1.9 and 2.9 fold), CYP2D1 (2, 2.1, 1.2 and 2.5 fold), and CYP2D1 (3.4, 2.9, 2.7 and 4.1 fold). Similarly, PHF treatment for 1, 2, 3 and 4 weeks decreased the mRNA levels of CYP3A1 (1.9, 2.8, 2.3 and 1.6 fold) and CYP3A2 (2, 2.5, 2 and 1.6 fold), respectively. No significant modulation in mRNA level of CYP2B1 and CYP2C11 was observed. However, CYP2E1 mRNA level was not altered by 2 weeks but after 3 and 4 weeks of PHF treatment mRNA level of CYP2E1 was increased by 1.9 fold in comparison to control [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>].</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Time dependent effect of polyherbal formulation (PHF) pretreatment on hepatic cytochrome P450 mRNA level. Rats were given PHF (p.o 100 mg/kg/day) for 4 weeks and rats were sacrificed after every week. Control rats received the same volume of blank formulation for same time duration. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05,**<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01,***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g005"/></fig><p>In the same way, PHF treatment for 1, 2, 3 and 4 weeks increased the catalytic activities of CYP1A1 (3.5, 5, 7.2 and 8.6 fold), CYP1A2 (1.6, 1.5, 1.5 and 2.4 fold), and CYP2D (2.1, 2.1, 2.4 and 3 fold), respectively. Although increase in the mRNA level of CYP2B2 was observed, the CYP2B-dependent catalytic activity was increased significantly by 1.6 fold only after 4 weeks of PHF treatment. Similarly, CYP2E1-dependent catalytic activity was also increased by 1.4 fold after 3 weeks of PHF treatment. In addition, CYP3A-dependent catalytic activity significantly decreased by 1.8, 1.8, 2 and 2.1 fold after 1, 2, 3 and 4 weeks of PHF treatment [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>]. However, no difference in CYP2C9 and CYP2C19-dependent catalytic activities was observed. When Phase-II conjugation enzymes activities were assessed, it was observed that UDPGT and GST activities were increased only by 1.5 fold after every 1 week of PHF treatment compared to control. No difference in catalytic activity of SULT was observed up to 2 weeks of PHF treatment. However, after 3 weeks of PHF treatment SULT activity was increased by 1.8 fold in comparison to control [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>].</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>TTime dependent effect of polyherbal formulation (PHF) pretreatment on hepatic cytochrome P450 functional activity. Rats were given PHF (p.o 100 mg/kg/day) for 4 weeks and rats were sacrificed after every week. Control rats received the same volume of blank for same time duration. LC, LT1, LT2, LT3 and LT4 represents control group, 1 week pretreated group, 2 week pretreated group, 3 week pretreated group and 4 week pretreated group with PHF, respectively. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g006"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Time dependent effect of polyherbal formulation (PHF) pretreatment on hepatic Phase II conjugation enzyme functional activity. Rats were given PHF (p.o 100 mg/kg/day) for 4 weeks and rats were sacriced after every week. Control rats received the same volume of blank formulation for same time duration. LC, LT1, LT2, LT3 and LT4 represents control group, 1 week pretreated group, 2 week pretreated group, 3 week pretreated group and 4 week pretreated group with PHF, respectively. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-13"><title>Effect of PHF Discontinuation on Recovery of Modulated Hepatic DMEs</title><p>To assess the recovery of modulated hepatic CYP enzymes with discontinuation of PHF, rats were first treated for 1 week with PHF (100 mg/kg/day) for induction/inhibition and then PHF treatment was discontinued. Hepatic CYP mRNA expression level was assessed after the induction period and each week of the recovery period. Pretreatment with PHF (100 mg/kg/day) for seven days significantly increased the mRNA expression levels of CYP1A1 (5.2 fold), CYP1A2 (1.7 fold), CYP2B2 (3.1 fold), CYP2D1 (2.2 fold), and CYP2D2 (3.4 fold) in comparison to control. However, a significant decrease of 2 fold in mRNA expression of CYP3A1 and CYP3A2 was observed compared to control. However, no significant difference in mRNA level (CYP1A1, CYP1A2, CYP2D1, CYP2D1, CYP2D2, CYP3A1, and CYP3A2) was observed after 1 week of last PHF dose in comparison to control. No alteration in mRNA levels of CYP2B1, CYP2C11, and CYP2E1 was observed with PHF treatment [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>].</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Effect of one week discontinuation of polyherbal formulation (PHF) treatment on hepatic CYPs mRNA level. Rats were treated with PHF (p.o 100 mg/kg/day) for one week and then PHF administration was discontinued for 1-week. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) as compared to control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g008"/></fig><p>Similarly, all CYP enzyme activities and Phase-II conjugation enzyme activities that were modulated with PHF treatment reverted back to control level after 1 week of PHF discontinuation except CYP1A1 and CYP2D-dependent enzymatic activities. The CYP1A1-dependent and CYP2D-dependent catalytic activities recovered back to control level after 2 weeks of BM discontinuation [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Induction and recovery of hepatic CYP activities and Phase-II conjugation reactions in rats treated with PHF extract</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g009"/></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-14"><title>Dose-response of PHF Administration on Intestinal Phase-I and II DMEs</title><p>Pretreatment with PHF at 50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day dose significantly induced the mRNA level of CYP1A1 by 3.2, 3 and 4.3 fold, respectively. Interestingly, PHF pretreatment for 1 week decreased the mRNA level of CYP3A2 (2, 1.9 and 2.2 fold) at 50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day, respectively. However, the treatment with PHF (50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day dose) for 1 week did not alter the mRNA expression level of CYP2C11, 2D1, 2D2 and 2E1 compared to vehicle-treated control [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>].</p><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Dose response of polyherbal formulation (PHF) pretreatment on intestinal CYPs mRNA level. Rats were given 50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day of standardized PHF extract for 1-week and sacrificed on 8th day. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g010"/></fig><p>To validate our mRNA data with active protein level, we measured the catalytic activity of respective CYPs with specific probe substrate and the result obtained supported the mRNA data. In dose response study a significant increase in CYP1A1-dependent catalytic activity by 1.4, 1.7 and 1.6 fold was observed at 50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day, respectively. However, PHF pretreatment significantly decreased the CYP3A-dependent catalytic activity of testosterone 6b-hydroxylase by 1.5 fold at dose studied. No significant difference in the CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D, and CYP2E1-dependent catalytic activity was observed [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>].</p><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Dose dependent changes in intestinal cytochrome P450 activity in rats treated with standardized extract of polyherbal formulation (PHF). Rats were given 50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day of standardized PHF extract for 1-week and sacrificed on 8th day. Control rats received same volume of blank formulation for same time duration. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g011"/></fig><p>When Phase-II conjugation activity was assessed in dose-response study, no alteration in conjugation enzymes was observed at low PHF dose (50 mg/kg/day) when administered for 1 week. However, PHF pretreatment for one week significantly increased UDPGT (3.4 and 4.2 fold) and GST (1.4 and 1.9 fold) activity at 100 and 200 mg/kg/day, respectively. No alteration was observed in SULT activity with PHF treatment [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10</xref>].</p><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Dose dependent changes in intestinal conjugation Phase II enzyme activity in rats treated with extract of polyherbal formulation (PHF). Rats were given 50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day of standardized PHF extract for 1 week and sacrificed on 8th day. Control rats received same volume of blank formulation for same time duration. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g012"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-15"><title>Time-dependent Response of PHF Administration on Intestinal Phase-I and II DMEs</title><p>Similarly to evaluate the effect of different pretreatment duration on intestinal DMEs, rats were pretreated with PHF (100 mg/kg/day) for different time duration and any alteration in DMEs mRNA level and functional activity was measured and compared with control. In study, it was observed that mRNA level of CYP1A1 was increased by 3.3, 3.6, 3.5 and 5.4 fold after 1, 2, 3 and 4 weeks of treatment with PHF, respectively, compared to control. However, no significant difference was observed among the treatment duration. Similarly, no treatment time dependency was observed for CYP3A2 (2.2, 2.3, 2.1 and 2.1 fold decrease). In addition, PHF failed to alter the mRNA level of CYP2C11, 2D1, 2D2 and 2E1 compared to vehicle-treated control [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figure 11</xref>].</p><fig id="F11" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Time dependent effect of polyherbal formulation (PHF) pretreatment on intestinal cytochrome P450 mRNA level. Rats were given PHF (p.o 100 mg/kg/day) for 4 weeks and rats were sacrificed after every week. Control rats received the same volume of blank formulation for same time duration. IC, IT1, IT2, IT3 and IT4 represents control group, 1-week pretreated group, 2 week pretreated group, 3 week pretreated group and 4 week pretreated group with PHF, respectively. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g013"/></fig><p>To confirm the RT-PCR results with functional activity of respective CYP enzymes, it was observed that CYP1A-mediated catalytic activity (EROD) was increased by 1.2, 1.2, 1.3 and 1.5 fold after 1, 2, 3 and 4 weeks of PHF treatment, respectively. The CYP3A-mediated testosterone hydroxylase catalytic activity was decreased by 1.7, 1.9, 2.4 and 2.2 fold after 1, 2, 3 and 4 weeks of PHF treatment, respectively. Similar to CYP1A-mediated catalytic activity no treatment duration dependency was observed. No significant difference was observed in CYP2E1, however, catalytic activity was significantly increased by 2.1 after 3 and 4 weeks of PHF treatment. Furthermore, no significant difference in CYP2C9, CYP2C19, and CYP2D-dependent catalytic activity was observed even after 4 weeks of PHF treatment [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figure 12</xref>].</p><fig id="F12" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>Time dependent effect of polyherbal formulation (PHF) pretreatment on intestinal cytochrome P450 functional activity. Rats were given PHF (100 mg/kg/day) for 4 weeks and rats were sacrificed after every week. Control rats received the same volume of blank formulation for same time duration. IC, IT1, IT2, IT3 and IT4 represents control group, 1 week pretreated group, 2 week pretreated group, 3 week pretreated group and 4 week pretreated group with BM, respectively. Each value is expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error from three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate significant differences (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) from control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIE-5-372-g014"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Recent studies have explained the importance and putative effect of anti-diabetic herbs in a single formulation on CYPs and conjugating enzymes. In this study, we used self-prepared polyherbal formulation to evaluate its effect on hepatic and intestinal CYP and conjugation enzymes. This herbal preparation was prepared by five herbs that have been traditionally used as an option for the treatment of diabetes. For effective and safe use of potential herbs, DMEs mediated herb-drug interactions must be studied. To the best of our knowledge, there is no such report available on hepatic and intestinal CYP and Phase-II (conjugation) enzymes for this type of polyherbal formulation. Therefore, the mechanism of herb-drug interactions that might occur with herbal consumption, alterations at transcriptional and/or translational level of DMEs must be studied. The true measure of enzyme response is their catalytic activity instead of total protein. Therefore, in the present study, we directly measured the enzymatic activities of individual CYP enzymes along with individual mRNA level instead of protein level to assess the fundamental mechanism of PHF mediated herb-drug interactions.</p><p><italic>In vivo</italic> modulation of hepatic and intestinal DMEs was studied in a dose response manner using different doses, <italic>viz</italic>., 50, 100, and 200 mg/kg/day. Dose response experiment with PHF on CYP suggested that a lower dose (50 mg/kg/day) was adequate to produce effect on hepatic CYP enzymes. PHF pretreatment increased mRNA expression levels of hepatic CYPs to CYP1A1 &#x0003e; CYP2D2 &#x0003e; CYP2D1 &#x0003e; CYP2B2 &#x0003e; CYP1A2 that correspond well with catalytic activities of each CYP (CYP1A1-dependent EROD &#x0003e; CYP2D-dependent bufurolol hydroxylase &#x0003e; CYP1A2-depenedent phenacetin-O-dethylase). However, CYP1A1 is the only intestinal CYP that has been considerably upregulated with PHF treatment. Moreover, PHF pretreatment decreased the mRNA expression of hepatic and intestinal CYP3A1 and CYP3A2 genes and this decrease in mRNA level correspond well with CYP3A-dependent testosterone hydroxylase catalytic activity. Interestingly, no dose dependency was observed at mRNA level as well as the catalytic activity level of any CYPs. Alteration at mRNA level corresponds directly with the activity of respective CYP that may be attributed to alteration at the translational level. However, PHF at dose studied (50-200 mg/kg/day) failed to modulate the expression of hepatic and intestinal CYP2C11 and CYP2E1 activities at transcriptional and activity level. Besides, CYP2C11 and CYP2E1, intestinal CYP2D isoform was also unaffected both at transcriptional and catalytic activity level. Similarly, time response study with PHF (100 mg/kg/day) exhibited that 1 week pretreatment was sufficient to produce the alteration in CYPs at transcriptional and catalytic activity level, and no further modulation was observed with increased treatment duration. In addition, no dose and time dependency was observed (except CYP2E1, upregulated after 3 weeks of treatment) that suggests low dose and 1 week treatment was sufficient for absorption of PHF to concentration level and that too up to saturation level to put forth its effect. However, upregulation of CYP2E1 could be attributed to time taken by responsible PHF components to accumulate up to the level at which they can exert their effect. Even at high concentration pretreatment for 1 week, level that could alter the CYP2E1 was not achieved to exert its effect on CYP2E1. These alterations in the catalytic activity of various CYP enzymes with PHF administration may affect their own metabolism or drugs that are metabolized through these CYP&#x02019;s [<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>Similarly, a dose-dependent study with Phase-II conjugation activities revealed that PHF administration increased the hepatic and intestinal UDPGT and GST activity. No alteration was observed in intestinal SULT activity with various PHF doses and time-dependent durations. However, hepatic SULT activities were increased (1.8 fold) at higher doses (200 mg/kg/day). Conjugation enzymes (UDPGT and SULT) play a major role in drug metabolism. Therefore, an increase in activity of these enzymes might result in increased efficacy toward their role such as decreasing the risk of carcinogenicity and toxicity of many drugs, and their metabolites. Nevertheless, increased activity of the Phase-II DMEs (conjugation enzymes) might also affect the efficacy of many substrate drugs, e.g., Acetaminophen (UDPGT) 2-naphthol (SULT) [<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>We performed a recovery experiment to assess whether the altered level of DME&#x02019;s with PHF pretreatment recovered back to normal level or not after the discontinuation of PHF treatment. Although no considerable difference at mRNA and catalytic activity level of all CYP isoforms (hepatic) was observed in between control group and 1 week recovery group, the hepatic CYP1A1-dependent and hepatic CYP2D-dependent enzymatic activities were recovered back to control level after 2 weeks of PHF discontinuation. This late recovery could be attributed to increased amount of CYP1A1 and CYP2D protein that must be degraded to attain normal level. Similarly, to evaluate the effect of discontinuation of PHF after 1 week pre-treatment on Phase-II metabolizing enzymes, we observed a fast recovery of UDPGT, GST and SULT to control level with a recovery period of 7 days. Such fast recovery from induced to control level ruled out the possibilities of Phase-II enzyme mediated herb-drug interaction following the PHF treatment. However, further investigation in human microsomes, human hepatocytes are required to validate their effect to clinical implementation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-5"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Findings from the present study suggest that the PHF formulation has both inductive and inhibitory effect on DMEs when orally administered. PHF are likely to induce DMEs except CYP3A but less likely to produce significant drug interactions. Certain major factors of metabolism such as competition between co-administered drugs, unspecific interactions with proteins and enzyme induction due to chronic intake are not addressed <italic>in vitro</italic> assay. However, data presented in this study clearly demonstrate that PHF might have the potential to inhibit or induce the metabolism of certain co-administered antidiabetic drugs which are metabolized by CYPs and Phase-II conjugated enzymes.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</title><p>We gratefully acknowledge the Department of Pharmacology, King George&#x02019;s Medical University, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India, where the study was carried out. The authors are also thankful to the Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR) for financial assistance through a grant to DK.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Source of Support: Nil,</bold></p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest: None declared.</bold></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Guariguata</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IDF diabetes atlas: Global estimates of the prevalence of diabetes for 2011 and 2030</article-title><source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source><year>2011</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22079683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egede</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence and pattern of complementary and alternative medicine use in individuals with diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>324</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11815504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahile</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrated approaches towards drug development from Ayurveda and other Indian system of medicines</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16271286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponnusankar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytochrome P450 inhibitory potential of Triphala--a Rasayana from Ayurveda</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2011</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20883765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatuphonprasert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarukamjorn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of six fruits--banana, guava, mangosteen, pineapple, ripe mango and ripe papaya--on murine hepatic cytochrome P450 activities</article-title><source>J Appl Toxicol</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>994</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22499231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheweita</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Newairy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yousef</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of some hypoglycemic herbs on the activity of phase I and II drug-metabolizing enzymes in alloxan-induced diabetic rats</article-title><source>Toxicology</source><year>2002</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11985890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Usia</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiratsuka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Watabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tezuka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CYP3A4 and CYP2D6 inhibitory activities of Indonesian medicinal plants</article-title><source>Phytomedicine</source><year>2006</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenhoek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Budzinski</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Krantis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of several Chinese natural health products of human cytochrome P450 metabolism</article-title><source>J Pharm Pharm Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12207872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Leduc</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marles</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnason</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The inhibition of human cytochrome P450 by ethanol extracts of North American botanicals</article-title><source>Pharm biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>27</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilote</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;langer</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamelin</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A convenient five-drug cocktail for the assessment of major drug metabolizing enzymes: A pilot study</article-title><source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2004</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15327588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rendic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Carlo</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human cytochrome P450 enzymes: A status report summarizing their reactions, substrates, inducers, and inhibitors</article-title><source>Drug Metab Rev</source><year>1997</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9187528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vats</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathi</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-hyperglycemic effect of Eugenia jambolana and <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> in experimental diabetes and their effects on key metabolic enzymes involved in carbohydrate metabolism</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2000</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11091000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Uma</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fruit extracts of <italic>Momordica charantia</italic> potentiate glucose uptake and up-regulate Glut-4, PPAR gamma and PI3K</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2009</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19744549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antidiabetic effects of extracts from <italic>Psidium guajava</italic></article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2005</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15619559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roman-Ramos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores-Saenz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Alarcon-Aguilar</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-hyperglycemic effect of some edible plants</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>1995</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8569244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vats</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethanolic extract of Ocimum sanctum leaves partially attenuates streptozotocin-induced alterations in glycogen content and carbohydrate metabolism in rats</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2004</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14698524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Panduri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandsana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of memory enhancing clinically available standardized extract of <italic>Bacopa monniera</italic> on P-glycoprotein and cytochrome P450 3A in Sprague-Dawley rats</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e72517</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24015255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umegaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozuka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ginkgo biloba extract markedly induces pentoxyresorufin O-dealkylase activity in rats</article-title><source>Jpn J Pharmacol</source><year>2002</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12501011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jerdi</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Daali</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Oestreicher</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherkaoui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simplified analytical method for a phenotyping cocktail of major CYP450 biotransformation routes</article-title><source>J Pharm Biomed Anal</source><year>2004</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1203</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15336365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000f6;sser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neugebauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolgos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of sarizotan&#x02019;s impact on the pharmacokinetics of probe drugs for major cytochrome P450 isoenzymes: A combined cocktail trial</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2006</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16525816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ilett</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tee</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Minchin</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism of drugs and other xenobiotics in the gut lumen and wall</article-title><source>Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1990</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2181492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Klotz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extrahepatic metabolism of drugs in humans</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source><year>1994</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8162658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaminsky</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The small intestine as a xenobiotic-metabolizing organ</article-title><source>Drug Metab Dispos</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1520</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14625348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leblond</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu&#x000e9;vin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Demers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellerin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascon-Barr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichette</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Downregulation of hepatic cytochrome P450 in chronic renal failure</article-title><source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source><year>2001</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vang</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Frandsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000f8;rensen</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000f8;rensen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical effects of dietary intakes of different broccoli samples. I. Differential modulation of cytochrome P-450 activities in rat liver, kidney, and colon</article-title><source>Metabolism</source><year>2001</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1123</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11586481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozuka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Umegaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction and recovery of hepatic drug metabolizing enzymes in rats treated with Ginkgo biloba extract</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><year>2004</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>953</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letelier</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepe</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fa&#x000fa;ndez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aracena</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microsomal UDP-glucuronyltransferase in rat liver: Oxidative activation</article-title><source>Basic Clin Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2005</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15910413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wrighton</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanden Branden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of human liver cytochrome P450 2C19: Correlation between 2C19 and S-mephenytoin 4&#x02019;-hydroxylation</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>1993</year><volume>306</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8215410</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>