<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">mSphere</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">mSphere</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">msph</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">msph</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mSphere</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>mSphere</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2379-5042</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>1752 N St., N.W., Washington, DC</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6344601</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">mSphere00554-18</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00554-18</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Applied and Environmental Science</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Wood-Derived Dietary Fibers Promote Beneficial Human Gut Microbiota</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Woody Fibers as Candidate Prebiotics</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short-authors">La Rosa et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>La Rosa</surname><given-names>Sabina Leanti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kachrimanidou</surname><given-names>Vasiliki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buffetto</surname><given-names>Fanny</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>Phillip B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pudlo</surname><given-names>Nicholas A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>Eric C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rastall</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>Glenn R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Westereng</surname><given-names>Bj&#x000f8;rge</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label><addr-line>Faculty of Chemistry, Biotechnology and Food Science, Norwegian University of Life Sciences, Aas, Norway</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label><addr-line>Department of Food and Nutritional Sciences, University of Reading, Reading, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label><addr-line>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>Maria L.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><aff>University of California, Davis</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Address correspondence to Bj&#x000f8;rge Westereng, <email>bjorge.westereng@nmbu.no</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Citation</bold> La Rosa SL, Kachrimanidou V, Buffetto F, Pope PB, Pudlo NA, Martens EC, Rastall RA, Gibson GR, Westereng B. 2019. Wood-derived dietary fibers promote beneficial human gut microbiota. mSphere 4:e00554-18. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/mSphere.00554-18">https://doi.org/10.1128/mSphere.00554-18</ext-link>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e00554-18</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 La Rosa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>La Rosa et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p>The architecture of the gut bacterial ecosystem has a profound effect on the physiology and well-being of the host. Modulation of the gut microbiota and the intestinal microenvironment via administration of prebiotics represents a valuable strategy to promote host health. This work provides insights into the ability of two novel wood-derived preparations, AcGGM and AcAGX, to influence human gut microbiota composition and activity. These compounds were selectively fermented by commensal bacteria such as <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>-<italic>Prevotella</italic>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content>, and clostridial cluster IX spp. This promoted the microbial synthesis of acetate, propionate, and butyrate, which are bene&#x0fb01;cial to the microbial ecosystem and host colonic epithelial cells. Thus, our results demonstrate potential prebiotic properties for both AcGGM and AcAGX from lignocellulosic feedstocks. These findings represent pivotal requirements for rationally designing intervention strategies based on the dietary supplementation of AcGGM and AcAGX to improve or restore gut health.</p></abstract><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Woody biomass is a sustainable and virtually unlimited source of hemicellulosic polysaccharides. The predominant hemicelluloses in softwood and hardwood are galactoglucomannan (GGM) and arabinoglucuronoxylan (AGX), respectively. Based on the structure similarity with common dietary fibers, GGM and AGX may be postulated to have prebiotic properties, conferring a health benefit on the host through specific modulation of the gut microbiota. In this study, we evaluated the prebiotic potential of acetylated GGM (AcGGM) and highly acetylated AGX (AcAGX) obtained from Norwegian lignocellulosic feedstocks <italic>in vitro</italic>. In pure culture, both substrates selectively promoted the growth of <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, and <italic>Bacteroides</italic> species in a manner consistent with the presence of genetic loci for the utilization of &#x003b2;-manno-oligosaccharides/&#x003b2;-mannans and xylo-oligosaccharides/xylans. The prebiotic potential of AcGGM and AcAGX was further assessed in a pH-controlled batch culture fermentation system inoculated with healthy adult human feces. Results were compared with those obtained with a commercial fructo-oligosaccharide (FOS) mixture. Similarly to FOS, both substrates significantly increased (<italic>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;</italic>0.05) the <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> population. Other bacterial groups enumerated were unaffected with the exception of an increase in the growth of members of the <italic>Bacteroides</italic>-<italic>Prevotella</italic> group, <named-content content-type="genus-species">Faecalibacterium prausnitzii</named-content>, and clostridial cluster IX (<italic>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;</italic>0.05). Compared to the other substrates, AcGGM promoted butyrogenic fermentation whereas AcAGX was more propiogenic. Although further <italic>in vivo</italic> confirmation is necessary, these results demonstrate that both AcGGM and AcAGX from lignocellulosic feedstocks can be used to direct the promotion of beneficial bacteria, thus exhibiting a promising prebiotic ability to improve or restore gut health.</p><p><bold>IMPORTANCE</bold> The architecture of the gut bacterial ecosystem has a profound effect on the physiology and well-being of the host. Modulation of the gut microbiota and the intestinal microenvironment via administration of prebiotics represents a valuable strategy to promote host health. This work provides insights into the ability of two novel wood-derived preparations, AcGGM and AcAGX, to influence human gut microbiota composition and activity. These compounds were selectively fermented by commensal bacteria such as <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>-<italic>Prevotella</italic>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content>, and clostridial cluster IX spp. This promoted the microbial synthesis of acetate, propionate, and butyrate, which are bene&#x0fb01;cial to the microbial ecosystem and host colonic epithelial cells. Thus, our results demonstrate potential prebiotic properties for both AcGGM and AcAGX from lignocellulosic feedstocks. These findings represent pivotal requirements for rationally designing intervention strategies based on the dietary supplementation of AcGGM and AcAGX to improve or restore gut health.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>carbohydrate-active enzymes</kwd><kwd>dietary fibers</kwd><kwd>gut microbiota</kwd><kwd>hemicellulose</kwd><kwd><italic>in vitro</italic> fecal fermentation</kwd><kwd>prebiotics</kwd><kwd>short-chain fatty acids</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="award1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Norwegian Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>244259</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Rastall</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>Glenn</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>Eric C.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>Phillip B.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>La Rosa</surname><given-names>Sabina Leanti</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Pudlo</surname><given-names>Nicholas A.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Westereng</surname><given-names>Bj&#x000f8;rge</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Kachrimanidou</surname><given-names>Vasiliki</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Buffetto</surname><given-names>Fanny</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><counts><count count="7" count-type="supplementary-material"/><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="67"/><page-count count="16"/><word-count count="11197"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January/February 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The community of microbes inhabiting the human gastrointestinal tract consists of a large variety of bacterial species that collectively influence numerous aspects of human nutrition and health (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). <italic>Firmicutes</italic>, <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>, and <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> phyla are typically dominant, with specific symbiotic members supplying an arsenal of carbohydrate-active enzymes (CAZymes) for the saccharification and fermentation of otherwise indigestible dietary polysaccharides to short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Accumulation of SCFAs in the gut is thought to benefit the host by promoting immune system development and improving local and systemic health. For example, butyrate is the primary energy source for colonocytes and is essential for the regulation of cell growth and differentiation (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>); propionate is metabolized in the liver, where it promotes gluconeogenesis and regulates cholesterol synthesis (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>); and acetate enters the systemic circulation and is used to generate ATP in muscle tissue and for lipogenesis (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Prebiotics are non-host-digestible food ingredients which can shift the gut microbiota composition and metabolic activities, eventually conferring health benefits to the host (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Currently established prebiotics are inulin-derived fructans (inulin and fructooligosaccharides [FOS]), galactans (galactooligosaccharides [GOS]), and lactulose (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). These aforementioned compounds induce a selective enhancement of <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> populations, which are considered beneficial bacteria and therefore represent a common benchmark for prebiotic action (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Recently, it has been recognized that the prebiotic effect can go beyond stimulation of these two microbial targets and that further health benefits may be derived from a broader range of beneficial bacteria, including SCFA-producing taxa (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In addition, considering the limited number of available prebiotics, there is a large potential for the generation of novel candidates (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). These new prebiotics can be manufactured from readily available, renewable carbohydrate sources, i.e., plant cell walls.</p><p>Hemicelluloses represent the second most abundant class of plant polysaccharides, with xylans and mannans being the most prevalent (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Xylans are major components of commonly consumed cereal grains, fruits, and vegetables, where they may constitute more than 30% of the dry weight. Xylans consist of a &#x003b2;-1,4-linked xylose main chain that can be substituted with arabinose linked at xylose <italic>O</italic>-2 and/or <italic>O</italic>-3 (arabinoxylan), unmethylated and/or methylated glucuronic acid linked to the <italic>O</italic>-2 position (glucuronoxylan, glucuronarabinooxylan), acetic acid in the <italic>O</italic>-2 and/or <italic>O</italic>-3 position, or ferulic acid esterified on the <italic>O</italic>-5 of the substituted arabinose (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1a</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">c</xref>). &#x003b2;-Mannans are polysaccharides found in certain nuts, beans, and legume seeds, and some are widely utilized as food-thickening agents. The homopolymeric mannan backbone consists of a linear chain of &#x003b2;-1,4-linked mannose residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1e</xref>) and can be branched with &#x003b1;-1,6-linked galactosyl groups in galactomannans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1g</xref>) (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Glucomannan contains a combination of &#x003b2;-1,4-linked mannose and glucose sugars as a backbone and can be acetylated at positions <italic>O</italic>-2, <italic>O</italic>-3, and/or <italic>O</italic>-6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1f</xref>) (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Strikingly, &#x003b2;-mannans and xylans from woody biomass share high structural similarities with those from food sources. Thus, galactoglucomannan from Norwegian spruce wood has a main chain, which is made up of randomly distributed mannose and glucose sugars, substituted with acetyl groups and galactose units linked to the mannose units (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1h</xref>) (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Spruce galactoglucomannan alone shows the same structural variations as the different types of mannans listed above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1h</xref>). Arabinoglucuronoxylan from Norwegian birch wood includes a main chain ornamented with acetyl groups, arabinose, and methylated glucuronic acid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1d</xref>) (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Notably, the presence of acetylations and various substituents requires an extensive set of CAZymes for the complete removal of side chains, thus rendering the wood-based oligosaccharides highly selective for microbes equipped with a suitable complex utilization apparatus. Moreover, they may provide increased bioavailability of acetic acid in the colon, where extracellular microbial esterases can release the acetyl groups (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of xylans and &#x003b2;-mannans present in cereals, vegetables, legume seeds, and wood biomass. The shown substrates are as follows: a, wheat arabinoxylan; b, hardwood glucuronoxylan; c, glucuronoarabinoxylan from cereals; d, highly acetylated arabinoglucuronoxylan from Norwegian birch wood; e, unsubstituted mannan from aloe vera; f, konjac glucomannan; g, carob galactomannan; h, acetylated galactoglucomannan from Norwegian spruce wood.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-f0001"/></fig><p>The extraction of hemicelluloses from different forms of woody biomass offers the possibility of valorizing these abundant and virtually unlimited compounds and provides novel xylo-oligosaccharides (XOS)/xylans or &#x003b2;-manno-oligosaccharides (&#x003b2;-MOS)/&#x003b2;-mannans with various degrees of polymerization (DP) and substitutions (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Even though there has been increasing interest in the structure and utilization of XOS/xylans and &#x003b2;-MOS/&#x003b2;-mannans manufactured from woody biomass, limited information is available on their use as a potential resource with health-promoting properties. Previous studies investigating the prebiotic potential of XOS employed fractions obtained from cereals and fruit waste streams (corn cobs [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], corn straw [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], olive [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and rice husk [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]), brewers&#x02019; spent grains, and eucalyptus wood (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The XOS mentioned above selectively stimulated bifidobacteria, which led to an increase in levels of SCFAs in fecal batch culture (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and in <italic>in vivo</italic> studies (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), thus showing prebiotic effects. The level of SCFA production and the fermentation rate were found to be dependent on XOS length and the presence of various substituents (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). On the other hand, only one study has evaluated the fermentability of glucomannan and galactoglucomannan mixtures from pine wood by human fecal microbiota, reporting increased bifidobacterial numbers and higher acetate levels (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). In addition, Polari et al. showed that a galactoglucomannan mixture prepared from spruce sapwood promoted the growth of bifidobacteria in pure cultures (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>Understanding how novel wood biomass-derived oligosaccharides impact the growth of commensal gut bacteria could lead to selective manipulation of the microbiota through their supplementation in diets, eventually promoting host health. Thus, the aim of the present study was to provide an insight into the potential prebiotic properties of AcGGM and AcAGX from Norwegian lignocellulosic biomass. <italic>In vitro</italic> single and batch cultures were used to determine their ability to stimulate the growth of beneficial human gut bacterial groups and to determine the profile of fermentative SCFAs corresponding to fecal human microbiota inocula.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><sec id="s2.1"><title>Preparation and characterization of the AcGGM and AcAGX samples.</title><p>The samples were prepared using methods similar to those described previously (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), except that the spruce wood was pretreated for 10 min at 200&#x000b0;C and then subjected to steam explosion treatment (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Briefly, hemicelluloses from the pretreated spruce and birch wood samples were extracted by the use of warm water, and the extracts were filtered by bag filtering prior to ultrafiltration and nanofiltration. The retentate from the nanofiltration step was lyophilized, yielding AcGGM and AcAGX preparations from spruce and birch wood, respectively. Composition analysis showed that the molar ratio of mannose/glucose/galactose/acetyl units in the AcGGM preparation was 1:0.32:0.16:0.28, whereas the AcAGX preparation consisted of xylosyl units with glucuronic (uronic) acid, arabinose, and acetyl substituents in a molar ratio of 1:0.08:0.01:0.54 (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). As expected, mannose (52.8%) and xylose (81.7%) were the most abundant monosaccharides in the AcGGM and AcAGX preparations, respectively. Arabinose (3.3%), uronic acids (2.4%), and xylose (16.2%) were also found in the AcGGM sample. These sugars likely resulted from the presence of a minor amount of xylan in the spruce wood, consistent with the results obtained in previous studies (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Similarly, in the AcAGX sample, the levels of mannose (5.0%) and glucose (4.2%) indicated the presence of a minor amount of glucomannan in birch wood, according to data shown previously (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Monosaccharide composition of AcGGM and AcAGX preparations obtained by HPAEC-PAD, HPLC, and colorimetric analyses<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.1"><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>
</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sample</th><th colspan="6" rowspan="1">Monosaccharide composition<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2"><sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</xref> (mol/100 mol)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ara</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gal</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glc</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xyl</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">U<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.3"><sup><italic>c</italic></sup>
</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcGGM<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.4"><sup><italic>d</italic></sup>
</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcAGX<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.5"><sup><italic>e</italic></sup>
</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other" id="ngtab1.1"><label>a</label><p>Ara, arabinose; Gal, galactose; Glc, glucose; Xyl, xylose; Man, mannose; U, uronic acid; Ac, acetyl group.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="ngtab1.2"><label>b</label><p>Values (mol/100&#x02009;mol [i.e., percentage value]) were calculated based on the total sugar molarity measured on each sample.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="ngtab1.3"><label>c</label><p>The uronic acid (U) content is based on the adapted colorimetric assay developed by Scott (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>) described in Materials and Methods.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="ngtab1.4"><label>d</label><p>Man:Glc:Gal:Ac acetylation ratio (mol/mol) per mannose: 1:0.32:0.16:0.28. Please note that the degree of acetylation cannot be precisely evaluated since the fraction contains Xyl, which can be esterified by acetyl groups.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="ngtab1.5"><label>e</label><p>Xyl:U:Ara:Ac acetylation ratio (mol/mol) per xylose: 1:0.08:0.01:0.54. Please note that the degree of acetylation cannot be precisely evaluated since the fraction contains Man, which can be esterified by acetyl groups.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To look for additional information on mass distribution and structural features, the two preparations were analyzed by high-performance anion-exchange chromatography (HPAEC) coupled with a pulsed amperometric detector (HPAEC-PAD) and matrix-assisted laser desorption&#x02013;ionization time of flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). HPAEC-PAD analysis of the AcGGM preparation revealed the presence of &#x003b2;-MOS with DP of 2 to 10 and manno-polysaccharides (DP of &#x02265;11) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2a</xref>). The AcAGX preparation consisted predominantly of oligosaccharides with DP of 2 to 10 but also polymeric xylan (DP of &#x02265;11) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2d</xref>). Both preparations contained less than 1% monosaccharides. A deeper insight into the structure of the different components with low to medium molecular weight was obtained from the MALDI-TOF data. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">c</xref>, the AcGGM preparation contained a series of oligomers with DP ranging from 2 to 14 with single, double, triple, and quadruple acetylations. The degree of acetylation increased for higher-DP &#x003b2;-MOS; the most complex detectable components were DP 13 and DP 14 saccharides bearing four acetyl groups. The AcAGX preparation contained native and acetylated oligomers with DP ranging from 2 to 18 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2e</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">f</xref>). The degree of acetylation increased in the higher-DP XOS, where DP 17 to 18 had up to 10 acetylations.</p><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Characterization of the carbohydrate preparations. (a) HPAEC-PAD traces showing the manno-oligosaccharides (degree of polymerization [DP], between 2 and 10) and manno-polysaccharides (MPS) (DP, &#x0003e;10) present in the AcGGM preparation. The AcGGM sample was chromatographed with the following external standards: M<sub>1</sub>, mannose; M<sub>2</sub>, mannobiose; M<sub>3</sub>, mannotriose; M<sub>4</sub>, mannotetraose; M<sub>5</sub>, mannopentaose; M<sub>6</sub>, mannohexaose. (b and c) MALDI-TOF spectra of low-molecular-weight (b) to medium-molecular-weight (c) components present in the AcGGM preparation. Masses of the sodium adduct ion (Mass + Na<sup>+</sup>) are shown. (d) HPAEC-PAD traces showing the xylo-oligosaccharides (DP ranging from 2 to 10) and xylo-polysaccharides (XPS) (DP, &#x0003e;10) present in the AcAGX preparation. Samples were analyzed with the following external standards: X<sub>1</sub>, xylose; X<sub>2</sub>, xylobiose; X<sub>3</sub>, xylotriose; X<sub>4</sub>, xylotetraose; X<sub>5</sub>, xylopentaose; X<sub>6</sub>, xylohexaose. (e and f) MALDI-TOF spectra of low-molecular-weight (e) to medium-molecular-weight (f) components present in the AcAGX preparation. Spectra show sodium adducts (Mass + Na<sup>+</sup>). In panels b, c, d, and e, the following abbreviations are used: Ac, acetyl group; Hex, hexose; Me, methyl group; GlcA, glucuronic acid; Xyl, xylose.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-f0002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2.2"><title>Growth experiments with single bacterial cultures.</title><p>The ability of the gut microbes to degrade and metabolize &#x003b2;-MOS/&#x003b2;-mannans and XOS/xylans with various DP and substitutions has been reported for several numerically dominant and physiological relevant members of the gut microbiome, including members of the <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, and <italic>Bacteroides</italic> genera (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In order to determine the fermentability of wood-derived AcGGM and AcAGX by these bacteria, independent <italic>in vitro</italic> culture experiments were conducted for a collection of 5 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> strains, 6 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> strains, and 32 <italic>Bacteroides</italic> strains. Bacteria were cultured in either minimal medium (MM) (for <italic>Bacteroides</italic>) or semidefined medium (SDM) (for bifidobacteria and lactobacilli) supplemented with 0.5% (wt/vol) of either AcGGM (MM-AcGGM or SDM-AcGGM) or AcAGX (MM-AcAGX or SDM-AcAGX) separately, as the sole carbon source, and growth was evaluated as maximum optimal density at 600&#x02009;nm (OD<sub>600</sub>). Commercial polymeric &#x003b2;-mannans (carob glucomannan [CGM] and konjac galactomannan [KGM]) and xylans (wheat arabinoxylan [WAX]) were used as controls. All the bacteria displayed growth on MM or SDM supplemented with 0.5% (wt/vol) glucose (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS1">Table&#x000a0;S1</xref> in the supplemental material). <named-content content-type="genus-species">Bacteroides cellulosilyticus</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. ovatus</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. plebeius</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. uniformis</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. dorei</named-content>, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. xylanisolvens</named-content> all grew in the presence of AcGGM, whereas they displayed various levels of the ability to metabolize either CGM or KGM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3a</xref>). <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. fragilis</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. clarus</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. intestinalis</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. oleiciplenus</named-content>, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. eggerthii</named-content> achieved considerable growth on AcGGM but failed to grow in the presence of both CGM and KGM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3a</xref>). These data suggest that these strains might be able to utilize the low-molecular-weight &#x003b2;-MOS present in the AcGGM mixture but cannot metabolize the high-molecular-weight &#x003b2;-mannans CGM and KGM. AcAGX supported the growth of <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. cellulosilyticus</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. ovatus</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. xylanisolvens</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. eggerthii</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. oleiciplenus</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. plebeius</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. intestinalis</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. dorei</named-content>, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. vulgatus</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3b</xref>). Under these conditions, most of the bacteria reached higher maximum OD<sub>600</sub> levels than those observed on WAX. Overall, several isolates did not show growth in MM-AcGGM or MM-AcAGX, consistent with the fact that the efficient utilization of &#x003b2;-mannans and xylans is not universal in the gut resident <italic>Bacteroides</italic> (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Utilization of xylans and &#x003b2;-mannans by selected <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> members. (a and b) Bacteroides (number of strains shown in parentheses) were inoculated into MM containing individual &#x003b2;-mannans (CGM, carob galactomannan; KGM, konjac glucomannan; AcGGM, acetylated galactoglucomannan) (a) or xylans (WAX, wheat arabinoxylan; AcAGX, acetylated arabinoglucuronoxylan) (b) as the sole carbon source. (c and d) Bifidobacteria and lactobacilli (number of strains shown in parentheses) were cultivated in SDM supplemented with &#x003b2;-mannans (c) or xylans (d) as described above. Growth was measured as optical density at 600&#x02009;nm (OD<sub>600</sub>). The figures show the maximum OD<sub>600</sub> value for each culture corrected by the OD<sub>600</sub> value of the baseline (carbohydrate-free control) at the same time. Data are averages from three biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-f0003"/></fig><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="tabS1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00554-18.6</object-id><label>TABLE&#x000a0;S1</label><p>Bacterial strains used in this study. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="tS1" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-st001.pdf" content-type="local-data">Table&#x000a0;S1, PDF file, 0.2 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 La Rosa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>La Rosa et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><p><named-content content-type="genus-species">Bifidobacterium adolescentis</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. animalis</named-content> subsp. <italic>lactis</italic> Bl-04, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. dentium</named-content> were capable of fermenting AcGGM and AcAGX, while all strains failed to grow on the pure polymeric substrates CGM, KGM, and WAX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">d</xref>). These results are in agreement with a previous study showing that only a few of the <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> strains isolated from the human gut were capable of growth on high-molecular-weight XOS and MOS (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p><p>Lactobacilli, in contrast, do not metabolize XOS and MOS significantly (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), with the exception of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Lactobacillus brevis</named-content> (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). However, they can utilize linear short-chain oligosaccharides (DP of 2 to 3), as exemplified by the uptake of mannobiose and mannotriose by <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. plantarum</named-content> WCFS1 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS4">Fig.&#x000a0;S4</xref> in the supplemental material). This is in agreement with our results, where <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. brevis</named-content> grew well on SDM-AcGGM and SDM-AcAGX whereas the other strains displayed limited growth on these substrates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">d</xref>). None of the lactobacilli displayed growth on CGM, KGM, and WAX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">d</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2.3"><title>Identification of gene clusters for metabolism of &#x003b2;-MOS/&#x003b2;-mannans and XOS/xylans.</title><p>Genomic analyses revealed the presence of putative gene clusters that may sustain growth on &#x003b2;-MOS/&#x003b2;-mannans and XOS/xylans in specific <italic>Bacteroides, Bifidobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS2">S2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS3">S3</xref>). In <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, the annotated polysaccharide utilization loci (PUL) for &#x003b2;-mannan (PUL-Mannan) and xylan (PUL-Xyl) degradation contain a classical SusC/SucD sensor/transcriptional regulator and one or more genes encoding predicted CAZymes, including &#x003b2;-mannanases (glycoside hydrolase 26 [GH26], GH5), &#x003b2;-glucosidases (GH2, GH3), &#x003b1;-galactosidase (GH36), carbohydrate esterases (CE1-6, CE7, CE9), xylanases (GH10), &#x003b1;-arabinofuranosidase (GH43), and &#x003b1;-glucuronosidase (GH115) (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS2">S2</xref>). Xylan degradation systems have been previously described and characterized at the enzyme level in <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. ovatus</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. xylanisolvens</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. intestinalis</named-content>, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. cellulosilyticus</named-content> (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). In addition, we detected large PUL-Xyls in the genome of <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. eggerthii</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. oleiciplenus</named-content>, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. plebeius</named-content> and smaller ones in the genome of <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. vulgatus</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. dorei</named-content> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1</xref>). The galactomannan utilization locus in <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. ovatus</named-content> has been described previously, and the biochemical properties of two GH26 &#x003b2;-mannanases, <italic>Bo</italic>Man26A and <italic>Bo</italic>Man26B, and a GH36 &#x003b1;-galactosidase (<italic>Bo</italic>Gal36A) have been characterized (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). A homologous PUL was detected in <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. xylanisolvens</named-content> strains capable of growing on galactomannan (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). McNulty et al. revealed the presence of putative GH26 &#x003b2;-mannanase genes in the genome of <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. cellulosilyticus</named-content> WH2 (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>); these genes are located in three putative PULs, with one similar to the PUL involved in galactomannan degradation in <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. ovatus</named-content> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS2">Fig.&#x000a0;S2</xref>). We observed a PUL-Mannan similar to that described for <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. fragilis</named-content> (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) in the genome of <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. intestinalis</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. eggerthii</named-content>. <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. uniformis</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. dorei</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. clarus</named-content>, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. oleiciplenus</named-content> harbored PUL-Mannans with previously undescribed gene configurations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS2">Fig.&#x000a0;S2</xref>). Notably, the large variations in gene content and organization observed when comparing the putative xylan and &#x003b2;-mannan PULs from different <italic>Bacteroides</italic> underscore how its members may have evolved diverse strategies for the exploitation of these hemicelluloses.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figS1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00554-18.1</object-id><label>FIG&#x000a0;S1</label><p>Organization of the xylan utilization loci based on the annotated <italic>Bacteroides</italic> genomes. Genes are depicted based on the function of their products as follows: glycoside hydrolase (GH) genes in red, carbohydrate esterase (CE) in blue, <italic>sus</italic>C-like genes in purple, <italic>sus</italic>D-like genes in orange, and hybrid two-component system (HTCS) genes in green. Genes encoding proteins of unknown function are shown in white. An asterisk indicates that the PUL has been already described in/biochemical data are available from previous studies. This applies to <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. cellulosilyticus</named-content> (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. ovatus</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. xylanisolvens</named-content> (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. intestinalis</named-content> (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). The PULs for which biochemical data are available are highlighted in yellow. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="fS1" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-sf001.tif" content-type="local-data">FIG&#x000a0;S1, TIF file, 0.4 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 La Rosa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>La Rosa et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figS2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00554-18.2</object-id><label>FIG&#x000a0;S2</label><p>Organization of the &#x003b2;-mannan utilization loci based on the annotated <italic>Bacteroides</italic> genomes. Genes are depicted according to the function of their products as follows: glycoside hydrolase (GH) genes in red, carbohydrate esterase (CE) genes in blue, <italic>sus</italic>C-like genes in purple, <italic>sus</italic>D-like genes in orange, hybrid two-component system (HTCS) genes in green, and transcriptional regulator (TR) genes in yellow. Genes encoding proteins of unknown function are shown in white. An asterisk indicates that the PUL has been already described in/biochemical data are available from previous studies. This applies to <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. cellulosilyticus</named-content> (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. ovatus</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. xylanisolvens</named-content> (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. fragilis</named-content> (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The PULs for which biochemical data are available are highlighted in yellow. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="fS2" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-sf002.tif" content-type="local-data">FIG&#x000a0;S2, TIF file, 0.3 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 La Rosa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>La Rosa et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figS3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00554-18.3</object-id><label>FIG&#x000a0;S3</label><p>Gene clusters for XOS and &#x003b2;-MOS utilization in bifidobacteria and lactobacilli. (a) Organization of the gene cluster for arabinoxylo-oligosaccharide utilization detected in the tested <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> strains. The organization of these genes was described previously (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). (b) Schematic view of the gene cluster potentially involved in the utilization of linear short-chain &#x003b2;-MOS and XOS in lactobacilli. The gene cluster in <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. gasseri</named-content> ATCC 33323 was described in reference <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, while the gene-encoded proteins involved in xylan degradation in <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. brevis</named-content>
<named-content content-type="gene">ATCC</named-content> 14869 were characterized in reference <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>. In both panel a and panel b, genes are depicted based on the function of their products as follows: glycoside hydrolase (GH) genes in red, carbohydrate esterase (CE) genes in blue, ABC transporter genes in orange (AXBP, arabino-xylan binding protein; Perm, permease), and transcriptional regulator (TR) genes in yellow. Genes encoding non-CAZymes are shown in light green. HPr, kinase/phosphorylase. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="fS3" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-sf003.pdf" content-type="local-data">FIG&#x000a0;S3, PDF file, 0.8 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 La Rosa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>La Rosa et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figS4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00554-18.4</object-id><label>FIG&#x000a0;S4</label><p>Utilization of manno-oligosaccharides by <named-content content-type="genus-species">Lactobacillus plantarum</named-content> WCFS1. (a) Growth curves of <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. plantarum</named-content> WCFS1 on minimal medium (MM) supplemented with 0.5% glucose (blue), polymeric carob galactomannan (pink), GH26-treated carob (orange), or GH36/GH26-treated carob (red) or without supplementation of any carbon source (dark red). Growth was measured as the optical density at 600 nm (OD<sub>600</sub>). (b) pH measurements before (light blue) and after (purple) overnight culturing of <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. plantarum</named-content> on the same substrates as described for panel a. In both panel a and panel b, data are representative of three independent experiments. (c) HPAEC-PAD analysis of MM supplemented with untreated carob, GH26-treated carob, and GH36/GH26-treated carob before and after fermentation with <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. plantarum</named-content>. Numbers 1 to 6 on the uppermost chromatogram indicate the positions of mannose (1), mannobiose (2), mannotriose (3), mannotetraose (4), mannopentaose (5), and mannohexaose (6). The asterisk indicates the galactose peak. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="fS4" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-sf004.tif" content-type="local-data">FIG&#x000a0;S4, TIF file, 0.3 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 La Rosa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>La Rosa et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><p>In contrast to <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, bifidobacteria lack extracellular endo-xylanases (GH10), thus exhibiting no hydrolytic capabilities with respect to polymeric xylans (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). However, previous studies have shown that several members of the <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> genus are able to grow on XOS and that XOS uptake and metabolism rely on the presence of an ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter and cytoplasmic enzymes that process these to their monosaccharide components (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS3">Fig.&#x000a0;S3a</xref>). <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. animalis</named-content> subsp. <italic>lactis</italic> Bl-04 possesses an arabinoxylo-oligosaccharide (AXOS) utilization locus (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS3">Fig.&#x000a0;S3a</xref>) consisting of a LacI transcriptional regulator, xylosidases (GH8, GH43, and GH120), arabinofuranosidases (GH43), and acetyl esterases for the removal of arabinosyl and acetyl substituents, as well as an ABC transporter (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Consistent with the fact that this locus is conserved across different XOS-utilizing <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> species, it was found in the genome of the <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. adolescentis</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. dentium</named-content> (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS3">Fig.&#x000a0;S3a</xref>). Some <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> strains, including <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. adolescentis</named-content>, can ferment GGM, KGM, and glucomannan oligosaccharides (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>); nevertheless, the &#x003b2;-mannan degradation system in bifidobacteria remains largely underexplored. A study reported by Kulcinskaja et al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) characterized a multimodular <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. adolescentis</named-content> &#x003b2;-mannanase (BaMan26A), although the ability of this bacterium to hydrolyze all of the potential linkages found in &#x003b2;-mannan has not been confirmed. BaMan26A homologs were found in the genome of &#x003b2;-mannan-utilizing <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. animalis</named-content> subsp. <italic>lactis</italic> Bl-04 and <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. dentium</named-content> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS1">Table&#x000a0;S1</xref>).</p><p>Carbohydrates are mainly imported by phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP):carbohydrate phosphotransferase system (PTS) transporters in lactobacilli (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). These systems consist of cytoplasmic components (enzyme E1 and histidine-phosphorylatable protein HPr) that lack sugar specificity and of membrane-associated enzymes (enzymes E2A, E2B, E2C, and sometimes E2D) that transfer a phosphate group from PEP to the incoming sugar, preventing it from diffusing back out of the cell. Glycans are then hydrolyzed by specific phospho-&#x003b2;-glucosidases (GH1) into the glycolytic precursors glucose-6-phosphate and glucose. These glycan utilization loci are conserved in the genome of <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. plantarum</named-content> WCFS1, <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. helveticus</named-content>, <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. acidophilus</named-content>, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. gasseri</named-content> (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS3">Fig.&#x000a0;S3b</xref>). This system would allow the bacteria to transport and metabolize short-chain undecorated XOS and &#x003b2;-MOS, whereas larger polysaccharides could not be processed. Indeed, polymeric CGM did not support growth of <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. plantarum</named-content> WCFS1, whereas the bacterium was able to grow and take up &#x003b2;-MOS derived from GH36/GH26 hydrolysis of CGM (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS4">Fig.&#x000a0;S4</xref>). As an exception, <named-content content-type="genus-species">L. brevis</named-content> is capable of fermenting arabinoxylan-oligosaccharide (AXOS) through the action of arabinofuranosidases, including a GH43 and two GH51s (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Overall, consistent with the absence of metabolism involving &#x003b2;-MOS/&#x003b2;-mannans and XOS/xylans, no related gene clusters were found in the genome of the <italic>Bacteroides, Bifidobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> strains lacking the ability to grow on these hemicelluloses <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS1">Table&#x000a0;S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2.4"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> fermentation of AcGGM and AcAGX.</title><p>Batch pH-controlled fermentations were set up to investigate the prebiotic potential of the AcGGM and AcAGX mixtures. Samples were taken at designated time intervals for enumeration of physiologically relevant bacterial groups by fluorescent <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) coupled with flow cytometry (FISH-FCM). For comparisons, commercial FOS was used as a positive control due to its established prebiotic properties (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Results presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref> show an increase of the total bacterial population (enumerated using the EUB338 probe) after 10&#x02009;h of fermentation in response to both substrates and FOS. In the absence of any carbon source (negative control), the total bacterial numbers decreased during fermentation, thus confirming the suitability of AcGGM and AcAGX as substrates for the metabolism of the human fecal microbiota. Comparisons of both substrates with FOS revealed that the total bacterial populations at the end of the fermentation were not significantly different (<italic>P&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;</italic>0.05). Counts of bifidobacteria (probe BIF164) increased significantly after 5&#x02009;h of fermentation in response to the positive control and to both AcGGM and AcAGX. At 24&#x02009;h of fermentation, the highest increase (of 1.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml) was observed in the samples supplemented with FOS, followed by increases of 1.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 and 1.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml in AcGGM and AcAGX samples, respectively. Previous studies indicated that an increase of 0.5 to 1.0 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml in the population of bifidobacteria elicits a major shift in the gut microbiota toward a healthier composition in infants and adults (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Thus, both AcGGM and AcAGX can be considered bifidogenic under the conditions tested. Fermentation of AcGGM and AcAGX for 24&#x02009;h increased the <italic>Bacteroides</italic>-<italic>Prevotella</italic> (probe BAC303) populations significantly (by 1.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml), while FOS increased the population by 0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml. These results are in agreement with those obtained for low-molecular-weight XOS from oil palm empty fruit bunches and corn cobs (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Similar results were also reported with wood-derived &#x003b2;-MOS (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Previous studies demonstrated that bifidobacteria are equipped with efficient machinery for utilization of XOS (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>); thus, the increase in the population could be attributed to the fermentation of the low-molecular-weight undecorated and acetyl-decorated XOS which have been shown to be present in the AcAGX mixture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2e</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">f</xref>). Alternatively, it is likely that the <italic>Bacteroides</italic> serve as primary degraders of the high-molecular-weight carbohydrates into shorter molecules; bifidobacteria can eventually utilize these degradation products thanks to their cross-feeding behavior (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>FISH-FCM analysis. Bacterial enumeration was performed using FISH-FCM following batch culture fermentation with no carbon source (green) or with AcGGM (turquoise), AcAGX (magenta), and FOS (blue). Cultures were inoculated with healthy human fecal microbiota, and samples were taken at 0, 5, 10, and 24 h. Histograms depict means of data from three biological replicates &#x000b1; standard deviations. An asterisk (*) indicates a significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) compared with the value at 0 h; ns, nonsignificant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.05). EUB338, total bacteria; BIF164, <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> spp.; BAC303, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>-<italic>Prevotella</italic> spp.; FPRAU655, <named-content content-type="genus-species">Faecalibacterium prausnitzii</named-content> cluster; ATO291, <italic>Atopobium</italic> cluster; PROP853, clostridial cluster IX; LAB158, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>-<italic>Leuconostoc</italic>-<italic>Enterococcus</italic> spp.; EREC482, clostridial clusters XIVa and XIVb; RREC584, <italic>Roseburia</italic> spp.; DSV687, <italic>Desulfovibrionales</italic> and <italic>Desulfuromonales</italic>; CHIS150; <named-content content-type="genus-species">Clostridium histolyticum</named-content> group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-f0004"/></fig><p>While the populations of butyrogenic bacteria of the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Faecalibacterium prausnitzii</named-content> (probe FPRAU655) cluster and of propionate-producing bacteria belonging to clostridial cluster IX (probe PROP853) declined or remained stable throughout FOS fermentation, overall significant increases were detected with AcGGM (0.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml for FPRAU655 and 0.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml for PROP853) and AcAGX (0.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml for FPRAU655 and 0.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml for PROP853) between 0 and 24&#x02009;h. In pure culture experiments, <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> DSM 17677 was not able to degrade CGM, KGM, or arabinoxylans from oat and wheat to any extent (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). However, the increased numbers of <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> cells in the batch culture experiment performed with AcGGM and AcAGX can be explained by the presence of strains equipped with machinery for utilization of these hemicelluloses. Indeed, we identified a cluster encoding enzymes involved in &#x003b2;-mannan metabolism in two <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> strains whose genome were sequenced (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS5">Fig.&#x000a0;S5</xref>). The cluster lacks a GH26 endomannanase, as would be required to hydrolyze the &#x003b2;-mannan backbone into smaller oligosaccharides, but it may allow growth of these <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> strains through cross-feeding on &#x003b2;-MOS released by other colonic microorganisms. <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> strain 2789STDY5834930, isolated in the United Kingdom from a fecal sample, possesses two &#x003b2;-xylosidases/arabinosidases (ERS852542_01151/01152) that might support the growth on AXOS. It is likely that similar strains present in the fecal samples that we employed in this study are able to hydrolyze and ferment the XOS present in the AcAGX preparation. Aside from being a ubiquitous primary source of butyrate in the colon, <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> is thought to regulate gut homeostasis and to have anti-inflammatory properties (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Thus, stimulation of <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> growth through AcGGM and AcAGX treatments could result in an overall beneficial effect on host health.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figS5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00554-18.5</object-id><label>FIG&#x000a0;S5</label><p>Schematic of the utilization loci of &#x003b2;-manno-oligosaccharides in <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> SL3/3 and M21/2. Genes are depicted based on the function of their products as follows: glycoside hydrolase (GH) genes in red, carbohydrate esterase (CE) genes in blue, ABC transporter genes in orange (MnBP, manno-oligosaccharide binding protein; MPP, manno-oligosaccharide permease protein), and transcriptional regulator (TR) genes in yellow. Genes encoding non-CAZymes are shown in light green. In <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> SL3/3, the two gene clusters correspond to the loci FPR_17170-17320 and FPR_09740-09750. In <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> M21/2, the two gene clusters correspond to the loci FAEPRAM212_01132-01147 and FAEPRAM212_01007-01008. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="fS5" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-sf005.tif" content-type="local-data">FIG&#x000a0;S5, TIF file, 2.5 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 La Rosa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>La Rosa et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><p>The counts of another member of the <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> group, i.e., the <italic>Atopobium</italic> cluster (probe ATO291), increased after 24&#x02009;h of growth with AcGGM (0.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml) and FOS (0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 log<sub>10</sub> cells/ml), whereas AcAGX did not enhance its growth. These findings are in line with previous studies reporting that FOS promoted the growth of <italic>Atopobium</italic>, which, on the other hand, was unaffected by high-molecular-weight XOS or AXOS (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). To date, no study has investigated the &#x003b2;-mannan fermentation capabilities of the <italic>Atopobium</italic> cluster; thus, it remains unclear whether the increase in this population seen with the AcGGM mixture is supported by the activity of mannolytic <italic>Atopobium</italic> strains.</p><p>No significant changes were detected at any time point in other bacterial populations, namely, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> spp. (probe LAB158), <named-content content-type="genus-species">Clostridium coccoides</named-content>-<named-content content-type="genus-species">Eubacterium rectale</named-content> genus (probe EREC482), and the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Clostridium histolyticum</named-content> group (probe CHIS150). AcGGM and AcAGX supported a stable <italic>Roseburia</italic> sp. population throughout the fermentation, whereas a significant decrease was seen in the cultures supplemented with FOS after 5&#x02009;h. Also, an overall decrease in numbers of the sulfate-reducing <italic>Desulfovibrio</italic> spp. was observed with all substrates tested.</p><p>Although the total number of bacteria decreased during fermentation in the absence of any carbon source, we observed an increase in the populations of clostridium cluster IX and <italic>Bacteroides</italic> after 10&#x02009;h of fermentation and constant numbers of bifidobacteria and the <italic>Atopobium</italic> cluster bacteria over time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). Growth of the <italic>Bacteroides</italic> members is consistent with their ability to utilize peptide and yeast &#x003b1;-mannan/&#x003b2;-glucans, deriving from the peptone and yeast extract components of the basal medium as previously shown (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2.5"><title>Organic acid analysis.</title><p><xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref> summarizes the amounts of the SCFAs acetate, propionate, and butyrate as measured by the use of a gas chromatograph analyzer equipped with a flame ionization detector (GC-FID) in the fermentation supernatants of the batch cultures over time. Total organic acid concentrations increased throughout the fermentation, and the increases were more pronounced in the cultures supplemented with the carbohydrates than in the negative-control samples (<italic>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;</italic>0.05). Acetate was the dominant SCFA produced (65% to 75% of the total) for all substrates tested, with significant differences seen at all time points. The highest concentration was achieved in the cultures containing AcAGX, followed by those containing FOS and AcGGM. The increase in acetate levels is consistent with the higher abundance of bifidobacteria detected by FISH-FCM. Previous studies (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) have shown that fermentation of XOS resulted in a higher concentration of acetate, which is in agreement with the present findings. Acetate is considered the primary SCFA in colonic fermentation and is used for <italic>de novo</italic> lipogenesis once it enters the systemic circulation. In addition, the increase in acetate could result in a more acidic colonic pH, thus inhibiting the proliferation of pathogenic bacteria, which are generally sensitive to low pH values (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Concentrations of acetate, propionate, and butyrate during fermentation with different carbohydrates or no carbon source<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.1"><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>
</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/><col width="" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Organic acid</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Time (h)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Concn (mM)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No carbon</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcGGM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcAGX</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.08 &#x000b1; 7.06*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.42 &#x000b1; 2.57*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6 &#x000b1; 23.08<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.15 &#x000b1; 3.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.39 &#x000b1; 17.99*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.63 &#x000b1; 14.87*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.33 &#x000b1; 7.74*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.63 &#x000b1; 1.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.53 &#x000b1; 21.1*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.89 &#x000b1; 14.59*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.14 &#x000b1; 30.82*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Acetate (A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.40 &#x000b1; 6.43*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.45 &#x000b1; 1.77*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.25 &#x000b1; 21.43<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22 &#x000b1; 2.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.09 &#x000b1; 12.96*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.05 &#x000b1; 10.47*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.20 &#x000b1; 3.47*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.79 &#x000b1; 0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.60 &#x000b1; 11.53*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.83 &#x000b1; 8.20*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.62 &#x000b1; 14.37*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Propionate (P)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 &#x000b1; 0.55*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 &#x000b1; 0.45*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#x000b1; 1.79<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 &#x000b1; 0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17 &#x000b1; 1.64<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28 &#x000b1; 3.83*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 &#x000b1; 1.51<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01 &#x000b1; 0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.78 &#x000b1; 4.92*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.76 &#x000b1; 4.13*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.18 &#x000b1; 2.17*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Butyrate (B)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 &#x000b1; 0.08<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 &#x000b1; 0.35<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 &#x000b1; 0.56<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13 &#x000b1; 3.39<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 &#x000b1; 0.57*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88 &#x000b1; 2.76<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 &#x000b1; 0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.15 &#x000b1; 4.65*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 &#x000b1; 2.26*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.34 &#x000b1; 14.28<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A:P:B ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:0:0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:0:0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:0:0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:0:0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:0:0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0.025:0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.06:0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.05:0.014</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.28:0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.05:0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.2:0.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.03:0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.2:0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.19:0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.31:0.095</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:0.12:0.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other" id="ngtab2.1"><label>a</label><p>Values represent the means &#x000b1; standard deviations of results from three biological replicates. Asterisks (*) indicate significant differences (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x02009;</italic>0.05) from the baseline value (no carbon) at the same time point. Nonsignificant differences (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x02265;<italic>&#x02009;</italic>0.05) are indicated with a hash mark (<sup>#</sup>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The production profile of propionate was similar to that of acetate, although it reached lower levels. This is in accordance with the significant enhancement in the <italic>Bacteroides</italic>-<italic>Prevotella</italic> and clostridial cluster IX populations, as these bacteria are known to be propionate producers (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). The propionate levels of AcGGM at 24&#x02009;h were comparable to those measured for FOS; however, fermentation of AcAGX generated more propionate (1:0.31:0.095&#x02009;mM [acetate/propionate/butyrate] ratio) than fermentation of AcGGM and FOS (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). Propionic acid production has been reported to result in beneficial health effects on the host, including appetite regulation, lower levels of glucose-induced insulin secretion, and antiproliferative effects on liver cancer cells (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Moreover, while acetate acts as a precursor for biosynthesis of blood lipids, propionate is able to inhibit this process. Thus, a low acetate/propionate ratio helps in regulating levels of blood lipids and potentially reducing cardiovascular disease risk (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>).</p><p>The wood-derived substrates tested generated a major change in the level of butyrate production (<italic>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;</italic>0.05). This is in good agreement with the results showing an increased abundance of <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content>, which is a major butyrate producer, in the samples supplemented with AcGGM and AcAGX. Interestingly, fermentation of AcGGM generated more butyrate (1:0.19:0.34&#x02009;mM [acetate/propionate/butyrate] ratio) than fermentation of AcAGX and FOS at 24 h, indicating that that substrate promotes butyrogenic fermentation in particular (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). The ability of FOS to promote butyrate synthesis has been reported previously, and it has been linked to the conversion of acetate into butyrate by the gut microbiota (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). The production of butyrate by commensal bacteria has received much attention for its health-promoting functions (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). It serves as the main energy source for colonocytes (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>) and exhibits anticarcinogenic, anti-inflammatory, and barrier-protective properties in the distal gut (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>).</p><p>Fermentation of the negative control resulted in a limited but still significant increase of acetate, propionate and butyrate levels after 10&#x02009;h of fermentation (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). Production of acetate and propionate could be linked to the increases in the levels of the <italic>Bacteroides</italic> and clostridial cluster IX populations (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). The gut microbiota is capable of converting some of the acetate into butyrate that thus does not originate from the butyrate-producing capacity in the fecal slurry (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2.6" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions.</title><p>Our results prove that AcGGM and AcAGX, which consist of oligosaccharides and polysaccharides with different DP and structure, can influence the composition of the gut microbiota. Both preparations displayed <italic>in vitro</italic> prebiotic activity, in terms of increasing the number of bifidobacteria, besides stimulating the growth of other beneficial bacteria, including the <italic>Bacteroides</italic>-<italic>Prevotella</italic>, clostridial cluster IX, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">F. prausnitzii</named-content> groups. Metabolite production correlated well with changes in bacterial populations; acetate was the prevalent SCFA released, followed by butyrate for AcGGM and propionate for AcAGX. The total levels of SCFAs produced by fermentation of AcGGM and AcAGX were comparable with those seen with the established prebiotic FOS.</p><p>Although further <italic>in vivo</italic> investigations should be conducted to ultimately confirm the beneficial health effect for the host, AcGGM and AcAGX from lignocellulosic biomass can be considered new potential prebiotics for human consumption.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s3"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s3.1"><title>Substrates and standards.</title><p>Xylan and &#x003b2;-mannan were isolated from multiple batches of steam-exploded Norwegian birch and spruce wood, respectively, as described previously (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Briefly, wood sawdust was pretreated by steam explosion (10-min residence time at 200&#x000b0;C with a solid-to-liquid ratio of 1:1 [wt/wt]). The hemicellulose released was extracted by the use of hot water, and the resulting soluble material was subjected to ultrafiltration using 1-kDa- and 5-kDa-molecular-weight-cutoff membranes (Alfa Laval, Sweden) for xylan and &#x003b2;-mannan, respectively. The retentates from the ultrafiltration were concentrated on a nanofiltration membrane (TriSep 2540-XN45-TSF membrane; Lenntech, The Netherlands). Ultrafiltration and nanofiltration were conducted using UF/NF model G filtration (Gea, Denmark). The nanofiltration retentate was lyophilized on an Alpha 2-4 LD Plus freeze-dryer (Christ, Germany), yielding further two preparations named acetylated galactoglucomannan (AcGGM) and acetylated arabinoglucuronoxylan (AcAGX). Fructo-oligosaccharides (FOS; Actilight) were obtained from Tereos (Lille, France). Manno- and xylo-oligosaccharides (DP, 2 to 6), konjac glucomannan (KGM), carob galactomannan (CGM), and wheat arabinoxylan (WAX) were purchased from Megazyme International (Wicklow, Ireland). Acetic, propionic, and butyric acid standards were of analytical grade and were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title>Sugar composition analysis.</title><p>The neutral sugar composition of AcGGM and AcAGX was analyzed using HPAEC (Dionex ICS-3000) (CarboPac PA1 columns [2 &#x000d7; 50&#x02009;mm and 2 &#x000d7; 250&#x02009;mm]; 30&#x000b0;C) coupled with a PAD detector (HPAEC-PAD). Samples (5&#x02009;mg/ml) were heated at 121&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h with 4% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> to induce hydrolysis. Hydrolysates were diluted with 15&#x02009;mM NaOH to obtain an optimal range of concentrations for the quantification. Neutral sugars were eluted with an isocratic concentration of 1&#x02009;mM NaOH at a flow rate of 0.25&#x02009;ml/min for 35&#x02009;min. The uronic acid quantification was adapted from reference <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>. Hydrolysis was initiated in silicate tubes with a mixture of 0.3&#x02009;ml of polysaccharides (1&#x02009;mg/ml) and 0.3&#x02009;mg sodium boric acid solution (2% boric acid and 3% NaCl dissolved in water). Samples were incubated at 70&#x000b0;C for 40&#x02009;min with 5&#x02009;ml of concentrated sulfuric acid. The hydrolysates were cooled for 20&#x02009;min. The colorimetric reaction was performed with the addition of 0.2&#x02009;ml dimethylphenol (0.1% [wt/vol] in glacial acetic acid) at room temperature (RT) for 15&#x02009;min and kept on ice until the absorbance was read. The total uronic concentration was proportional to the absorbance difference at wavelengths of 450&#x02009;nm and 400&#x02009;nm using glucuronic acid as a standard. The quantification of acetic acid was initiated with the saponification of the acetyl groups; this was done by incubating the carbohydrates (10&#x02009;mg/ml) overnight at 4&#x000b0;C with 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH to release bound acetyl groups. The analysis was performed using a Dionex Ultimate 3000 high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) system with 30&#x02009;min of isocratic elution (5&#x02009;mM H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) on a Rezex ROA-organic acid-H+ column (7.8 &#x000d7; 300 mm) coupled to a Carbo-H4 security guard cartridge (3.0-mm internal diameter). Acetic acid was detected at the wavelength of 210&#x02009;nm.</p></sec><sec id="s3.3"><title>Analysis of sugar monosaccharides and oligosaccharides by HPAEC-PAD.</title><p>Samples were analyzed by HPAEC-PAD using a Dionex ICS-3000 chromatographic system operated using Chromeleon software version 7 (Dionex, Thermo Scientific). The system was equipped with a CarboPac PA1 analytical column (Dionex, Thermo Scientific) (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;250 mm) in combination with a CarboPac PA1 guard column (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;50 mm), and it was run at a flow rate of 0.25&#x02009;ml/min. The elution conditions for the analysis of manno-oligosaccharides and manno-polysaccharides were 0 to 9&#x02009;min 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH; 9 to 35&#x02009;min 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH with a 0 to 0.3&#x02009;M sodium acetate (NaOAc) gradient; 35 to 40&#x02009;min 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH with 0.3&#x02009;M NaOAc; and 40 to 50&#x02009;min 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH. The elution conditions for the xylo-oligosaccharides and xylo-polysaccharides were 0 to 10&#x02009;min 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH with a 0 to 0.1&#x02009;M NaOAc gradient; 10 to 35&#x02009;min 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH with a 0.1 to 0.3 M NaOAc gradient; 35 to 40&#x02009;min 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH with a 0.3 to 1&#x02009;M NaOAc gradient; and 40 to 50&#x02009;min 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH. Commercial manno-oligosaccharides and xylo-oligosaccharides (DP, 2&#x02009;to&#x02009;6) from Megazyme were used as standards.</p></sec><sec id="s3.4"><title>MALDI-TOF.</title><p>MALDI-TOF analyses were conducted using an Ultraflex MALDI-TOF/TOF instrument (Bruker Daltonics, Germany) equipped with a 337-nm-wavelength nitrogen laser. All measurements were performed in positive mode. Data were collected from 100 laser shots using the lowest energy level necessary to obtain sufficient spectral intensity. The mass spectrometer was calibrated with a mixture of manno-oligosaccharides or xylo-oligosaccharides (DP, 2&#x02009;to&#x02009;6) obtained from Megazyme. For sample preparation, 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of sample solution was mixed with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of matrix (9% 2,5-dihydroxybenzoic acid [DHB]&#x02013;30% acetonitrile [vol/vol]), directly applied on a MTP 384 target plate (Bruker Daltonics, Germany), and dried under a stream of warm air.</p></sec><sec id="s3.5"><title>Bacterial strains and growth assays.</title><p>The bacterial strains used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS1">Table&#x000a0;S1</xref> in the supplemental material. Most of the bacterial strains were of human origin and were selected to represent the genetic diversity of the <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, and <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> genera. The years of isolation of the selected strains spanned 1960 to &#x0003e;2000, and the strains originated in most parts of the world, including the United States, Europe, and Japan.</p><p><italic>Bacteroides</italic> species were routinely cultured in a custom chopped meat (CM) medium (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>) overnight at 37&#x000b0;C in an anaerobic chamber (Coy Lab Products, MI) under an 85% N<sub>2</sub>, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, and 10% H<sub>2</sub> atmosphere. Bifidobacteria and lactobacilli were grown in de Man-Rogosa-Sharpe medium (MRS) (Oxoid, United Kingdom) overnight at 37&#x000b0;C in an anaerobic cabinet (Whitley A95 workstation; Don Whitley, United Kingdom) when appropriate. To evaluate the bacterial growth in pure cultures, <italic>Bacteroides</italic> cells were pregrown overnight in minimal medium (MM) (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>) supplemented with a monosaccharide mixture (glucose, mannose, xylose, galactose, fructose, and <italic>N</italic>-acetylglucosamine from Sigma-Aldrich). Bifidobacteria and lactobacilli were grown overnight in semidefined medium (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>) supplemented with 0.5&#x02009;mg/ml glucose. Aliquots (1 ml) of bacterial cultures were centrifuged to pellet the cells, which were then washed with 1&#x02009;ml of the appropriate medium without carbon source, prior to exposure to each single carbohydrate (5&#x02009;mg/ml). The growth experiments performed with <italic>Bacteroides</italic> were conducted in 200-&#x000b5;l cultures in 96-well microtiter plates. Growth was assessed by measuring the optical density (absorbance) at 600&#x02009;nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) at 15-min intervals for 24 to 96&#x02009;h by using either a Powerwave HT absorbance reader coupled with a Biostack plate handling device (Biotek Instruments, Winooski, VT) or a Spectrostar Nano microplate reader (BMG Labtech, USA). The growth experiments performed with bifidobacteria and lactobacilli were conducted in 2-ml culture volumes, and growth was assessed by measuring the optical density (absorbance) at 600&#x02009;nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) at 8-h intervals for 24 to 96&#x02009;h. Each species was tested in triplicate for each carbohydrate.</p></sec><sec id="s3.6"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> batch fermentation.</title><p>The prebiotic potential of wood-based AcAGX and AcGGM was evaluated using an <italic>in vitro</italic> batch culture fermentation system inoculated with human fecal inocula. Briefly, sterile stirred batch culture fermentation vessels (20-ml working volume) were filled with 17&#x02009;ml of sterile basal medium and gassed overnight with oxygen-free nitrogen (15&#x02009;ml/min) to obtain anaerobic conditions. The basal medium consisted of the following ingredients: peptone water (2&#x02009;g/liter), yeast extract (2&#x02009;g/liter), NaCl (0.1&#x02009;g/liter), K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> (0.04&#x02009;g/liter), KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> (0.04&#x02009;g/liter), MgSO<sub>4</sub>&#x000b7;7H<sub>2</sub>O (0.01&#x02009;g/liter), CaCl<sub>2</sub>&#x000b7;6H<sub>2</sub>O (0.01&#x02009;g/liter), NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (2&#x02009;g/liter), Tween 80 (2&#x02009;ml/liter), hemin (0.05&#x02009;g/liter), vitamin K (10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/liter), L&#x02212;cysteine hydrochloride (0.5&#x02009;g/liter), and bile salts (sodium glycocholate and sodium taurocholate) (0.5&#x02009;g/liter). Each carbohydrate was added at the concentration of 1% (wt/wt) just prior to the addition of the fecal inoculum. Three vessels with no added carbohydrate source were included as negative controls. Temperature and pH were kept at levels that mimicked those of the distal region of the human large intestine. Thus, the temperature was held at 37&#x000b0;C by the use of a circulating water bath connected to each fermentation vessel; pH was maintained in the range of 6.6 to 7.0 via the use of pH controllers (Fermac 260; Electrolab, United Kingdom) and was automatically adjusted by adding 0.5&#x02009;M NaOH or 0.5&#x02009;M HCl to the vessels when required. The fermentation of each carbohydrate source was carried out in triplicate with the samples from each of three healthy human fecal donors. Subjects were free of any metabolic or gastrointestinal disorder, and they had not taken probiotic or prebiotic supplements or antibiotics for six months prior to the study. Fecal samples were collected and immediately placed in an anaerobic jar (AnaeroJar; Oxoid) (2.5&#x02009;liters) equipped with a gas-generating kit (AnaeroGen; Oxoid). Samples were diluted at 10% (wt/wt) in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) (0.1&#x02009;M, pH 7.4) and homogenized in a stomacher (Stomacher 400; Seward, United Kingdom) for 2&#x02009;min at 260 paddle beats/min.</p><p>A 2-ml volume of the fecal slurries (1% [vol/vol]) was used to inoculate the vessels containing the anaerobic fermentation medium and treatments. Batch culture fermentations were carried out for 24&#x02009;h, and samples were collected at 0, 5, 10, and 24&#x02009;h for analysis of bacterial populations and organic acids.</p></sec><sec id="s3.7"><title>Enumeration of bacterial populations by fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) combined with flow cytometry (FISH-FCM).</title><p>Differences in bacterial population numbers were assessed by FISH-FCM using 16S rRNA targeted oligonucleotide probes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS2">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>). All probes were labeled at the 5&#x02032; end with fluorescent Cy3 dye (Sigma-Aldrich). For each of the time points, 375&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of sample was mixed with three volumes of ice-cold 4% (wt/vol) paraformaldehyde (PFA) solution and fixed for 4&#x02009;h at 4&#x000b0;C followed by centrifugation at 13,000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 5&#x02009;min. The cell pellet was washed twice in 1&#x02009;ml sterile PBS and then resuspended in 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of a solution consisting of sterile PBS-absolute ethanol (1:1 [vol/vol]). Samples were stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C until analysis. For the hybridization, 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of each PFA-fixed batch culture sample was washed in PBS and treated with 1&#x02009;mg/ml lysozyme&#x02013;100&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl&#x02013;0.05&#x02009;mM EDTA) (pH 8.0) at room temperature for 10&#x02009;min to permeabilize the cells for use with the probes. Cells were washed in PBS and then resuspended in 1&#x02009;ml hybridization buffer (5&#x02009;M NaCl, 1&#x02009;M Tris-HCl [pH 8], 30% formamide, double-distilled water [ddH<sub>2</sub>O], 10% SDS). An aliquot of 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of sample was added to an Eppendorf tube with 4&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of each probe (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS2">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>) and 4&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of EUB338 I-II-III (linked to Alexa488). Hybridization was carried out at 35&#x000b0;C overnight. For the washing step, cells were pelleted by centrifugation, resuspended in 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of washing buffer solution (5&#x02009;M NaCl, 1&#x02009;M Tris-HCl [pH 8], 0.5&#x02009;M EDTA [pH 8], ddH<sub>2</sub>O, 10% SDS), and incubated for 20&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C. The pellet was then collected by centrifugation, suspended in 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;l PBS, and stored at 4&#x000b0;C until flow cytometry (BD Accuri C6 Plus; Becton, Dickinson Biosciences, NJ, USA). Numbers of specific and total bacteria were determined, taking into account the dilution factor calculated from different volumes used in the steps of sample preparation, and the numbers of events per microliter were obtained from averaged numbers from NON EUB338 and EUB338 I-II-III probes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS2">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>) analyzed by flow cytometry.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="tabS2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00554-18.7</object-id><label>TABLE&#x000a0;S2</label><p>Oligonucleotide probes used in this study for FISH-FCM enumeration of bacterial populations. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="tS2" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="mSphere.00554-18-st002.docx" content-type="local-data">Table&#x000a0;S2, DOCX file, 0.03 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 La Rosa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>La Rosa et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s3.8"><title>Organic acid analysis.</title><p>Acetic, propionic, and butyric acid concentrations were quantified using a gas chromatograph analyzer equipped with a flame ionization detector (GC-FID) following the method described by Richardson et al. (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>) with ethyl butyric acid used as an internal standard. A GC analyzer (Agilent/HP 6890) equipped with an HP-5MS column (30&#x02009;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;mm) with a 0.25-&#x003bc;m-pore-size coating (cross-linked 5% phenyl methylpolysiloxane; Hewlett Packard, United Kingdom) was employed. Helium was used as the carrier gas at a flow rate of 1.7&#x02009;ml/min (head pressure, 133 KPa). The oven initial temperature was set at 63&#x000b0;C followed by a temperature ramp of 15&#x000b0;C/min to 190&#x000b0;C and was then held constant for 3 min. A split ratio of 100:1 was used. Quantification of SCFA in the chromatograms was confirmed based on the retention times of the respective commercial SCFA standards (Sigma-Aldrich, United Kingdom) at concentrations ranging between 2 to 10&#x02009;mM.</p></sec><sec id="s3.9"><title>Statistical analysis.</title><p>A paired Student's <italic>t</italic> test was used to evaluate significant differences among bacterial numbers and organic acid concentrations at the time of inoculation and the different sampling points. Data are presented as means &#x000b1; standard deviations. Differences were considered statistically significant at <italic>P</italic> values of <italic>&#x0003c;</italic>0.05.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We thank Carlos Poveda of the University of Reading Department of Food and Nutritional Sciences for excellent technical assistance with flow cytometry. We thank G. Mathiesen, D. B. Diep, and K. Rudi for kindly providing the <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> strains.</p><p>This research was financed by the Norwegian Research Council under grant number 244259.</p><p>Experiments were primarily designed by S.L.L.R., V.K., G.G., E.C.M., and B.W. S.L.L.R. and V.K. conducted the <italic>in vitro</italic> batch culture fermentation, FISH-FCM, and organic acid analyses. Growth experiments were conducted by S.L.L.R. and N.A.P. F.B. conducted the monosaccharide composition analysis. Production of AcGGM and AcAGX was performed by B.W. S.L.L.R. analyzed the data, performed the comparative genomic analyses, and wrote the manuscript. B.W., V.K., P.B.P., G.G., R.A.R., and E.C.M. discussed and revised the manuscript. The figures were prepared by S.L.L.R. All of us read and approved the final manuscript.</p><p>We declare that we have no competing interests.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnenburg</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Backhed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Diet-microbiota interactions as moderators of human metabolism</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>535</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature18846</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27383980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rincon</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Polysaccharide utilization by gut bacteria: potential for new insights from genomic analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1817</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18180751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Keefe</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Diet, microorganisms and their metabolites, and colon cancer</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>691</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>706</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrgastro.2016.165</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27848961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Lahham</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peppelenbosch</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roelofsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vonk</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Venema</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Biological effects of propionic acid in humans; metabolism, potential applications and underlying mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1801</volume>:<fpage>1175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1183</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2010.07.007</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20691280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sleeth</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sahuri-Arisoylu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lizarbe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cerdan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anastasovska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghourab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hankir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swann</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viardot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Louise Thomas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The short-chain fatty acid acetate reduces appetite via a central homeostatic mechanism</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>3611</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms4611</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24781306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutkins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salminen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cani</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verbeke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Expert consensus document: the International Scientific Association for Probiotics and Prebiotics (ISAPP) consensus statement on the definition and scope of prebiotics</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>502</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrgastro.2017.75</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28611480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rastall</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Recent developments in prebiotics to selectively impact beneficial microbes and promote intestinal health</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source>
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2014.11.002</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25448231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheller</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulvskov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Hemicelluloses</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042809-112315</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gidley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fincher</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Heterogeneity in the chemistry, structure and function of plant cell walls</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>724</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>732</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.439</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20852610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lundqvist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teleman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Junel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zacchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tjerneld</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>St&#x000e5;lbrand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Isolation and characterization of galactoglucomannan from spruce (<italic>Picea abies</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Carbohydr Polym</source>
<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0144-8617(01)00210-7</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biely</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cziszarova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uhliarikova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agger</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eijsink</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westereng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Mode of action of acetylxylan esterases on acetyl glucuronoxylan and acetylated oligosaccharides generated by a GH10 endoxylanase</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1830</volume>:<fpage>5075</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5086</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2013.07.018</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23891707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biely</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Microbial carbohydrate esterases deacetylating plant polysaccharides</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Adv</source>
<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1575</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1588</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2012.04.010</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22580218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalheiro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Girio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loureiro-Dias</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esteves</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> fermentation of xylooligosaccharides from corn cobs autohydrolysis by <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> strains</article-title>. <source>LWT&#x02013;Food Sci Technol</source>
<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>963</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>972</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2006.07.013</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moniz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rastall</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalheiro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Assessment of the bifidogenic effect of substituted xylo-oligosaccharides obtained from corn straw</article-title>. <source>Carbohydr Polym</source>
<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>466</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>473</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2015.09.046</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26572377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kosik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovegrove</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charalampopoulos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rastall</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> fermentability of xylo-oligosaccharide and xylo-polysaccharide fractions with different molecular weights by human faecal bacteria</article-title>. <source>Carbohydr Polym</source>
<volume>179</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2017.08.077</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29111070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gullon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esteves</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Girio</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parajo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Assessment on the fermentability of xylooligosaccharides from rice husks by probiotic bacteria</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>7482</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7487</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf800715b</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18642926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kortenoeven</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schols</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voragen</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> fermentability of differently substituted xylo-oligosaccharides</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>6205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6210</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf020220r</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12358503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Selected indigestible oligosaccharides affect large bowel mass, cecal and fecal short-chain fatty acids, pH and microflora in rats</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>
<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>136</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/127.1.130</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9040556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roytio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alhoniemi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forssten</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hudjec</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steger</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yaqoob</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuohy</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rastall</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ouwehand</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Xylo-oligosaccharides alone or in synbiotic combination with <italic>Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic>lactis</italic> induce bifidogenesis and modulate markers of immune function in healthy adults: a double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomised, factorial cross-over study</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>
<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>1945</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1956</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114513004261</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24661576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Dietary intake of xylooligosaccharides improves the intestinal microbiota, fecal moisture, and pH value in the elderly</article-title>. <source>Nutrition Res</source>
<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>756</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>761</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nutres.2007.09.014</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gullon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gullon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parajo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Manufacture and properties of bifidogenic saccharides derived from wood mannan</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>4296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4305</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf300524s</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22489573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ojansivu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Makela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eckerman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmbom</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salminen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Galactoglucomannan extracted from spruce (<italic>Picea abies</italic>) as a carbohydrate source for probiotic bacteria</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>11037</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11043</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf303741h</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23067113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michalak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knutsen</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aarum</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westereng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Effects of pH on steam explosion extraction of acetylated galactoglucomannan from Norway spruce</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Biofuels</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-018-1300-z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30455740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Boada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rencoret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>del R&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez-Barbero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Analysis of lignin-carbohydrate and lignin-lignin linkages after hydrolase treatment of xylan-lignin, glucomannan-lignin and glucan-lignin complexes from spruce wood</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>239</volume>:<fpage>1079</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1090</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-014-2037-y</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24531838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teleman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nordstrom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tenkanen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Isolation and characterization of <italic>O</italic>-acetylated glucomannans from aspen and birch wood</article-title>. <source>Carbohydr Res</source>
<volume>338</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>534</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0008-6215(02)00491-3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12668108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cockburn</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koropatkin</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Polysaccharide degradation by the intestinal microbiota and its influence on human health and disease</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>428</volume>:<fpage>3230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3252</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2016.06.021</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27393306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seekatz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koropatkin</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pudlo</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terrapon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilmes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stappenbeck</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>A dietary fiber-deprived gut microbiota degrades the colonic mucus barrier and enhances pathogen susceptibility</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>167</volume>:<fpage>1339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1353 e21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.10.043</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27863247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pudlo</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McNulty</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bolam</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Recognition and degradation of plant cell wall polysaccharides by two human gut symbionts</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>e1001221</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001221</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22205877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palframan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rastall</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Carbohydrate preferences of <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> species isolated from the human gut</article-title>. <source>Curr Issues Intest Microbiol</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14503691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaskari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kontula</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siitonen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jousimies-Somer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattila-Sandholm</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poutanen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Oat beta-glucan and xylan hydrolysates as selective substrates for <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> strains</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9534257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michlmayr</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohmdorfer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kneifel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Arabinoxylan oligosaccharide hydrolysis by family 43 and 51 glycosidases from <italic>Lactobacillus brevis</italic> DSM 20054</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>6747</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6754</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02130-13</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23995921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortimer</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tryfona</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terrapon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupree</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bolam</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Glycan complexity dictates microbial resource allocation in the large intestine</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>7481</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms8481</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26112186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNulty</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pudlo</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muegge</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hettich</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Effects of diet on resource utilization by a model human gut microbiota containing <italic>Bacteroides cellulosilyticus</italic> WH2, a symbiont with an extensive glycobiome</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>e1001637</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001637</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23976882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Despres</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lepercq</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Comtet-Marre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jubelin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chambon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeoman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berg Miller</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terrapon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mosoni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Xylan degradation by the human gut <italic>Bacteroides xylanisolvens</italic> XB1A(T) involves two distinct gene clusters that are linked at the transcriptional level</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>326</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-2680-8</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27142817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chekan</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radlinski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Revindran</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackie</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Xylan utilization in human gut commensal bacteria is orchestrated by unique modular organization of polysaccharide-degrading enzymes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>111</volume>:<elocation-id>E3708</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1406156111</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25136124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagenholm</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouraoui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulcinskaja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bahr</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aurelius</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koropatkin</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stalbrand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Galactomannan catabolism conferred by a polysaccharide utilization locus of <italic>Bacteroides ovatus</italic>: enzyme synergy and crystal structure of a beta-mannanase</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>292</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>243</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M116.746438</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27872187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bagenholm</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pudlo</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouraoui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koropatkin</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stalbrand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>A beta-mannan utilization locus in <italic>Bacteroides ovatus</italic> involves a GH36 alpha-galactosidase active on galactomannans</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>590</volume>:<fpage>2106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2118</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1873-3468.12250</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27288925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senoura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taira</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wasaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The mannobiose-forming exo-mannanase involved in a new mannan catabolic pathway in <italic>Bacteroides fragilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source>
<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00203-013-0938-y</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24217874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turroni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahony</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Sinderen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Glycan utilization and cross-feeding activities by bifidobacteria</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol</source>
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>350</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2017.10.001</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29089173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ejby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fredslund</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vujicic-Zagar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slotboom</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abou Hachem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Structural basis for arabinoxylo-oligosaccharide capture by the probiotic <italic>Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic>lactis</italic> Bl-04</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.12419</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24279727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrangou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abou Hachem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lahtinen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klaenhammer</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional analysis of oligosaccharide utilization by <italic>Bifidobacterium lactis</italic> Bl-04</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>312</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-14-312</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23663691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Antioxidative capacity produced by <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>- and <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic>-mediated fermentations of konjac glucomannan and glucomannan oligosaccharides</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric</source>
<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>1294</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1300</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.3226</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulcinskaja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosengren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolenova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stalbrand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Expression and characterization of a <italic>Bifidobacterium adolescentis</italic> beta-mannanase carrying mannan-binding and cell association motifs</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02118-12</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23064345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorca</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barabote</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zlotopolski</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winnen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hvorup</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stonestrom</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Transport capabilities of eleven gram-positive bacteria: comparative genomic analyses</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1768</volume>:<fpage>1342</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1366</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2007.02.007</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17490609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Theilmann</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klaenhammer</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrangou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abou Hachem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title><italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> metabolizes dietary plant glucosides and externalizes their bioactive phytochemicals</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>e01421-17</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01421-17</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29162708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Precha-Atsawanan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Immerzeel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stalbrand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adlercreutz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Xylooligosaccharides from hardwood and cereal xylans produced by a thermostable xylanase as carbon sources for <italic>Lactobacillus brevis</italic> and <italic>Bifidobacterium adolescentis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>7333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7340</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf401249g</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23822770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Prebiotic capacity of inulin-type fructans</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>
<volume>137</volume>:<fpage>2503S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2506S</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/137.11.2503S</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holtmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shanahan</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staudacher</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Dietary fiber intervention on gut microbiota composition in healthy adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>965</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>983</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/nqy041</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29757343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Siles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harmsen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Gil</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Cultured representatives of two major phylogroups of human colonic <italic>Faecalibacterium prausnitzii</italic> can utilize pectin, uronic acids, and host-derived substrates for growth</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>420</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.06858-11</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22101049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rastall</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> fermentation by human fecal microflora of wheat arabinoxylans</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>4589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4595</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf070293g</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Prebiotic stimulation of human colonic butyrate-producing bacteria and bifidobacteria, <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>
<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6941.12186</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23909466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teitelbaum</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Nutritional impact of pre- and probiotics as protective gastrointestinal organisms</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Nutr</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.nutr.22.110901.145412</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12055340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Understanding the effects of diet on bacterial metabolism in the large intestine</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>
<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>1197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1208</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2007.03322.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17448155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Formation of short chain fatty acids by the gut microbiota and their impact on human metabolism</article-title>. <source>Gut Microbes</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19490976.2015.1134082</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26963409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bindels</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porporato</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dewulf</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verrax</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neyrinck</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buc Calderon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feron</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muccioli</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sonveaux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cani</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delzenne</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Gut microbiota-derived propionate reduces cancer cell proliferation in the liver</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>
<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>1337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1344</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.2012.409</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22976799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rycroft</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rastall</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>A comparative <italic>in vitro</italic> evaluation of the fermentation properties of prebiotic oligosaccharides</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>878</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>887</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.2001.01446.x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jonkers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Venema</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanhoutvin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Troost</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brummer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Review article: the role of butyrate on colonic function</article-title>. <source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source>
<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>119</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2036.2007.03562.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17973645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roediger</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1980</year>
<article-title>Role of anaerobic bacteria in the metabolic welfare of the colonic mucosa in man</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>798</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7429343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Butyrate enhances intestinal epithelial barrier function via up-regulation of tight junction protein Claudin-1 transcription</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis Sci</source>
<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>3126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3135</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-012-2259-4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22684624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lockett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Head</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Topping</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>A review of the potential mechanisms for the lowering of colorectal oncogenesis by butyrate</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>
<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>820</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>831</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114512001948</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22676885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Canfora</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jocken</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaak</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Short-chain fatty acids in control of body weight and insulin sensitivity</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>577</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>591</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrendo.2015.128</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26260141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boets</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomand</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deroover</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeulen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Preter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van den Mooter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Vuyst</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Courtin</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Annaert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delcour</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verbeke</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Systemic availability and metabolism of colonic-derived short-chain fatty acids in healthy subjects: a stable isotope study</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>
<volume>595</volume>:<fpage>541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>555</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/JP272613</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27510655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<article-title>Colorimetric determination of hexuronic acids in plant materials</article-title>. <source>Anal Chem</source>
<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>936</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>941</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac50043a036</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pudlo</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>German</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Symbiotic human gut bacteria with variable metabolic priorities for host mucosal glycans</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<elocation-id>e01282</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01282-15</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26556271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Mucosal glycan foraging enhances fitness and transmission of a saccharolytic human gut bacterial symbiont</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>457</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2008.09.007</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18996345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrangou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altermann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutkins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klaenhammer</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Functional and comparative genomic analyses of an operon involved in fructooligosaccharide utilization by <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>8957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8962</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1332765100</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12847288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calder</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Simultaneous determination of volatile and non-volatile acidic fermentation products of anaerobes by capillary gas chromatography</article-title>. <source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.1989.tb00278.x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>