<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int Sch Res Notices</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int Sch Res Notices</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISRN</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Scholarly Research Notices</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2356-7872</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4897258</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/976264</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Simultaneous Estimation of Four Antitussive Components from Herbal Cough Syrup by HPTLC</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deore</surname><given-names>Sharada L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jaju</surname><given-names>Payal S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baviskar</surname><given-names>Bhushan A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Government College of Pharmacy, Kathora Naka, Amravati 444604, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Sharada L. Deore: <email>sharudeore_2@yahoo.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editor: Jiiang H. Jeng</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>2014</volume><elocation-id>976264</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Sharada L. Deore et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A new simple, rapid, selective and precise high performance thin layer chromatographic (HPTLC) method has been developed for simultaneous estimation of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole in herbal cough syrup. The retention factors of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole are 0.53, 0.44, 0.75, and 0.77, respectively. Chromatography was performed on 60F<sub>254</sub> percolated TLC plate using n-hexane&#x02009;:&#x02009;ethyl acetate&#x02009;:&#x02009;glacial acetic acid (8.5&#x02009;:&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;:&#x02009;0.5&#x02009;v/v/v). Methods are validated according to ICH guidelines and can be adopted for the routine analysis of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol and cineole in herbal cough syrup.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Herbal cough syrup is a pharmaceutical dosage form used to treat coughing and related conditions. Many of these herbal or ayurvedic cough syrups are incorporated with cough suppressants or expectorants from vasaka, liquorice, tulsi, ginger, kantkari, black pepper, camphor, and many more [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Out of these plants, constituents from vasaka, liquorice, tulsi and ginger are chosen for simultaneous estimation.</p><p>Vasaka is perennial, evergreen shrub of biological source<italic> Adhatoda vasica</italic> belonging to family Acanthaceae. It contains quinazoline alkaloids like vasicine and vasicinone and also essential oil. Vasicine present in the leaves possesses respiratory stimulant activity and induces bronchodilation as well as relaxation of the tracheal muscle. It offered significant protection against histamine induced bronchospasm [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Liquorice is root of<italic> Glycerrhiza glabra</italic> belonging to family Leguminosae. It contains majorly triterpenoid saponin glycyrrhizin and few flavonoids. Glycyrrhizin exerts antitussive effect by stimulating salivation and inducing a more frequent swallowing reflex [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Tulsi is evergreen plant of<italic> Ocimum sanctum </italic>belonging to family Lamiaceae. It contains volatile oil 0.4&#x02013;0.8% comprising eugenol and beta-caryophyllene and many other monoterpenes. Eugenol shows an antitussive effect by central action mediated through both opioid and GABAergic system [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Ginger is dried as well as fresh rhizomes of<italic> Zingiber officinalis</italic> belonging to family Zingiberaceae. It contains 1&#x02013;4% volatile oil containing cineole, zingiberene, borneol, and resins like gingerol and shogaol. Cineole shows antitussive effect by suppressing the cough reflex through direct action of cough centre in the medulla [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>According to World Health Organisation's (WHO) standardisation guidelines, development and validation of analytical methods are needed to help in discovery, development, and marketing of quality herbal formulations. The literature [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] revealed that various TLC methods are available for estimation of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole as individual component only; hence, in present work attempt has been made to develop simple, rapid, accurate, precise, and economical method for simultaneous estimation of all these four constituents in herbal cough syrup.</p><p>HPTLC is preferred over HPLC because HPTLC offers visual inspection throughout the process, less solvent consumption, multiple choices of fresh stationary phases, faster simultaneous estimation of many compounds with good analytical precision, and accuracy within less time.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Experimental</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>2.1. Reagents and Materials</title><p>All chemicals and solvents used were of AR and HPLC grade (E. Merck, Mumbai, India). Marker standard vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>) were obtained as gift sample from Natural Remedies, Bangalore, India. TLC aluminium plates precoated with silica gel 60F<sup>254</sup> (20&#x02009;cm &#x000d7; 20&#x02009;cm, 0.2&#x02009;mm thick) were from E. Merck, Darmstadt, Germany.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>2.2. Instrumentation</title><p>The method has been developed on Camag HPTLC system (Camag, Muttenz, Switzerland) consisting of twin trough chamber, Linomat V applicator, TLC scanner III, and WinCATS software version 1.4.4. Separation and identification of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole were performed on aluminium backed silica gel 60F<sup>254</sup> (20&#x02009;cm &#x000d7; 10&#x02009;cm of plate size, layer thickness 0.2&#x02009;mm).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>2.3. Chromatographic Conditions</title><p>Standard solutions of vasicine (99%), glycyrrhizin (98%), eugenol (98%), and cineole (98%) were prepared either separately or in a mixture at a concentration of 1&#x02009;mg&#x02009;mL each in absolute methanol. Ultrasonication of mixture was required to ensure complete dissolution. The experiment was performed on a silica gel 60F<sup>254</sup> (0.2&#x02009;mm thickness) HPTLC plates (20 &#x000d7; 10&#x02009;cm). Samples were applied by Linomat-V applicator to the plates as 4&#x02009;mm bands with 4&#x02009;mm distance. Many mobile phase compositions from solvents toluene, ethyl acetate, n-hexane, methanol, glacial acetic acid, and water were tried. Finally the plates were developed by the ascending technique, in a twin trough glass chamber with a stainless steel lid, using an optimised mobile phase composed of n-hexane&#x02009;:&#x02009;ethyl acetate&#x02009;:&#x02009;glacial acetic acid (8.5&#x02009;:&#x02009;1&#x02009;:&#x02009;0.5 v/v/v). The chamber saturation time was kept as 20&#x02009;min. After development, plates were dried with a hot hair dryer; the spots which separated on plate were visualised when it was placed in iodine chamber and then scanned with a TLC Scanner, using WinCATS software in absorbance mode, with slit dimensions 3.00 &#x000d7; 0.45&#x02009;mm. The detection wavelength 300&#x02009;nm was selected. The Rf values for vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole were 0.53, 0.44, 0.75, and 0.77, respectively, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>2.4. Quantification of Vasicine, Glycyrrhizin, Eugenol, and Cineole through Calibration Curve</title><p>All the standards were spotted in triplicate on 20 &#x000d7; 10&#x02009;cm TLC plates for preparing six-point linear calibration curves. The calibration graph was plotted using the concentration versus average peak area at 300&#x02009;nm for all standards. Peak area and concentration data were treated by linear least-squares regression analysis. Various standard dilutions of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole were applied on TLC plate, developed, and scanned to know linearity range with reference to peak area.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>2.5. Validation</title><p>As per ICH guidelines the method is validated for linearity, accuracy, precision, LOD, LOQ, ruggedness, and robustness [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p>Linearity: standard stocks of 1&#x02009;mg&#x02009;mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole were prepared and diluted to appropriate concentrations. The linearity was evaluated using linear least-squares regression analysis for generation of calibration curve. The regression equation with slope, intercept, and coefficient of correlation was calculated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p>Accuracy<italic> (recovery)</italic>: the accuracy of the method was assessed by spiking preanalyzed samples with known amounts of standard vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole solution and then reanalysed by the HPTLC method. The spiking was done at three different concentration levels and average percent recovery at each concentration level was calculated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p>Precision: the precision (%RSD) was determined by analysing standard solution of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole over the entire calibration range for different days.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iv)</label><p>
<italic>Limit of detection</italic>: the limit of detection (LOD) was determined using formula LOD = 3.3(SD)/<italic>S</italic>, where SD is standard deviation of response and <italic>S</italic> is average of the slope of the calibration curve. The minimum detectable limit was found to be ng/spot for vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(v)</label><p>Limit of quantification: the limit of quantitation (LOQ) was determined using formula LOQ = 10(SD)/<italic>S</italic>, where SD is standard deviation of response and <italic>S</italic> is average of slope of the calibration curve. The minimum quantified limit was found to be ng/spot for vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole. It was observed that other constituents present in the formulation did not interfere either with the peak of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, or cineole. Therefore the developed method is specific.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(vi)</label><p>Ruggedness of the method:it expresses the precision within laboratories variations like different analysts. Ruggedness of the method was assessed by spiking the standards 5 times with different analyst by using the same equipment.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(vii)</label><p>Robustness of the method: by introducing small changes in the mobile phase composition, development distance, mobile phase volume, and duration of chamber saturation, the effects on the results were examined.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Results and Discussion</title><p>HPTLC method was optimized with view to quantify all four constituents in liquid herbal cough syrup. As far as individual estimation of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole by chromatographic methods is concerned, a number of solvent systems have been reported. However, there has not been cited a single report for separation of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole simultaneously in a single solvent system. n-Hexane&#x02009;:&#x02009;ethyl acetate&#x02009;:&#x02009;glacial acetic acid in ratio of 8.5&#x02009;:&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;:&#x02009;0.5&#x02009;v/v/v shown good resolution for vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole with Rf value of 0.53, 0.44, 0.75, and 0.77, respectively. Well-defined spots were obtained after chamber was saturated for 20&#x02009;min at room temperature. TLC plate was visualized when placed in iodine chamber without derivatization. The identity of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole was confirmed by comparing chromatogram of standard vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole with that of extract and by comparing retention factor of reference with standard.</p><p>Calibration plot shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref> indicates that the response is linear function of concentration in the range of 300&#x02013;900, 1000&#x02013;5000, 400&#x02013;1000, and 2000&#x02013;10,000&#x02009;ng/spot for vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole, respectively. The correlation coefficient, intercept, and slope for vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>As per validation results given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref>, lower %RSD (&#x0003c;2%) suggests precision of the method. The good recovery within acceptable limit indicates accuracy of method. The limit of detection (LOD) and limit of quantitation (LOQ) of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole show adequate sensitivity of method. Good correlation of 0.99, 0.99, 0.99, and 0.97 was obtained between the standard and sample of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole, respectively.</p><p>Ruggedness and robustness parameters confirmed that the method is able to withstand minor experimental changes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref>). It was observed that other constituents present in the formulations did not interfere with any of the peaks of all four constituents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>); therefore the method is specific.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>4. Conclusion</title><p>Therapeutic efficacy, safety, and quality evaluation of herbal formulations is basic requirement of many regulatory authorities all over the world to grant its marketing approval and advanced analytical techniques are proving to be rapid and specific tool in the herbal drug research as well as in setting specific quality standards by their manufacturers. Hence, in the present work, for the first time, a rapid, simple, accurate, and specific HPTLC method for quantitative estimation of four antitussive constituents, that is, vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole present in herbal cough syrup, has been developed and validated. The present method could be part of routine quality analysis of any polyherbal cough syrups available in market despite interference of other constituents. Limitation like closeness of Rf values of cineole and eugenol is overcome by the use of HPTLC method instead of HPLC. Still future perspective involves better resolution with these two components along with separation and estimation of maximum antitussive components from herbal cough syrup by HPTLC.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>The authors are highly thankful to the Principal of Government College of Pharmacy, Amravati, Maharashtra, India, for his support.</p></ack><sec sec-type="conflict"><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interests.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nos&#x000e1;l'Ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fle&#x00161;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural features and antitussive activity of water extracted polysaccharide from <italic>Adhatoda vasica</italic>
</article-title><source><italic>Carbohydrate Polymers</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>83</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1970</fpage><lpage>1974</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2010.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-78650519118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamei</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asano</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profiles of the antitussive principles of <italic>Glycyrrhizae radix</italic> (licorice), a main component of the Kampo preparation Bakumondo-to (Mai-men-dong-tang)</article-title><source><italic>European Journal of Pharmacology</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>507</volume><issue>1&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2004.11.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-12344321554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic uses of <italic>Ocimum sanctum Linn</italic> (tulsi) with a note on eugenol and its pharmacological actions: a short review</article-title><source><italic>Indian Journal of Physiology and Pharmacology</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-18744389453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16170979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nadig</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laxmi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of anti-tussive activity of <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> linn in guinea pigs</article-title><source><italic>Indian Journal of Physiology and Pharmacology</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-18744386107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16170996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sayyad Sadikali</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhary R</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of volatile oil from some plants of zingiberaceae family and estimation of their antibacterial potential</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Current Pharmaceutical Research</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Standardization and evaluation of polyherbal cough syrup</article-title><source><italic>The Indian Pharmacist</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><issue>45</issue><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sunilson</surname><given-names>J. A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anandarajagopal</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasha</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>Q. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunaraja</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antihistaminic evaluation of formulated polyherbal cough syrup</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Medicinal Plants Research</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>1482</fpage><lpage>1485</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohapatra</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antitussive evaluation of formulated polyherbal cough syrup</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Drug Delivery &#x00026; Therapeutics</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadlag</surname><given-names>V. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasture</surname><given-names>V. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosavi</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhalke</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Standardization of marketed adulsa syrup containing vasaka by high performance thin layer chromatography</article-title><source><italic>Asian Journal of Chemistry</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1917</fpage><lpage>1921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79954587708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><article-title>Q2 (R1) validation of analytical procedure: text and methodology</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the 2005 International Conference on Harmonization</conf-name><conf-date>November 2005</conf-date></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><graphic xlink:href="ISRN2014-976264.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>HPTLC plate showing simultaneous estimation of eugenol (E1&#x02013;E5), cineole (C1&#x02013;C5), glycyrrhizin (G1&#x02013;G5), vasicine (V1&#x02013;V5), and adulsa cough syrup (A).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ISRN2014-976264.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Chromatogram, calibration curve, and 3D display of vasicine.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ISRN2014-976264.003"/></fig><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Chromatogram, calibration curve, and 3D display of glycyrrhizin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ISRN2014-976264.004"/></fig><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Chromatogram, calibration curve, and 3D display of eugenol.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ISRN2014-976264.005"/></fig><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Chromatogram, calibration curve, and 3D display of cineole.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ISRN2014-976264.006"/></fig><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>3D display of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole in simultaneous estimation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ISRN2014-976264.007"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Method validation parameters for quantification of vasicine, glycyrrhizin, eugenol, and cineole in herbal cough syrup by the proposed HPTLC method.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Validation parameters</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vasicine</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycyrrhizin</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eugenol</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cineole</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation coefficient, <italic>n</italic> = 3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linearity range (ng/spot), <italic>n</italic> = 3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#x02013;900</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000&#x02013;5000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400&#x02013;1000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000&#x02013;10,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limit of detection (ng/spot), <italic>n</italic> = 3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limit of quantification (ng/spot), <italic>n</italic> = 3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">350</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">800</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instrumental precision (RSD), <italic>n</italic> = 6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method precision (RSD), <italic>n</italic> = 6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Robustness (RSD), <italic>n</italic> = 3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Parameters used for ruggedness and robustness.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sr. number</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial condition</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Changed condition</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect </th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mobile phase</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n-Hexane&#x02009;:&#x02009;ethyl acetate&#x02009;:&#x02009;glacial acetic acid (8.5&#x02009;:&#x02009;1&#x02009;:&#x02009;0.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n-Hexane&#x02009;:&#x02009;ethyl acetate&#x02009;:&#x02009;glacial acetic acid (8&#x02009;:&#x02009;1&#x02009;:&#x02009;1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very minute effect on the resolution, quantitative estimations, Rf, and peak area/height</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development distance</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02009;cm</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02009;cm</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very minute effect on the resolution, quantitative estimations, Rf, and peak area/height</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 &#x000b1; 3&#x000b0;C (winter)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 &#x000b1; 3&#x000b0;C (summer)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Affects greatly the resolution, quantitative estimations, Rf, and peak area/height</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tank saturation time</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#x02009;min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x02009;min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very minute effect on the resolution, quantitative estimations, Rf, and peak area/height</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analyst </td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analyst 1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analyst 2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very minute effect on the resolution, quantitative estimations, Rf, and peak area/height</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>