<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6262304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.02764</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Shifts of Hydrogen Metabolism From Methanogenesis to Propionate Production in Response to Replacement of Forage Fiber With Non-forage Fiber Sources in Diets <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Kun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/532195/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nan</surname><given-names>Xuemei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Kangkang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Jinjin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/548764/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Liang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Shanshan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Guangyong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Linshu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Benhai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/588183/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition, Institute of Animal Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition, College of Animal Science and Technology, China Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Beijing Dairy Cattle Center, Beijing Capital Agribusiness Group</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Beijing Key Laboratory for Dairy Cow Nutrition, Beijing University of Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Angel Angelov, Technische Universit&#x000e4;t M&#x000fc;nchen, Germany</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Patrick K. H. Lee, City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong; Franck Carbonero, University of Arkansas, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Linshu Jiang, <email>jls@bac.edu.cn</email> Benhai Xiong, <email>xiongbenhai@caas.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>This article was submitted to Systems Microbiology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>2764</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Wang, Nan, Chu, Tong, Yang, Zheng, Zhao, Jiang and Xiong.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang, Nan, Chu, Tong, Yang, Zheng, Zhao, Jiang and Xiong</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The rumen microbial complex adaptive mechanism invalidates various methane (CH<sub>4</sub>) mitigation strategies. Shifting the hydrogen flow toward alternative electron acceptors, such as propionate, was considered to be a meaningful mitigation strategy. A completely randomized design was applied in <italic>in vitro</italic> incubation to investigate the effects of replacing forage fiber with non-forage fiber sources (NFFS) in diets on methanogenesis, hydrogen metabolism, propionate production and the methanogenic and bacterial community. There are two treatments in the current study, CON (a basic total mixed ration) and TRT (a modified total mixed ration). The dietary treatments were achieved by partly replacing forage fiber with NFFS (wheat bran and soybean hull) to decrease forage neutral detergent fiber (fNDF) content from 24.0 to 15.8%, with the composition and inclusion rate of other dietary ingredients remaining the same in total mixed rations. The concentrations of CH<sub>4</sub>, hydrogen (H<sub>2</sub>) and volatile fatty acids were determined using a gas chromatograph. The archaeal and bacterial 16S rRNA genes were sequenced by Miseq high-throughput sequencing and used to reveal the relative abundance of methanogenic and bacterial communities. The results revealed that the concentration of propionate was significantly increased, while the concentration of acetate and the acetate to propionate ratio were not affected by treatments. Compared with CON, the production of H<sub>2</sub> increased by 8.45% and the production of CH<sub>4</sub> decreased by 14.06%. The relative abundance of <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic> was significantly increased, but the relative abundance of <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> tended to decrease in TRT group. At the bacterial phylum level, the TRT group significantly decreased the relative abundance of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and tended to increase the relative abundance of <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>. The replacement of forage fiber with NFFS in diets can affect methanogenesis by shifting the hydrogen flow toward propionate, and part is directed to H<sub>2</sub>
<italic>in vitro</italic>. The shift was achieved by a substitution of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> by <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>, another substitution of <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> by <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic>. Theoretical predictions of displacements of H<sub>2</sub> metabolism from methanogenesis to propionate production was supported by the dietary intervention <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>non-forage fiber sources</kwd><kwd>methanogenesis</kwd><kwd>hydrogen metabolism</kwd><kwd>propionate production</kwd><kwd>archaeal and bacterial community</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="65"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Microorganisms in the rumen can ferment feeds rich in cellulose and can convert plant materials that people can&#x02019;t utilize directly into meat and milk products. At the same time, the process of hydrolyzing complex compounds is accompanied by the formation of gasses, such as hydrogen (H<sub>2</sub>) and carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>). To keep the fermentation continuing, methanogenic archaea in the rumen produce methane (CH<sub>4</sub>) by using H<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> to scavenge H<sub>2</sub> and keep the partial pressure of H<sub>2</sub> low (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Moss et al., 2000</xref>). Methanogenesis from ruminants can result in a significant loss of feed efficiency (2&#x02013;12%), depending upon the types of diets (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Johnson and Johnson, 1995</xref>). To mitigate the negative impact on climate change and to improve feed efficiency, various mitigation strategies have been conducted to reduce CH<sub>4</sub> emissions from ruminants, including using essential oils (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Patra and Yu, 2012</xref>), plant extracts (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>), ionophores (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Weimer et al., 2008</xref>), and vaccines (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 2009</xref>). However, the rumen ecosystem is exceedingly complex and the ability of this system to efficiently convert complex carbohydrates to volatile fatty acids (VFA) is in part due to the effective disposal of H<sub>2</sub> by reducing CO<sub>2</sub> to produce CH<sub>4</sub>. Methanogenesis can be inhibited for short periods, but the ecology of the system is such that it frequently reverts back to the initial levels of methane production through all various adaptive mechanisms (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">McAllister and Newbold, 2008</xref>). On the other hand, the problem with chemical residues, toxicity, and high costs, have greatly limited these strategies utilization in animal production.</p><p>The type of feed offered to ruminants has a major effect on the profile of VFA and the level of methane production. <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Kessel and Russell (1996)</xref> reported that methane production was completely inhibited at a pH less than 6.0 when feeding a high-concentrate diet. However, when microorganisms in the rumen are exposed to large amounts of fermentable substrates for short periods, the rate of VFA production will exceed the VFA utilization, resulting in subacute ruminal acidosis or acute ruminal acidosis, which has negative impacts on animal health and performance (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Nagaraja and Titgemeyer, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Sato, 2015</xref>). Non-forage fiber sources (NFFS) from high-fiber byproducts usually have limited utility in non-ruminant diets, but ruminant nutritionists can use them to partially replace both forages and concentrates in lactation diets (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Allen and Grant, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Stock et al., 2000</xref>). Although they have different production responses (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Huhtanen, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Huhtanen et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Alamouti et al., 2009</xref>), NFFS-based diets can maintain or improve the performance of dairy cattle under certain conditions (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Ertl et al., 2015</xref>). The strategy of primarily replacing some forage fiber with NFFS for higher-producing cows but only partially replacing some starch for lower-producing cows can optimize nutrient utilization and potentially control feed costs without compromising animal health or productivity (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bradford and Mullins, 2012</xref>). Moreover, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Pereira and Armentano (2000)</xref> reported that low-forage, medium-neutral detergent fiber (NDF) (12.6% forage NDF, 27.5% total NDF) diets and low-forage, high-NDF diets (12.7% forage NDF, 35.7% total NDF) had a lower acetate to propionate ratio and a higher proportion of propionate than the traditional diet (20.1% forage NDF, 25.2% total NDF). The formation of acetate and butyrate results in production of H<sub>2</sub> which can be used to generate CH<sub>4</sub> by methanogenic archaea (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Moss et al., 2000</xref>). Propionate is an end-product of rumen fermentation that is probably the principal alternative of the H<sup>+</sup> sink after CH<sub>4</sub>, and the acetate to propionate ratio in the rumen has a relationship with methanogenesis (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Lana et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Russell, 1998</xref>). The balance between propionate formation and acetate and butyrate formation has a key role in determining H<sub>2</sub> available in rumen for utilization by methanogenic archaea. <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Janssen (2010)</xref> reported that increases in propionate formation are strongly associated with decreases in CH<sub>4</sub> production. In a meta-analysis, <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Ungerfeld (2015)</xref> found that inhibiting CH<sub>4</sub> production in batch cultures resulted in redirection of metabolic hydrogen toward propionate and H<sub>2</sub>, but not butyrate. In addition, propionate is predominantly used as a glucose precursor in ruminants, and more propionate formation would likely result in a more efficient utilization of feed energy. Maximizing the flow of metabolic hydrogen in the rumen away from CH<sub>4</sub> and toward VFA (mainly propionate) would increase the efficiency of ruminant production and decrease its environmental impact (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Ungerfeld, 2015</xref>). Therefore, modifying the dietary formulation with NFFS may be an effective measure to shift the hydrogen flow toward alternative electron acceptors such as propionate.</p><p>The objective of this study was to build a model of metabolic hydrogen shifts <italic>in vitro</italic> to explore the effects of replacing forage fiber with NFFS in diets on methanogenesis, hydrogen metabolism, propionate production and the methanogenic and bacterial community by high-throughput sequencing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Experimental Design and <italic>in vitro</italic> Incubation</title><p>A completely randomized design was applied in an <italic>in vitro</italic> incubation to investigate the effects of the replacement of forage fiber with NFFS in diets on rumen fermentation, methanogenesis and the methanogenic and bacterial community. There are two treatments in the current study: CON (a basic total mixed ration) and TRT (a modified total mixed ration). The dietary treatments were achieved by partly replacing forage fiber with NFFS (wheat bran and soybean hull) to decrease the content of forage neutral detergent fiber (fNDF) from 24.0 to 15.8%, with the composition and inclusion rate of other dietary ingredients remaining the same in total mixed rations (TMRs) (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Composition and nutrient levels of experiment substrates.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Experiment Substrates<hr/></th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRT</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ingredient, % of DM</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alfalfa hay</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.51</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn silage</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.06</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steam-flaked corn</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.47</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cottonseed meal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beet pulp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.51</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DDGS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat bran</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.27</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean hull</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.27</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Premix<sup>1</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chemical composition, % of DM</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDP (% of CP)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDF</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f NDF</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADF</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFC<sup>2</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starch</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE<sub>L</sub><sup>3</sup>, Mcal/kg</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup>1</sup>Premix composition per kilogram: 1,230 mg of Cu [minimum (min)], 4,950 mg of Zn (min), 1,760 mg of Mn (min), 50 mg of I (min), 61 mg of Se (min), 37 mg of Co (min), 504,800 IU of vitamin A (min), 88,800 IU of vitamin D<sub>3</sub> (min), and 2,100 IU of vitamin E (min), 700 mg of vitamin B<sub>3</sub> (min).</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>2</sup>Calculated as 100 &#x02212; (% NDF + % CP + % ether extract + % ash).</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>3</sup>Estimated according to <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">National Research Council [NRC] (2001)</xref></italic>.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences Animal Care and Use Committee (Beijing, China) approved the procedures used to collect the rumen fluid from donor animals. The ruminal fluid for the <italic>in vitro</italic> incubations was collected from three rumen-cannulated lactating Holstein cows 2 h after the morning feeding; the animals were fed a TMR twice daily. Ruminal fluid was brought to the laboratory within 30 min and was strained through layers of cheesecloth under continuous flushing with CO<sub>2</sub>. Equal volumes of rumen fluid collected from each of the cows were combined as the inoculum and diluted with buffer solution (1:2 v/v), which was prepared as described by (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Menke, 1988</xref>), at 39&#x000b0;C with the continuous flow of CO<sub>2</sub> for 3&#x02013;5 s to remove headspace air. The inoculum-buffer mixture was dispensed into 120-ml serum bottles (75 mL/bottle) containing 500 mg of TMR substrates (CON or TRT). An extra three bottles without any substrate served as blanks. After they were sealed with butyl rubber plus crimped aluminum seals, all the serum bottles were connected with vacuumed air bags and incubated at 39&#x000b0;C for 48 h with horizontal shaking at 60 rpm. The <italic>in vitro</italic> incubation was repeated in three experimental batches and three fermentations per treatment were arranged in each batch.</p></sec><sec><title>Sampling and Analyses of Biogas and VFAs</title><p>At the end of the 48 h of incubation, the total gas production of each air bag was measured using 100 mL calibrated glass syringes (H&#x000e4;berle Labortechnik, Lonsee-Ettlenschie&#x000df;, Germany), and the inner wall was coated with Vaseline. The pH values of the <italic>in vitro</italic> incubations were measured using a portable pH meter (Seven Go<sup>TM</sup> portable pH meter, Mettler Toledo, Switzerland). The whole biomass material in each bottle was individually filtered through pre-weighed nylon bags (8 cm &#x000d7; 12 cm, 42 &#x003bc;m). The filtered incubation fluid samples (2.5 ml) were individually collected into microcentrifuge tubes and preserved at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C for VFAs and microbial analysis. Afterwards, the nylon bags were washed gently with cold running water till the effluent ran clear and then they were dried at 55&#x000b0;C for 48 h till they achieved a constant weight for analysis of dry matter (DMD), neutral detergent fiber (NDFD) and acid detergent fiber (ADFD) disappearance. The contents of NDF and ADF were determined using the Ankom A200 fiber analyzer (Ankom Technology, Macedon, NY, United States) based on the procedures of <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Van Soest et al. (1991)</xref> using &#x003b1;-amylase and sodium sulfide for NDF.</p><p>The concentrations of methane and hydrogen in the gas samples were determined using a gas chromatograph (7890B, Agilent Technologies, United States) equipped with a thermal conductivity detector and a packed column (Porapak Q, Agilent Technologies, United States). The initial oven temperature was maintained at 30&#x000b0;C and held at this temperature for 1.5 min, and the reaction continued for 1.5 min. The detector temperature was 100&#x000b0;C, and the carrier gas was nitrogen. Gas production volume (total gas, CH<sub>4</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>) was corrected for temperature (25&#x000b0;C) and pressure (101.325 kPa) conditions. The productions of methane and hydrogen were calculated from the methane and hydrogen concentration and total gas production. The VFA concentrations in the cultures were also analyzed by a gas chromatograph (7890B, Agilent Technologies, United States) fitted with a flame ionization detector and a capillary column (30 m &#x000d7; 0.250 mm &#x000d7; 0.25 &#x003bc;m; BD-FFAP, Agilent Technologies, United States). The oven initial temperature was maintained at 90&#x000b0;C, increased by 5&#x000b0;C/min to 120&#x000b0;C, holding at this temperature for 2 min, and the reaction continued for 8 min. Then, the temperature was increased by 20&#x000b0;C/min to 250&#x000b0;C and held at this temperature for 10 min and the reaction continued for 24.5 min. The injector temperature was 250&#x000b0;C, the detector temperature was 280&#x000b0;C, and the carrier gas was nitrogen.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA Extraction</title><p>Microbial DNA was extracted using an extraction kit (E.Z.N.ATM Mag-Bind Soil DNA Kit, Omega, Norcross, Georgia, United States) in triplicate according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions and the resulting extracts were composited to average out the bias in sampling and extraction. The concentration and quality of the extracted DNA were assessed by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis and a Qubit 3.0 spectrometer (Invitrogen, United States), respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Microbial 16S rRNA Genes Amplification and Illumina Sequencing</title><p>The V4 region of the bacterial and archaeal 16S rRNA gene was amplified using the universal primers 515F (5&#x02032;-GTGCCAGCMGCCGCGGTAA-3&#x02032;) and 806R (5&#x02032;- GGACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3&#x02032;) (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Caporaso et al., 2011</xref>) with forward primers tagged with unique barcode sequences for each sample. While the abundance of the archaeal community was much lower in comparison to the bacterial community, the archaeal community was especially analyzed using nested PCR. In the nested PCR approach, the specific archaeal community was first amplified using the primers Arch340F (5&#x02032;-CCCTAYGGGGYGCASCAG-3&#x02032;) and Arch1000R (5&#x02032;-GAGARGWRGTGCATGGCC-3&#x02032;) as described by <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Gantner et al. (2011)</xref>, and then the PCR product was used as a template in the second PCR using the primers Arch349F (5&#x02032;-GYGCASCAGKCGMGAAW-3&#x02032;) and Arch806R (50-GGACTACVSGGGTATCTAAT-3&#x02032;) (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Takai and Horikoshi, 2000</xref>). A 30 &#x003bc;L PCR reaction mixture contained 15 &#x003bc;L of 2 &#x000d7; Taq Master Mix, 1 &#x003bc;L of 10 &#x003bc;M Bar-PCR primer F, 1 &#x003bc;L of 10 &#x003bc;M Primer R, and 10&#x02013;20 ng of genomic DNA template. PCR was performed using a T100<sup>TM</sup> Thermal Cycler (BIO-RAD, United States) under the following conditions: 94&#x000b0;C for 3 min; followed by 5 cycles of 94&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 45&#x000b0;C for 20 s, and 65&#x000b0;C for 30 s; then 20 cycles of 94&#x000b0;C for 20 s, 55&#x000b0;C for 20 s, and 72&#x000b0;C for 30 s; and finished with a final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 5 min. Illumina bridge-type compatible PCR primers were introduced for the next round (the second round for bacterial DNA and the third round for archaea DNA) of PCR. The next round of PCR was performed under the following conditions: 95&#x000b0;C for 3 min followed by 5 cycles of 94&#x000b0;C for 20 s, 55&#x000b0;C for 20 s, and 72&#x000b0;C for 30 s; and concluding with a final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 5 min. DNA was amplified in triplicate for each sample, and then PCR amplicons were further purified with a DNA purification kit (Gel Purification kits, Sangon, Shanghai, China), and the concentrations were determined using spectrometry (Qubit 3.0, Invitrogen, United States). At last, the purified 16S rRNA gene amplicons were pooled and subjected to paired-end sequencing using the Illumina MiSeq platform at Shanghai Sangon Biotech Co., Ltd.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequencing Data Processing and Analysis</title><p>Pairs of reads from the original DNA fragments were first merged using FLASH (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Mago&#x0010d; and Salzberg, 2011</xref>), and then PRINSEQ was used for quality control of these merged reads (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Schmieder and Edwards, 2011</xref>). Merged reads were assigned to each sample based on the unique barcode. Then, the barcode and primers were removed. PCR chimeras were filtered out using UCHIME (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2011</xref>). After the above filtration, the average length of all the clean reads was 416 and 379 bp, and the average sequencing depth was ca. 68,381 and 61,343 clean reads for bacterial and archaeal community analysis, respectively. Operational taxonomic units (OTU) were clustered at 97% sequence identity using UPARSE (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2011</xref>). The taxonomic classification of the sequences was carried out using the Ribosomal Database Project (RDP) Classifier at the bootstrap cutoff of 80% as suggested by the RDP. Simpson, Shannon, Chao1, Coverage and ACE indices were calculated for each sample. The weighted UniFrac distance was used for a principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Lozupone et al., 2007</xref>), and an analysis of similarity (ANOSIM) in QIIME with 999 permutations (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">R Core Team, 2013</xref>) was conducted to assess the significant differences between treatments. The relative abundance of bacteria was expressed as a percentage. The difference in relative abundance of bacteria and archaea was expressed as a percentage and extended error bar plot was performed to visualize the difference by bioinformatics software (STAMP). Welch&#x02019;s two-sided test was used and Welch&#x02019;s inverted was 0.95 (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Parks et al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Gas production volume (total gas, CH<sub>4</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>), pH, VFAs, DMD, NDFD, ADFD, bacterial abundance, and diversity index were analyzed using PROC MIXED of SAS 9.4 (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, NC, United States) as shown in the following model: <italic>Y</italic><sub>ijk</sub> = &#x003bc; + T<sub>i</sub> + B<sub>j</sub> + TB<sub>ij</sub> + e<sub>ijk</sub>, where <italic>Y</italic><sub>ijk</sub> is the dependent variable, &#x003bc; is the overall mean, <italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub> is the effect of treatment (CON or TRT, considered fixed), <italic>B</italic><sub>j</sub> is the effect of batches (<italic>j</italic> = 1,2,3, considered fixed), TB<sub>ij</sub> is the interaction between <italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub>j</sub> (considered fixed effects), and <italic>e</italic><sub>ijk</sub> is the residual. Data on the bacterial abundance were transformed to log10 (n+1) to ensure normal distribution. Other data were checked for normal distribution and homogeneity by Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk&#x02019;s and Levene&#x02019;s tests in SAS 9.4. Differences were declared significant at <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 and trends at 0.05 &#x02264;<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.10.</p></sec><sec><title>Nucleotide Sequence Accession Number</title><p>All the raw sequences were submitted to the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref></sup>), under accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SRP134679">SRP134679</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Biogas Production, Degradability, pH, and VFA</title><p>The DMD, NDFD, and ADFD increased significantly when the dietary forage fibers were partly replaced by NFFS. The concentration of propionate was significantly increased, while the concentration of the acetate and acetate to propionate ratio were not affected by the treatments. The production of total gas was not significantly affected in response to treatments, it just decreased by only 6.4%. Compared with CON, the production of H<sub>2</sub> of TRT increased by 8.45% and was also not significantly affected. The production of CH<sub>4</sub> tended to decrease by 14.06%, when the dietary forage fibers (mainly from alfalfa) were partly replaced by NFFS (wheat bran and soybean hull) (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of the replacement of forage fiber with NFFS in diets on rumen fermentation and biogas production <italic>in vitro</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 9).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Treatment (f NDF/%)<sup>1</sup><hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM<sup>2</sup></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON(24.0)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRT(15.8)</th><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3782</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMD<sup>3</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8227</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8450</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00440</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0007</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDFD<sup>4</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7717</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8296</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00923</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0007</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFD<sup>5</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7492</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8169</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01074</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TVFA/(mmol/L)<sup>6</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6896</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetate/(mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.563</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7966</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propionate/(mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0146</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isobutyrate/(mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9023</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyrate/(mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5361</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isovalerate/(mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4917</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valerate/(mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8978</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetate/Propinate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2347</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total gas production/(mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.829</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6258</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>/(&#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.481</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2526</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CH<sub>4</sub>/(mg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0789</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup>1</sup>CON, control diet, a basic total mixed ration; TRT, treatment diet, a modified total mixed ration with replacement of alfalfa by wheat bran and soybean hull.</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>2</sup>SEM, standard error of the mean.</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>3</sup>DMD, dry matter disappearance.</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>4</sup>NDFD, neutral detergent fiber disappearance.</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>5</sup>ADFD, acid detergent fiber disappearance.</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>6</sup>TVFA, total valid fatty acid</italic>.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Diversity of Methanogenic and Bacterial Community</title><p>The structure of the archaeal and bacterial community was characterized by sequencing the V4 region of 16S rRNA gene with Illumina MiSeq.</p><sec><title>Archaea</title><p>After merging and a quality check, a total of 1,182,452 merged sequences and 1,142,612 high-quality sequences were generated from 18 samples, with an average read length of 379 bases acquired. After filtering the chimeras, the remaining 1,104,189 sequences were used to generate OTUs with 97% sequence similarity across all the samples. The OTU table was filtered, leaving 5,163 OTUs for further analysis. The archaeal community was represented by two different phyla, <italic>Euryarchaeota</italic> and <italic>Thaumarchaeota</italic>, where <italic>Euryarchaeota</italic> represented on average 99.9%. Genera that were each represented by &#x02265;0.1% of the total sequences were selected for further analysis. The 5 predominant genera were <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic> (57.62%), <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> (28.67%), <italic>Methanomicrobium</italic> (11.36%), <italic>Methanobacterium</italic> (1.76%), and <italic>Methanosphaera</italic> (0.37%) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Composition of the predominant archaea genera among treatments <italic>in vitro</italic>. CON, control diet, a basic total mixed ration; TRT, treatment diet, a modified total mixed ration with the replacement of forage fiber by wheat bran and soybean hull. The top 5 abundant archaea genera are shown and the others are not shown (<italic>n</italic> = 9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02764-g001"/></fig><p>Alpha diversity indices of the archaeal community were presented in Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. No significant differences were observed among treatments based on the OTU numbers and coverage, indicating that the sequencing depth was desirable for the analysis. The alpha diversity indices of Chao1, ACE, Shannon and Simpson were not affected by treatments, showing that decreasing the content of fNDF from 24.0 to 15.8% didn&#x02019;t change the archaeal community richness and diversity. PCoA analysis based on the weighted UniFrac metrics was performed to compare the two treatments (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The ANOSIM analysis revealed no significant differences in the structure of the archaeal community between CON and TRT (<italic>R</italic> = 0.016, <italic>P</italic> = 0.304). Principal coordinate 1, 2, and 3 accounted for 69.4, 19.4, and 5.7% of the total variation, respectively.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Alpha diversity indices of archaea and bacteria among treatments <italic>in vitro</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 9).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Treatment (f NDF/%)<sup>1</sup><hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM<sup>2</sup></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON(24.0)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRT(15.8)</th><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Archaea</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OTU<sup>3</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1127</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1093</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5057</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coverage</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3506</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chao1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2042</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1888</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0946</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACE<sup>4</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2631</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2625</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9890</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shannon</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3591</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simpson</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0951</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Bacteria</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OTU</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4062</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4131</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5868</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coverage</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7395</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chao1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5978</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5983</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9802</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6926</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6787</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6396</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shannon</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0954</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simpson</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5094</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup>1</sup>CON, control diet, a basic total mixed ration; TRT, treatment diet, a modified total mixed ration with replacement of forage fiber by wheat bran and soybean hull.</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>2</sup>SEM, standard error of the mean.</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>3</sup>OTU, operational taxonomic units.</italic></attrib><attrib><italic><sup>4</sup>ACE, abundance-based coverage estimator</italic>.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) of archaeal community structures among treatments <italic>in vitro</italic>. PCoA plots were performed using the weighted UniFrac method. CON, control diet, a basic total mixed ration; TRT, treatment diet, a modified total mixed ration with the replacement of forage fiber by wheat bran and soybean hull (<italic>n</italic> = 9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02764-g002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Bacteria</title><p>A total of 1,414,889 merged sequences and 1,367,883 high-quality sequences were generated from 18 samples, with an average read length of 416 bases acquired. After removing chimeric sequences, the remaining 1,230,862 sequences were used to generate OTUs with 97% sequence similarity across all the samples. After filtering the OTU table, 15,542 OTUs were left for further analysis. Across all samples, 19 bacterial phyla were identified. <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> were the dominant phyla, representing 48.03 and 41.79% of the total sequences, respectively. <italic>Verrucomicrobia</italic>, <italic>Actinobacteria</italic>, and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> represented average percentages of 2.74, 1.47 and 1.44%, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The remaining phyla represented less than 1% of all the sequences. Genera that were each represented by &#x02265;0.1% of the total sequences were selected for further analysis. The nine predominant genera were <italic>Prevotella</italic> (6.59%), <italic>Acetobacteroides</italic> (3.87%), <italic>Falsiporphyromonas</italic> (3.60%), <italic>Succiniclasticum</italic> (3.20%), <italic>Sporobacter</italic> (2.68%), <italic>Subdivision5_genera_incertae_sedis</italic> (2.31%), <italic>Ruminococcus</italic> (2.21%), <italic>Lachnospiracea_incertae_sedis</italic> (2.12%) and <italic>Lachnobacterium</italic> (2.08%).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Composition of the predominant bacterial phyla among treatments <italic>in vitro</italic>. CON, control diet, a basic total mixed ration; TRT, treatment diet, a modified total mixed ration with the replacement of forage fiber by wheat bran and soybean hull. The top 5 abundant bacteria phyla are shown and the others are not shown (<italic>n</italic> = 9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02764-g003"/></fig><p>Alpha diversity indices of the bacterial community were also presented in Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Similar to the archaeal community, no significant differences were observed about any alpha diversity indices. Therefore, the replacement of forage fiber with NFFS in diets didn&#x02019;t change the bacterial community richness and diversity. PCoA analysis based on the weighted UniFrac metrics was performed to compare the two treatments (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The ANOSIM analysis revealed no significant differences on the structure of the bacterial community between treatments (<italic>R</italic> = &#x02212;0.100, <italic>P</italic> = 0.953). Principal coordinate 1, 2, and 3 accounted for 48.1, 14.6, and 13.6% of the total variation, respectively.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) of bacterial community structures among treatments <italic>in vitro</italic>. PCoA plots were performed using the weighted UniFrac method. CON, control diet, a basic total mixed ration; TRT, treatment diet, a modified total mixed ration with the replacement of forage fiber by wheat bran and soybean hull (<italic>n</italic> = 9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02764-g004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Relative Abundance of Methanogenic and Bacterial Communities</title><sec><title>Archaea</title><p>At the phylum level, <italic>Euryarchaeota</italic>, as the most predominant archaeal phylum, represented on average 99.9% of the all sequences. <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic>, <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic>, <italic>Methanomicrobium</italic>, <italic>Methanobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Methanosphaera</italic> from <italic>Euryarchaeota</italic> were the five predominant genera in the present study. The relative abundance of <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic> was significantly increased in TRT compared with the CON group (<italic>P</italic> = 0.001). However, the relative abundance of <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> tended to decrease in the TRT group (<italic>P</italic> = 0.076). Similarly, the relative abundance of <italic>Methanomicrobium</italic> was lower in TRT group, but not significantly decreased (<italic>P</italic> = 0.123) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Difference in the relative abundance of 5 predominant archaeal genera (abundance of the genera was expressed as %). Extended error bar plot was performed by bioinformatics software (STAMP). Welch&#x02019;s two-sided test was used and Welch&#x02019;s inverted was 0.95. CON, control diet, a basic total mixed ration; TRT, treatment diet, a modified total mixed ration with the replacement of forage fiber by wheat bran and soybean hull (<italic>n</italic> = 9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02764-g005"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Bacteria</title><p>At the phylum level, replacement of the forage fiber with NFFS in diets significantly decreased the relative abundance of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.012) and tended to increase the relative abundance of <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.065). The other phylum that accounted for &#x02265;1% of the total sequences in at least one of the samples were not significantly affected by treatments (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p>Difference in the relative abundance of 5 predominant bacteria phyla (abundance of the phylum was expressed as %). Extended error bar plot was performed by bioinformatics software (STAMP). Welch&#x02019;s- two-sided test with two-side was used and Welch&#x02019;s inverted is was 0.95. CON, control diet, a basic total mixed ration; TRT, treatment diet, a modified total mixed ration with the replacement of forage fiber by wheat bran and soybean hull (<italic>n</italic> = 9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02764-g006"/></fig><p>At the genus level, the relative abundance that was represented by &#x02265;0.1% of the total sequences in at least one of the samples were further analyzed. The influenced genera by treatments and the other six predominant genera were listed in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>. All the influenced genera belonged to <italic>Firmicutes</italic>. Compared with the CON group, the relative abundance of most influenced genera was decreased. Specifically, replacement of forage fiber with NFFS in diets significantly decreased the relative abundance of <italic>Ruminococcus</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.031) and <italic>Clostridium XIVa</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.049) and tended to decrease the relative abundance of <italic>Lachnospiracea_incertae_sedis</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.050), <italic>Coprococcus</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.053), <italic>Lachnobacterium</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.056) and <italic>Acetatifactor</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.097). In contrast, the relative abundance of <italic>Marvinbryantia</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.08) was significantly increased in the TRT group. The relative abundance of <italic>Hydrogenoanaerobacterium</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.063) and <italic>Christensenella</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.063) were tended to increase in TRT group. In addition, the relative abundance of <italic>Succiniclasticum</italic>, <italic>Sporobacter</italic> and <italic>Prevotella</italic> was higher, but the relative abundance of <italic>Acetobacteroides</italic> and <italic>Subdivision5_genera_incertae_sedis</italic> was lower in the TRT group. They were not significantly affected by treatments.</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>FIGURE 7</label><caption><p>Difference in the relative abundance of bacterial genera that accounted for &#x02265;0.1% of the total sequences in at least one of the samples and other predominant genera (abundance of the genera was expressed as %). Extended error bar plot was performed by bioinformatics software (STAMP). Welch&#x02019;s two-sided test was used and Welch&#x02019;s inverted was 0.95. CON, control diet, a basic total mixed ration; TRT, treatment diet, a modified total mixed ration with the replacement of forage fiber by wheat bran and soybean hull (<italic>n</italic> = 9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-02764-g007"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Non-forage fiber sources are generated by several industries, which are high in fiber (like forages) but are rapidly passed from the rumen (like concentrates). The judicious use of NFFS can improve the productivity and health of cattle in all stages of lactation while potentially controlling feed costs (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bradford and Mullins, 2012</xref>). Most non-forage fiber is relatively digestible compared with forge fiber, resulting in higher digestibility (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bhatti and Firkins, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Dann et al., 2007</xref>). In our study, the replacement of forage fiber with NFSS significantly increased DMD, NDFD, and ADFD, but numerically increased the concentration of TVFA. On the contrary, total gas production was numerically decreased, unlike the concentration of TVFA. This may be explained by the fact that non-forage fiber is more digestible, but not better in fermentation than alfalfa fiber, which usually was considered to be the best forage fiber. The production of CH<sub>4</sub> decreased by 14.06%, and H<sub>2</sub> production was numerically increased by 8.45%, followed by significant increases in the concentration of propionate. The formation of acetate and butyrate results in production of H<sub>2</sub> which can be used to generate CH<sub>4</sub> by methanogenic archaea (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Moss et al., 2000</xref>). In propionate formation, pyruvate is reduced to propionate, while in H<sub>2</sub> formation, protons (H<sup>+</sup>) are reduced to H<sub>2</sub>. The two pathways are both electron accepting, so <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Janssen (2010)</xref> thought that propionate formation was an alternative pathway to H<sub>2</sub> formation and was accompanied by decreasing in CH<sub>4</sub> production. The balance between propionate formation and acetate and butyrate formation has a key role in determining H<sub>2</sub> available in rumen for utilization by methanogenic archaea. These results indicated that the replacement of forage fiber with NFFS may reduce the utilization of hydrogen in methanogenesis and shift hydrogen flow from CH<sub>4</sub> to propionate and H<sub>2</sub> by changing the relative abundance of certain archaea or bacteria. Similar to previous studies, inhibition of CH<sub>4</sub> production in batch cultures resulted in the redirection of metabolic hydrogen toward propionate and H<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Ungerfeld, 2015</xref>). <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Mitsumori et al. (2012)</xref> found that some [H] spared from CH<sub>4</sub> production is redirected to propionate, and part is directed to atypical [H] sinks like H<sub>2</sub>.</p><p>As the sole producers of methane in the rumen, a correlation between the number of methanogens and methanogenesis might be expected. <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Wallace et al. (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Veneman et al. (2015)</xref> suggested that the number of archaea, rather than the population structure, might be the major driver of methane production in the rumen. Some strategies, including supplementation of essential oils (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Duarte et al., 2017b</xref>) or ionophores (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al., 2017</xref>), reduce enteric methane emissions by inhibiting the activity or richness of the microbiota. Inhibition of the microbiota generally results in decreasing feed digestion (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Ungerfeld, 2015</xref>). However, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Morgavi et al. (2010)</xref> reported that decreasing methane production did not affected fiber digestibility in several <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments. <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al. (2017)</xref> found that supplementation of nisin in diets decreased methane production, while feed digestion was unaffected. This may be explained by shifts in the microbial population. Various methanogen groups have different methanogenic potential (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Leahy et al., 2013</xref>) and a shift in the methanogen community toward less effective methanogenesis might also explain the differences in methane production. We observed decreased methane production and increased propionate concentration, while dry matter disappearance was increased in the present study. It is possible that changes in the population structure of the microbiota can also affect the methane production, like the inhibition of microbial richness or activity. <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Belanche et al. (2016)</xref> found that ivy fruit saponins reduced the methane production by modifying the structure of the methanogen community and decreasing its diversity. In contrast, chitosan promoted a shift in the fermentation pattern toward propionate production to reduce the methane production, which is achieved by a simplification of the structure in the bacterial community. Therefore, both the richness of the methanogen and the population structure of the microbial community plays an important role in methanogenesis. On the other hand, the richness and diversity of the archaeal and bacterial community were not affected by treatments, together with a similar pH value and TVFA production, also suggesting that the replacement of forage fiber with NFFS in the diets didn&#x02019;t have significant detrimental effects on the overall rumen fermentation <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p><sec><title>Archaea</title><p>Methane is produced in the rumen as a product of normal fermentation of the feedstuffs, and methanogens, which belong to the domain <italic>Archaea</italic> and the phylum <italic>Euryarchaeota</italic> are the only known microorganisms capable of methane production (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Hook et al., 2010</xref>). However, compared to the number of methanogens, the efficiency of different methanogens is considered to be more important in methanogenesis (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2014</xref>). Given that the positive relationship of increased methane production and increased transcripts of <italic>mcrA</italic> gene, methanogens that can express more <italic>mcrA</italic> genes are believed to contribute more to methane production (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Freitag and Prosser, 2009</xref>). In our study, differences between treatments were observed at the genus level, where the relative abundance of <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic> (belongs to <italic>Methanomassiliicoccaceae</italic> family) was significantly increased, but the relative abundance of <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> tended to decrease in the TRT group. <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Danielsson et al. (2017)</xref> reported that unclassified <italic>Methanomassiliicoccaceae</italic> was 1.5-fold more abundant in low CH<sub>4</sub> emitters than that in high CH<sub>4</sub> emitters. <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al. (2017)</xref> reported that dietary pea fiber increased the diversity of the colonic methanogen community structure of pigs with a shift from <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> to <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic> and <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic>-like genus. Hydrogenotrophic pathway, methylotrophic pathway and acetoclastic pathway are the three major pathways of methanogenesis. <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> is one kind of hydrogenotrophic methanogen, that converts H<sub>2</sub> and/or formate to CH<sub>4</sub> (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Leahy et al., 2013</xref>), while <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic>, which belong to the novel order <italic>Methanomassiliicoccales</italic>, has capacity to use methylamine substrates for methanogenesis by H<sub>2</sub>-dependent methylotrophic pathway (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Lang et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Moissl-Eichinger et al., 2018</xref>). Although methanogenic archaea can acquire substrates form environment, some species would increase efficiency by forming contacts with protozoa, which produce large quantities of H<sub>2</sub> by their hydrogenosomes (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Embley et al., 2003</xref>). <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> is considered to be the predominant protozoa-associated methanogens (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Belanche et al., 2014</xref>), while the relation between <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic> and protozoa has not been reported. Compared with <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic>, <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic> may be less effective in methane production. Different sources of fiber may stimulate the growth of different microbiota and change the relative abundance of the microbial community. Replacement of forage fiber with NFFS in diets would mitigate CH<sub>4</sub> emission from ruminants by changing the relative abundance of <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> and <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic> at the archaea level.</p><p><italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic> is more abundant in our study than <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic>, which was believed to be the most predominant genus in a previous study (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Janssen and Kirs, 2008</xref>). In another recent study (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Danielsson et al., 2017</xref>), <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> was also observed as the most predominant genus. <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Danielsson et al. (2017)</xref> used the same primers of both bacteria and archaea to construct 16S rRNA amplicon libraries, resulting in an average of 505 archaeal sequences per sample (61434 archaeal sequences per sample in our study). Different sequencing depths may be responsible for the difference between our study and others. Similar to our study, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Paul et al. (2015)</xref> also reported a high abundance of <italic>Methanomassiliicoccaceae</italic> present in the rumen of Nili-Ravi buffalo by 16S rDNA analysis of archaea.</p></sec><sec><title>Bacteria</title><p>In the present study, the rumen microbiota was dominated by <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> and <italic>Firmicutes</italic>, which are considered to be the predominant phyla in most studies (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">de Menezes et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Martinez-Fernandez et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Duarte et al., 2017a</xref>). The <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> are considered net H<sub>2</sub> utilizers whereas the <italic>Firmicutes</italic> phylum includes H<sub>2</sub> producers (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Stewart et al., 1997</xref>). <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Belanche et al. (2016)</xref> reported that supplementing chitosan in the control diet promoted a shift in the fermentation pattern toward propionate production, which explained about a third of the decrease in methanogenesis, which was achieved by the substitution of fibrolytic (<italic>Firmicutes</italic> and <italic>Fibrobacteres</italic>) by amylolytic bacteria (<italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>). In another study, a shift in the microbiota with an increase in the <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> to <italic>Firmicutes</italic> ratio was accompanied by a 30% decrease in methanogenesis and increase in propionate production, using chloroform as a methane inhibitor (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Martinez-Fernandez et al., 2016</xref>). <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Kittelmann et al. (2013)</xref> observed a positive correlation between the occurrence of methanogens and fibrolytic bacteria. In the present study, the TRT group had a higher abundance of <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> (mainly amylolytic bacteria) and a lower abundance of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> (mainly fibrolytic bacteria) compared with the CON group. This substitution of fibrolytic by amylolytic bacteria may result in the higher concentration of propionate as fermentation products in the TRT group.</p><p>At the genus levels, all bacterial genera whose relative abundance changed (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.1) belonged to the <italic>Firmicutes</italic> phylum. Most of these genera have higher relative abundance in the CON group, except <italic>Marvinbryantia</italic>, <italic>Hydrogenoanaerobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Christensenella</italic>. <italic>Marvinbryantia</italic> belongs to the <italic>Lachnospiraceae</italic> family, which degrades complex polysaccharides to short chain fatty acids, including acetate, butyrate, and propionate (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Biddle et al., 2013</xref>). <italic>Hydrogenoanaerobacterium</italic> belong to the <italic>Ruminococcaceae</italic> family, which contains a large number of healthy gut-associated butyrate-producing bacteria (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Morissette et al., 2017</xref>). A recent study suggests that the presence of <italic>Christensenella</italic> in the gut, a low abundant (less than 0.001%) and highly heritable (transmissible from parent to offspring) bacterial genus, decreases body weight gain in obese mice (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Goodrich et al., 2014</xref>). There are few references about these genera and whether they participate in the metabolism of propionate is unknown. However, as described above, these genera are all involved in energy metabolism and maybe have certain relationships with shifting hydrogen flow toward propionate.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Theoretical predictions of displacements of H<sub>2</sub> metabolism from methanogenesis to propionate production was supported by the dietary intervention <italic>in vitro</italic>. A modified dietary formulation strategy can affect methanogenesis by shifting the hydrogen flow toward propionate and partially toward to H<sub>2</sub>. The shift was achieved by a substitution of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> by <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> and another substitution of <italic>Methanobrevibacter</italic> by <italic>Methanomassiliicoccus</italic>. In conclusion, the replacement of forage fiber with NFFS in diets may be a meaningful strategy to shift the hydrogen flow toward propionate and further studies need to be conducted to explore if the same microbiota modulation would be observed <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>KW, BX, and LJ designed the study. KW, XN, SZ, and KC conducted the experiments. KW, XN, and LY analyzed the data. KW wrote the manuscript. JT, XN, GZ, LJ, and BX revised the paper. All authors carefully read and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This study was financially supported by the National Key Research and Development Plan (Grant Nos. 2016YFD0700205, 2016YFD0700201, and 2016YFD0500507).</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alamouti</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alikhani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghorbani</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zebeli</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Effects of inclusion of neutral detergent soluble fibre sources in diets varying in forage particle size on feed intake, digestive processes, and performance of mid-lactation Holstein cows.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anim. Feed Sci. Technol.</italic></source>
<volume>154</volume>
<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2009.07.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Interactions between forage and wet corn gluten feed as sources of fiber in diets for lactating dairy Cows1.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>322</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(00)74882-X</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10714868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10714868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belanche</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Fuente</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newbold</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Study of methanogen communities associated with different rumen protozoal populations.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>677</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6941.12423</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25195951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25195951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belanche</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinloche</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preskett</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newbold</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Effects and mode of action of chitosan and ivy fruit saponins on the microbiome, fermentation and methanogenesis in the rumen simulation technique.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>92</volume>:<issue>fiv160</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsec/fiv160</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26676056?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26676056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Firkins</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Kinetics of hydration and functional specific gravity of fibrous feed by-products.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Anim. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>1449</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1458</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/1995.7351449x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 7665376?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7665376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biddle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leschine</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Untangling the genetic basis of fibrolytic specialization by Lachnospiraceae and Ruminococcaceae in diverse gut communities.</article-title>
<source><italic>Diversity</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>640</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/d5030627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Invited review: strategies for promoting productivity and health of dairy cattle by feeding nonforage fiber sources.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>4735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4746</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2012-5393</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22916877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22916877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauber</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg-Lyons</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Global patterns of 16S rRNA diversity at a depth of millions of sequences per sample.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>108</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>), <fpage>4516</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4522</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1000080107</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20534432?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20534432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danielsson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicksved</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnurer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Methane production in dairy cows correlates with rumen methanogenic and bacterial community structure.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>226</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.00226</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28261182?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28261182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotanch</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Effect of partial replacement of forage neutral detergent fiber with by-product neutral detergent fiber in close-up diets on periparturient performance of dairy cows.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>1789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1801</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2006-692</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17369220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Menezes</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Donovan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>B. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clipson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Microbiome analysis of dairy cows fed pasture or total mixed ration diets.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>78</volume>
<fpage>256</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>265</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.2011.01151.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21671962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21671962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durmic</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vercoe</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017a</year>). <article-title>The type of forage substrate preparation included as substrate in a RUSITEC system affects the ruminal microbiota and fermentation characteristics.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>704</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.00704</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28473826?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28473826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiri</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Breves</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017b</year>). <article-title>incubation temperature, but not pequi oil supplementation, affects methane production, and the ruminal microbiota in a rumen simulation technique (Rusitec) system.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>1076</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01076</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28701999?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28701999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quince</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>UCHIME improves sensitivity and speed of chimera detection.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>2194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr381</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21700674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Embley</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Giezen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyal</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Hydrogenosomes, mitochondria and early eukaryotic evolution.</article-title>
<source><italic>IUBMB Life</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>395</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15216540310001592834</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 14584589?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14584589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ertl</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zebeli</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zollitsch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knaus</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Feeding of by-products completely replaced cereals and pulses in dairy cows and enhanced edible feed conversion ratio.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>98</volume>
<fpage>1225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1233</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2014-8810</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25483200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25483200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freitag</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prosser</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Correlation of methane production and functional gene transcriptional activity in a peat soil.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>6679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6687</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01021-09</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19749064?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19749064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gantner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso-Saez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertilsson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Novel primers for 16S rRNA-based archaeal community analyses in environmental samples.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Microbiol. Methods</italic></source>
<volume>84</volume>
<fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mimet.2010.10.001</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20940022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20940022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutter</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blekhman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Human genetics shape the gut microbiome.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cell</italic></source>
<volume>159</volume>
<fpage>789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>799</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.09.053</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25417156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25417156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>A.-D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Methanogens: methane producers of the rumen and mitigation strategies.</article-title>
<source><italic>Archaea</italic></source>
<volume>2010</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2010/945785</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21253540?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21253540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huhtanen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The effects of concentrate energy source and protein content on milk production in cows given grass silage ad libitum.</article-title>
<source><italic>Grass Forage Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>355</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2494.1993.tb01868.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huhtanen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaakkola</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saarisalo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The effects of concentrate energy source on the milk production of dairy cows given a grass silage-based diet.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anim. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1357729800008109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Influence of hydrogen on rumen methane formation and fermentation balances through microbial growth kinetics and fermentation thermodynamics.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anim. Feed Sci. Technol.</italic></source>
<volume>160</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2010.07.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Structure of the archaeal community of the rumen.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>3619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3625</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02812-07</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18424540?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18424540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Methane emissions from cattle.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Anim. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>2483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/1995.7382483x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8567486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessel</surname><given-names>J. A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The effect of pH on ruminal methanogenesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.1996.tb00319.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Status of the phylogenetic diversity census of ruminal microbiomes.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.2010.01029.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21223325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21223325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kittelmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seedorf</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Simultaneous amplicon sequencing to explore co-occurrence patterns of bacterial, archaeal and eukaryotic microorganisms in rumen microbial communities.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>e47879</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047879</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23408926?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23408926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lana</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Amburgh</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The role of pH in regulating ruminal methane and ammonia production.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Anim. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>2190</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2196</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/1998.7682190x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9734871?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9734871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuldes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klingl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poehlein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunea</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>New mode of energy metabolism in the seventh order of methanogens as revealed by comparative genome analysis of &#x0201c;<italic>Candidatus</italic> methanoplasma termitum&#x0201d;.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>1338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1352</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.03389-14</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25501486?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25501486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leahy</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronimus</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedlock</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altermann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Attwood</surname><given-names>G. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Genome sequencing of rumen bacteria and archaea and its application to methane mitigation strategies.</article-title>
<source><italic>Animal</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 2</issue>), <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>243</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731113000700</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23739466?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23739466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamady</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Quantitative and qualitative &#x003b2; diversity measures lead to different insights into factors that structure microbial communities.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>1576</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1585</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01996-06</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17220268?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17220268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Dietary pea fiber increases diversity of colonic methanogens of pigs with a shift from Methanobrevibacter to Methanomassiliicoccus-like genus and change in numbers of three hydrogenotrophs.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>:<issue>17</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-016-0919-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28095773?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28095773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mago&#x0010d;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>FLASH: fast length adjustment of short reads to improve genome assemblies.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>2957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2963</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr507</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21903629?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21903629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Fernandez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Denman</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsumori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McSweeney</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Methane inhibition alters the microbial community, hydrogen flow, and fermentation response in the rumen of cattle.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>1122</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.01122</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27486452?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27486452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newbold</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Redirecting rumen fermentation to reduce methanogenesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Austr. J. Exp. Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/Ea07218</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16303299?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16303299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menke</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Estimation of the energetic feed value obtained from chemical analysis and in vitro gas production using rumen fluid.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anim. Res. Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitsumori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinkai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takenaka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Enishi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Responses in digestion, rumen fermentation and microbial populations to inhibition of methane formation by a halogenated methane analogue.</article-title>
<source><italic>Br. J. Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>482</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>491</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114511005794</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22059589?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22059589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moissl-Eichinger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pausan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taffner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Archaea Are interactive components of complex microbiomes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trends Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>70</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2017.07.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28826642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28826642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgavi</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newbold</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Microbial ecosystem and methanogenesis in ruminants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Animal</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>1024</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1036</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731110000546</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22444607?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22444607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morissette</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaulieu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lessard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Growth performance of piglets during the first two weeks of lactation affects the development of the intestinal microbiota.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Anim. Physiol. Anim. Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>532</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.12784</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28990221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28990221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouany</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newbold</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Methane production by ruminants: its contribution to global warming.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annales De Zootechnie</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>253</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/animres:2000119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagaraja</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Titgemeyer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Ruminal acidosis in beef cattle: The current microbiological and nutritional outlook1, 2.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>E17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17517750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Research Council [NRC]</collab> (<year>2001</year>). <source><italic>Nutrient Requirements of Dairy Cattle.</italic></source>
<edition>7th Edn</edition>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyson</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hugenholtz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beiko</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>STAMP: statistical analysis of taxonomic and functional profiles.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>3123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3124</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu494</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25061070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25061070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Effects of essential oils on methane production and fermentation by, and abundance and diversity of, rumen microbial populations.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>78</volume>
<fpage>4271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4280</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00309-12</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22492451?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22492451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Somvanshi</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathore</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>16S rDNA analysis of archaea indicates dominance of Methanobacterium and high abundance of Methanomassiliicoccaceae in rumen of Nili-Ravi buffalo.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anaerobe</italic></source> 35(Pt B), <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2015.06.002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26103451?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26103451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Armentano</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Partial replacement of forage with nonforage fiber sources in lactating cow diets. II. Digestion and rumen function.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>2876</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2887</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(00)75188-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11132860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11132860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>E. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oetzel</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Armentano</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Partial replacement of forage with nonforage fiber sources in lactating cow diets. I. Performance and health.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>2716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2730</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(99)75528-1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10629819?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10629819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>R Core Team</collab> (<year>2013</year>). <source><italic>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name> Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org/">http://www.R-project.org/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The importance of pH in the regulation of ruminal acetate to propionate ratio and methane production in vitro.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>3222</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3230</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(98)75886-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9891267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9891267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Subacute ruminal acidosis (SARA) challenge, ruminal condition and cellular immunity in cattle.</article-title>
<source><italic>Japn. J. Vet. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>63</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>), <fpage>S25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S36</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 25872324?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25872324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmieder</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Quality control and preprocessing of metagenomic datasets.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>864</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr026</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21278185?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21278185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Monensin and Nisin affect rumen fermentation and microbiota differently in vitro.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>1111</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01111</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28670304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28670304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leahy</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Froula</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kittelmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Methane yield phenotypes linked to differential gene expression in the sheep rumen microbiome.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome Res.</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>1517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1525</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.168245.113</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24907284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24907284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;The rumen bacteria,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>&#x02018;The Rumen Microbial Ecosystem&#x02019;</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hobson</surname><given-names>P. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>), <fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-009-1453-7_2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klopfenstein</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milton</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Review of new information on the use of wet and dry milling feed by-products in feedlot diets.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Anim. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>77</volume>(<issue>E&#x02013;Suppl.</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas2000.77E-Suppl1w</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horikoshi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Rapid detection and quantification of members of the archaeal community by quantitative PCR using fluorogenic probes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>5066</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5072</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.66.11.5066-5072.2000</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11055964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11055964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ungerfeld</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Shifts in metabolic hydrogen sinks in the methanogenesis-inhibited ruminal fermentation: a meta-analysis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>37</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Soest</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Dairy Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>3583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3597</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(91)78551-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 1660498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veneman</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muetzel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moorby</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perdok</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Does Dietary mitigation of enteric methane production affect rumen function and animal productivity in dairy cows?</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>e0140282</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140282</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26509835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26509835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rooke</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duthie</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyslop</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKain</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Archaeal abundance in post-mortem ruminal digesta may help predict methane emissions from beef cattle.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>:<issue>5892</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep05892</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25081098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25081098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Medicinal herbs as a potential strategy to decrease methane production by rumen microbiota: a systematic evaluation with a focus on <italic>Perilla frutescens</italic> seed extract.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>9757</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9771</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-016-7830-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27660180?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27660180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Effect of monensin feeding and withdrawal on populations of individual bacterial species in the rumen of lactating dairy cows fed high-starch rations.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>145</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-008-1528-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18535825?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18535825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Popovski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rea</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skillman</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toovey</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Northwood</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A vaccine against rumen methanogens can alter the composition of archaeal populations.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>1860</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1866</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02453-08</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19201957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19201957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>