<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6324907</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evy213</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evy213</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Diversity and Evolution of Sensor Histidine Kinases in Eukaryotes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kabbara</surname><given-names>Samar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="evy213-FM2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000e9;rivaux</surname><given-names>Ana&#x000ef;s</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="evy213-FM2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dug&#x000e9; de Bernonville</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Courdavault</surname><given-names>Vincent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clastre</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gastebois</surname><given-names>Amandine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>Marwan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamze</surname><given-names>Monzer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cock</surname><given-names>J Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schaap</surname><given-names>Pauline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Papon</surname><given-names>Nicolas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evy213-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evy213-cor1"/><!--<email>nicolas.papon@univ-angers.fr</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Bill</given-names></name><role>Associate Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="evy213-aff1"><label>1</label>Groupe d&#x02019;Etude des Interactions H&#x000f4;te-Pathog&#x000e8;ne, GEIHP, EA3142, Universit&#x000e9; d&#x02019;Angers, SFR 4208 ICAT, France</aff><aff id="evy213-aff2"><label>2</label>Biomol&#x000e9;cules et Biotechnologies V&#x000e9;g&#x000e9;tales, BBV, EA2106, Universit&#x000e9; Fran&#x000e7;ois Rabelais de Tours, France</aff><aff id="evy213-aff3"><label>3</label>Laboratoire Microbiologie Sant&#x000e9; et Environnement, Facult&#x000e9; de Sant&#x000e9; Publique, Universit&#x000e9; Libanaise, Tripoli, Lebanon</aff><aff id="evy213-aff4"><label>4</label>Algal Genetics Group, UMR 8227, Integrative Biology of Marine Models, Station Biologique de Roscoff, Sorbonne Universit&#x000e9;, UPMC Universit&#x000e9; Paris 06, CNRS, Roscoff, France</aff><aff id="evy213-aff5"><label>5</label>School of Life Sciences, University of Dundee, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><fn id="evy213-FM2"><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><corresp id="evy213-cor1">Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>nicolas.papon@univ-angers.fr</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-09-25"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="evy213.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Histidine kinases (HKs) are primary sensor proteins that act in cell signaling pathways generically referred to as &#x0201c;two-component systems&#x0201d; (TCSs). TCSs are among the most widely distributed transduction systems used by both prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms to detect and respond to a broad range of environmental cues. The structure and distribution of HK proteins are now well documented in prokaryotes, but information is still fragmentary for eukaryotes. Here, we have taken advantage of recent genomic resources to explore the structural diversity and the phylogenetic distribution of HKs in the prominent eukaryotic supergroups. Searches of the genomes of 67 eukaryotic species spread evenly throughout the phylogenetic tree of life identified 748 predicted HK proteins. Independent phylogenetic analyses of predicted HK proteins were carried out for each of the major eukaryotic supergroups. This allowed most of the compiled sequences to be categorized into previously described HK groups. Beyond the phylogenetic analysis of eukaryotic HKs, this study revealed some interesting findings: 1) characterization of some previously undescribed eukaryotic HK groups with predicted functions putatively related to physiological traits; 2) discovery of HK groups that were previously believed to be restricted to a single kingdom in additional supergroups, and 3) indications that some evolutionary paths have led to the appearance, transfer, duplication, and loss of HK genes in some phylogenetic lineages. This study provides an unprecedented overview of the structure and distribution of HKs in the Eukaryota and represents a first step toward deciphering the evolution of TCS signaling in living organisms.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>histidine kinases</kwd><kwd>cell signaling</kwd><kwd>two-component systems</kwd><kwd>eukaryotes</kwd><kwd>phylogenetic analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">University of Angers</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100008280</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Agence Nationale de la Recherche</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100001665</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="23"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Protein phosphorylation is one of the most widespread processes in living organisms and is commonly used to regulate numerous cell signaling pathways. Protein phosphorylation is mediated by enzymes belonging to the kinase superfamily. Kinases catalyze the transfer of a phosphate from ATP to various amino acids including serine/threonine (Ser/Thr kinases), tyrosine (Tyr kinases), and histidine (His kinases). To date, histidine kinases (HKs) have been described in archaea, bacteria, amoebae, plants, fungi, viruses, and bacteriophages (<xref rid="evy213-B38" ref-type="bibr">Delaroque et&#x000a0;al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B99" ref-type="bibr">Mascher et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B109" ref-type="bibr">Osakabe et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B59" ref-type="bibr">Hargreaves et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B62" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B128" ref-type="bibr">Schaap et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B46" ref-type="bibr">Galp&#x000e9;rin et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). HK activity has also been detected in mammals (<xref rid="evy213-B9" ref-type="bibr">Attwood 2013</xref>), but mammalian genomes do not encode any typical bacterial or eukaryotic HK-like proteins. Consequently, approaches aiming at pharmacologically targeting HK proteins represent a promising strategy for the future development of antimicrobials in the context of human disease (<xref rid="evy213-B14" ref-type="bibr">Bem et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B135" ref-type="bibr">Shor and Chauhan 2015</xref>).</p><p>The canonical structure of HKs is composed of various domains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). The first region corresponds to a highly variable N-terminal sequence that determines which stimulus is perceived by the HK. This region is referred to as the &#x0201c;sensing domain.&#x0201d; The central region is the transmitter domain consisting of both histidine kinase A (dimerization/phosphoacceptor) (HisKA) and cognate histidine kinase-like ATPase catalytic (HATPase_c) subdomains. The HisKA domain includes a H-box, usually containing a phosphorylatable histidine, and an X-box (<xref rid="evy213-B54" ref-type="bibr">Grebe and Stock 1999</xref>). The HATPase_c subdomain includes four distinct boxes: the N-, G1-, F-, and G2-boxes (<xref rid="evy213-B54" ref-type="bibr">Grebe and Stock 1999</xref>). In contrast to prokaryotic HKs, most eukaryotic HKs harbor an additional C-terminal receiver domain (REC) characterized by the presence of a three amino-acid signature (DDK) that includes a phosphorylatable aspartate residue. Thus, eukaryotic HKs are generally called hybrid HKs (<xref rid="evy213-B5" ref-type="bibr">Appleby et&#x000a0;al. 1996</xref>).
</p><fig id="evy213-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 1.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Domain organization and TCSs signaling. The canonical structure of HKs is composed of: 1) a highly variable N-terminal sequence that determines which stimulus is perceived by the HK (sensing-D); 2) and both histidine kinase A (H(X)) (including a phosphorylatable histidine residue in the H-box and an X-box) and histidine kinase-like ATPase catalytic (including four distinct boxes: the N-, G1-, F-, and G2-boxes) subdomains. In prokaryotes, TCSs usually consist of a two-step phosphorelay between an HK and an RR. Perception of a stimulus induces autophosphorylation of the HK which thus acts as a primary sensor, and the phosphate is then transferred to an RR which acts as a transcription factor to directly regulate a series of genes required for an adapted response. Most eukaryotic HKs harbor an additional C-terminal receiver domain (REC) characterized by the presence of a three amino acid signature (DDK). Thus, eukaryotic HKs are generally called hybrid HKs (HHKs). In eukaryotes, TCSs are composed of additional modules, such as the Hpt domain and the signaling routes that mediate the perception of stimuli correspond to a multistep phosphorelay between three families of proteins (HHK, Hpt, and RR). In most eukaryotic TCSs, the RR either acts directly as a transcription factor or governs downstream elements (MAPK cascades, the cAMP pathway, or Raf-like kinases). Note that in a few HKs, the Hpt domain is fused to the REC domain.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evy213f1"/></fig><p>HKs are primary sensor proteins involved in cell signaling pathways generically referred to as &#x0201c;two-component systems&#x0201d; (TCSs) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). TCSs are among the most widely distributed transduction systems used by both prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms to detect and respond to a wide range of environmental cues. In prokaryotes, TCSs usually involve communication between two functional modules, that is, HKs and response regulators (RRs), via phosphorylation events (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). The perception of a stimulus induces autophosphorylation of the HK, and the phosphate is then transferred to an RR which acts as a transcription factor to directly regulate a series of target genes required for an adapted response (<xref rid="evy213-B5" ref-type="bibr">Appleby et&#x000a0;al. 1996</xref>). In eukaryotes, TCSs are composed of additional modules, such as the histidine-containing phosphotransfer (Hpt) domain and the signaling routes that mediate the perception of stimuli involve a multistep phosphorelay between three families of proteins: HK &#x02192; Hpt &#x02192; RR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). In most eukaryotic TCSs, the RR either acts directly as a transcription factor or regulates downstream elements such as mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) cascades or cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) signaling systems (<xref rid="evy213-B62" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). In plants, some HKs are known to directly regulate other types of signaling proteins such as Raf-like kinases (<xref rid="evy213-B28" ref-type="bibr">Clark et&#x000a0;al. 1998</xref>). Finally, few other variations in the architecture of TCSs have been described in some models (<xref rid="evy213-B74" ref-type="bibr">Jung et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>).</p><p>It is now well documented that prokaryotic HKs govern a wide range of crucial processes, including nutrient acquisition, various metabolic pathways (nitrogen, glucose, cell wall biosynthesis), adaptation to changes in the environment (osmolarity, light, chemotaxis, temperature, oxygen), developmental pathways (sporulation, biofilm formation, competence), virulence, antibiotic resistance, and many others (e.g., flagellar assembly, secretion systems) (<xref rid="evy213-B99" ref-type="bibr">Mascher et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). In amoebae, HKs regulate a large panel of fundamental processes during multicellular development such as motility, morphogenesis, osmoregulation, as well as spore differentiation, encapsulation and dormancy (<xref rid="evy213-B39" ref-type="bibr">Du et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). In plants, HKs participate in the regulation of female gametophyte development and vegetative growth, as osmosensors by regulating drought, salt-stress and stomatal closure responses, and are involved in light and phytohormones (cytokinin and ethylene) perception and signal transduction (<xref rid="evy213-B109" ref-type="bibr">Osakabe et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). Finally, HKs are also widespread in fungi and to date have been reported to be involved in stress adaptation (high osmolarity and oxidant conditions), red-light perception, morphogenesis, and virulence (<xref rid="evy213-B62" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>)</p><p>While the structure and distribution of these sensing proteins are now well documented in prokaryotes (<xref rid="evy213-B81" ref-type="bibr">Kim and Forst 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B99" ref-type="bibr">Mascher et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B46" ref-type="bibr">Galp&#x000e9;rin et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>), information is still fragmentary for eukaryotes. Plant and fungal HKs are currently categorized into 7 and 16 groups, respectively (<xref rid="evy213-B129" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). Some studies exploring the structure of HKs in Dictyosteliaceae, Physaraceae, and Protosteliaceae initiated the establishment of a classification of these sensing proteins in amoebae (<xref rid="evy213-B42" ref-type="bibr">Eichinger et&#x000a0;al. 2005</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B61" ref-type="bibr">Heidel et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B128" ref-type="bibr">Schaap et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B64" ref-type="bibr">Hillmann et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Thus, although recent advances have provided a preliminary insight into the distribution of HKs in fungi, plants, and amoebae, the underlying mechanisms that drive the marked diversity among eukaryotic HKs, the number of genes, the structure, and the functional variations remain largely obscure. More precisely, the evolutionary paths that led to the appearance, transfer, duplication, and loss of HK genes have not been addressed broadly across the eukaryotes. In the present work, we have taken advantage of recent genomic resources to explore the structural diversity and the phylogenetic distribution of HKs in the six prominent eukaryotic clades: Archaeplastida (and sister clades Cryptophyta and Haptophyta), Opisthokonta, Amoebozoa, Apusozoa, Excavata, and SAR (Stramenopiles, Alveolates, and Rhizaria) (<xref rid="evy213-B53" ref-type="bibr">Grant and Katz 2014</xref>). This study represents an essential step toward deciphering the evolution of TCS cell signaling pathways in eukaryotes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>HK Sequence Search, Analysis, and Annotation</title><p>BLAST (<xref rid="evy213-B2" ref-type="bibr">Altschul et&#x000a0;al. 1990</xref>) searches were performed against the NCBI and JGI genome sequence databases. The protein domains HisKA (PFAM00512) and HATPase_c (PFAM02518) were used as queries against both databases without threshold constraints. In order to eliminate redundant protein sequences, a multiple alignment was performed using the Clustal Omega algorithm (<xref rid="evy213-B136" ref-type="bibr">Sievers et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). After annotation, domain organization was predicted for each unique protein using the SMART (<xref rid="evy213-B132" ref-type="bibr">Schultz et&#x000a0;al. 1998</xref>) and the Conserved Domain Database (<xref rid="evy213-B97" ref-type="bibr">Marchler-Bauer et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>) algorithms. The TMHMM (<xref rid="evy213-B84" ref-type="bibr">Krogh et&#x000a0;al. 2001</xref>) algorithm was used to predict transmembrane helices in the predicted proteins. Importantly, following the domain analysis, we only retained putative HK sequences that possessed at least two of the three following domains: HisKA (PFAM00512), HATPase_c (PFAM02518), and REC (PFAM00072). HK protein sequences were annotated using the first letter of the genus followed by the first four letters of the species, HK, and the number of the sequence (e.g., KniteHK1 for <italic>Klebsormidium nitens</italic> Histidine Kinase 1) except for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans, Oryza sativa</italic>, and <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic> HKs for which the previously published nomenclature was conserved.</p></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic Analysis</title><p>Alignments were built with Cobalt 2.0.2 (<xref rid="evy213-B110" ref-type="bibr">Papadopoulos and Agarwala 2007</xref>), applying an additional constraint on conserved domains that were compared with the CDD domain bank v0.75. The alphabet chosen was of the regular type and a maximum distance between two sequences of 0.7 was chosen (fraction of the number of words in common to all the words). The resulting alignments were curated using Gblocks 0.91b (<xref rid="evy213-B145" ref-type="bibr">Talavera and Castresana 2007</xref>) to remove nonconserved positions that could prevent correct reconstruction of the phylogeny. Several Gblocks parameter values were tested to retain between 11% and 13% of the positions in each initial alignment. For each alignment, the minimum length of a block was set to four positions and all positions corresponding to a gap in one block were retained. The parameters related to 1) the number of sequences required to consider a position as being conserved, 2) the number of sequences required to consider a position as being flanking, and 3) the maximum number of contiguous nonconserved positions that were optimized to define each block (Opisthokonta: 102, 102, 100; Archaeplastida and sister clades: 116, 116, 100; Excavata: 16, 26, 30; Amoebozoa: 64, 64, 175; SAR: 74, 79, 115; Apusozoa: 6, 6, 50; respectively). A phylogeny was constructed using the curated alignments with the package &#x0201c;Phangorn&#x0201d; (<xref rid="evy213-B131" ref-type="bibr">Schliep 2011</xref>) in R (<xref rid="evy213-B122" ref-type="bibr">R Development Core Team, 2013</xref>). A Neighbor-Joining tree was used as a primer tree, and distances between sequences were fitted using the maximum likelihood approach and the <xref rid="evy213-B89" ref-type="bibr">Le and Gascuel (2008)</xref> substitution matrix after several substitution models had been tested using the &#x0201c;Modeltest&#x0201d; function with both invariant sites and the gamma distribution. We retained the LG model (the model of <xref rid="evy213-B89" ref-type="bibr">Le and Gascuel 2008</xref>). which was always the most appropriate as determined by its Bayesian information criterion. Branch position was optimized with a nearest neighbor interchange algorithm. Branch robustness was evaluated using parametric resampling (bootstrap of 100) carried out in multicore computing machines of the CCSC (CNRS, Orl&#x000e9;ans, France).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Exploring the Structure and Distribution of HKs in Eukaryota</title><p>In order to acquire a representative sampling to study the structure and distribution of HKs in the Eukaryota, we browsed the genomes of 67 species (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref>) spread throughout the eukaryotic tree of life (<xref rid="evy213-B53" ref-type="bibr">Grant and Katz 2014</xref>). Most eukaryotic HKs are hybrid, containing a C-terminal REC domain downstream of HisKA and HATPase_c domains, but there are some examples of eukaryotic HKs that lack the REC domain. This is the case, for example, of some diverged groups of HKs, such as plant phytochromes, ERS2-type ethylene receptors, and chloroplast TCS sensors. These proteins progressively acquired serine threonine kinase activity and non-RR functional partners during evolution (<xref rid="evy213-B22" ref-type="bibr">Cashmore 1998</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B117" ref-type="bibr">Puthiyaveetil and Allen 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B130" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B45" ref-type="bibr">Gallie 2015</xref>). We therefore searched all 67 genomes with the Pfam domains HisKA (PFAM00512) and HATPase_c (PFAM02518) and only retained putative HK sequences that had at least two out of the three following domains: HisKA (PFAM00512), HATPase_c (PFAM02518), and REC (PFAM00072). This strategy not only helped to remove a number of non-HK sequences that contain just a single HATPase_c domain, such as, for instance, pyruvate dehydrogenases, heat shock proteins 90, and DNA mismatch repair proteins MutL, but also provided the opportunity to capture divergent proteins related to the HK family. This allowed the compilation of 748 predicted proteins (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The HK family is known to be highly divergent, even within a single kingdom (<xref rid="evy213-B99" ref-type="bibr">Mascher et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B60" ref-type="bibr">He et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B63" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). Thus, independent phylogenetic analyses of HK predicted proteins were carried out for each of the six major eukaryotic supergroups: Archaeplastida, Opisthokonta, Amoebozoa, Apusozoa, Excavata, and SAR (<xref rid="evy213-B53" ref-type="bibr">Grant and Katz 2014</xref>).
<table-wrap id="evy213-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>List of Eukaryotic Species in Which the Presence of Predicted HK Sequences Was Investigated for This Study </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clades</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Simplified Classification</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species Name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain Name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of HKs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Archaeplastida</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glaucocystophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cyanophora paradoxa</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCMP329</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhodophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cyanidioschizon merolae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viridiplantae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prasinophytes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Micromonas pusilla</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCMP1545</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorophyceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Volvox carteri</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Streptophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charophytes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Klebsormidium nitens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NIES-2285</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>67</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bryophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>54</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marchantiophytes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Marchantia polymorpha</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lycopodiopsida</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Selaginella moellendorffii</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acrogymnospermae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pinus taeda</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnoliophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Amborella trichopoda</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>9</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnoliophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnoliophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Oryza sativa</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P0709F06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cryptophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Guillardia theta</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCMP2712</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haptophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Emiliana huxleyi</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCMP1516</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opisthokonta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metazoa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eumetazoa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cnidaria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nematostella vectensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CH2xCH6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arthropoda</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platyhelminthes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puerto Rico</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chordata</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Homo sapiens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choanoflagellates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Monosiga brevicollis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MX1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesomycetozoa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Capsaspora owczarzaki</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC30864</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dikarya</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basidiomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pucciniomycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Puccinia graminis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDL75&#x02013;36-700&#x02013;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ustilaginomycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ustilago maydis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">521</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agaricomycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JC21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pezizomycetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tuber melanosporum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mel28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orbiliomycetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arthrobotrys oligospora</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC24927</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>17</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurotiomycetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Af293</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lecanoromycetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Usnea florida</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC18376</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leotiomycetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sordariomycetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fusarium verticillioides</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC38932</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xylonomycetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Xylona heveae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saccharomycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Candida albicans</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC5314</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taphrinomycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Taphrina deformans</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PYCC5710</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucoromycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glomeromycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhizophagus irregularis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAOM181602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortierellomycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mortierella elongata</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AG-77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucoromycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Umbelopsis ramanniana</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zoopagomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zoopagomycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Syncephalis plumigaleata</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NRRL S24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entomophthoromycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conidiobolus coronatus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NRRL28638</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kickxellomycotina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ramicandelaber brevisporus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBS 109374</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blastocladiomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Catenaria anguillulae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PL171</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chytridiomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gonapodya prolifera</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JEL478</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neocallimastigomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Piromyces finnis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microsporidia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Enterocytozoon bieneusi</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">H348</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cryptomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rozella allomyces</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSF55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amoebozoa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discosea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longamoebia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Centramoebida</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acanthamoeba castellani</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neff</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>48</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mycetozoa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myxogastria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myxogastromycetidae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physarum polycephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LU352</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>51</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dictyostelids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dictyosteliales</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AX4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>14</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acytosteliales</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Polysphondylium pallidum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PN500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Archamoebae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HM-1: IMSS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apusozoa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Thecamonas trahens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC50062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excavata</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterolobosea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Naegleria gruberi</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEG-M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>24</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Euglenozoa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Leishmania infantum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JPCM5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAL972</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fornicata</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diplomonadida</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Spironucleus salmonicida</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC 50377</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Giardia intestinalis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC 50803</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parabasalia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stramenopiles</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelagophyceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelagomonadales</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aureococcus anophagefferens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCMP1984</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacillariophyta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacillariophyceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fistulifera solaris</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DA0580</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>34</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PX clade</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phaeophyceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ectocarpus siliculosus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ec32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oomycetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albuginaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Albugo laibachii</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nc14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alveolata</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apicomplexa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haemosporida</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3D7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piroplasmida</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Babesia bovis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2Bo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coccidia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coccidia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cryptosporidium hominis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TU502</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dinophyceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Symbiodinium microadriaticum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCMP2467</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromerida</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vitrella brassicaformis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCMP3155</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perkinsea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Perkinsus marinus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CB5D4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciliophora</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SB210</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>70</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhizaria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cercozoa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Plasmodiophora brassicae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">e3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foraminifera</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Reticulomyxa filosa</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p><sc>Note</sc>.&#x02014;EDF, early diverging fungi.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Improving the Categorization of HK Proteins in Archaeplastida, Opisthokonta, and Amoebozoa</title><sec><title>Archaeplastida and Sister Clades (Cryptophyta and Haptophyta)</title><p>Several recent studies have provided important advances in our understanding of the structure and distribution of land plant HKs (<xref rid="evy213-B129" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B161" ref-type="bibr">Yasumura et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B56" ref-type="bibr">Gruhn et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B91" ref-type="bibr">Liu et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). However, there is a need to extend this analysis to the whole green lineage (Archaeplastida), which encompasses glaucophytes (Glaucocystophyta), red algae (Rhodophyta), green algae (Chlorophyta), and land plants (Streptophyta), together with the sister clades Cryptophyta and Haptophyta in some phylogenies (<xref rid="evy213-B53" ref-type="bibr">Grant and Katz 2014</xref>). Genome searches revealed that HKs are broadly represented throughout all these clades since we identified sequences in the Glaucocystophyta (<italic>Cyanophora paradoxa</italic>, one HK) (<xref rid="evy213-B115" ref-type="bibr">Price et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>) and the Rhodophyta (<italic>Cyanidioschyzon merolae</italic>, one HK) (<xref rid="evy213-B100" ref-type="bibr">Matsuzaki et&#x000a0;al. 2004</xref>). We also identified three and seven HK sequences from the genomes of the aquatic green algae <italic>Micromonas pusilla</italic> (Prasinophytes) (<xref rid="evy213-B157" ref-type="bibr">Worden et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>) and <italic>Volvox carteri</italic> (Chlorophyceae) (<xref rid="evy213-B116" ref-type="bibr">Prochnik et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>), respectively, 67 HKs in the genome of <italic>K</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>nitens</italic> (Charophyta, terrestrial green alga) (<xref rid="evy213-B65" ref-type="bibr">Hori et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>), 54 HKs in the genome of <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> (Bryophytes) (<xref rid="evy213-B124" ref-type="bibr">Rensing et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>), 20 HKs in the genome of <italic>Marchantia polymorpha</italic> (Liverworts) (<xref rid="evy213-B18" ref-type="bibr">Bowman et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>), and 16 HKs in the genome of <italic>Selaginella moellendorffii</italic> (Lycophytes) (<xref rid="evy213-B12" ref-type="bibr">Banks et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>). The Acrogymnospermae clade was represented by the loblolly pine genome (<italic>Pinus taeda</italic>) (<xref rid="evy213-B106" ref-type="bibr">Neale et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>) in which we annotated ten HKs. Concerning Magnoliophyta (flowering plants), we identified nine HKs in <italic>Amborella trichopoda</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B3" ref-type="bibr">Amborella Genome Project 2013</xref>), a model early-diverging species from the Magnoliophyta, to which we added the 16 previously described HKs from <italic>A</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>thaliana</italic> (a Eudicot model species) (<xref rid="evy213-B67" ref-type="bibr">Hwang et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>) and the 13 HKs from <italic>O</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>sativa</italic> (a Monocot model species) (<xref rid="evy213-B111" ref-type="bibr">Pareek et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). Finally, we identified ten and three HKs in the genomes of representative species from the sister clades Cryptophyta (<italic>Guillardia theta</italic>) (<xref rid="evy213-B35" ref-type="bibr">Curtis et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>) and Haptophyta (<italic>Emiliania huxleyi</italic>) (<xref rid="evy213-B123" ref-type="bibr">Read et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>), respectively (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref>).</p><p>To gain insight into the phylogenetic relationships between HKs from glaucophytes (Glaucocystophyta), red algae (Rhodophyta), green algae (Chlorophyta), land plants (Streptophyta), and the sister clades Cryptophyta and Haptophyta, we generated a robust phylogenetic tree after multiple alignment of 230 predicted sequences (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). This analysis revealed that most of the deduced HK sequences tended to cluster in the previously described major plant HK groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>) (<xref rid="evy213-B129" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B68" ref-type="bibr">Ishida et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). These included the AHK1 group, known to act as osmosensors in Eudicots (<xref rid="evy213-B151" ref-type="bibr">Urao 1999</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B26" ref-type="bibr">Chefdor et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>), the CKI1 group (<xref rid="evy213-B76" ref-type="bibr">Kakimoto 1996</xref>), which constitutes key regulators of central cell specification in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> female gametophyte (<xref rid="evy213-B114" ref-type="bibr">Pischke et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>), the CKI2 group (<xref rid="evy213-B76" ref-type="bibr">Kakimoto 1996</xref>), which was reported to be involved in stress-induced stomatal closure (<xref rid="evy213-B101" ref-type="bibr">Mira-Rodado et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>), the phytochrome group (<xref rid="evy213-B129" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>), which consists in photoswitchable red/far-red photoreceptors regulating competition with neighboring plants for photosynthetically active red light (<xref rid="evy213-B126" ref-type="bibr">Rockwell and Lagarias 2017</xref>), the ethylene receptor group (ETR), which has been divided into two subfamilies (<xref rid="evy213-B45" ref-type="bibr">Gallie 2015</xref>) that display the three predicted transmembrane helices containing the crucial residues involved in ethylene perception (<xref rid="evy213-B155" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>), the cytokinin receptor group (CKR), which consists of proteins displaying a cyclases/histidine kinase-associated sensing extracellular (CHASE) domain in their N-terminal region (<xref rid="evy213-B4" ref-type="bibr">Anantharaman and Aravind 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B105" ref-type="bibr">Mougel and Zhulin 2001</xref>) known to be essential for the binding of the hormones (<xref rid="evy213-B56" ref-type="bibr">Gruhn et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>), and the more recently described membrane-associated sensor 1 (MASE1) domain-containing HKs of unknown function (<xref rid="evy213-B68" ref-type="bibr">Ishida et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). Most of these HK groups, including AHK1, CKR, and ETR, were found exclusively in the Streptophyta (<italic>K. nitens</italic>, <italic>P. patens</italic>, <italic>M</italic><italic>ar</italic><italic>. polymorpha</italic>, <italic>S. moellendorffii</italic>, <italic>P</italic><italic>i</italic><italic>. taeda</italic>, <italic>A</italic><italic>m</italic><italic>. trichopoda</italic>, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, and <italic>O. sativa</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). It is noteworthy that most of the CHASE domain-containing HKs predicted from the <italic>K. nitens</italic> and <italic>P. patens</italic> genomes tended to cluster in the subfamily 2 of plant CKRs (<xref rid="evy213-B56" ref-type="bibr">Gruhn et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>) whereas <italic>K. nitens</italic> KniteHK9 and KniteHK48 did not appear to cluster with the two previously described subfamilies, thus defining a new subfamily of putative CKRs in Archaeplastida (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The MASE1 domain-containing HK group appeared to be restricted to early diverging land plants (<italic>P. patens</italic>, <italic>M</italic><italic>ar</italic><italic>. polymorpha</italic>, and <italic>S. moellendorffii</italic>). Finally, this phylogenetic analysis reveals that the CKI1 and CKI2 groups are restricted to land plants and that, interestingly, the CKI1 group has likely emerged from a structural specialization of AHK1-like ancestors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>).
</p><fig id="evy213-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 2.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Phylogeny estimation of HK predicted protein sequences in Archaeplastida. A representative structure is provided for each defined HK group. Athal, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana;</italic> Atric, <italic>Amborella trichopoda;</italic> Cmero, <italic>Cyanidioschyzon merolae;</italic> Cpara<italic>, Cyanophora paradoxa;</italic> Ehuxl, <italic>Emiliania huxleyi;</italic> Gthet, <italic>Guillardia theta;</italic> Knite, <italic>Klebsormidium nitens;</italic> Mpusi, <italic>Micromonas pusilla;</italic> Osati, <italic>Oryza sativa;</italic> Ppate, <italic>Physcomitrella patens;</italic> Ptaed, <italic>Pinus taeda;</italic> Smoel, <italic>Selaginella moellendorffii;</italic> Vcart, <italic>Volvox carteri.</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evy213f2"/></fig><p>In addition to these observations, several interesting advances were provided by the phylogenetic analysis. First, the genome of the red alga <italic>C</italic><italic>y</italic><italic>. merolae</italic> encodes a unique HK (CmeroHK1) that belongs to the chloroplast sensor kinase (CSK) group (<xref rid="evy213-B118" ref-type="bibr">Puthiyaveetil et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The first nuclear-encoded CSK was described in <italic>A. thaliana</italic>. CSK genes are believed to have originated from cyanobacterial histidine kinase 2 (Hik2). CSK homologs are present in all major lineages of photosynthetic eukaryotes, but they were not included in the present study because they lack a typical HisKA Pfam domain. A unique aspect of CSK evolution is that these proteins occur as a canonical HKs along with an RR partner in nongreen algae but in green algae and plants they are modified HKs that have lost the conserved histidine residue and its cognate RR partner. As is also the case for land plant ethylene receptors, plant CSK has been rewired during evolution to work with a non-RR functional partner, in the case of CSKs to link chloroplast gene expression with photosynthetic electron transport (<xref rid="evy213-B117" ref-type="bibr">Puthiyaveetil and Allen 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B119" ref-type="bibr">Puthiyaveetil et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref><xref rid="evy213-B120" ref-type="bibr">, 2013</xref>). Glaucocystophyta CparaHK1 shares high similarity with several cyanophytochromes (not shown) and tended to cluster in the tree with Streptophyta phytochromes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). This is in accordance with previous analyses demonstrating that despite the lack of detectable sequence similarity, Archaeplastida phytochromes originated from cyanophytochromes (<xref rid="evy213-B83" ref-type="bibr">Koo&#x000df; and Lamparter 2017</xref>). CparaHK1 was previously shown to act as a phytochrome, detecting light broadly throughout the visible spectrum (blue, green, orange, red, and far-red) in contrast to land plant phytochromes that only use the ratio of red to far-red light to detect shading by neighboring plants and to control photomorphogenesis (<xref rid="evy213-B125" ref-type="bibr">Rockwell et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). Few HKs were found in green algae (e.g., <italic>M. pusilla</italic>, three HKs), including notably a single phytochrome (MpusiHK1) (<xref rid="evy213-B40" ref-type="bibr">Duanmu et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>), which appears to be distantly related to land plant phytochromes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The two other <italic>M. pusilla</italic> HKs (MpusiHK2 and MpusiHK3) are predicted to have multiple transmembrane regions within their N-terminus and therefore correspond to a previously undescribed HK group that displays similarity to sequences from the Cryptophyta (<italic>G. theta</italic>, GthetHK3, GthetHK5, GthetHK8, and GthetHK10) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><p>Some HKs from the Archaeplastida sister clades Cryptophyta (<italic>G. theta</italic>) and Haptophyta (<italic>E. huxleyi</italic>) were also of interest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). These included not only <italic>G. theta</italic> GthetHK6, which clustered with the Archaeplastida phytochrome group, and GthetHK2, GthetHK7, and GtethHK9 that harbor a combination of PAS/PAC domains (Per-period circadian protein; Arnt-Ah receptor nuclear translocator protein; Sim-single minded protein) (<xref rid="evy213-B102" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000f6;glich et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>) within their N-termini (referred here as multi-PAS HKs). We also detected GthetHK1 and EhuxlHK3, which are members of the Hik33/ycf26 group of HKs. This class of HKs is known to participate in the chloroplast TCS (<xref rid="evy213-B144" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki et&#x000a0;al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B117" ref-type="bibr">Puthiyaveetil and Allen 2009</xref>).</p><p>One important finding was that both <italic>K</italic>. <italic>nitens</italic>, a model species representing the early transition step from aquatic algae to land plants, and, to a lesser extent, basal Embryophyta species (<italic>P. patens, M</italic><italic>ar</italic><italic>. polymorpha</italic>, and <italic>S. moellendorffii</italic>) possessed a broad range of HKs, some of which had features that have not been described for land plant HKs. For example, KniteHK26 and KniteHK43 share the same domain topology and cluster with the bacteriorhodopsins VcartHK1, VcartHK3, VcartHK4, VcartHK5, and VcartHK6 from the green alga <italic>V. carteri</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B80" ref-type="bibr">Kianianmomeni and Hallmann 2014</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Homologs of these proteins, which are located in the eyespot of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> (another green alga), play a crucial role in the adaptation of behavioral responses in the presence of UV-A light (<xref rid="evy213-B78" ref-type="bibr">Kateriya et&#x000a0;al. 2004</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B148" ref-type="bibr">Troein et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B95" ref-type="bibr">Luck et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>). Five other HKs, KniteHK15, KniteHK19, KniteHK23, KniteHK28, and KniteHK34, possess an N-terminal sensing region that shares domain topology and significant similarity with the light, oxygen, or voltage (LOV) domain found in blue-light photoreceptors from cyanobacteria and chlorophyta (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>) (<xref rid="evy213-B33" ref-type="bibr">Crosson et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B50" ref-type="bibr">Glantz et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). This similarity suggests that green algae retained this type of light-sensing HK protein during the first steps of terrestrialization but that it was later lost in land plants and replaced by cryptochromes and phototropins, allowing them to perceive and to adapt to UV-A and blue light (<xref rid="evy213-B143" ref-type="bibr">Sullivan and Deng 2003</xref>). Another interesting finding was that KniteHK29, KniteHK44, SmoelHK12, SmoelHK15, and PpateHK38 possess an N-terminal sensing region that shares domain topology and significant similarity with bacterial NarX nitrate/nitrite sensors (<xref rid="evy213-B99" ref-type="bibr">Mascher et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). It is thus possible that such transduction systems were acquired via horizontal gene transfer during the evolution of green algae and allowed adaptation to the particular form of nitrogen source offered by soils during the terrestrialization process. It is also interesting to note that KniteHK1 and KniteHK2 correspond to dual HKs, which have hitherto only been reported in fungi and the Amoebozoa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>) (<xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B128" ref-type="bibr">Schaap et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Finally, it was also surprising to observe, for the first time in the green lineage, members belonging to the prominent fungal group X HK (KniteHK20, KniteHK56, and KniteHK59) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). A previous study suggested that these HKs were also acquired by fungi during the land colonization process allowing their adaptation to the particular oxidant conditions imposed by terrestrial habitats (<xref rid="evy213-B63" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Opisthokonta</title><p>Opisthokonta represents a supergroup of morphologically highly diversified species, including animals (Metazoa), choanoflagellates, Mesomycetozoa, and fungi. Although some previous studies have suggested the presence of HKs in some animals (<xref rid="evy213-B121" ref-type="bibr">Putnam et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B66" ref-type="bibr">Hughes and Friedman 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B137" ref-type="bibr">Simakov et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B162" ref-type="bibr">You et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B165" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B166" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B57" ref-type="bibr">Gulia-Nuss et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B107" ref-type="bibr">Neave et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>), our analysis demonstrated that all metazoan HK candidates (about 150 sequences) found in the NCBI database corresponded either to an inappropriate annotation or to contamination by bacterial sequences (not shown). Thus, our analysis confirms that animals do not possess any typical eukaryotic HKs.</p><p>However, HKs appear to occur broadly in the remaining Opisthokonta clades because one predicted protein was identified in a representative species of choanoflagellate (<italic>Monosiga brevicollis</italic>) (<xref rid="evy213-B82" ref-type="bibr">King et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>) and 11 HKs were found in the mesomycetozoan model species <italic>Capsaspora owczarzaki</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B142" ref-type="bibr">Suga et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). We also included HK sequences from 23 broadly distributed species from the kingdom Fungi in this phylogenetic analysis (<xref rid="evy213-B55" ref-type="bibr">Grigoriev et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). These included the Basidiomycota species <italic>Puccinia graminis</italic> (Pucciniomycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B41" ref-type="bibr">Duplessis et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>), <italic>Ustilago maydis</italic> (Ustilaginomycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B77" ref-type="bibr">Kamper et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>), and <italic>Cr</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>neoformans</italic> (Agaricomycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B92" ref-type="bibr">Loftus et&#x000a0;al. 2005</xref>); the Ascomycota species <italic>Tuber melanosporum</italic> (Pezizomycetes) (<xref rid="evy213-B98" ref-type="bibr">Martin et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>), <italic>Arthrobotrys oligospora</italic> (Orbiliomycetes) (<xref rid="evy213-B160" ref-type="bibr">Yang et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>), <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> (Eurotiomycetes) (<xref rid="evy213-B108" ref-type="bibr">Nierman et&#x000a0;al. 2005</xref>), <italic>Usnea florida</italic> (Lecanoromycetes), <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> (Leotiomycetes) (<xref rid="evy213-B140" ref-type="bibr">Staats and van Kan 2012</xref>), <italic>Fusarium verticillioides</italic> (Sordariomycetes) (<xref rid="evy213-B34" ref-type="bibr">Cuomo et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>), <italic>Xylona heveae</italic> (Xylonomycetes) (<xref rid="evy213-B49" ref-type="bibr">Gazis et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>), <italic>C</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>albicans</italic> (Saccharomycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B72" ref-type="bibr">Jones et&#x000a0;al. 2004</xref>), and <italic>Taphrina deformans</italic> (Taphrinomycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B27" ref-type="bibr">Cisse et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>); and the early diverging fungi <italic>Rhizophagus irregularis</italic> Glomeromycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B147" ref-type="bibr">Tisserant et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>), <italic>Mortierella elongata</italic> (Mortierellomycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B150" ref-type="bibr">Uehling et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>), <italic>Umbelopsis ramanniana</italic> (Mucoromycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B63" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>), <italic>Syncephalis plumigaleata</italic> (Zoopagomycotina), <italic>Conidiobolus coronatus</italic> (Entomophthoromycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B25" ref-type="bibr">Chang et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>), <italic>Ramicandelaber brevisporus</italic> (Kickxellomycotina) (<xref rid="evy213-B63" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>), <italic>Catenaria anguillulae</italic> (Blastocladiomycota) (<xref rid="evy213-B103" ref-type="bibr">Mondo et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>), <italic>Gonapodya prolifera</italic> (Chytridiomycota) (<xref rid="evy213-B25" ref-type="bibr">Chang et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>), <italic>Piromyces finnis</italic> (Neocallimastigomycota) (<xref rid="evy213-B58" ref-type="bibr">Haitjema et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>), <italic>Enterocytozoon bieneusi</italic> (Microsporidia) (<xref rid="evy213-B1" ref-type="bibr">Akiyoshi et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>), <italic>Rozella allomyces</italic> (Cryptomycota) (<xref rid="evy213-B71" ref-type="bibr">James et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). A total of 203 predicted fungal HK proteins was thus included in our analysis (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online).</p><p>The opisthokont phylogenetic analysis allowed the 11 prominent fungal HK groups (I&#x02015;XI) originally categorized by <xref rid="evy213-B23" ref-type="bibr">Catlett et&#x000a0;al. (2003)</xref> to be recovered from the Ascomycota along with the five additional groups described by <xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). Although the function of most of these latter groups remains unknown, some fungal HK groups have been shown to be involved in the regulation of various physiological processes (<xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B62" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>).
</p><fig id="evy213-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 3.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Phylogeny estimation of HK predicted protein sequences in Opisthokonta. A representative structure is provided for each defined HK group. Afumi, <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus;</italic> Aolig, <italic>Arthrobotrys oligospora;</italic> Bcine, <italic>Botrytis cinerea;</italic> Calbi, <italic>Candida albicans;</italic> Cangu, <italic>Catenaria anguillulae;</italic> Ccoro, <italic>Conidiobolus coronatus;</italic> Cneof, <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans;</italic> Cowcz, <italic>Capsaspora owczarzaki;</italic> Fvert, <italic>Fusarium verticillioides;</italic> Gprol, <italic>Gonapodya prolifera;</italic> Mbrev, <italic>Monosiga brevicollis;</italic> Melon, <italic>Mortierella elongata;</italic> Pgram, <italic>Puccinia graminis;</italic> Rallo, <italic>Rozella allomycis;</italic> Rbrev, <italic>Ramicandelaber brevisporus;</italic> Rirre, <italic>Rhizophagus irregularis;</italic> Splum, <italic>Syncephalis plumigaleata;</italic> Tdefo, <italic>Taphrina deformans;</italic> Tmela, <italic>Tuber melanosporum;</italic> Uflor, <italic>Usnea florida;</italic> Umayd, <italic>Ustilago maydis;</italic> Urama, <italic>Umbelopsis ramanniana;</italic> Xheve, <italic>Xylona heveae</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evy213f3"/></fig><p>Group I HKs are known to be highly divergent within the group (<xref rid="evy213-B23" ref-type="bibr">Catlett et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>). These proteins are present not only in various fungal clades including the Ascomycota and Basidiomycota but also in early diverging fungi and appear to have been expanded in the phytopathogenic Ascomycota. A group I HK mutant in the rice blast fungus <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> (Ascomycota) displayed a slight decline in conidiation and an attenuated virulence (<xref rid="evy213-B70" ref-type="bibr">Jacob et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>), but there was no apparent altered phenotype for an equivalent mutant in <italic>C</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. neoformans</italic> (Basidiomycota) (<xref rid="evy213-B11" ref-type="bibr">Bahn et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). Group II fungal HKs are present in the Sordariomycetes, the Orbiliomycetes, and the Leotiomycetes (<xref rid="evy213-B23" ref-type="bibr">Catlett et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>). The function of these proteins is unknown. Most available data concerning the roles of fungal HKs were gained from functional characterization of proteins belonging to group III. Fungal group III HKs proteins contain a variable number of HAMP (histidine kinases&#x02013;adenylate cyclases&#x02013;methyl accepting proteins and phosphatases) domain repeats (<xref rid="evy213-B8" ref-type="bibr">Aravind and Ponting 1999</xref>) within the sensing domain and have been primarily reported to be implicated in virulence in human, plant, and insect pathogenic fungi but also in osmosensing, morphogenesis, conidiation, and cell wall integrity (<xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B62" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Fungal group III HKs were only found in terrestrial species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>) suggesting that these sensing proteins were acquired for/during the land colonization process. Group IV fungal HKs were exclusively present in the Eurotiomycetes and the Sordariomycetes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>), where they have been shown to be involved in the virulence of <italic>As</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>fumigatus</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B30" ref-type="bibr">Clemons et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>). Group V fungal HKs are large proteins with PAS/PAC repeats within the sensing domain. Group V fungal HKs were found not only in several clades of the Ascomycota and Basidiomycota but also in early diverging fungi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>) and have been shown to be implicated in vegetative growth, conidiation, stress adaptation, and virulence in <italic>M</italic><italic>ag</italic><italic>. oryzae</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B70" ref-type="bibr">Jacob et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). Group VI HKs appeared to be restricted to the Ascomycota (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>) and are known to mainly act as transmembrane osmosensors by governing the high-osmolarity glycerol MAPK pathway (<xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B62" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). The canonical N-terminus of these transmembrane proteins includes two hydrophobic helices flanking an osmosensing extracellular loop, as found in Archaeplastida AHK1-related HKs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). Group VII fungal HKs were present in the Ascomycota and Basidimycota clades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>), but the function of these proteins is unknown. Phytochromes (group VIII or Fph) are light-perceiving receptors, broadly represented in nearly all fungal clades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). These proteins mediate red light sensing in fungi, while other types of photoreceptors are involved in sensing light of shorter wavelengths (<xref rid="evy213-B13" ref-type="bibr">Bayram et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). Group IX fungal HKs were found in several clades of the Ascomycota and Basidiomycota but not in early diverging fungi. Their function is unknown. Group X fungal HKs are large proteins with a canonical N-terminus that includes a serine/threonine kinase-related (S/TKr) domain and a GAF domain (<xref rid="evy213-B8" ref-type="bibr">Aravind and Ponting 1997</xref>). Like fungal group III HKs, group X HKs have been extensively studied and have been shown to govern virulence, morphogenesis, and peroxide adaptation (<xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B62" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Group X HKs are broadly represented across the fungi. The phylogenetic tree indicates that this group is polyphyletic, defining fungal groups X-A, X-B, and X-C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). Finally, group XI fungal HKs are known to be highly divergent within the group (<xref rid="evy213-B23" ref-type="bibr">Catlett et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>) and appeared to be broadly spread in the Ascomycota and Basidiomycota but not in early diverging fungi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). <italic>Magnaporthe</italic><italic>oryzae</italic> group XI fungal HKs have been shown to be implicated in vegetative growth, conidiation, stress adaptation, and virulence (<xref rid="evy213-B70" ref-type="bibr">Jacob et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>).</p><p>Importantly, the phylogenetic tree shed light on additional clusters that allowed us to refine the categorization of fungal HKs by defining new fungal HK groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>), a process that was recently initiated in <xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</xref> and <xref rid="evy213-B62" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</xref>. These new groups include XII-A in Basidiomycota (PgramHK1, CneoTCO2, and CneoTCO4) and XII-B in early diverging fungi (RirreHK2, RirreHK3, MelonHK3, and UramaHK3), which correspond to the polyphyletic groups of dual-HKs (<xref rid="evy213-B88" ref-type="bibr">Lav&#x000ed;n et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). The dual-HK CneoTCO2 in <italic>C</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. neoformans</italic> has been shown to be involved in heavy metal and antifungal susceptibility as well as in oxidant condition adaptation (<xref rid="evy213-B11" ref-type="bibr">Bahn et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). Group XIII (formerly known as IB or CneoTCO5) HKs were found in <italic>C</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. neoformans</italic>, <italic>T. deformans</italic> and <italic>R. irregularis</italic> whereas group XIV, which appeared to be restricted to the Basidiomycota, includes predicted proteins in <italic>U. maydis</italic> and <italic>C</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. neoformans</italic> (UmaydHK4, UmaydHK5, and CneoTCO7) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). Group XV HKs (MelonHK10 and UramaHK9), also referred to as MS-HKI, as well as group XVI HKs (MelonHK11 and MelonHK12), formerly called MS-HKII, were exclusively found in the Mucoromycotina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>) according to previous studies (<xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B62" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Predicted HK proteins from the Lecanoromycetes (UflorHK3), the Orbiliomycetes (AoligHK11), and the Pucciniomycotina (PgramHK4) now define the new group XVII of fungal HKs. It is noteworthy that the recently described ethylene receptor homologs in early diverging fungi (<xref rid="evy213-B63" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>) tended to cluster into two different groups (groups XVIII-A and XVIII-B) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>) suggesting a polyphyletic origin for these fungal phytohormone-sensing proteins. CHASE domain-containing HKs (here categorized as group XIX) appeared particularly abundant in early diverging fungi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>) and tended to cluster together suggesting a monophyletic origin for these cytokinin receptor homologs. The remaining predicted sequences that do not cluster with the above mentioned HK groups, and which were either found in a single species, were positioned in branches supported by low bootstrap values or did not have a common N-terminal domain arrangement, have not been incorporated into this refined classification of fungal HKs.</p><p>Most of the <italic>C</italic><italic>ap</italic><italic>. owczarzaki</italic> (Mesomycetozoa) HKs possessed a sensing region with multiple predicted transmembrane helices that could indicate that <italic>C</italic><italic>ap</italic><italic>. owczarzaki</italic> contains few intracellular HKs and mostly membrane bound HKs. One of these HKs, CowczHK2, clustered with ethylene receptors (group XVIII-A) from early diverging fungi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>) (<xref rid="evy213-B63" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). As revealed by an alignment with ethylene receptors from plants, green algae, and cyanobacteria, CowczHK2 displays the three predicted transmembrane helices and contained all of the conserved, essential residues involved in ethylene perception (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) (<xref rid="evy213-B155" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). Another remarkable finding was the occurrence of a dual-HK in <italic>C</italic><italic>ap</italic><italic>. owczarzaki</italic> (CowcHK5) because this group of HKs was long believed to be restricted to the Basidiomycota within the opisthokonts (<xref rid="evy213-B88" ref-type="bibr">Lav&#x000ed;n et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). None of the remaining <italic>C</italic><italic>ap</italic><italic>. owczarzaki</italic> HKs displayed significant phylogenetic relationships with other fungal HK groups. They thus represent potential founder members of novel Opisthokonta HK groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Amoebozoa</title><p>More than 2,000 species of amoebozoid protists have been described. These unicellular organisms, which often possess pseudopods, are known to behave either as free-living cells in water and soils or as parasites of humans and other organisms. We incorporated the predicted HK sequences from four species broadly distributed across the phylogenetic tree of the Amoebozoa (<xref rid="evy213-B134" ref-type="bibr">Shadwick et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>) into the present phylogenetic analysis. These included the 51 recently described <italic>Physarum polycephalum</italic> HKs (<xref rid="evy213-B128" ref-type="bibr">Schaap et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>) and the 14 HKs of <italic>D</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>discoideum</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B42" ref-type="bibr">Eichinger et&#x000a0;al. 2005</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B141" ref-type="bibr">Sucgang et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>), and we annotated 48 and 13 predicted sequences from <italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B29" ref-type="bibr">Clarke et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>) and <italic>Polysphondylium pallidum</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B61" ref-type="bibr">Heidel et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>), respectively. No HK sequences were found in the genome of the obligate human parasite <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B93" ref-type="bibr">Loftus et&#x000a0;al. 2005</xref>) (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref>).</p><p>Although a recent study reported a phylogeny of HKs for <italic>P</italic><italic>hysa</italic><italic>. polycephalum</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B128" ref-type="bibr">Schaap et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>), little is known about the conservation of these sensing proteins within the various clades of the Amoebozoa. We therefore constructed a phylogenetic tree based on an alignment of the 126 predicted HK sequences from the four above-mentioned species (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). To date, very little data are available about the function of HKs in Amoebozoa, and what exists is derived from studies on <italic>D. discoideum</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B39" ref-type="bibr">Du et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). A homolog of <italic>D. discoideum</italic> DhkA shares a CHASE domain-containing sensing domain with plant cytokinin receptors (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). However, in <italic>D. discoideum</italic> this domain detects a peptide, SDF-2, which functions both in the regulation of prestalk gene expression and in the control of the terminal differentiation of prespore cells (<xref rid="evy213-B153" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 1996</xref><xref rid="evy213-B154" ref-type="bibr">, 1999</xref>). DhkA was also identified in <italic>P. pallidum</italic> (PpallHK9) but was not found in two other taxon-group-representative species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). Homologs of <italic>D. discoideum</italic> DhkB, which regulates spore germination and maintenance of spore dormancy (<xref rid="evy213-B167" ref-type="bibr">Zinda and Singleton 1998</xref>), and DhkC, which is required for the initiation of fruiting body formation (<xref rid="evy213-B139" ref-type="bibr">Singleton et&#x000a0;al. 1998</xref>) and also affects chemotaxis (<xref rid="evy213-B85" ref-type="bibr">Kuwayama and Kubohara 2016</xref>), were also found in <italic>P. pallidum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). Finally, homologs of <italic>D. discoideum</italic> DhkF and DhkG, for which no functions are known, were identified in <italic>P. pallidum</italic> but were absent from the genomes of <italic>P</italic><italic>hysa</italic><italic>. polycephalum</italic> and <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic><italic>. castellanii</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). This indicated that some of the <italic>D. discoideum</italic> HKs are likely restricted to the Dictyostelia, with possible roles in their multicellular development to fruiting bodies, which does not occur in the other Amoebozoa with sequenced genomes (<xref rid="evy213-B127" ref-type="bibr">Schaap 2011</xref>).
</p><fig id="evy213-F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 4.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Phylogeny estimation of HK predicted protein sequences in Amoebozoa. A representative structure is provided for each defined HK group. Acast, <italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii;</italic> Ddisc, <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum;</italic> Ppall, <italic>Polysphondylium pallidum;</italic> Ppoly, <italic>Physarum polycephalum.</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evy213f4"/></fig><p>Compared with the explored supergroups, the domain topology of amoebozoan HKs was highly diversified and many domains found in plant and fungal HKs, such as PAS, GAF, S/TKrd, were also found in the sensing regions of these proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). Some proteins contained domains that have not been described previously in eukaryotic HKs. These included the TyrK (tyrosine kinase) domain found in DhkG and PpallHK13 and the MeTrc (methyltransferase, chemotaxis proteins) domain found in PpolyHK19. PpolyHK19 is homologous to the prokaryotic CheB/CheR HK, which plays a central role in bacterial chemotaxis (<xref rid="evy213-B16" ref-type="bibr">Bischoff and Ordal 1992</xref>). Interestingly, some <italic>P</italic><italic>hysa</italic><italic>. polycephalum</italic> HK proteins contain an Hpt domain fused to the C-terminal REC domain (i.e., PpolyHK5, PpolyHK18). To date, this particular feature has been observed previously only in facultative aerobic bacteria (notably the oxygen-sensing HK ArcB, <xref rid="evy213-B96" ref-type="bibr">Malpica et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>) and to our knowledge, this hybrid HK structure is unique to Amoebozoa within the Eukaryota.</p><p>We also detected the presence of some amoebozoan HK groups displaying topologies found in other eukaryotic supergroups. Two <italic>P</italic><italic>hysa</italic><italic>. polycephalum</italic> HK sequences (PpolyHK37 and PpolyHK38) that contain an N-terminal GAF domain correspond to light-sensing phytochromes (<xref rid="evy213-B128" ref-type="bibr">Schaap et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). Most of the amoebozoan Dual HKs cluster with the DhkD branch. Dual HKs were believed to be restricted to Basidiomycota, where the function of these large HKs remains obscure. In the future, it will be important to understand how these sensing proteins orchestrate their phosphorelay events during signaling and how their particular topologies dovetailed the currently accepted canonical TCS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). The predicted amoebozoan HKs with domain topologies similar to those of fungal group X exhibited marked polyphyly, while the HKs related to fungal group III tended to cluster together in the tree (DhkJ group). We also found that PpolyHK39 displays an N-terminal sensing region that shares domain topology and significant similarity with <italic>K. nitens</italic> (terrestrial green algae) KniteHK29 and KniteHK44, and bacterial NarX nitrate/nitrite sensors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) (<xref rid="evy213-B99" ref-type="bibr">Mascher et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). Finally, as revealed by alignment with ethylene receptors from plants, green algae, cyanobacteria, and early diverging fungi, three <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic><italic>. castellanii</italic> HKs (AcastHK27, AcastHK28, and AcastHK35) contained three predicted transmembrane helices containing all of the conserved residues required for ethylene perception within their N-termini (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) (<xref rid="evy213-B155" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). Thus, this represents the first description of phytohormone receptor homologs in Amoebozoa.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Exploring the Structure and the Phylogeny of HK Proteins in Apusozoa, Excavata, and SAR</title><sec><title>Apusozoa</title><p>Apusozoa are unicellular flagellated organisms occurring in soils and aquatic habitats where they feed essentially on bacteria. To date, the genome of only one species has been sequenced, namely <italic>Thecamonas trahens</italic> (Russ et al. unpublished). We identified 11 predicted proteins that display the canonical HK feature in the <italic>T</italic><italic>h</italic><italic>. trahens</italic> genome (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The structures of <italic>T</italic><italic>h</italic><italic>. trahens</italic> HKs are relatively diverse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F5">fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>). Half of these HKs are likely to be located at the membrane because multiple transmembrane regions were found within their N-termini. Several domains usually associated with HK sensing, such as PAS or GAF, were observed in some <italic>T</italic><italic>h</italic><italic>. trahens</italic> HKs. Two particular structures stood out from the identified series of predicted proteins. These included the topology VSP-CYCc-GAF-HisKA-HATPase_c-RE-REC of TtrahHK8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F5">fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>). Although the CYCc domain (adenylyl/guanylyl cyclase catalytic) has been found in a small number of eukaryotic HKs (from the Archeaplastida and Amoebozoa), VSP (Giardia variant-specific surface protein) domains mediating antigenic variation at the surface of <italic>Giardia</italic><italic>intestinalis</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B48" ref-type="bibr">Gargantini et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>) have not been described previously in HKs. Another interesting finding in <italic>T</italic><italic>h</italic><italic>. trahens</italic> was the occurrence of a bacteriorhodopsin HK, that is, TtrahHK4 (previously observed in the green algae) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F5">fig.&#x000a0;5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Thus, bacteriorhodopsin HKs appear to be used for UVA sensing in several distantly related lineages but sharing similar environments: some halophilic prokaryotes (Haloarchaea, in which bacteriorhodopsins were originally found) and marine unicellular eukaryotes (green algae and <italic>T</italic><italic>h</italic><italic>. trahens</italic>).
</p><fig id="evy213-F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 5.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Phylogeny estimation of HK predicted protein sequences in Apusozoa. The structure of each HK is provided. Ttrah, <italic>Thecamonas trahens.</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evy213f5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Excavata</title><p>Excavata corresponds to unicellular, heterotrophic, and commonly flagellated species. Most are free-living organisms in the environment, whereas others are commensals, symbionts or parasites of animals. Seven and 24 HK sequences were predicted in the genomes of <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> (Metamonada) (<xref rid="evy213-B21" ref-type="bibr">Carlton et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>) and <italic>Naegleria gruberi</italic> (Discoba) (<xref rid="evy213-B44" ref-type="bibr">Fritz-Laylin et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>), respectively, but no HKs were found in the genomes of the other representative Excavata species (<italic>Spironucleus salmonicida, Gi</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>intestinalis, Leishmania infantum</italic>, and <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic>) (<xref rid="evy213-B104" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B112" ref-type="bibr">Peacock et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B69" ref-type="bibr">Jackson et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B158" ref-type="bibr">Xu et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>) (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online).</p><p>To gain insight into the phylogenetic relationships between <italic>T</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. vaginalis</italic> and <italic>N. gruberi</italic> HKs, the domain organization of each protein was investigated and a phylogenetic tree was built using a multiple alignment of all the predicted sequences from both species. Based on this analysis and, in particular, sequence similarities between HisKA domains and N-terminal sensing regions, four groups of Excavata HK are proposed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F6">fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>).
</p><fig id="evy213-F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 6.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Phylogeny estimation of HK predicted protein sequences in Excavata. A representative structure is provided for each defined HK group. Ngrub, <italic>Naegleria gruberi;</italic> Tvagi, <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis.</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evy213f6"/></fig><p>All seven <italic>T</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. vaginalis</italic> HKs are hybrid and tended to cluster together in the phylogenetic tree (Excavata group I, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F6">fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>) independently of the 24 HKs from <italic>N. gruberi</italic>. Most of the <italic>T</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. vaginalis</italic> HKs possessed a sensing region with no similarity to known domains, but the presence of one or two predicted transmembrane helices in some of these proteins could indicate that <italic>T</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. vaginalis</italic> contains both intracellular and membrane-bound HKs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F6">fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>). Although the structure of the predicted <italic>N. gruberi</italic> HK proteins seems relatively well conserved at a first glance, the sequences were distributed into three major clades (Excavata groups II, III, and IV, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F6">fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>). Most of these HKs harbor multiple predicted hydrophobic helices indicating that the majority of <italic>N. gruberi</italic> HKs are transmembrane proteins. Two <italic>N. gruberi</italic> HKs possessed domains that are often associated with the eukaryotic HK sensing region: PAS in NgrubHK23 and GAF in NgrubHK11. In contrast, five of the 24 HKs from <italic>N. gruberi</italic> did not contain any detectable N-terminal sensing region, as previously observed in some fungal HKs (<xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). None of the <italic>N. gruberi</italic> and <italic>T</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. vaginalis</italic> predicted HK sequences were found to share any homology with other previously described prokaryotic or eukaryotic HK groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Stramenopiles, Alveolates, and Rhizaria</title><p>The SAR is a highly diversified supergroup encompassing not only various unicellular and multicellular algal and planktonic species but also ciliates and oomycetes.</p><p>HKs appear to be broadly represented in Stramenopiles because 1&#x02015;34 predicted proteins were identified in pelagophytes (<italic>Aureococcus anophagefferens</italic>, two HKs) (<xref rid="evy213-B52" ref-type="bibr">Gobler et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>), diatoms (<italic>Fistulifera solaris</italic>, 34 HKs) (<xref rid="evy213-B146" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>), brown algae (<italic>Ectocarpus</italic> sp., 13 HKs) (<xref rid="evy213-B31" ref-type="bibr">Cock et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B32" ref-type="bibr">Cormier et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>), and oomycetes (<italic>Albugo laibachii</italic>, two HKs) (<xref rid="evy213-B79" ref-type="bibr">Kemen et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>). However, the distribution of HKs in Alveolata is highly heterogeneous because no HK sequence was detected in the apicomplexan genomes (e.g., <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>, <italic>Babesia bovis, Toxoplasma gondii</italic>, and <italic>Cryptosporidium hominis</italic>) (<xref rid="evy213-B47" ref-type="bibr">Gardner et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B159" ref-type="bibr">Xu et&#x000a0;al. 2004</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B19" ref-type="bibr">Brayton et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B94" ref-type="bibr">Lorenzi et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>) or in the Dinophyceae (<italic>Symbiodinium microadriaticum</italic>) (<xref rid="evy213-B6" ref-type="bibr">Aranda et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>), whereas a few members were identified in the Chromerida (<italic>Vitrella brassicaformis</italic>, seven HKs) (<xref rid="evy213-B156" ref-type="bibr">Woo et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) and the Perkinsae (<italic>Perkinsus marinus</italic>, three HKs) (<xref rid="evy213-B73" ref-type="bibr">Joseph et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). Interestingly, we also observed a marked increase in the number of HK predicted sequences in the Alveolata lineage Ciliophora (70 HKs in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>) (<xref rid="evy213-B43" ref-type="bibr">Eisen et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). For Rhizaria, HKs were found in the Cercozoa (<italic>Plasmodiophora brassicae</italic>, 16 HKs) (<xref rid="evy213-B133" ref-type="bibr">Schwelm et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) but were absent from a Foraminifera genome (<italic>Reticulomyxa filosa</italic>) (<xref rid="evy213-B51" ref-type="bibr">Gl&#x000f6;ckner et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>) (<xref rid="evy213-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Although it is well documented that the SAR includes a large number of genetically distant species with strongly divergent genomes, which could possibly complicate phylogenomic approaches (<xref rid="evy213-B53" ref-type="bibr">Grant and Katz 2014</xref>), we attempted to provide insight into the evolutionary relationship of HKs in this supergroup by carrying out a robust phylogenetic analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>).
</p><fig id="evy213-F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 7.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Phylogeny estimation of HK predicted protein sequences in SAR. A representative structure is provided for each defined HK group. Aanop, <italic>Aureococcus anophagefferens</italic>; Alaib, <italic>Albugo laibachii</italic>; Esili, <italic>Ectocarpus siliculosus</italic>; Fsola, <italic>Fistulifera solaris</italic>; Pbras, <italic>Plasmodiophora brassicae</italic>; Pmar, <italic>Perkinsus marinus</italic>; Tterm, <italic>Tetrahymena termophila</italic>; Vbras, <italic>Vitrella brassicaformis</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evy213f7"/></fig><p>Surprisingly, <italic>T</italic><italic>e</italic><italic>. thermophila</italic> HKs tended to cluster in a single clade, consistent with the current hypothesis that paramecia have evolved rapidly and independently and therefore differ markedly from other Alveolata clades (<xref rid="evy213-B43" ref-type="bibr">Eisen et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B10" ref-type="bibr">Aury et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). All except one of the <italic>T</italic><italic>e</italic><italic>. thermophila</italic> HKs are hybrid HKs and most of these harbor multiple predicted hydrophobic helices within the N-terminal sensing region that presumably allow these proteins to be anchored to the cell membrane. Most of these proteins do not have any known domains in the N-terminal region; exceptions include 12 HKs that have a PAS domain (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>). Despite the large number of <italic>T</italic><italic>e</italic><italic>. thermophila</italic> HKs, there is a limited structural diversity suggesting that <italic>T</italic><italic>e</italic><italic>. thermophila</italic> HK genes, as previously reported for many other kinase families in paramecia, are the result of a rapid gene family expansion process (<xref rid="evy213-B15" ref-type="bibr">Bemm et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>).</p><p>Concerning the phylogeny of HKs from the other selected SAR species, we identified a set of three HKs from the Alveolata group Perkinsae (<italic>P</italic><italic>e</italic><italic>. marinus</italic>) that tend to cluster together (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>). Among these, PmariHK1 has a CYCc domain in its C-terminus. Five out of the seven Chromerida <italic>V</italic><italic>i</italic><italic>. brassicaformis</italic> HKs possess multiple hydrophobic helices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>). The genome of this species encodes another hybrid HK structure, VbrasHK1, with a domain topology (HisKA-HATPase_C-REC-REC-CYCc) that has never been observed previously in the Eukaryota. Thus, as observed in this study for green algae, some Alveolata TCS are coupled with adenylyl/guanylyl cyclase activity.</p><p>In the Rhizaria, most of the HKs found in the representative species <italic>P</italic><italic>l</italic><italic>. brassicae</italic> (Cercozoa) were predicted to be cytoplasmic proteins. Some possess PAS/PAC domains and these tended to cluster within two clades in the tree. Interestingly, two Cercozoa HKs are predicted to be transmembrane proteins with two hydrophobic helices that border an osmosensing extracellular loop, as found in Archaeplastida AHK1-related HKs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">figs.&#x000a0;2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">7</xref>).</p><p>In the stramenopiles, the oomycete <italic>A</italic><italic>l</italic><italic>. laibachii</italic> possesses two HKs that differ drastically from those of other SAR clades because their N-termini contain multiple PAS domain repeats and because they display an Hpt domain fused to a C-terminal REC domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>). We identified similar multi-PAS HKs in the Archaeplastida sister clades Cryptophyta (<italic>G. theta</italic>) and Haptophyta (<italic>E. huxleyi</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F2">figs.&#x000a0;2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">7</xref>). <italic>Aureococcus</italic><italic>anophagefferens</italic> (pelagophyte), <italic>F. solaris</italic> (diatom), and <italic>Ectocarpus</italic> sp. (brown alga) share some common HK structures including proteins with PAS or GAF domains within their N-terminal sensing domains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>). The Ectocarpus predicted proteins EsiliHK3, EsiliHK7, EsiliHK8, and EsiliHK9 correspond to previously described light-sensing phytochromes (<xref rid="evy213-B126" ref-type="bibr">Rockwell and Lagarias 2017</xref>). Further analyses revealed some interesting findings concerning the HK genes detected in the genome of the brown alga <italic>Ectocarpus</italic> sp.: 1) Six of these genes (EsiliHK3, EsiliHK4, EsiliHK5, EsiliHK10, EsiliHK11, and EsiliHK13, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>) are located either within a large, integrated, transcriptionally silent viral genome (<xref rid="evy213-B37" ref-type="bibr">Delaroque and Boland 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B31" ref-type="bibr">Cock et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>) similar to <italic>Ectocarpus siliculosus virus 1</italic> (<xref rid="evy213-B38" ref-type="bibr">Delaroque et&#x000a0;al. 2001</xref>) located on chromosome 6 or within another inserted viral fragment on scaffold 490, and should therefore be considered as viral rather than algal genes; 2) of the remaining genes, all except EsiliHK6 share one or more features with viral HK genes including high sequence similarity (EsiliHK1, EsiliHK6, EsiliHK7, EsiliHK8, and EsiliHK12; 25&#x02015;86% identity), phylogenetic proximity (EsiliHK12 clusters with EsiliHK10 and EsiliHK13, and EsiliHK7, EsiliHK8 and EsiliHK9 cluster with EsiliHK3 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>), and/or only a small number (zero or one) of introns (EsiliHK2, EsiliHK7, EsiliHK8, EsiliHK9, and EsiliHK12), suggesting possible evolutionary relationships between the viral and algal genes; 3) the N-terminal sensing regions of two of the inserted viral genes, EsiliHK10 and EsiliHK12, encode proteins with typical MASE1 domains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>) that were herein described in early diverging Archaeplastida; and 4) the <italic>Ectocarpus</italic> sp. genome possesses non-hybrid HK genes (e.g., EsiliHK6) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>) that appear to have a cyanobacterial origin. The most interesting finding of the SAR analysis was the identification of HKs displaying a CHASE domain within their N-terminus in the brown alga <italic>Ectocarpus</italic> sp. (EsiliHK2) and the diatom <italic>F. solaris</italic> (FsolaHK22 to FsolaHK26) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The CHASE domain is a characteristic feature of plant cytokinin receptors. Surprisingly, alignment of four <italic>F. solaris</italic> HKs (FsolaHK12&#x02015;FsolaHK15) with ethylene receptors from plants, green algae, cyanobacteria, Amoebozoa, and early diverging fungi allowed the identification, within their N-termini, of three predicted transmembrane helices with all of the conserved residues necessary for ethylene perception (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F7">fig.&#x000a0;7</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) (<xref rid="evy213-B155" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). Thus, this represents the first description of cytokinin and ethylene receptor homologs in SAR.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Significant advances in knowledge concerning the structure, classification, and distribution of HKs have been made within the past decade in plants, fungi, and to a lesser extent in amoebae, but these analyses have not been more broadly addressed in Eukaryota. The present study reports for the first time a preliminary but global phylogenetic analysis of this prominent family of sensing proteins in all the eukaryotic supergroups including Archaeplastida, Opisthokonta, Amoebozoa, Apusozoa, Excavata, and SAR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). This analysis allowed most of the compiled sequences to be categorized into a previously described HK group, but we also propose to refine the HK classification for some supergroups, notably the Archaeplastida and Opisthokonta. Unfortunately, the large genetic distances between the representative species in each supergroup and the limited quantity of genomic resources for some clades have precluded the categorization of some highly divergent HKs (notably from the Amoebozoa). Beyond this phylogenetic analysis and classification of eukaryotic HKs, our study has revealed several interesting findings: 1) a description of some previously overlooked eukaryotic HK groups with predicted putative physiological functions; 2) the observation that some HK groups, previously believed to be restricted to one kingdom (plants or fungi), occur in additional supergroups; and 3) the suggestion of evolutionary paths that have led to the appearance, transfer, duplication, and loss of HK genes in some phylogenetic lineages.
</p><fig id="evy213-F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 8.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Occurrence of prominent HK groups in eukaryotic clades. For each eukaryotic clade, the presence of main HK groups is indicated with a pink box. The total number of predicted HK sequences is indicated in the right column.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evy213f8"/></fig><sec><title>HKs in Archaeplastida: Unprecedented Structures and Evolution</title><p>It is now generally admitted that a common ancestor of the Archaeplastida acquired many genes from cyanobacteria through the primary endosymbiotic event that produced their plastids approximately 1.5 Ga (<xref rid="evy213-B20" ref-type="bibr">Brodie et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). Therefore, it has been suggested that the initial pool of HK genes were acquired from cyanobacteria (<xref rid="evy213-B86" ref-type="bibr">Lacey and Binder 2016</xref>). In Archaeplastida, we observed first that unicellular aquatic species possess few HK genes (1&#x02015;7 HKs in Glaucocystophyta, Rhodophyta, and Chlorophyta). The number of HKs is significantly greater in the Charophyta lineage (67 HKs in the model terrestrial algae), but these genes are less abundant in land plants (54 HKs in the model moss, and 9&#x02015;16 in the remaining studied species) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). Thus, it could be hypothesized that Archaeplastida algae progressively extended and diversified their HK battery prior to the conquest of terrestrial habitats, notably acquiring the ability to sense new nutrient sources offered by terrestrial niches (nitrate/nitrite sensor homologs in <italic>K. nitens, P. patens</italic>, and <italic>S. moellendorffii</italic>) and by developing capacity to respond to various constraints related to terrestrial habitats such as oxidant stresses (homologues of fungal group X oxidant sensors in <italic>K. nitens</italic>), osmotic stresses (proteins related to the osmosensor AthalHK1 in <italic>K. nitens</italic>) or direct sunlight exposure (homologues of bacteriorodopsins and LOV blue-light photoreceptors in <italic>K. nitens</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). CKI2, which is involved in stress-induced stomatal closure (<xref rid="evy213-B101" ref-type="bibr">Mira-Rodado et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>), was detected in species that have colonized terrestrial habitats. Domain-based phylogenetic analysis suggested that CKI1, which directs specification of the endosperm precursor central cell resulting in seeds containing an embryo and an endosperm, appeared within the seed-forming flowering plants (Angiosperms) (<xref rid="evy213-B163" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>).</p><p>An important feature of the diversification of the structure of green algal HKs was the apparition of ethylene and cytokinin receptors from the terrestrial alga <italic>K. nitens</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). Both ethylene and cytokinin are largely documented as prominent phytohormones essential for land plant developmental programs (<xref rid="evy213-B164" ref-type="bibr">Zdarska et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). The apparition of ethylene and cytokinin-sensing HKs in large numbers in the terrestrial algae (<italic>K. nitens</italic>) is likely to have played an essential role in progressively shaping the first multicellular Archaeplastida for growth and nutrition in various land ecotopes.</p></sec><sec><title>Strengthening the Classification of HKs in Opisthokonta</title><p>For the Opisthokonta, we first confirmed the absence of typical prokaryotic or eukaryotic HKs in animals. This is of course an essential prerequisite for approaches aimed at developing antimicrobials that target HKs in the context of human disease, for example (<xref rid="evy213-B14" ref-type="bibr">Bem et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; Shor and Chauhan 2015).</p><p>Fungal HKs were initially categorized into 11 groups (<xref rid="evy213-B23" ref-type="bibr">Catlett et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>) and then subsequently into 16 groups (<xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). Our analysis of a large panel of Dikarya (Ascomycota and Basidiomycota) and early diverging fungi indicated that classification of fungal HKs needs to be extended because previously undescribed topologies were identified and, consequently, some new groups have been proposed.</p><p>Exploration of the structure of HKs in the mesomycetozoan model species <italic>C</italic><italic>ap</italic><italic>. owczarzaki</italic> revealed the unexpected presence of an HK that shared a high degree of similarity with plant ethylene receptors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). However, we failed to detect any plant cytokinin receptor homologs in this species. Importantly, phytohormone receptor homologs (ethylene and cytokinin receptors) were recently found not only in early diverging fungi that are plant root symbionts or endophytes but also in species that colonize decaying plant material. It was thus speculated that these particular sensing proteins have promoted the interaction of early diverging fungi with plants leading to the conquest of land by these ancestral fungi (<xref rid="evy213-B63" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). The presence of such phytohormone receptor homologs in the Mesomycetozoa suggests that the acquisition of these sensing proteins occurred in a common ancestor of fungi and Mesomycetozoa. In cyanobacteria, ethylene receptors are bifunctional sensing proteins that mediate responses to both light and ethylene (<xref rid="evy213-B86" ref-type="bibr">Lacey and Binder 2016</xref>). It would be thus interesting to investigate the precise origin of ethylene receptors and their roles in the Mesomycetozoa and early diverging fungi.</p></sec><sec><title>A Marked Structural Diversity in Amoebozoan HKs</title><p>In contrast to plant and fungal HKs, knowledge about the function and physiological roles of HKs in amoebae remains fragmentary. The domain topologies of amoebozoan HKs were found to be highly diversified compared with other eukaryotic supergroups, indicating that they are likely to have a broad range of biochemical outputs and functions. Phylogenetic distribution provided some clues about the evolutionary paths driving the amoebozoan HKs diversity. For example, HKs with N-terminal CHASE domains (DhkA) were found exclusively in Dictyostelia, that is, amoebae that form true multicellular fruiting bodies (sorocarps) to produce spores. We also found some domain topologies in the Amoebozoa that had been observed previously only in fungi, such as group III HKs, which are reported to act as osmosensors, group X HKs, known to mediate oxidant stress adaptation (<xref rid="evy213-B36" ref-type="bibr">Defosse et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) and light-sensing phytochromes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). A similar situation was observed for some domain topologies that had been observed previously only in bacteria and plants, such as nitrate/nitrite sensors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). Most importantly, we described, for the first time, the occurrence of ethylene receptor homologs in the Amoebozoa, especially in the free-living amoeba <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic><italic>. castellanii</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). However, the physiological role of homologs of fungal group III, group X, phytochromes, and ethylene receptors remains to be established.</p><p>Globally, the number of HKs differed sharply between amoebozoan species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). The size of an organism HKs complement appeared to be inversely related to its level of developmental complexity (<italic>D. discoideum</italic> and <italic>P. pallidum</italic> vs. <italic>P</italic><italic>hysa</italic><italic>. polycephalum</italic>) or to its dependency on a host species (the free living <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic><italic>. castellanii</italic> vs. the obligate parasite <italic>E</italic><italic>n</italic><italic>. histolytica</italic>). However, these trends will need to be validated using larger scale phylogenomic analyses when more amoebozoan genomes are available.</p></sec><sec><title>First Description of HKs in Apusozoa</title><p>In this study, we also took the opportunity to advance the description of HKs in Eukaryota by investigating the structure and distribution of these proteins in unexplored eukaryotic supergroups. We describe here for the first time predicted HK structures for the Apusozoa. The phylogenetic position of this clade is still controversial, but recent molecular evidence suggests that it is a paraphyletic phylum related to the Opisthokonta (<xref rid="evy213-B24" ref-type="bibr">Cavalier-Smith et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). We identified 11 predicted proteins in the <italic>T</italic><italic>h</italic><italic>. trahens</italic> genome that display canonical HK features and these proteins were structurally diversified. Some interesting topologies were observed, notably HKs with a VSP domain in their N-terminal sensing region and bacteriorhodopsins. However, we have not been able to characterize this protein family further due to a lack of additional genomic resources and functional genomic data for the Apusozoa, and the lack of similarity of Apusozoa HKs with other bacterial and eukaryotic HK sequences.</p></sec><sec><title>HKs Are Restricted to Some Clades within the Excavata Supergroup</title><p>Searches of genomic resources for Excavata identified seven and 24 predicted HK sequences in the genomes of <italic>T</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. vaginalis</italic> (Metamonada) and <italic>N. gruberi</italic> (Discoba), respectively, but no HKs were found in the genomes of other prominent genera from the Excavata (<italic>Giardia</italic> sp<italic>., Leishmania</italic> sp., and <italic>Trypanosoma</italic> sp.). This distribution seems surprising but it is important to highlight the fact that, the genetic distance between <italic>T</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. vaginalis</italic> and <italic>G</italic><italic>i</italic><italic>. intestinalis</italic> is large, as that between <italic>N. gruberi</italic> and other species within the Discoba (<xref rid="evy213-B53" ref-type="bibr">Grant and Katz 2014</xref>). However, it was interesting to note the previously unreported occurrence of HKs in two prominent species <italic>T</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. vaginalis</italic> (human parasite) and <italic>N. gruberi</italic> (closely related to the human parasite <italic>Naegleria</italic><italic>fowleri</italic>). Three main observations can be highlighted concerning the predicted Excavata HKs: 1) Metamonada and Discoba HKs appear to be highly diverged, reflecting the large genetic distance between these two major clades of the Excavata; 2) although a small number of the Excavata HKs are likely to act as intracellular sensing proteins, most are predicted to be anchored in the cell membrane; and 3) very few of the Excavata HKs have known domains in their N-termini that have been implicated in sensing in other prokaryotic and eukaryotic HKs. Thus, the HK family appears to have evolved structurally in a specific manner in the Excavata supergroup.</p></sec><sec><title>First Description of Cytokinin and Ethylene Receptor Homologs in SAR</title><p>Finally, we report here the first description of HK structures in the SAR supergroup. The distribution of these predicted proteins was highly heterogeneous within the SAR clades, and we failed to identify any homologs in the genomes of Apicomplexa. Hence, therapeutic developments based on the inhibition of HK activity will unfortunately not be useful in combatting malaria, toxoplasmosis, or other coccidian diseases. The high level of genetic divergence between the genomes of the representative SAR species selected for this analysis complicated the phylogenomic approaches, and it was not possible to draw any general conclusions about the evolutionary relationships of HKs in this supergroup. However, interesting findings were made. Notably the presence in the genomes of photosynthetic diatoms and brown algae of genes encoding HKs that bear within their N-termini a CHASE domain, the characteristic feature of plant cytokinin receptors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). In addition, we described here for the first time the occurrence of ethylene receptor homologs in photosynthetic diatoms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). It is currently admitted that the diatom/brown algal lineage underwent an ancient secondary endosymbiosis events involving engulfment of a red alga by a stramenopile protist cell (<xref rid="evy213-B20" ref-type="bibr">Brodie et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). It is thus possible that phytohormone-like receptors were acquired by some Stramenopiles lineages via this secondary endosymbiosis. This is in line with the current hypothesis that the acquisition of HKs in eukaryotic lineages occurred via both the early mitochondrial endosymbiosis and the later endosymbiosis involving a cyanobacterium-like prokaryote that gave rise to plastids (<xref rid="evy213-B130" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>). We also observed indications that brown algal HK gene complements may have been enriched by exchanges with large DNA viruses, mediated by insertions of the genomes of these viruses into algal genomes. Inserted viral DNA containing HK genes was detected in <italic>Ectocarpus</italic> sp., for example. Moreover, not only did most of the bona fide algal HK genes share a high level of similarity with viral genes or cluster with them in phylogenetic trees but they also tended to be intron-poor, which is unusual for brown algal genes but is a typical feature of viral genomes. Taken together, these observations suggest that both endosymbiotic and other horizontal gene transfer mechanisms may have played an important role during the evolutionary history of stramenopile HKs.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Concluding Remarks</title><p>This study provides a preliminary overview of the structure and distribution of HKs in Eukaryota (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). Although HKs had been previously identified in plants, fungi, and Amoebozoa, we present here the first description of this family of HK proteins in unexplored clades such as Apusozoa, Excavata, and SAR. We observed conservation of some HK groups that are putatively involved in crucial physiological processes, including light perception, hormone sensing, development, and stress adaptation within eukaryotic supergroups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evy213-F8">fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). We show that data concerning the function of HK groups can be combined with robust phylogenetic analysis to decipher the evolutionary history and currently known functions of HKs, notably by correlating the presence of specific domain topologies with physiological traits. This approach was applied for the Archaeplastida and, to a lesser extent, for the Opisthokonta (mainly fungi). Critically, phylogenetic analysis suggested that cytokinin and/or ethylene signaling systems are not only found in plants but may also occur in various other eukaryotic (brown algae, diatoms, amoebae, fungi, and Mesomycetozoa) (this study and <xref rid="evy213-B63" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000e9;rivaux et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>) and prokaryotic (cyanobacteria and eubacteria) clades (<xref rid="evy213-B86" ref-type="bibr">Lacey and Binder 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B152" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>; <xref rid="evy213-B75" ref-type="bibr">Kabbara et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>) where they probably regulate cellular processes in a functional context with chemotaxis, developmental processes, and interkingdom communication.</p><p>In conclusion, this analysis extends our knowledge of the dissemination of TCS signaling pathways in eukaryotes. From an evolutionary perspective, it would be interesting in the near future to use phylogenetic methods to explore the evolutionary origins of eukaryotic HKs to predict whether they are derived from the archetypal ancestors of chloroplasts, mitochondria, or the archaebacterial host. In the same way, it would be highly relevant to identify eukaryotic HKs that were acquired thanks to more or less recent lateral gene transfer events from prokaryotes or eukaryotes. From a functional point of view, it remains also essential to accelerate the acquisition of data concerning the roles of eukaryotic HKs, notably for pathogenic fungi, Metamonada (<italic>T</italic><italic>r</italic><italic>. vaginalis</italic>), Discoba (<italic>N. gruberi</italic>), and oomycetes. This could shed light on their potential as new targets for antimicrobial development, as suggested over the past few years for bacteria (<xref rid="evy213-B14" ref-type="bibr">Bem et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic>Genome Biology and Evolution</italic> online.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Data</label><media xlink:href="evy213_supp.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank the U.S. Department of Energy Joint Genome Institute and the PIs of the 1000 Fungal Genomes Project (J. Spatafora, A. Gryganskyi, T. James, M.E. Smith, and J. Magnuson) for permission to use the <italic>Usnea florida, Syncephalis plumigaleata, Umbelopsis ramanniana</italic>, and <italic>Ramicandelaber brevisporus</italic> genome data before publication. We also acknowledge the Broad Institute Genome Sequencing Platform for making the <italic>Thecamonas trahens</italic> genome publicly available. We thank S. Gribaldo (Institut Pasteur, Paris) for constructive conversations about this manuscript. S.K. was supported by a fellowship from association AZM. A.H. was supported by a fellowship from the University of Angers. N.P. was funded by the Agence Nationale de la Recherche (program ANR-PRCE Mycormones).</p></ack><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evy213-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akiyoshi</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Genomic survey of the non-cultivatable opportunistic human pathogen, <italic>Enterocytozoon bieneusi</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e1000261</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19132089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>. <volume>215</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Amborella Genome Project.</collab>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Amborella</italic> genome and the evolution of flowering plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>342</volume>(<issue>6165</issue>):<fpage>1241089</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24357323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anantharaman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The CHASE domain: a predicted ligand-binding module in plant cytokinin receptors and other eukaryotic and bacterial receptors</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>. <volume>26</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>582</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Appleby</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bourret</surname><given-names>RB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Signal transduction via the multi-step phosphorelay: not necessarily a road less traveled</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>86</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>848</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8808618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genomes of coral dinoflagellate symbionts highlight evolutionary adaptations conducive to a symbiotic lifestyle</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>39734</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28004835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>CP.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>The GAF domain: an evolutionary link between diverse phototransducing proteins</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>. <volume>22</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>458</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9433123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>CP.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>The cytoplasmic helical linker domain of receptor histidine kinase and methyl-accepting proteins is common to many prokaryotic signalling proteins</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>. <volume>176</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10418137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Attwood</surname><given-names>PV.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Histidine kinases from bacteria to humans</article-title>. <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source>. <volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1023</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1028</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23863173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aury</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Global trends of whole-genome duplications revealed by the ciliate <italic>Paramecium tetraurelia</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>444</volume>(<issue>7116</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>178</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17086204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahn</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heitman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>A unique fungal two-component system regulates stress responses, drug sensitivity, sexual development, and virulence of <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>3122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16672377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Selaginella</italic> genome identifies genetic changes associated with the evolution of vascular plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>332</volume>(<issue>6032</issue>):<fpage>960</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>963</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21551031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braus</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Romero</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Spotlight on <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> photosensory systems</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>. <volume>47</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>900</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>908</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20573560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bem</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Bacterial histidine kinases as novel antibacterial drug targets</article-title>. <source>ACS Chem Biol</source>. <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25436989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bemm</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>F&#x000f6;rster</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>A kinome of 2600 in the ciliate <italic>Paramecium tetraurelia</italic></article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>. <volume>583</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>3589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3592</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19840790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bischoff</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ordal</surname><given-names>GW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title><italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> chemotaxis: a deviation from the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> paradigm</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1738311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Insights into land plant evolution garnered from the <italic>Marchantia polymorpha</italic> genome</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>171</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304.e15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28985561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brayton</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Genome sequence of <italic>Babesia bovis</italic> and comparative analysis of apicomplexan hemoprotozoa</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <volume>3</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17953480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Biotic interactions as drivers of algal origin and evolution</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <volume>216</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>670</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>681</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28857164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Draft genome sequence of the sexually transmitted pathogen <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>315</volume>(<issue>5809</issue>):<fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>212</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17218520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cashmore</surname><given-names>AR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Higher-plant phytochrome: &#x0201c;I used to date histidine, but now I prefer serine.&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>95</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>13358</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13360</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9811805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Catlett</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turgeon</surname><given-names>BG.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Whole-genome analysis of two-component signal transduction genes in fungal pathogens</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>. <volume>2</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1161</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14665450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalier-Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Multigene phylogeny resolves deep branching of Amoebozoa</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25150787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Phylogenomic analyses indicate that early fungi evolved digesting cell walls of algal ancestors of land plants</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1590</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1601</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25977457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chefdor</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Osmotic stress sensing in <italic>Populus</italic>: components identification of a phosphorelay system</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>. <volume>580</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16359674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cisse</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Genome sequencing of the plant pathogen <italic>Taphrina deformans</italic>, the causal agent of peach leaf curl</article-title>. <source>Mbio</source><volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e00055</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e00013</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23631913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Association of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> CTR1 Raf-like kinase with the ETR1 and ERS ethylene receptors</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>95</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>5401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5406</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9560288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Genome of <italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii</italic> highlights extensive lateral gene transfer and early evolution of tyrosine kinase signaling</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>R11</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23375108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemons</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selitrennikoff</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>DA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Fos-1, a putative histidine kinase as a virulence factor for systemic aspergillosis</article-title>. <source>Med Mycol</source>. <volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12146755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cock</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Ectocarpus</italic> genome and the independent evolution of multicellularity in brown algae</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>465</volume>(<issue>7298</issue>):<fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>621</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20520714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cormier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Re-annotation, improved large-scale assembly and establishment of a catalogue of noncoding loci for the genome of the model brown alga <italic>Ectocarpus</italic></article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <volume>214</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>232</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27870061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crosson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rajagopal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moffat</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The LOV domain family: photoresponsive signaling modules coupled to diverse output domains</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source><volume>42</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12515534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuomo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> genome reveals a link between localized polymorphism and pathogen specialization</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>317</volume>(<issue>5843</issue>):<fpage>1400</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1402</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17823352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Algal genomes reveal evolutionary mosaicism and the fate of nucleomorphs</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>492</volume>(<issue>7427</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23201678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Defosse</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Hybrid histidine kinases in pathogenic fungi</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <volume>95</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>914</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>924</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25560420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delaroque</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The genome of the brown alga <italic>Ectocarpus siliculosus</italic> contains a series of viral DNA pieces, suggesting an ancient association with large dsDNA viruses</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>. <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>110</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18405387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delaroque</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The complete DNA sequence of the <italic>Ectocarpus siliculosus</italic> Virus EsV-1 genome</article-title>. <source>Virology</source><volume>287</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schilde</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaap</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The evolution of aggregative multicellularity and cell-cell communication in the Dictyostelia</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>. <volume>427</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>3722</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3733</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26284972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duanmu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Marine algae and land plants share conserved phytochrome signaling systems</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>111</volume>(<issue>44</issue>):<fpage>15827</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15832</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25267653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duplessis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Obligate biotrophy features unraveled by the genomic analysis of rust fungi</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>108</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>9166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9171</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21536894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eichinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>The genome of the social amoeba <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>435</volume>(<issue>7038</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15875012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Macronuclear genome sequence of the ciliate <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>, a model eukaryote</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <volume>4</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e286</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16933976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritz-Laylin</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The genome of <italic>Naegleria gruberi</italic> illuminates early eukaryotic versatility</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>140</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>631</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>642</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20211133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallie</surname><given-names>DR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Appearance and elaboration of the ethylene receptor family during land plant evolution</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>. <volume>87</volume>(<issue>4&#x02015;5</issue>):<fpage>521</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>539</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25682121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galp&#x000e9;rin</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Makarova</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Phyletic distribution and lineage-specific domain architectures of archaeal two-component signal transduction systems</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <volume>200</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):pii: e00681&#x02013;17.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Genome sequence of the human malaria parasite <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>419</volume>(<issue>6906</issue>):<fpage>498</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>511</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gargantini</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Antigenic variation in the intestinal parasite <italic>Giardia lamblia</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>. <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27177351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gazis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The genome of <italic>Xylona heveae</italic> provides a window into fungal endophytism</article-title>. <source>Fungal Biol</source>. <volume>120</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26693682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glantz</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Functional and topological diversity of LOV domain photoreceptors</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>113</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>E1442</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E1451</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26929367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gl&#x000f6;ckner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The genome of the foraminiferan <italic>Reticulomyxa filosa</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24332546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gobler</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Niche of harmful alga <italic>Aureococcus anophagefferens</italic> revealed through ecogenomics</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>108</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>4352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4357</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21368207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Building a phylogenomic pipeline for the eukaryotic tree of life&#x02014;addressing deep phylogenies with genome-scale data</article-title>. <source>PloS Curr</source>. <volume>6</volume>:pii: ecurrents.tol.e089df47766ed1e9dabac39c76bae266.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grebe</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>JB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>The histidine protein kinase superfamily</article-title>. <source>Adv Microb Physiol</source>. <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10500846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grigoriev</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>MycoCosm portal: gearing up for 1000 fungal genomes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>42</volume>(<issue>Database issue</issue>):<fpage>D699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D704</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruhn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seidl</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heyl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>A subfamily of putative cytokinin receptors is revealed by an analysis of the evolution of the two-component signaling system of plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <volume>165</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24520157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gulia-Nuss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genomic insights into the <italic>Ixodes scapularis</italic> tick vector of Lyme disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>10507</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26856261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haitjema</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>A parts list for fungal cellulosomes revealed by comparative genomics</article-title>. <source>Nat Microbiol</source>. <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>17087</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28555641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kropinski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clokie</surname><given-names>MR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>What does the talking? Quorum sensing signalling genes discovered in a bacteriophage genome</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e85131.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24475037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide identification and expression analysis of two-component system genes in tomato</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):pii: E1204.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heidel</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Phylogeny-wide analysis of social amoeba genomes highlights ancient origins for complex intercellular communication</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <volume>21</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1882</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1891</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21757610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e9;rivaux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Major sensing proteins in pathogenic fungi: the hybrid histidine kinase family</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source><volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e1005683</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27467512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e9;rivaux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>The identification of phytohormone receptor homologs in early diverging fungi suggests a role for plant sensing in land colonization by fungi. mBio</article-title><volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>8</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Multiple roots of fruiting body formation in Amoebozoa</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>606</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29378020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title><italic>Klebsormidium flaccidum</italic> genome reveals primary factors for plant terrestrial adaptation</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>3978</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24865297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>A survey of schistosome protein domain types: insights into unique biological properties</article-title>. <source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source>. <volume>177</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21315771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Two-component signal transduction pathways in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <volume>129</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>500</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12068096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Classification of the genes involved in the two-component system of the moss <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic></article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source>. <volume>74</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2542</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2545</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21150091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The genome sequence of <italic>Trypanosoma brucei gambiense</italic>, causative agent of chronic human African trypanosomiasis</article-title>. <source>PloS Negl Trop Dis</source>. <volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e658</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20404998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yemelin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thines</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Histidine kinases mediate differentiation, stress response, and pathogenicity in <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiologyopen</source><volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>668</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>687</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25103193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Shared signatures of parasitism and phylogenomics unite Cryptomycota and Microsporidia</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1548</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1553</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23932404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The diploid genome sequence of <italic>Candida albicans</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>101</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>7329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7334</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15123810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The alveolate <italic>Perkinsus marinus</italic>: biological insights from EST gene discovery</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>11</volume>:<fpage>228</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20374649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Behr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heermann</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Histidine kinases and response regulators in networks</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>. <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>124</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22172627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabbara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schm&#x000fc;lling</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papon</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>CHASEing cytokinin receptors in plants, bacteria, fungi, and beyond</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29366683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kakimoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>CKI1, a histidine kinase homolog implicated in cytokinin signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>274</volume>(<issue>5289</issue>):<fpage>982</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>985</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8875940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Insights from the genome of the biotrophic fungal plant pathogen <italic>Ustilago maydis</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>444</volume>(<issue>7115</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17080091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kateriya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bamberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hegemann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>&#x0201c;Vision&#x0201d; in single-celled algae</article-title>. <source>News Physiol Sci</source>. <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15143209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Gene gain and loss during evolution of obligate parasitism in the white rust pathogen of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <volume>9</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e1001094</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21750662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kianianmomeni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Algal photoreceptors: in vivo functions and potential applications</article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>239</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24081482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forst</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Genomic analysis of the histidine kinase family in bacteria and archaea</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Read Engl</source>. <volume>147</volume>(<issue>Pt 5</issue>):<fpage>1197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1212</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The genome of the choanoflagellate <italic>Monosiga brevicollis</italic> and the origin of metazoans</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>451</volume>(<issue>7180</issue>):<fpage>783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>788</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18273011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koo&#x000df;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamparter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Cyanobacterial origin of plant phytochromes</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source><volume>254</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>607</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26869366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: application to complete genomes</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>. <volume>305</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kubohara</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Differentiation-inducing factor 2 modulates chemotaxis via the histidine kinase DhkC-dependent pathway in <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic></article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>. <volume>590</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>760</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>768</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26919666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacey</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>BM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Ethylene regulates the physiology of the <italic>Cyanobacterium synechocystis</italic> sp. PCC 6803 via an ethylene receptor</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <volume>171</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2798</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2809</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27246094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lav&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarasola-Puente</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pisabarro</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oguiza</surname><given-names>JA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Dual-histidine kinases in basidiomycete fungi</article-title>. <source>C R Biol</source>. <volume>337</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24581805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>OLG.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>An improved, general amino-acid replacement matrix</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1320</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18367465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide identification, phylogeny, duplication, and expression analyses of two-component system genes in Chinese cabbage (<italic>Brassica rapa</italic> ssp. Pekinensis)</article-title>. <source>DNA Res.</source><volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>396</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24585003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loftus</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>The genome of the protist parasite <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>433</volume>(<issue>7028</issue>):<fpage>865</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>868</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15729342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loftus</surname><given-names>BJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>The genome of the basidiomycetous yeast and human pathogen <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>307</volume>(<issue>5713</issue>):<fpage>1321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1324</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Local admixture of amplified and diversified secreted pathogenesis determinants shapes mosaic <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> genomes</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <fpage>7: 10147</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>A photochromic histidine kinase rhodopsin (HKR1) that is bimodally switched by ultraviolet and blue light</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>287</volume>(<issue>47</issue>):<fpage>40083</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40090</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23027869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malpica</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandoval</surname><given-names>GRP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Georgellis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Signaling by the arc two-component system provides a link between the redox state of the quinone pool and gene expression</article-title>. <source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source>. <volume>8</volume>(<issue>5&#x02015;6</issue>):<fpage>781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>795</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16771670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchler-Bauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>CDD/SPARCLE: functional classification of proteins via subfamily domain architectures</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>45</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27899674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Perigord black truffle genome uncovers evolutionary origins and mechanisms of symbiosis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>464</volume>(<issue>7291</issue>):<fpage>1033</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1038</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20348908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mascher</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helmann</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Unden</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Stimulus perception in bacterial signal-transducing histidine kinases</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>. <volume>70</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>910</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>938</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17158704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Genome sequence of the ultrasmall unicellular red alga <italic>Cyanidioschyzon merolae</italic> 10D</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>; 428</volume>(<issue>6983</issue>):<fpage>653</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>657</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mira-Rodado</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Identification of two-component system elements downstream of AHK5 in the stomatal closure response of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Signal Behav</source>. <volume>7</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1476</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22951399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#x000f6;glich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayers</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moffat</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Structure and signaling mechanism of Per-ARNT-Sim domains</article-title>. <source>Structure</source><volume>17</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1294</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19836329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Widespread adenine N6-methylation of active genes in fungi</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>964</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28481340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B104"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Genomic minimalism in the early diverging intestinal parasite <italic>Giardia lamblia</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>317</volume>(<issue>5846</issue>):<fpage>1921</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1926</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17901334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mougel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhulin</surname><given-names>IB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>CHASE: an extracellular sensing domain common to transmembrane receptors from prokaryotes, lower eukaryotes and plants</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>. <volume>26</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>582</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>584</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B106"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Decoding the massive genome of loblolly pine using haploid DNA and novel assembly strategies</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>R59</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24647006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B107"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neave</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michell</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Apprill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voolstra</surname><given-names>CR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title><italic>Endozoicomonas</italic> genomes reveal functional adaptation and plasticity in bacterial strains symbiotically associated with diverse marine hosts</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>40579</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28094347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B108"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nierman</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Genomic sequence of the pathogenic and allergenic filamentous fungus <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>438</volume>(<issue>7071</issue>):<fpage>1151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1156</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16372009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B109"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osakabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>LS.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Sensing the environment: key roles of membrane-localized kinases in plant perception and response to abiotic stress</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>. <volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>458</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23307915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B110"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwala</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>COBALT: constraint-based alignment tool for multiple protein sequences</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>23</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1073</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1079</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17332019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B111"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pareek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Whole-genome analysis of <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> reveals similar architecture of two-component signaling machinery with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <volume>142</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>380</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16891544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B112"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Comparative genomic analysis of three <italic>Leishmania</italic> species that cause diverse human disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>847</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17572675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B114"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pischke</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>An <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> histidine kinase is essential for megagametogenesis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>99</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>15800</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15805</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12426401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B115"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title><italic>Cyanophora paradoxa</italic> genome elucidates origin of photosynthesis in algae and plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>335</volume>(<issue>6070</issue>):<fpage>843</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>847</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22344442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B116"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prochnik</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Genomic analysis of organismal complexity in the multicellular green alga <italic>Volvox carteri</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>329</volume>(<issue>5988</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20616280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B117"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puthiyaveetil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JF.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Chloroplast two-component systems: evolution of the link between photosynthesis and gene expression</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci</source>. <volume>276</volume>(<issue>1665</issue>):<fpage>2133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2145</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19324807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B118"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puthiyaveetil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The ancestral symbiont sensor kinase CSK links photosynthesis with gene expression in chloroplasts</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>105</volume>(<issue>29</issue>):<fpage>10061</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10066</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18632566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B119"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puthiyaveetil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional control of photosynthesis genes: the evolutionarily conserved regulatory mechanism in plastid genome function. Genome</article-title><source>Biol Evol</source>. <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>888</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>896</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B120"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puthiyaveetil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JF.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Evolutionary rewiring: a modified prokaryotic gene-regulatory pathway in chloroplasts</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>. <volume>368</volume>(<issue>1622</issue>):<fpage>20120260.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23754813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B121"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Sea anemone genome reveals ancestral eumetazoan gene repertoire and genomic organization</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>317</volume>(<issue>5834</issue>):<fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17615350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B122"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>R Development Core Team</collab>. <year>2013</year> R: a language and environment for statistical computing. Vienna (Austria)&#x000a0;: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org/">http://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B123"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Pan genome of the phytoplankton <italic>Emiliania</italic> underpins its global distribution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>499</volume>(<issue>7457</issue>):<fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23760476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B124"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rensing</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Physcomitrella</italic> genome reveals evolutionary insights into the conquest of land by plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>319</volume>(<issue>5859</issue>):<fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B125"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Eukaryotic algal phytochromes span the visible spectrum</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>111</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3871</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3876</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24567382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B126"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>JC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Phytochrome diversification in cyanobacteria and eukaryotic algae</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>. <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28445833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B127"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaap</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Evolutionary crossroads in developmental biology: <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source><volume>138</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>396</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21205784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B128"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaap</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Physarum polycephalum</italic> genome reveals extensive use of prokaryotic two-component and metazoan-type tyrosine kinase signaling</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B129"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kieber</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>S-H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Two-component signaling elements and histidyl-aspartyl phosphorelays</article-title>. <source>Arabidopsis Book</source><volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e0112.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22303237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B130"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Two-component systems and their co-option for eukaryotic signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <volume>21</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>R320</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>R330</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21549954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B131"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schliep</surname><given-names>KP.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Phangorn: phylogenetic analysis in R</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>592</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>593</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21169378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B132"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milpetz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>CP.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>SMART, a simple modular architecture research tool: identification of signaling domains</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>95</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>5857</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5864</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9600884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B133"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwelm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Plasmodiophora brassicae</italic> genome reveals insights in its life cycle and ancestry of chitin synthases</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>11153</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26084520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B134"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shadwick</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shadwick</surname><given-names>JDL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silberman</surname><given-names>JD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Eumycetozoa = Amoebozoa? SSUrDNA phylogeny of protosteloid slime molds and its significance for the amoebozoan supergroup</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>4</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e6754.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19707546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B135"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>A case for two-component signaling systems as antifungal drug targets</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e1004632</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25723524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B136"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Fast, scalable generation of high-quality protein multiple sequence alignments using Clustal Omega</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>. <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>539</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B137"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simakov</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Insights into bilaterian evolution from three spiralian genomes</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>493</volume>(<issue>7433</issue>):<fpage>526</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>531</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23254933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B139"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zinda</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mykytka</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>The histidine kinase dhkC regulates the choice between migrating slugs and terminal differentiation in <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic></article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <volume>203</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>357</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9808785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B140"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Staats</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Kan</surname><given-names>JA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Genome update of <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> strains B05.10 and T4</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>. <volume>11</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1414</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B141"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sucgang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Comparative genomics of the social amoebae <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic> and <italic>Dictyostelium purpureum</italic></article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>R20</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21356102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B142"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Capsaspora</italic> genome reveals a complex unicellular prehistory of animals</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>2325</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23942320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B143"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>From seed to seed: the role of photoreceptors in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> development</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <volume>260</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12921732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B144"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanesaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Cold-regulated genes under control of the cold sensor Hik33 in <italic>Synechocystis</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B145"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talavera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Improvement of phylogenies after removing divergent and ambiguously aligned blocks from protein sequence alignments</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <volume>56</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>577</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17654362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B146"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Oil accumulation by the oleaginous diatom <italic>Fistulifera solaris</italic> as revealed by the genome and transcriptome</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25634988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B147"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tisserant</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Genome of an arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus provides insight into the oldest plant symbiosis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>110</volume>(<issue>50</issue>):<fpage>20117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24277808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B148"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Troein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Multiple light inputs to a simple clock circuit allow complex biological rhythms</article-title>. <source>Plant J Cell Mol Biol</source>. <volume>66</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>385</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B150"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uehling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Comparative genomics of <italic>Mortierella elongata</italic> and its bacterial endosymbiont <italic>Mycoavidus cysteinexigens</italic></article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol</source>. <volume>19</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2964</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2983</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28076891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B151"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>A transmembrane hybrid-type histidine kinase in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> functions as an osmosensor</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>11</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1743</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1754</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10488240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B152"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>BZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>A bacterial receptor PcrK senses the plant hormone cytokinin to promote adaptation to oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. <volume>21</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2940</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2951</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29212037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B153"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaulsky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Escalante</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>WF.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>A two-component histidine kinase gene that functions in <italic>Dictyostelium</italic> development</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <volume>15</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>3890</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3898</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8670894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B154"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>S&#x000f6;derbom</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anjard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaulsky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>WF.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>SDF-2 induction of terminal differentiation in <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic> is mediated by the membrane-spanning sensor kinase DhkA</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>. <volume>19</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>4750</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4756</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10373524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B155"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Identification of important regions for ethylene binding and signaling in the transmembrane domain of the ETR1 ethylene receptor of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>18</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3442</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B156"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Chromerid genomes reveal the evolutionary path from photosynthetic algae to obligate intracellular parasites</article-title>. <source>eLife</source><volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e06974</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26175406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B157"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Worden</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Green evolution and dynamic adaptations revealed by genomes of the marine picoeukaryotes <italic>Micromonas</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>324</volume>(<issue>5924</issue>):<fpage>268</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19359590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B158"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The genome of <italic>Spironucleus salmonicida</italic> highlights a fish pathogen adapted to fluctuating environments</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e1004053</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24516394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B159"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The genome of <italic>Cryptosporidium hominis</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>431</volume>(<issue>7012</issue>):<fpage>1107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15510150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B160"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Genomic and proteomic analyses of the fungus <italic>Arthrobotrys oligospora</italic> provide insights into nematode-trap formation</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e1002179</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21909256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B161"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasumura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pierik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fricker</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voesenek</surname><given-names>LACJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Studies of <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> reveal that ethylene-mediated submergence responses arose relatively early in land-plant evolution</article-title>. <source>Plant J Cell Mol Biol</source>. <volume>72</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>947</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>959</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B162"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>A heterozygous moth genome provides insights into herbivory and detoxification</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>220</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23313953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B163"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The CKI1 histidine kinase specifies the female gametic precursor of the endosperm</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source>. <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27046830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B164"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zdarska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Illuminating light, cytokinin, and ethylene signalling crosstalk in plant development</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>. <volume>66</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>4913</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4931</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26022257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B165"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Recent geological events and intrinsic behavior influence the population genetic structure of the Chiru and Tibetan gazelle on the Tibetan Plateau</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e60712</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23637761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B166"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Baiji genomes reveal low genetic variability and new insights into secondary aquatic adaptations</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>2708</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24169659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evy213-B167"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zinda</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>CK.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>The hybrid histidine kinase dhkB regulates spore germination in <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic></article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <volume>196</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9576830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>