<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6338801</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">36446</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-36446-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dissecting Heterosis During the Ear Inflorescence Development Stage in Maize <italic>via</italic> a Metabolomics-based Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Xia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xuehai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Dakun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiangge</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Weihua</given-names></name><address><email>liwh416@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Jihua</given-names></name><address><email>tangjihua1@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.108266.b</institution-id><institution>National Key Laboratory of Wheat and Maize Crop Science, </institution><institution>Henan Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Zhengzhou, 450002 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410654.2</institution-id><institution>Hubei Collaborative Innovation Center for Grain Industry, </institution><institution>Yangtze University, </institution></institution-wrap>Jingzhou, 434025 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>212</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Heterosis can increase the yield of many crops and has been extensively applied in agriculture. In maize, female inflorescence architecture directly determines grain yield. Thus, exploring the relationship between early maize ear inflorescence development and heterosis regarding yield-related traits may be helpful for characterizing the molecular mechanisms underlying heterotic performance. In this study, we fine mapped the overdominant heterotic locus (<italic>hlEW2b</italic>), associated with ear width, in an approximately 1.98-Mb region based on analyses of chromosome segment substitution lines and the corresponding testcross population. Maize ear inflorescences at the floral meristem stage were collected from two inbred lines, one chromosome segment substitution line that carried <italic>hlEW2b</italic> (sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>), the receptor parent lx9801, and the Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 hybrid lines. A total of 256 metabolites were identified, including 31 and 24 metabolites that were differentially accumulated between the two hybrid lines and between the two inbred lines, respectively. Most of these metabolites are involved in complex regulatory mechanisms important for maize ear development. For example, nucleotides are basic metabolites affecting cell composition and carbohydrate synthesis. Additionally, nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolism is important for photosynthesis, plant stress responses, and cell expansion. Moreover, flavonoid and phenolic metabolites regulate auxin transport and cell apoptosis. Meanwhile, phytohormone biosynthesis and distribution influence the cell cycle and cell proliferation. Our results revealed that changes in metabolite contents may affect the heterotic performance related to ear width and yield in maize hybrid lines. This study provides new clues in heterosis at the metabolomics level and implies that differentially accumulated metabolites made distinct contributions to the heterosis at an early stage of ear inflorescences development.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Henan Province Science and Technology Attack Project (182102110349)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Henan Province Science and Technology Attack Project (152102110062)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China (National Science Foundation of China)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>91335205</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Jihua</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Central Plains Scholar of Henan Major Science and Technology of Henan Province (161100110500)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Heterosis refers to the phenomenon that hybrids perform better than their parents regarding phenotypic traits, including biomass, development rate, fertility, nutrient quality, disease resistance, and crop yield<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Heterosis can increase grain yield and has been applied to improve agricultural production for a few hundred years. Three classical genetic hypotheses (i.e., dominance hypothesis, overdominance hypothesis, and epistasis hypothesis) were proposed early last century to explain the genetic basis of heterosis. The overdominance hypothesis has been validated using the <italic>SINGLE FLOWER TRUSS</italic> (<italic>SFT</italic>) locus of tomato<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. However, these hypotheses did not end the century-long debate regarding whether they fully explain the genetic basis of heterosis because they represent largely conceptual models and do not describe the underlying molecular mechanism. Advances in high-throughput technologies have enabled researchers to develop new strategies for dissecting the genetic or molecular mechanism regulating heterosis. However, multiple omics-based researches (i.e., genomics, transcriptomics and epigenetics) in plants for hybrids and their parents, have been conducted to explore the cause of heterosis, the genetic mechanism mediating heterosis remains unclear up to now<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Genomics-based studies revealed that the complementation of two parental genomes makes an important contribution to heterosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Moreover, based on transcriptomics and proteomics, additive and non-additive effects have been estimated between parents and hybrids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Due to a large amount of redundant information was generated along with the high-throughput data obtained by genomics, transcriptomics and proteomics technologies, making it even more difficult to elucidate the genetic mechanism of heterosis at one or multiple loci. As so far, at the single-locus level, <italic>SFT</italic> is the first identified overdominance gene associated with heterosis, has been cloned in tomato<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Although considerable efforts have been made to dissect the genetic basis of heterosis in plants, there is no appropriate method for analyzing heterotic performance because of the complexity of genetic backgrounds and controversies regarding the underlying mechanism.</p><p id="Par4">To eliminate the influence of genetic backgrounds, backcross populations of chromosome segment substitution lines (CSSLs) were developed and used for characterizing the relationship between heterosis and grain yield as well as the associated components in tomato and rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Compared with other populations, such as recombinant inbred lines (RIL) or doubled haploid populations, CSSLs enable the identification of the chromosomal segment responsible for heterotic effects under the same genetic background in multiple environments. Testcross populations have been widely applied to detect quantitative trait loci associated with heterosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. For example, Wang <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> used 66 testcross F<sub>1</sub> lines developed from the corresponding CSSLs to demonstrate that partial dominance and overdominance represent the genetic basis of the heterosis of yield and yield-related traits in rice hybrids. Using a set of 202 CSSLs and the corresponding testcross population, 15 heterotic loci (HLs) for plant height were detected in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Integrating the backcross and testcross populations of CSSLs may clarify the genetic and biological basis of heterosis.</p><p id="Par5">Recent metabolomics-based investigations have more thoroughly clarified the metabolic activities of many crops, with potential implications for breeding new high-yielding varieties with improved nutritional composition. Metabolites are useful for efficiently predicting the hybrid performance of several crops, including maize and rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. However, relatively few studies comparing the concentrations of secondary metabolites in hybrids and their parents have been conducted in maize, especially involving two inbred lines (one origin inbred line and its progeny with a single chromosome segment from a backcross), with the corresponding hybrids crossed with a common test parent.</p><p id="Par6">Heterosis of ear traits has significant positive correlations with maize yield<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Ear traits including ear length, ear width, kernel row number and kernel number per row, are determined in developing immature maize ears<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. During ear inflorescence development, the floret meristem (FM) stage is critical for ear development and heterosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Consequently, this stage is ideal for studying heterosis. Furthermore, metabolites represent the basic compounds accumulating in plant organs that influence the phenotype. However, there is very little or no available information regarding the relationship between secondary metabolites and heterosis. Thus, analyzing the secondary metabolites in hybrids and their parents may provide new insights and clarify the genetic mechanism underlying heterosis. In this study, we collected immature maize ears during the FM stage from two inbred lines [i.e., sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> containing an heterotic locus (HL) associated with ear width and its receptor parent lx9801] and their corresponding hybrids crossed with a common tester, Zheng58. We integrated the results of our targeted metabolomics approach with relevant gene expression data to (1) explore the metabolic processes involved in early maize ear development; (2) identify metabolites associated with heterosis; (3) construct a metabolites interaction network explaining heterotic performance. These results may help to elucidate the mechanism underlying heterotic performance at the metabolomics level.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Fine mapping the heterotic locus <italic>hlEW2b</italic></title><p id="Par7">We previously mapped <italic>hlEW2b</italic> on chromosome 2 between markers umc1555 and umc1465, and determined that it accounts for 8.5% of the ear width heterosis over the standard control (Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. To more precisely locate <italic>hlEW2b</italic>, 152 homozygous sub-CSSLs were identified among 1,652 F<sub>2</sub> individuals derived from the CSSL<sub>125</sub>&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 cross by genotyping with 12 new polymorphism markers within the <italic>hlEW2b</italic> region. Meanwhile, a test population was generated by crossing 152 homozygous sub-CSSLs with the test parent Zheng58 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We compared the ear width of Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 with that of the test population. A total of 37 homozygous recombinant lines carrying the <italic>hlEW2b</italic>-containing donor genomic segment between SSR markers 7HY-304 and umc1024 had ears that were wider than those of Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). Screening with molecular markers resulted in the mapping of <italic>hlEW2b</italic> to a 1.98-Mb region between 7HY-304 and 1HY-100 (see Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Development of a CSSL testcross population and identification of heterotic loci. The Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;CSSL<sub>125</sub> population exhibited significant heterosis for maize ear width. The sub-CSSL population was constructed from 152 homozygous sub-CSSL F<sub>2</sub> plants, which were derived from a cross between CSSL<sub>125</sub> and lx9801. The corresponding test population was constructed by crossing the test parent Zheng58 with sub-CSSLs. Red, green, and blue represent the genomes of lx9801 (receptor parent), Chang7-2 (donor parent), and Zheng58 (test parent), respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36446_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e456"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">A total of 42 candidate genes, including 30 functional genes coding proteins, 3 transcription factors and 8 unknown functional genes, were found in this mapping region (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Three genes, Zm00001d002896, Zm00001d002929 and Zm00001d002934 encodes TUB-transcription factor, auxin response factor and NAC domain-transcription factor, respectively. Additionally, Zm00001d002882 encodes SKP1-interacting partner and Zm00001d002933 encodes DDB1-, CUL4-associated factor has the same functions, all of which are component of the E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase complex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. One genes Zm00001d002888 [encoding Medicago truncatula NODULIN 21 (MtN21)] was a homolog of Zm00001d002893 [encoding Walls-Are-Thin 1 (WAT1) related protein], which could disrupt auxin transport to regulating cell elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Moreover, several candidate genes encode some important enzymes, for example, Zm00001d002880 encodes an isopropylmalate dehydrogenase, Zm00001d002889 encodes a soluble inorganic pyrophosphatase, Zm00001d002922 encode an inositol polyphosphate multi kinase beta, Zm00001d002912, Zm00001d002916 encode the glyoxal oxidase-related protein and five candidate genes (Zm00001d002897, Zm00001d002898, Zm00001d002899, Zm00001d002901 and Zm00001d002902) encode the peroxidase. These candidate genes maybe contribute to heterosis, more work needed to narrow down the mapping interval and confirm the functional gene. Furthermore, according to the heterosis for ear width and the genotype of the homozygous recombinant lines, one sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> line with the shortest donor chromosomal segment (1.98&#x02009;Mb) harboring <italic>hlEW2b</italic> was selected for a metabolomics analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Phenotype and heterosis effects analysis</title><p id="Par9">Phenotypic analyses in four environments revealed significant differences in ear width (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) between the hybrids of Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and the Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801, while there were no significant differences in other ear related traits (including ear length, kernel row number and kernel number per row) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Additionally, there were no significant differences in all five ear traits between the inbred lines lx9801 and the sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> in two environments (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). In order to characterize the genetic effect of HL (<italic>hlEW2b</italic>), we calculated the additive and dominant value of HL (<italic>hlEW2b</italic>) based on the following equations: a&#x02009;=&#x02009;(P<sub>1</sub>&#x02013;P<sub>2</sub>)/2 and d&#x02009;=&#x02009;F<sub>1</sub>&#x02212;(P<sub>1</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;P<sub>2</sub>)/2, here, a is the additive effect, d is the dominant effect, P<sub>1</sub> refers to the trait value of Zheng58, P<sub>2</sub> stands for the trait value of sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>, and F<sub>1</sub> refers to the value of the trait for the hybrid Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>). Theoretically, a ratio of estimated dominance to the absolute value of additive effect (d/a) &#x0003e;1, =1, &#x0003c;1 were regarded as overdominance, dominance and partial-dominance, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Our results revealed that the HL (<italic>hlEW2b</italic>) of ear width exhibits high overdominance (d/a&#x000bb;1, d&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.19, a&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.07) (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Thus, overdominance is the most contributor to heterosis of ear width.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Maize ear traits of Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> in four environments.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Trait</th><th rowspan="2">Environments</th><th colspan="3">Hybrids</th></tr><tr><th>Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801</th><th>Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub></th><th>P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4">Ear width(mm)</td><td>E1</td><td>50.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.00</td><td>52.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.30**</td><td>1.17E-03</td></tr><tr><td>E2</td><td>46.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.96</td><td>47.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.32*</td><td>1.04E-02</td></tr><tr><td>E3</td><td>51.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.65</td><td>53.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.11**</td><td>2.65E-04</td></tr><tr><td>E4</td><td>50.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.43</td><td>53.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.26**</td><td>8.62E-05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Ear length (cm)</td><td>E1</td><td>19.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.77</td><td>19.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78</td><td>8.43E-01</td></tr><tr><td>E2</td><td>18.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.14</td><td>19.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.75</td><td>2.27E-01</td></tr><tr><td>E3</td><td>19.44&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.85</td><td>18.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.30</td><td>9.14E-02</td></tr><tr><td>E4</td><td>18.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.49</td><td>17.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.93</td><td>1.83E-01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Kernel row number</td><td>E1</td><td>13.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.48</td><td>14.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.84</td><td>2.79E-01</td></tr><tr><td>E2</td><td>13.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.26</td><td>13.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.65</td><td>7.64E-01</td></tr><tr><td>E3</td><td>13.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.65</td><td>13.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.40</td><td>7.73E-01</td></tr><tr><td>E4</td><td>12.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.03</td><td>13.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.03</td><td>3.98E-01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Kernel number per row</td><td>E1</td><td>36.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.02</td><td>34.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.65</td><td>2.14E-01</td></tr><tr><td>E2</td><td>38.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.16</td><td>37.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.35</td><td>8.68E-02</td></tr><tr><td>E3</td><td>38.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.89</td><td>37.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.36</td><td>1.60E-01</td></tr><tr><td>E4</td><td>37.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.99</td><td>38.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.01</td><td>1.96E-01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Ear weight (g)</td><td>E1</td><td>181.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;22.35</td><td>204.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.75**</td><td>8.87E-03</td></tr><tr><td>E2</td><td>118.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.79</td><td>125.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.38*</td><td>2.78E-02</td></tr><tr><td>E3</td><td>211.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.70</td><td>225.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.34*</td><td>3.85E-02</td></tr><tr><td>E4</td><td>195.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.54</td><td>216.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;24.13*</td><td>2.74E-02</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>E1, E2, E3, and E4 represent Xinxiang and Hebi in 2015 and Xinxiang and Hebi in 2016, respectively.</p><p>*<sup>,</sup> ** indicate significant differences at the 0.05 and 0.01 probability levels, respectively.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Global metabolomics</title><p id="Par10">Considerable differences in the secondary metabolite profiles of ears collected at the FM stage were observed (see Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). A total of 256 metabolites were identified in each hybrid and inbred line. A PCA was completed to objectively interpret the metabolomics data for the analyzed hybrids and inbred lines. All samples could be divided into four groups based on the 256 metabolites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Moreover, 42.4% of the variance in the total data was explained by the first two principal components. An obvious separation between the inbred lines and their corresponding hybrids was detected for PC1, which explained 28.6% of the variance. A clear separation between hybrids was also observed for PC2, which explained 13.8% of the variance. Moreover, two inbred lines, sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and lx9801, were distributed together along the Y-axis. The PCA model also revealed a generally good biological reproducibility within groups because the three biological replicates of each sample exhibited satisfactory clustering. The general trends for Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 indicated their metabolite profiles were similar. This observation was supported by the fact Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 were clustered in one subclass (see Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Moreover, two inbred lines, lx9801 and sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>, clustered more with each other than with the hybrid lines (see Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). These results implied that the metabolic activities of the hybrids and inbred lines are likely different during the early stage of maize ear development.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Principal component analysis score plots. The first two principal component (PCs) explained 42.4% of the variation. Additionally, PC1 separated the hybrid lines from the inbred lines, and explained 28.6% of the variation. Meanwhile, PC2 explained 13.8% of the variation, indicating the hybrid lines could be discriminated from the inbred lines. Three biological replicates of each sample were clustered in the same quadrant. HY: Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>; CK: Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36446_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e907"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Metabolite-specific accumulation</title><p id="Par11">Partial least-squares-discriminant analysis (PLS-DA) model is a statistical method for supervised classification that can be exploited to predict the group among new and unlabeled samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Thus, the PLS-DA supervised multivariate analysis was used to maximize the variance among groups and identify specific metabolites. We applied this model to identify the metabolites that were differentially abundant in the hybrid lines. On the basis of the PLS-DA score plots, we observed an obvious separation between the hybrids regarding the first component (R<sup>2</sup>X&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.478, R<sup>2</sup>Y&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.997, Q<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.749) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). This observation indicated the inter-group differences were significant. Additionally, 31 metabolites were differentially abundant between Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Moreover, the PLS-DA results for the two inbred lines revealed that sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> was markedly different from lx9801 (R<sup>2</sup>X&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.702, R<sup>2</sup>Y&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.999, and Q<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.974) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>). A total of 24 differentially abundant metabolites were identified based on the VIP and fold-change ratio thresholds (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Partial least squares discriminant scores plot. (<bold>A</bold>) Principal component 1 (PC1) and PC2 explained 31.4% and 16.4% of the variation, respectively, indicating Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> (HY) could be discriminated from Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (CK). (<bold>B</bold>) PC1 and PC2 explained 21% and 18.2% of the variation, illustrating the separation between sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and lx9801. R<sup>2</sup>X, R<sup>2</sup>Y, and Q<sup>2</sup> refer to the interpretation and predictability values of the partial least squares discriminant analysis models.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36446_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e985"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Identified metabolites significantly differentially accumulated in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Compound name</th><th>Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801</th><th>Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub></th><th>Fold change</th><th>VIP<sup>a</sup></th><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">ALKALOIDS</td><td>Papaverine</td><td>4.50E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.88E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>0.64</td><td>1.38</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>Trigonelline</td><td>3.80E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>6.42E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.69</td><td>1.84</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">AMINO ACID DERIVATIVES</td><td>Aspartic acid O-rutinoside</td><td>7.12E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>4.41E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>0.62</td><td>1.73</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>Phenylglycine</td><td>1.28E&#x02009;+&#x02009;06</td><td>3.21E&#x02009;+&#x02009;06</td><td>2.52</td><td>2.17</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>3-(2-Naphthyl)-D-alanine</td><td>3.81E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.65E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>4.33</td><td>2.79</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Homocystine</td><td>2.49E&#x02009;+&#x02009;06</td><td>4.24E&#x02009;+&#x02009;06</td><td>1.70</td><td>1.61</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">CARBOHYDRATES</td><td>D(-)-Threose</td><td>1.07E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.67E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.56</td><td>1.29</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Sucrose</td><td>2.31E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>4.99E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>2.16</td><td>2.29</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>CHOLINES</td><td>Carbachol</td><td>1.41E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.95E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.09</td><td>2.13</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>COUMARINS AND ITS DERIVATIVES</td><td>4-Methylumbelliferone</td><td>4.74E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>3.00E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>0.63</td><td>1.39</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">FLAVONOID</td><td>Tricetin</td><td>1.42E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>3.16E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>0.02</td><td>2.40</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>C-hexosyl-apigenin C-pentoside</td><td>3.76E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>2.43E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>0.65</td><td>1.53</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>Quercetin O-rutinoside</td><td>2.74E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>4.24E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.55</td><td>1.52</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">LIPIDS-GLYCEROPHOSPHOLIPID</td><td>LysoPC 20:1</td><td>4.08E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>6.40E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.57</td><td>1.66</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>LysoPC 20:2</td><td>1.40E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>2.34E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.67</td><td>1.64</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">NUCLEOTIDE AND ITS DERIVATES</td><td>beta-Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide</td><td>3.53E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>2.29E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>0.65</td><td>1.41</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>Inosine</td><td>2.01E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.33E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>0.66</td><td>1.48</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>Guanine</td><td>1.09E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.77E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.62</td><td>1.58</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>2&#x02032;-Deoxyadenosine monohydrate</td><td>8.56E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.67E&#x02009;+&#x02009;06</td><td>1.96</td><td>1.82</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Guanosine 5&#x02032;-monophosphate</td><td>5.23E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.04E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.99</td><td>1.84</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Thymine</td><td>1.57E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>3.48E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>2.22</td><td>1.93</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">PHENYLPROPANOIDS</td><td>Sinapoyl O-hexoside</td><td>8.90E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.00E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>2.25</td><td>1.96</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Sinapic acid</td><td>2.04E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>4.81E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.36</td><td>2.25</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Geranyl acetate</td><td>1.32E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>4.74E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>3.60</td><td>2.95</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">PHYTOHORMONES</td><td>Kinetin riboside</td><td>4.68E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>7.64E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.63</td><td>1.67</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>trans-Zeatin riboside (tZR)</td><td>4.02E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>6.98E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.74</td><td>1.82</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">TERPENOIDS</td><td>Phytocassane C</td><td>9.95E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.72E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.73</td><td>1.96</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Gentiopicrin</td><td>9.36E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>2.37E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.53</td><td>2.35</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>TRYPTAMINES AND ITS DERIVATIVES</td><td>N-acetyltryptamine</td><td>1.71E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>2.56E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.50</td><td>1.33</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">VITAMINE RELATED</td><td>4-Pyridoxic acid O-hexoside</td><td>1.16E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.84E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.59</td><td>1.75</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Nicotinamide</td><td>3.18E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>5.43E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.71</td><td>1.46</td><td>up</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Variable importance in the projection (VIP) values were obtained from PLS-DA with the threshold of 1.00.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Identified metabolites significantly differentially accumulated in lx9801 and sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Compound name</th><th>lx9801</th><th>sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub></th><th>Fold change</th><th>VIP<sup>a</sup></th><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4">AMINO ACID</td><td>N,N-Dimethylglycine</td><td>3.78E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.31E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>0.61</td><td>1.89</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>Glu-Glu</td><td>3.80E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.40E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>0.63</td><td>1.78</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>Aspartic acid O-rutinoside</td><td>5.40E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.03E&#x02009;+&#x02009;06</td><td>1.91</td><td>1.97</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>L-(&#x02212;)-Threonine</td><td>6.53E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.00E&#x02009;+&#x02009;06</td><td>1.53</td><td>1.51</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>CARBOHYDRATES</td><td>D(&#x02212;)-Threose</td><td>8.02E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.68E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.09</td><td>1.95</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>CHOLINES</td><td>sn-Glycero-3-phosphocholine</td><td>4.60E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>7.07E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.54</td><td>1.02</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>COUMARINS</td><td>4-Methylumbelliferone</td><td>1.43E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.38E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.66</td><td>1.79</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">FLAVONOID</td><td>Cyanidin 3-O-glucoside</td><td>5.78E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>7.53E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>0.13</td><td>3.77</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>Tangeretin</td><td>1.82E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>7.40E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>0.41</td><td>1.81</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>Tricetin</td><td>4.75E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>2.63E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>0.55</td><td>1.03</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>LIPIDS-GLYCEROPHOSPHOLIPID</td><td>LysoPC 20:1</td><td>4.53E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>7.14E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.58</td><td>1.42</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>NUCLEOTIDE</td><td>5&#x02032;-Deoxy-5&#x02032;-Methylthioadenosine</td><td>5.90E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>8.86E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.50</td><td>1.53</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>ORGANIC ACID</td><td>Ergothioneine</td><td>4.72E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.42E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>0.51</td><td>2.29</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>PHENOLAMIDES</td><td>N-Feruloyl spermidine</td><td>5.17E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>9.45E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.83</td><td>2.15</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">PHENYLPROPANOIDS</td><td>Sinapoyl O-hexoside</td><td>1.58E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>2.41E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.52</td><td>1.45</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Coumarin</td><td>3.67E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>5.96E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.63</td><td>1.63</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>Quinic acid</td><td>6.39E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.07E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.68</td><td>1.65</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">PHYTOHORMONES</td><td>N-[(&#x02212;)-Jasmonoyl]-(L)-Isoleucine (JA-Ile)</td><td>3.20E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>1.04E&#x02009;+&#x02009;03</td><td>0.33</td><td>2.52</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>(+)-Jasmonic acid (JA)</td><td>2.14E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.10E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>0.51</td><td>2.00</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>(+)-<italic>cis,trans</italic>-Abscisic acid (ABA)</td><td>2.57E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>4.29E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>1.67</td><td>1.87</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>trans-Zeatin (tZ)</td><td>1.88E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>3.66E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.95</td><td>2.31</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td>TERPENOIDS</td><td>Diosgenin</td><td>1.75E&#x02009;+&#x02009;06</td><td>2.91E&#x02009;+&#x02009;06</td><td>1.66</td><td>2.10</td><td>up</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">VITAMINE</td><td>Nicotinate ribonucleoside</td><td>1.79E&#x02009;+&#x02009;05</td><td>9.55E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>0.53</td><td>2.09</td><td>down</td></tr><tr><td>(S)-(+)-2-(anilinomethyl)pyrrolidine</td><td>1.56E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>2.48E&#x02009;+&#x02009;04</td><td>1.59</td><td/><td>up</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>(a) Variable importance in the projection (VIP) values were obtained from PLS-DA with the threshold of 1.00.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par12">A Venn diagram revealed six common metabolites in both comparison groups (i.e., Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> vs. Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 and sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> vs. lx9801). Furthermore, 25 metabolites were differentially accumulated between Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801, while 18 metabolites were only differentially accumulated between sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and lx9801 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref>). Of all the differentially abundant metabolites, 24 and 15 metabolites were upregulated, while seven and nine metabolites were downregulated in the Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> vs. Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 and sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> vs. lx9801 comparisons, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). Clearly, many metabolites identified in the current study by metabolomics presenting further evidence to understand metabolic processes that might involve in heterosis.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Differentially accumulated metabolites between hybrid and inbred lines. (<bold>A</bold>) Venn diagram of differentially accumulated metabolites in sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and lx9801 as well as in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> (HY) and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (CK). (<bold>B</bold>) Number of differentially accumulated metabolites in hybrids and inbred lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36446_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2251"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Secondary metabolite biosynthetic pathway</title><p id="Par13">To fully characterize the pathways that maybe involve in heterosis during an early stage of ear development, a network was constructed based on differentially abundant metabolites in the two hybrids. In this study, regarding nucleotide metabolism, guanosine 5&#x02032;-monophosphate (GMP) belongs to purine nucleotide was 1.99-fold higher in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801, and guanine as an important compounds of GMP having the same trend was 1.62-fold higher in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). Additionally, under the catalysis of structural genes, the flux of inosine to tZR monophosphate was enhanced in the trans-zeatin riboside (tZR) biosynthetic pathway and tZR monophosphate can be further hydrolyzed to tZR. Consequently, the tZR abundance was 1.74-fold higher in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). In terms of the nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolic pathway, the abundance of nicotinamide showed 1.71-fold increments in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 and nicotinamide as the precursor for synthesizing trigonelline may be also supported the higher accumulation of trigonelline (1.69-fold increments) in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Integrated metabolite changes and differentially expressed genes for analyzing the secondary metabolite biosynthetic pathways. Differentially accumulated metabolites indicated in red and blue were upregulated and downregulated, respectively. The red-to-blue colors in squares indicate high-to-low gene expression levels, respectively. (<bold>A</bold>) surE, 5&#x02032;-nucleotidase; IMPDH, inosine-5&#x02032;-phosphate dehydrogenase; GMPS, guanosine 5&#x02032;-monophosphate synthetase; APRT, adenine phosphoribosyl transferase; ADA, adenosine deaminase; ADK, adenosine kinase; CYP735A, cytokinin <italic>trans</italic>-hydroxylase; (<bold>B</bold>) NMNAT, nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyltransferase; SDT1, pyrimidine and pyridine-specific 5&#x02032;-nucleotidase; URH1, uridine nucleosidase; PNC1, nicotinamidase; NNM, nicotinamide <italic>N</italic>-methyltransferase.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36446_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2302"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Gene expression pattern analysis</title><p id="Par14">Most secondary metabolic pathways are regulated at the gene expression level. To investigate the expression of key genes, we completed quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) analyses. A total of 15 candidate genes associated with major secondary metabolic pathways were selected for an analysis of the secondary metabolism related to heterosis during the early stage of maize ear development. During the nucleotide metabolism, the genes of <italic>surE</italic> [5&#x02032;-nucleotidase; one differentially expressed gene (DEG)], <italic>IMPDH</italic> (inosine-5&#x02032;-phosphate dehydrogenase; three DEGs) and <italic>GMPS</italic> (guanosine 5&#x02032;-monophosphate synthetase; one DEG) that involved in the purine metabolic pathway were expressed at lower levels in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). These results implied that the conversion of inosine to GMP was less efficiency in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801. In contrast, the expression levels of several genes were upregulated in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>, including <italic>APRT</italic> (adenine phosphoribosyl transferase; two DEGs), <italic>ADA</italic> (adenosine deaminase; one DEG), and <italic>ADK</italic> (adenosine kinase; two DEGs) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Meanwhile, the expression of <italic>CYP735A</italic> (cytokinin trans-hydroxylase; two DEGs), which is involved in zeatin biosynthetic pathways, was significantly upregulated in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). These genes expression pattern were responsible for the increased biosynthesis of tZR in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Relative expression levels of genes in secondary metabolite biosynthetic pathways as determined by qRT-PCR. Relative expression levels are presented as the mean of three replicates&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error. HY: Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>; CK: Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801. * and **Indicate significant differences at P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, respectively, as determined by a one-way ANOVA with Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36446_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2369"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">In the nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolic pathway, the expression of <italic>NMNAT</italic> (nicotinamide mononucleotide adenylyl transferase; one DEG), which is an important structural gene related to nicotinamide mononucleotide (NaMN) synthesis, was significantly upregulated in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Additionally, <italic>SDT1</italic>(pyrimidine and pyridine-specific 5&#x02032;-nucleotidase; one DEG) was one of the most significantly upregulated DEGs (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.25E&#x02212;03) in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> vs. Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 group. Meanwhile, <italic>URH1</italic>(uridine nucleosidase; one DEG) catalyzing nicotinamide riboside (NR) to nicotinamide was upregulated in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). These results are consistent with our metabolomics analysis that trigonelline contents were higher in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Application of a CSSL test population to investigate the genetic basis of heterosis</title><p id="Par16">Heterosis is considerably influenced by the genetic background and environmental conditions. In previous studies, several primary segregated populations, such as BC<sub>1</sub>, F<sub>2</sub>, and F<sub>2:3</sub>, were used to study the genetic basis of heterosis. However, these populations represent temporary genotypes, making it difficult to obtain accurate phenotypic values over multiple years. To overcome the shortcomings of these populations, several permanently segregated populations, such as introgression lines and immortalized F<sub>2</sub> (IF<sub>2</sub>) populations, have been developed for identifying heterotic loci<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Hua <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> identified 44 HLs for grain yield and yield-related components in rice using IF<sub>2</sub> population that were developed from paired crosses of recombinant inbred lines, while Tang <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> detected 13 HLs for grain yield and its components in maize using the same genetic population. Compared with the primary segregated population and other permanently segregated population, the CSSLs and receptor parent test hybrids used in this study may be more appropriate for dissecting the genetic basis of heterosis. First, the influence of the genetic background can be eliminated during the identification of HLs in comparisons between the test population and the control hybrid Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801. Second, accurate phenotypic values may be obtained for the test hybrids under different environmental conditions during the identification of HLs.</p><p id="Par17">Predicting the generation of high-performance hybrids is an integral part of maize breeding. However, only small subsets of potential crosses have been evaluated under field conditions for selecting elite hybrids. Thus, predicting hybrid performance is important for breeding programs. Advanced molecular technologies enabled the acquisition of system-wide genome data for predicting hybrid performance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. High-throughput technologies were recently applied to accurately measure the accumulation of metabolites, resulting in large amounts of metabolomics data for analyzing rice hybrid performance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. In another study, Lima <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> detected more robust metabolite changes (e.g., organic acids and amino acids) in hybrid lines than in inbred lines. They also observed that a few secondary metabolites could be used as biological markers to predict heterosis. In this study, we conducted a metabolomics analysis with one CSSL and its receptor parent as well as test hybrids to identify nucleotides and their derivatives, alkaloids, flavonoids, phenolics, and phytohormones mediating heterosis for maize ear development. Our data suggested that several important metabolic pathways affect the heterosis for maize ear development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Differentially expressed genes associated with nucleotide metabolism and nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolism</title><p id="Par18">Biosynthetic and catabolic enzymes could regulate the pool size of nucleotides and nucleosides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. In this study, the enzyme of <italic>surE</italic> participated in the substrate cycles and influence the balance of nucleotides and nucleosides pools at the cellular levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, which have the lower expressed levels in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801. Additionally, the enzymes of <italic>IMPDH</italic> and <italic>GMPS</italic> exist in one branch of the guanine nucleotide synthesis and <italic>IMPDH</italic> controlling the gateway to guanine nucleotides for most organism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The conversion of inosine 5&#x02032;-monophosphate (IMP) to xanthosine 5&#x02032;-phosphate (XMP) is the first committed and rate-limiting step in guanine nucleotide biosynthesis, which was catalyzed by <italic>IMPDH</italic>. Subsequently, XMP is converted to GMP through the action of <italic>GMPS</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In this study, some genes in the same branch of guanine nucleotide biosynthetic pathway were expressed at lower levels in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801, including <italic>surE</italic>, <italic>IMPDH</italic> and <italic>GMPS</italic>. These observations suggested that the conversion of inosine to GMP was less activity in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801. Another branch of guanine nucleotide regeneration is the recycling of guanine. The <italic>APRT</italic> belongs to the phosphoribosyl transferases family. Each <italic>APRTs</italic> can reutilize purine bases (such as guanine), being substrates for the synthesis of high-energy nucleotides, and convert them into mononucleotides (such as GMP), instead of nucleotides <italic>de novo</italic> synthesis consuming high-energy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. In this branch of guanine nucleotide regeneration, two genes encoding <italic>APRT</italic> were significantly upregulated in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> comparing with in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801. This could largely explain the high accumulation of GMP in the Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>. Moreover, there are two enzymes potentially contribute to the adenosine metabolism in plant, <italic>ADA</italic> and <italic>ADK</italic>. One major route for adenosine salvage may be catalyzed by <italic>ADA</italic> in specific subcellular compartments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, and <italic>ADK</italic> as the housekeep enzymes phosphorylate adenosine to adenosine monophosphate (AMP) in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Moreover, in many organisms, AMP not only as an essential component in purine nucleotide pools, but also as the substrate be catalyzed to produce isopentenyladenine<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Furthermore, hydroxylation of isopentenyladenine was a key step, which was catalyzed by <italic>CYP735A</italic> in tZR biosynthetic pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. In this study, some upregulated expression genes involved in the adenosine metabolism including <italic>ADA</italic>, <italic>ADK</italic> and in the trans-zeatin riboside (tZR) biosynthetic pathway including <italic>CYP735A</italic> were recruited in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>, implied that expression pattern of these genes might be responsible for the increased biosynthesis of tZR in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>.</p><p id="Par19">In the nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolic pathway, the expression of <italic>NMNAT</italic>, as the central enzyme to control this conversion of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NAD) to NaMN<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>, was significantly upregulated in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>. In addition, <italic>SDT1</italic> are responsible for production of NR in cells and its activity is correlates with reduced cellular NAD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, which was one of the most significantly DEGs between Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801. These two enzymes have significant impact on the cellular NAD homeostasis, which are the regular steps in NAD metabolism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Moreover, <italic>URH1</italic>, as an apparent hydrolytic enzyme, makes a greater contribution to the conversion of NR to nicotinamide, and maintains the higher expression levels than other enzymes in this pathway of NR to nicotinamide salvage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The expression of <italic>URH1</italic> was upregulated in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>, which may result in the higher accumulation of nicotinamide in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801, thus, more trigonelline was synthesized from the nicotinamide.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Nucleotide and phytohormone metabolism</title><p id="Par20">Purine and pyrimidine nucleotides are precursors for the synthesis of primary and secondary products as well as the building blocks for nucleic acids. In higher plants, GMP can be used as a feedback signal to terminate the pathway responsible for <italic>de novo</italic> guanine nucleotide biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Salvage pathways are essential for the biosynthesis of nucleic acids in all organisms. In plants, they also help regenerate nucleotide pools by converting nucleosides to nucleotides, and they contribute to plant cell metabolism and catabolism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. To preserve energy, the purine salvage pathway is activated to regenerate guanine from GMP, while consuming only one adenosine triphosphate (ATP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Guanine nucleotides are important components of nucleotide pools. A small increase in nucleotide pools is accompanied by an increase in carbohydrate content<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. In the present study, the purine salvage pathway affected the accumulation of GMP and guanine, with higher levels in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801. These results may be explained by the fact that carbohydrates, such as sucrose (2.16-fold change) and D-(&#x02212;)-threose (1.56-fold change), accumulated more in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Additionally, carbohydrate synthesis might be limited by the nucleotide supply. Moreover, high sugar concentrations may provide sufficient nutrients for vigorous tissue morphogenesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par21">The conversion of inosine to AMP occurs by sequential reactions catalyzed by <italic>ADA</italic> and <italic>ADK</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. A previous study reported that the first step of cytokinin biosynthesis was the isopentenylation of AMP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Thus, AMP is a direct precursor involved in cytokinin synthesis. Cytokinin free bases, such as tZR and isopentenyl adenine, are physiologically active in plant tissues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. The disequilibrium distribution of tZR is a key signal for organ-to-organ communication and positively regulates various growth and developmental processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. As the cell cycle progresses, tZR seems to activate cell division during the early part of the S phase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. In this study, the tZR differentially accumulated in the two hybrids. Moreover, the upregulated expression of <italic>CYP375A</italic>, which encodes a cytokinin hydroxylase, enhanced tZR synthesis in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> by releasing active cytokinins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, which may be important for cell division and the early stage of maize ear development. These results implied that tZR may contribute to the heterosis of maize ear development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Alkaloid metabolism</title><p id="Par22">Nicotinamide is a vitamin B3 precursor that functions as a fundamental mediator of diverse biological processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. In higher plants, including <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, nicotinamide is likely converted to nicotinic acid and salvaged for NAD biosynthesis, which is generally active in vigorously growing cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Previous studies involving tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana sylvestris</italic>) provided evidence that NAD is an important coenzyme for photosynthesis and plant stress responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. Additionally, trigonelline synthesis during seed germination may contribute to the detoxification of surplus nicotinamide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Moreover, trigonelline induces cell expansion, which is an important determinant of grain width<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. In this study, the abundance of trigonelline (1.69-fold change) and nicotinamide (1.71-fold change) increased in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Thus, nicotinamide and trigonelline may be involved in the heterotic performance during the early stage of ear development. These findings implied that nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolism was more active in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Flavonoid and phenolic metabolism</title><p id="Par23">Flavonoids are common and widespread plant secondary metabolites that affect numerous physiological activities, including the negative regulation of auxin transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. Phosphoglycoprotein is an auxin transporter that requires the hydrolysis of ATP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. The <italic>PIN</italic> expression pattern and the subcellular localization of the encoded protein are consistent with the fact PIN functions in polar auxin transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Flavonoids appear to alter PIN cycling, possibly because of induced changes in auxin concentrations via modulated auxin transport directly mediated by phosphoglycoprotein, rather than through an interaction with PIN<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Additionally, C-hexosyl-apigenin C-pentoside was detected as a major flavonoid compound, with lower accumulation in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801. These results indicated that flavonoids were more abundant in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>, thereby inhibiting the transport of indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) and influencing the early stage of maize ear inflorescence development. Moreover, we also detected other flavonoids. For example, tricetin is a flavonoid exhibiting cytostatic properties by inducing the production of endogenous reactive oxygen species involved in apoptosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. Tricetin concentrations were higher in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), but were similar between inbred line lx9801 and sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). These results revealed that the elevated levels of intracellular flavonoids adversely affected cell growth and development by regulating apoptosis, with potential implications for heterosis in maize.</p><p id="Par24">Several known phenolic compounds, such as phenylpropanoids and coumarins, have been classified as natural regulators of plant growth, with phenylpropanoids important for responses to abscisic acid (ABA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. Abscisic acid is a major regulator of plant development, including seed dormancy and germination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. Sinapic acid is a small natural molecule from the phenylpropanoid family that might be imbibed into seeds, where it is converted into sinapic acid esters that regulate ABA homeostasis and may promote early seed germination in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. In this study, sinapic acid concentrations were more than 2-fold higher in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Thus, sinapic acid might interfere with ABA homeostasis to induce early maize ear inflorescence growth in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>.</p><p id="Par25">Auxin biosynthesis and transport promote heterosis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. Regarding auxin distribution, PIN is the crucial factor facilitating polar auxin transport, while SLR/IAA14 is a key mediator of auxin redistribution that is regulated by 4-methylumbelliferone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. In this study, 4-methylumbelliferone was detected during the early development of maize ear inflorescences. Additionally, 4-methylumbelliferone accumulated more in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 than in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), implying that it might restrict the IAA redistribution in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 and interfere with maize ear growth and development in the FM stage. These results provide new evidence that changes to phenolic compounds influence heterosis in maize.</p><p id="Par26">In this study, variations in gene expression patterns and metabolite contents were analyzed in maize ear inflorescences in CSSL, lx9801, and their corresponding hybrid lines. Additionally, a large-scale targeted metabolomics analysis revealed 24&#x02009;metabolites that were differentially accumulated between inbred lines, while the contents of 31 metabolites were significantly different in the hybrid lines. The variability in the abundance of metabolites, including nucleotides, alkaloids, flavonoids, and phenolics, as well as in gene expression levels were associated with many biological processes, such as carbohydrate synthesis, cell division and apoptosis, and phytohormone transport and distribution. This study offers novel insights into the influence on secondary metabolism related to heterosis and provides additional information on the mechanism of secondary metabolic pathway involving in heterosis at the metabolomics level.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Plant materials and the field experiment</title><p id="Par27">Previously, a maize CSSL panel of 184 lines was developed used two maize inbred lines (Chang7-2 as donor parent and lx9801 as the receptor parent), and a corresponding testcross population was constructed by crossing the CSSL panel with a test parent Zheng58. Of the 169 heterotic loci (HL) associated with grain yield were detected in the testcross population of Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;CSSL after comparing with the control hybrid Ludan9002 (Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. A maize CSSL<sub>125</sub> line carrying the HL <italic>hlEW2b</italic> was obtained from one of the CSSL test hybrids (Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;CSSL<sub>125</sub>) with an ear width significantly different from that of Ludan9002<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. In this study, various mapping populations, including backcross and inbred populations, were developed in the winter of 2013 (for backcrossing) in Sanya, Hainan province, China (E18&#x000b0;15&#x02032;, N109&#x000b0;30&#x02032;) and in the summer of 2014 (for selfing) in Xinxiang, Henan province, China (E113&#x000b0;31&#x02032;, N35&#x000b0;11&#x02032;). The sub-CSSL test population was constructed by crossing sub-CSSLs with Zheng58 in the winter of 2014 in Sanya. Additionally, the phenotypes of the sub-CSSL test population and the control hybrid, Ludan9002, were evaluated at two locations, Xinxiang and Hebi (E114&#x000b0;17&#x02032;, N35&#x000b0;90&#x02032;), in 2014 and 2015. Plants were grown with two replicates and a randomized complete block design. The control hybrid was also planted after every five testcross plants. Plots consisted of two rows (4 m long and 0.6&#x02009;m wide) that were separated by 0.22&#x02009;m. The final plant density was 67,500 plants per hectare. The plants were grown using standard agricultural practices.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Phenotypic data collection and fine mapping</title><p id="Par28">A maize inbred line, sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub>, which contained the shortest donor chromosomal segment harboring <italic>hlEW2b</italic>, was compared with other homozygous lines in the sub-CSSL population. Two inbred lines, sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and lx9801, along with their corresponding testcrosses, Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801, were planted in two-row plots in four environments (Xinxiang and Hebi in 2015 and 2016). In each plot, 10 ears were harvested at physiological maturity for phenotypic measurements. Ear length (cm), ear width (mm), ear weight (g), kernel row number, and kernel number per row were measured using standard procedures to confirm the presence of <italic>hlEW2b</italic>. Raw data underwent a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) using the SPSS 17.0 program (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). The HL associated with ear width were considered to exist in sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> when the ear width in Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> differed significantly from that of Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801 (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p><p id="Par29">In this study, we developed molecular markers for fine mapping. The simple sequence repeat (SSR) markers in the region flanked by umc1555 and umc1465 on chromosome 2 were obtained from the IBM 2008 Neighbors maize linkage map (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.maizegdb.org/data_center/map">http://www.maizegdb.org/data_center/map</ext-link>). Additionally, SSR sites were identified with the SSR Hunter program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. Primers were designed using the Primer 5.0 program (Premier Biosoft International, Palo Alto, CA, USA). Details regarding the primers used for mapping are listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>. Furthermore, possible candidate genes were identified for <italic>hlEW2b</italic> within 1.98-Mb region based on the filtered working gene list of the maize genome downloaded from MaizeGDB (Zea mays. AGPv4.37, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.maizegdb.org">http://www.maizegdb.org</ext-link>). Candidate genes were annotated according to InterProScan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/scan.html">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/scan.html</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Sample preparation</title><p id="Par30">Two hybrids, Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and Zheng58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;lx9801, as well as their corresponding inbred lines, sub-CSSL<sub>16</sub> and lx9801, were planted at the experimental station of Henan Agricultural University (Zhengzhou, China; E113&#x000b0;65&#x02032;, N34&#x000b0;76&#x02032;) on June 20, 2016. The ear development stage was confirmed based on the leaf age index and microscopic observation. Immature ears at the FM development stage were collected. Three biological replicates were collected for each sample, which comprised five randomly collected fresh immature ears. All samples were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C prior to metabolite analyses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Metabolite identification and quantification</title><p id="Par31">Samples were freeze-dried in a vacuum and then homogenized using an Retsch MM400 Mixer Mill (RETSCH GmbH, Haan, Germany) with zirconia beads (90&#x02009;s at 30&#x02009;Hz). Metabolites were extracted from 100&#x02009;mg powder with 70% aqueous methanol containing 0.1&#x02009;mg/L lidocaine. Samples were incubated overnight at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and then centrifuged at 10,000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;g for 10&#x02009;min. A 400-&#x000b5;L aliquot of the extract was filtered through an SCAA-104 membrane (0.22&#x02009;&#x000b5;m pore size; Millipore), and the filtrate was stored in sample bottles for a subsequent analysis by liquid chromatography (LC) and tandem mass spectrometry (MS/MS). The LC-MS/MS analysis was completed with a Shim-pack UFLC Shimadzu CBM30A HPLC system and a 4500 QTRAP ESI&#x02013;triple quadrupole&#x02013;linear ion trap mass spectrometer (Applied Biosystems) equipped with an ESI Turbo Ion-Spray interface, which was operated in a positive ion mode and controlled with the Analyst 1.6 program (AB/SCIEX, Framingham, MA, USA).</p><p id="Par32">Metabolites were identified and quantified according to a published protocol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>. Briefly, the multiple reaction monitoring model was applied to identify the precursor ion of the target material. Many ion fragments were formed after a collision-induced dissociation, and characteristic ions were filtered from the fragment ions. The retention time and mass-to-charge ratio were measured for all detectable ions. Metabolites were quantified according to integral correction and normalization methods for analyzing mass spectra for metabolites in different samples (i.e., peak area evaluation). Metabolites were analyzed qualitatively and quantitatively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Metabolite data analysis</title><p id="Par33">Metabolite data were log<sub>2</sub>-transformed before undergoing a multivariate statistical analysis with the SIMCA-P 13.0 program (Umetrics, Ume&#x000e5;, Sweden). The data then underwent an unsupervised principal component analysis (PCA), which is a widely used unsupervised dimensionality reduction method, to visualize general clustering and trends among the samples. To identify differentially accumulated metabolites for each group, the partial least squares discriminant analysis (PLS-DA) was applied to remove irrelevant variables and maximize the variance among samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. The efficiency and reliability of the PLS-DA model was assessed by a cross-validation with R<sup>2</sup>. The predictive performance was described by the Q<sup>2</sup> model. The variable importance in the projection (VIP) reflected the contribution of each variable to the model. Variables with a VIP value&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0 were considered to influence the separation of samples in the PLS-DA score plots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>. In addition to the multivariate approaches, fold-change ratios were used to assess the significance of each metabolite. A VIP value&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0 and a fold-change ratio &#x02265;1.5 or &#x02264;0.67 were set as the thresholds for screening potential metabolites with significant differences in abundance between samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>RNA extraction and quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) analysis</title><p id="Par34">Total RNA was extracted from each sample using the Trizol<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and then treated with DNase I. The quality of the purified RNA (i.e., degradation and contamination) was characterized by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis and with the Nano LabChip kit (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). Purified RNA was quantified at OD260nm by using a NanoDrop&#x02122; One (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Wilmington, DE, USA). The RNA was then used as the template for a reverse transcription with the PrimeScript&#x02122; RT reagent kit with gDNA Eraser (Takara, Japan). A quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) assay was conducted with the SYBR Premix Ex Taq Kit (Takara) and the BioRad iQ Cycler (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02032;s instructions. The Primer 5.0 program was used to design the qRT-PCR primers, which are listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>. Each sample was analyzed using three biological replicates and three technical replicates. The 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> method was applied to estimate relative gene expression levels. Additionally, gene expression data underwent a one-way ANOVA with the SPSS 17.0 program. The significance threshold was set as P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec22"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_36446_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Xia Shi and Xuehai Zhang contributed equally.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-36446-5.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was financially supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (91335205), the Central Plains Scholar of Henan, and the Major Science and Technology Programs of Henan Province (161100110500), the Henan Province Science and Technology Attack Project (152102110062, 182102110349).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>J.T. and W.L. designed the experiments and together with, X.S. and X.Z. carried out data analysis. X.S., D.S. and X.Z. carried out maize morphological investigation, validation of gene expression level. X.S., X.Z. and J.T. was mainly involved in preparation of manuscript. All authors reviewed and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shull</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The composition of a field of maize</article-title><source>Journal of Heredity</source><year>1908</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/os-4.1.296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lippman</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterosis: revisiting the magic</article-title><source>Trends in Genetics</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2006.12.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17188398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17188398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippman</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The flowering gene SINGLE FLOWER TRUSS drives heterosis for yield in tomato</article-title><source>Nature genetics</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.550</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20348958?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20348958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogra</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Birchler</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic dosage effects on heterosis in triploid maize</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>2665</fpage><lpage>2669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1221966110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23359717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23359717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frisch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome-based distance measures for grouping of germplasm and prediction of hybrid performance in maize</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-009-1204-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19911157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19911157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groszmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in 24-nt siRNA levels in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> hybrids suggest an epigenetic contribution to hybrid vigor</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>2617</fpage><lpage>2622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1019217108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21266545?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21266545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dooner</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intraspecific violation of genetic colinearity and its implications in maize</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>9573</fpage><lpage>9578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.132259199</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12060715?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12060715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide genetic changes during modern breeding of maize</article-title><source>Nature genetics</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2312</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22660547?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22660547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swanson-Wagner</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>All possible modes of gene action are observed in a global comparison of gene expression in a maize F<sub>1</sub> hybrid and its inbred parents</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>6805</fpage><lpage>6810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0510430103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16641103?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16641103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specific changes in total and mitochondrial proteomes are associated with higher levels of heterosis in maize hybrids</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2012</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2012.05056.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22607058?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22607058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overdominant quantitative trait loci for yield and fitness in tomato</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>12981</fpage><lpage>12986</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0604635103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16938842?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16938842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of Indica rice chromosome segments for the improvement of Japonica inbreds and hybrids</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-1792-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22311371?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22311371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dominance and epistasis are the main contributors to heterosis for plant height in rice</article-title><source>Plant Science</source><year>2014</year><volume>215&#x02013;216</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2013.10.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24388510?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24388510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heterotic loci for various morphological traits of maize detected using a single segment substitution lines test-cross population</article-title><source>Molecular Breeding</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-015-0287-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riedelsheimer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic and metabolic prediction of complex heterotic traits in hybrid maize</article-title><source>Nature genetics</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.1033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22246502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22246502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolomic Prediction of Yield in Hybrid Rice</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2016</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13242</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27311694?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27311694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between differential gene expression and heterosis during ear development in Maize (<italic>Zea mays L</italic>.)</article-title><source>J Genet Genomics.</source><year>2007</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1673-8527(07)60017-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17469788?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17469788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of gene expression profiles during ear development of maize</article-title><source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><year>2009</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-009-9457-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19160056?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19160056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A robust, high-throughput method for computing maize ear, cob, and kernel attributes automatically from images</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2016</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13320</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27585732?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27585732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome profiling and comparison of maize ear heterosis during the spikelet and floret differentiation stages</article-title><source>Bmc Genomics</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>976</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-3296-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27875998?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27875998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of heterotic loci associated with grain yield and its components using two CSSL test populations in maize</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>38205</fpage><lpage>38218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep38205</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27917917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27917917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> DDB1-CUL4 ASSOCIATED FACTOR1 forms a nuclear E3 ubiquitin ligase with DDB1 and CUL4 that is involved in multiple plant developmental processes</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1437</fpage><lpage>1455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.108.058891</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18552200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18552200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranocha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Walls are thin 1 (<italic>WAT1</italic>), an <italic>Arabidopsis homolog</italic> of <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> NODULIN21, is a tonoplast-localized protein required for secondary wall formation in fibers</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04256.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20497379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20497379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic composition of yield heterosis in an elite rice hybrid</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>15847</fpage><lpage>15852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1214141109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23019369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23019369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multivariate analysis in metabolomics</article-title><source>Curr Metabolomics.</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/2213235X11301010092</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26078916?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26078916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of combining ability loci for five yield-related traits in maize using a set of testcrosses with introgression lines</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-1985-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23011316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23011316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-locus heterotic effects and dominance by dominance interactions can adequately explain the genetic basis of heterosis in an elite rice hybrid</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>2574</fpage><lpage>2579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0437907100</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12604771?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12604771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dissection of the genetic basis of heterosis in an elite maize hybrid by QTL mapping in an immortalized F<sub>2</sub> population</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-009-1213-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19936698?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lima, F. A. <italic>et al</italic>. Metabolic robustness in young roots underpins a predictive model of maize hybrid performance in the field. <italic>Plant J</italic>. <bold>90</bold>, 10.1111/tpj.13495 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reichard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between deoxyribonucleotide and DNA synthesis</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem.</source><year>1988</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bi.57.070188.002025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3052277?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3052277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rampazzo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial deoxyribonucleotides, pool sizes, synthesis, and regulation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>17019</fpage><lpage>17026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M313957200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14747464?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14747464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedstrom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IMP dehydrogenase: structure, mechanism and inhibition</article-title><source>Chem Rev.</source><year>2009</year><volume>109</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2903</fpage><lpage>2928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr900021w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19480389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19480389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baranowska-Bosiacka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of erythrocyte phosphoribosyltransferases (APRT and HPRT) by Pb<sup>2+</sup>: A potential mechanism of lead toxicity</article-title><source>Toxicology</source><year>2009</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2009.02.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19428946?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19428946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moffatt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applying high throughput techniques in the study of adenosine kinase in plant metabolism and development</article-title><source>Front Biosci.</source><year>2004</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1771</fpage><lpage>1781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2741/1346</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14977585?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14977585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zrenner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnewald</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Boldt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyrimidine and purine biosynthesis and degradation in plants</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.57.032905.105421</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16669783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16669783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moffatt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adenosine kinase of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Kinetic properties and gene expression</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>1775</fpage><lpage>1785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.124.4.1775</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11115893?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11115893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> CYP735A1 and CYP735A2 encode cytokinin hydroxylases that catalyze the biosynthesis of trans-Zeatin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>41866</fpage><lpage>41872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M406337200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15280363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15280363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Niere</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The NMN/NaMN adenylyltransferase (NMNAT) protein family</article-title><source>Front Biosci.</source><year>2009</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2741/3252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bogan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of Isn1 and Sdt1 as glucose- and vitamin-regulated nicotinamide mononucleotide and nicotinic acid mononucleotide 5&#x02032;-nucleotidases responsible for production of nicotinamide riboside and nicotinic acid riboside</article-title><source>J Biol Chem.</source><year>2009</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>34861</fpage><lpage>34869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.056689</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19846558?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19846558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belenky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gazzaniga</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pletnev</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nicotinamide riboside and nicotinic acid riboside salvage in fungi and mammals. Quantitative basis for Urh1 and purine nucleoside phosphorylase function in NAD<sup>+</sup> metabolism</article-title><source>J Biol Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M807976200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19001417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19001417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moffatt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purine and Pyrimidine Nucleotide Synthesis and Metabolism</article-title><source>Arabidopsis Book</source><year>2002</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>e0018</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1199/tab.0018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22303196?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22303196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stasolla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Katahira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purine and pyrimidine nucleotide metabolism in higher plants</article-title><source>J Plant Physiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>1271</fpage><lpage>1295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1078/0176-1617-01169</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14658380?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14658380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schr&#x000f6;der</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giermann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zrenner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of the pyrimidine de novo synthesis pathway in solanaceous species</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1926</fpage><lpage>1938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.063693</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16024685?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16024685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyofuku</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose metabolism for the development of seminal root in Maize seedlings</article-title><source>Plant Production Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1626/pps.12.9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gin&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of epithelial and lymphocyte cell adhesion by adenosine deaminase-CD26 interaction</article-title><source>Biochemical Journal</source><year>2002</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/0264-6021:3610203</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11772392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11772392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Escuyer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of a unique adenosine kinase from <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><year>2003</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>6548</fpage><lpage>6555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.185.22.6548-6555.2003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14594827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14594827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kakimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of cytokinins</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Research</source><year>2003</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10265-003-0095-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12721785?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12721785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fr&#x000e9;bort</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hluska</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fr&#x000e9;bortov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Galuszka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of cytokinin biosynthesis and degradation</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2011</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>2431</fpage><lpage>2452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21321050?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21321050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobrev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transient accumulation of cis - and trans -zeatin type cytokinins and its relation to cytokinin oxidase activity during cell cycle of synchronized tobacco BY-2 cells</article-title><source>Plant Physiology &#x00026; Biochemistry</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0981-9428(02)01383-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Holdsworth</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nicotinamidase activity is important for germination</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2007</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03151.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17587307?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17587307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic fate of nicotinamide in higher plants</article-title><source>Physiologia Plantarum</source><year>2007</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.2007.00959.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18251891?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18251891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutilleul</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional mitochondrial complex I is required by tobacco leaves for optimal photosynthetic performance in photorespiratory conditions and during transients</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.011155</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12529534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12529534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutilleul</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Leaf mitochondria modulate whole cell redox homeostasis, set antioxidant capacity, and determine stress resistance through altered signaling and diurnal regulation</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1212</fpage><lpage>1216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.009464</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12724545?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashibe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in trigonelline (N-methylnicotinic acid) content and nicotinic acid metabolism during germination of mungbean (<italic>Phaseolus aureus</italic>) seeds</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1615</fpage><lpage>1623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eri156</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15837705?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15837705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative and parallel genome-wide association studies for metabolic and agronomic traits in cereals</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>12767</fpage><lpage>12776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms12767</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27698483?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27698483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Flavonoids act as negative regulators of auxin transport <italic>in vivo</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.126.2.524</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11402184?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geisler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cellular efflux of auxin catalyzed by the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> MDR/PGP transporter AtPGP1</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02519.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16212599?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16212599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gravitropism of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> roots requires the polarization of PIN2 toward the root tip in meristematic cortical cells</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1762</fpage><lpage>1776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.110.075317</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20562236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20562236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peer</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variation in expression and protein localization of the PIN family of auxin efflux facilitator proteins in flavonoid mutants with altered auxin transport in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1898</fpage><lpage>1911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.021501</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15208397?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tricetin induces apoptosis of human leukemic HL-60 cells through a reactive oxygen species-mediated c-Jun N-terminal kinase activation pathway</article-title><source>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1667</fpage><lpage>1680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms18081667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medinapuche</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MYB10 plays a major role in the regulation of flavonoid/phenylpropanoid metabolism during ripening of <italic>Fragaria</italic>&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>ananassa</italic> fruits</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2014</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24277278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkelstein</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abscisic acid: emergence of a core signaling network</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042809-112122</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20192755?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sinapic acid or its derivatives interfere with abscisic acid homeostasis during <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seed germination</article-title><source>Bmc Plant Biology</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-017-1048-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28587634?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28587634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PIF4-controlled auxin pathway contributes to hybrid vigor in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>E3555</fpage><lpage>E3562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1703179114</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28396418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28396418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tameda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lateral root formation is blocked by a gain-of-function mutation in the SOLITARY-ROOT/IAA14 gene of <italic>Arabidopsi</italic>s</article-title><source>Plant Journal for Cell &#x00026; Molecular Biology</source><year>2002</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0960-7412.2001.01201.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11862947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrasek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PIN proteins perform a rate-limiting function in cellular auxin efflux</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>312</volume><fpage>914</fpage><lpage>918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1123542</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16601150?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16601150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li, Q. &#x00026; Wan, J.M. SSRHunter: development of a local searching software for SSR sites.&#x000a0;<italic>Hereditas</italic><bold>27</bold>, 808&#x02013;810,&#x000a0;10.3321/j.issn:0253-9772.2005.05.023 (2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lisec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Willmitzer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gas chromatography mass spectrometry-based metabolite profiling in plants</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot0915-1457a</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17406261?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saccenti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoefsloot</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smilde</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerhuis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>MMWB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reflections on univariate and multivariate analysis of metabolomics data</article-title><source>Metabolomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-013-0598-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated transcriptomics and metabolomics analysis to characterize cold stress responses in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic></article-title><source>Bmc Genomics</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-017-3871-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28662642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28662642</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>