<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5970189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">26615</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-26615-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of straw mulch and seeding rate on the harvest index, yield and water use efficiency of winter wheat</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Changlu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Cheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>Victor O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Mao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Xueyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Shulan</given-names></name><address><email>zhangshulan@nwafu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 4150</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.144022.1</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Soil Erosion and Dryland Farming on the Loess Plateau, </institution><institution>Northwest A &#x00026; F University, </institution></institution-wrap>Yangling, 712100 Shaanxi China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 4150</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.144022.1</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Plant Nutrition and the Agri-environment in Northwest China, Ministry of agriculture, </institution><institution>College of Resources and Environment, Northwest A &#x00026; F University, </institution></institution-wrap>Yangling, 712100 Shaanxi China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>South Australian R &#x00026; D Institute, Waite Campus, Adelaide, 5064 Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>8167</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Straw mulching has been used to improve water use efficiency (WUE, yield per unit evapotranspiration) in the Loess Plateau of China, but the seeding rate may need to be adjusted from conventional practice. We tested the three-way interaction between seeding rate, soil management (conventional tillage and straw mulching) and seasons. Wheat yield ranged from 2851 to 6981&#x02009;kg&#x02009;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and WUE from 5.3 to 16.2&#x02009;kg&#x02009;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Generally, soil water storage was higher and soil temperature was lower under straw mulching than under conventional practice. Evapotranspiration was higher under straw mulching. Yield was significantly affected by the interaction between straw mulching and season. Conventional practice showed significantly higher mean harvest index (HI), yield, and WUE than straw mulching in favorable seasons. However, yield was significantly higher under mulching than under conventional tillage in very dry season. Seeding rate had no effect on yield, but low seeding rate increased HI compared to high seeding rate. It is concluded that low seeding rate would be suitable for straw mulching.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">In China Loess Plateau, dryland farming is practiced on about 12.8 million ha or 80% of its arable land<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> where precipitation has declined at a rate of 1&#x02013;2&#x02009;mm&#x02009;y<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the last five decades<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. With increasing population, the challenge is to increase food production with declining precipitation. Conservation tillage has been encouraged to conserve soil and water resources, and increase crop yield<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Winter wheat (<italic>Triticum aestvum</italic> L.) is widely grown in the Loess Plateau. About 40% of annual precipitation occurs from October through June when winter wheat is growing; hence, yield depends on both in-season precipitation and stored soil water at sowing, as in other systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Recent reviews have shown that the response of rainfed wheat yield to straw mulching in the Loess Plateau varies from &#x02212;20 to 74%, and the response of water use efficiency (WUE, yield per unit evapotranspiration) varies from &#x02212;9 to 96%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> compared with conventional practice, whereas harvest index is reduced under straw mulching<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. These results indicate that there is an opportunity to further increase yield and WUE with practices to improve harvest index under straw mulching. We hypothesized that higher availability of soil water early in the growing season under mulch may favor early growth at the expense of growth at critical reproductive stages, hence affecting harvest index, yield, and WUE.</p><p id="Par3">Seeding rate influences early biomass production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> and adjusting stand density to match water availability is common, for example, in the US corn-belt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Generally, seeding rate of rain-fed wheat is adjusted to account for climate, soil, varieties and sowing date<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. If straw mulch reduces grain yield by enhancing early growth and water use, then we can expect a three way interaction between soil management (mulch vs conventional), seeding rate and seasonal conditions. Few studies addressed this interaction. For rain-fed wheat in straw mulching systems or conservation tillage, the suitable seeding rates ranged widely between 111 and 470 seeds m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> with different varieties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. For example, Sunderman<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> concluded that seeding rates do not need adjustment under conservation tillage in various weather conditions. In wet and cold seasons, K&#x000fc;hling <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> documented no difference in wheat yield between two seeding rates (450 and 600 seeds m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) across no-till and conventional practice in the south of Western Siberia. In the Loess Plateau under straw mulching, normal seeding rate (320 seeds m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) and 25% higher rate returned similar yield<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, but lower rates were not tested. Thus, our objective was to test the three way interaction between seeding rate, soil management and seasonal conditions, and its impact on grain yield and its components including harvest index, water use and water use efficiency of winter wheat. We hypothesized that soil water storage improved by straw mulching would stimulate tillering, early growth and water use, thus lower seeding rate under straw mulching could partially counteract the risk of lower grain yield and harvest index.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Site and experimental design and crop husbandry</title><p id="Par4">Four-year field experiments were conducted at Wangdong village (35.14&#x02009;N, 107.41 E, 1206&#x02009;m above sea level), Shaanxi Province in the Loess Plateau from 2012 to 2016. Annual average temperature is 9.3&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The water table (50&#x02013;80&#x02009;m) is far below root zone and does not influence crop growth. Average annual precipitation is 578&#x02009;mm, with 55% between July and September. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the actual rainfall in two periods, fallow and crop growing season, and the aridity index (precipitation divided by potential evapotranspiration) summarizing the seasonal conditions of this study.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Winter wheat sowing and harvest date; precipitation during three periods: fallow (from wheat harvest at the end of June or early July to sowing in the late September or early October), in-crop season (from wheat sowing to harvest), and total (fallow&#x02009;+&#x02009;in-crop season), and aridity index at Wangdong village of Shaanxi Province.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Season</th><th rowspan="2">Sowing date</th><th rowspan="2">Harvest date</th><th colspan="3">Precipitation (mm)</th><th colspan="3">Aridity Index<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th></tr><tr><th>Fallow</th><th>In-crop season</th><th>Total</th><th>Fallow</th><th>In-crop season</th><th>Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>2012/9/21</td><td>2013/6/23</td><td>337</td><td>160</td><td>497</td><td>0.73</td><td>0.17</td><td>0.36</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>2013/9/29</td><td>2014/7/4</td><td>392</td><td>252</td><td>644</td><td>0.88</td><td>0.32</td><td>0.53</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>2014/10/2</td><td>2015/7/5</td><td>345</td><td>277</td><td>622</td><td>0.77</td><td>0.36</td><td>0.51</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>2015/9/25</td><td>2016/7/1</td><td>217</td><td>223</td><td>440</td><td>0.47</td><td>0.24</td><td>0.32</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Aridity index (AI) returns hyper-arid (AI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), arid (0.05&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;AI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.2), semi-arid (0.2&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;AI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.5), dry sub-humid (0.5&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;AI&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.65), and humid (AI&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.65) environments.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par5">The soil in this site is classified as an aridic and loamy, Cumulic Haplustoll<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, or a calcisol (WRB 2014) with a silt loam texture developed from loess deposits. At the start of experiment, top soil (0&#x02013;20&#x02009;cm) had 14.4&#x02009;g&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> organic matter, 0.95&#x02009;g&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> total nitrogen, 12.9&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> nitrate nitrogen, 1.8&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ammonium nitrogen, 19&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> available phosphorus, 157&#x02009;mg&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> available potassium and 1.21&#x02009;g&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> bulk density.</p><p id="Par6">The experiment included six treatments resulting from the factorial combination of two soil management practices, i.e. conventional tillage and straw mulching with reduced tillage, and three seeding rates. Low seeding rate (LS) was 225&#x02013;320 seeds m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and represents 75% of recommended rate for conventional practice; medium seeding rate (MS) was 300&#x02013;400 seeds m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, and is the recommended rate for conventional practice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>; high seeding rate (HS) was 375&#x02013;480 seeds m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and represents 125% of MS. Conventional practice included about 10&#x02009;cm high wheat stubble at harvest that was incorporated to the soil about one month later with tillage to ca. 20&#x02009;cm depth, then leaving bare soil until sowing. At sowing, fertilizers were incorporated into the soil by rotary ploughing to about 15&#x02009;cm depth. In the mulch treatment, we established 0.6&#x02009;kg dry stubble m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, after wheat harvest on July 2012 and maintained ground cover without tillage until sowing. At sowing, all wheat straw was temporarily removed when fertilizers were incorporated into the soil as conventional practice, and wheat was sowed manually. Then wheat straw returned to the plots evenly after correcting weight as it deteriorated during the time. Sowing rate and soil management treatments were arranged in a randomized block design with four replicates. Plot size was 20&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup> (4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;5&#x02009;m) including 20 rows spaced at 25&#x02009;cm.</p><p id="Par7">Winter wheat (cv Changhan 58) was sown in late September or early October and harvested in late June or early July, as shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Applied fertilizers were 150&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as urea and 75&#x02009;kg P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as triple superphosphate in the first three seasons, and 120&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 75&#x02009;kg P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the last season. Nitrogen rates were based on soil nitrate nitrogen content before sowing (45&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the topsoil, 0&#x02013;20&#x02009;cm) and N rate experiment at the same site showing no yield difference between 120 and 180&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Weeds and diseases were managed as recommended locally. Additionally, in the fourth season, we found some abnormal stems caused by wireworms (Elateridae) at GS39<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Thereafter, pests were immediately controlled with cyhalothrin.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Sampling and measurements</title><p id="Par8">Wheat shoot population was recorded at emergence (GS15), tillering in winter (GS25), jointing (GS35), and heading (GS59). At physiological maturity (GS92), number of culms or ears were counted from 0.5&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup> in each plot, it should be noted that the number of culms not bearing a spike were not included. At maturity, grain yield (12.5% moisture content), biomass, kernel-weight, the number of ears, and grains per ear were measured in each plot, and harvest index (HI) was calculated.</p><p id="Par9">Water content in the soil profile (0&#x02013;3&#x02009;m) was measured gravimetrically (one profile per plot) at sowing, anthesis (GS65) and harvest (GS92). Soil temperature was measured for about one week centred at three growth stages (GS30, GS35 and GS65) in 2013&#x02013;2014, 2014&#x02013;2015 and 2015&#x02013;2016. Since the second wheat season, daily soil temperature was derived by average of measurements at 8:00 a.m., 2:00 p.m. and 8:00 p.m. using bent-stem soil thermometers installed at 5, 10, 15 and 20&#x02009;cm depth in three replicated plots for the medium seeding rate under both conventional and straw mulching treatments.</p><p id="Par10">Precipitation was measured with a data logger (CR1000, Campbell Sci.) located about 1&#x02009;km away from the experimental field. The sensor was factory calibrated before installation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Calculations and statistical analyses</title><p id="Par11">Crop evapotranspiration (ET) was estimated from water balance equation;<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{ET}}={\rm{P}}+{\rm{\Delta }}{\rm{W}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ET</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">W</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_26615_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where P is precipitation and &#x00394;W change in soil water from sowing to harvest. We assumed negligible runoff, based on the flatness of the plots, and negligible drainage as precipitation rarely wets the soil below 2&#x02009;m, whereas &#x00394;W was measured down to 3&#x02009;m. Water use efficiency was calculated as grain yield divided by ET<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par12">Repeated measures ANOVA (general linear model) was used to evaluate the effects of season, soil management, seeding rate and their interactions on crop traits (yield, biomass, HI, ear number, grain number, kernel weight, ET, WUE) and soil water storage. In this model, the test seasons were referred to as the within-subjects factors, and the soil management and seeding rate were referred to as the between-subjects factors. A Greenhouse-Geisser correction was applied to the <italic>F</italic>-ratio, if the sphericity assumption was not met. Soil temperature was analysed with <italic>t</italic>-test to compare conventional practice and straw mulching. For each season, one-way ANOVA was performed to evaluate effects of seeding rate on crop traits and soil water. When <italic>F</italic>-values were significant, multiple comparisons of mean values were performed using the least significant difference method (LSD) at the 0.05 probability level. All statistical analysis was performed through SPSS software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Weather</title><p id="Par13">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows precipitation and air temperature during the four seasons. In four years, air temperatures during the growing season were generally similar to the long-term. Frost occurred in early April in 2013 and 2015 (beginning of jointing stage), which affected wheat stand and yield components. Additionally, hail occurred on grain filling in 2015 (May 30, 2015).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Monthly precipitation, monthly mean temperature, and the 45 years average (45a) during the growing period of winter wheat (September to July) in four seasons at Wangdong village of Shaanxi Province.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_26615_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e700"/></fig></p><p id="Par14">The long-term fallow, in-crop and total precipitation were 304&#x02009;mm, 274&#x02009;mm and 578&#x02009;mm, respectively. Total precipitation was below the long-term mean in the first season, mainly due to the very low in-crop precipitation of 160&#x02009;mm. The fourth season also showed lower total precipitation (440&#x02009;mm) relative to the long-term, but precipitation was more evenly distributed during wheat growth. Both the second (644&#x02009;mm) and third (622&#x02009;mm) seasons were wetter than the long-term mean, (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Fallow rainfall accounted for 68% (2012&#x02013;13), 61% (2013&#x02013;14), 55% (2014&#x02013;15) and 49% (2015&#x02013;16) of annual precipitation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Soil water and thermal conditions</title><p id="Par15">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows ANOVA for soil water at sowing, anthesis and harvest as affected by season, straw mulching, seeding rate and their interactions. Soil water at sowing varied seasonally, and was significantly higher under mulch than under conventional treatment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Straw mulching increased soil water storage at sowing by 88&#x02009;mm in the first season, by 73&#x02009;mm in the second season, by 49&#x02009;mm in the third season and by 60&#x02009;mm in the fourth season in comparison to conventional tillage. At anthesis and harvest, straw mulching showed higher soil water content than conventional practice in the third and fourth seasons, but there was no difference in the first and second seasons.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><italic>P</italic>-values from ANOVA testing effect of season, soil management (conventional tillage and straw mulching), seeding rate and their interactions on wheat grain yield, shoot biomass, harvest index (HI), yield components, evapotranspiration (ET), water use efficiency (WUE, yield per unit ET) and soil water storage at sowing, anthesis and harvest.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Item<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th>Yield</th><th>Biomass</th><th>HI</th><th>Ears No.</th><th>No. of grains</th><th>kernel weight</th><th>ET</th><th>WUE</th><th>W<sub>1</sub><sup>&#x02021;</sup></th><th>W<sub>2</sub></th><th>W<sub>3</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>s</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>sm</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.131</td><td>0.102</td><td>0.025</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.747</td><td>0.021</td><td>0.010</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>sr</td><td>0.537</td><td>0.611</td><td>0.049</td><td>0.124</td><td>0.619</td><td>0.504</td><td>0.028</td><td>0.130</td><td>0.230</td><td>0.006</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>s&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sm</td><td>0.004</td><td>0.012</td><td>0.019</td><td>0.532</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.440</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.433</td><td>0.007</td><td>0.578</td><td>0.003</td></tr><tr><td>s&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sr</td><td>0.877</td><td>0.854</td><td>0.042</td><td>0.973</td><td>1.000</td><td>0.208</td><td>0.586</td><td>0.844</td><td>0.191</td><td>0.316</td><td>0.146</td></tr><tr><td>sm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sr</td><td>0.636</td><td>0.635</td><td>0.394</td><td>0.459</td><td>0.407</td><td>0.636</td><td>0.490</td><td>0.697</td><td>0.539</td><td>0.754</td><td>0.108</td></tr><tr><td>s&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;sr</td><td>0.665</td><td>0.506</td><td>0.010</td><td>0.908</td><td>0.390</td><td>0.190</td><td>0.351</td><td>0.976</td><td>0.126</td><td>0.963</td><td>0.773</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>s, season; sm, soil management; sr, seeding rate. <sup>&#x02021;</sup>W<sub>1</sub>, W<sub>2</sub> and W<sub>3</sub> represent the soil water storage at sowing, anthesis and harvest, respectively.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Soil water storage (0&#x02013;3&#x02009;m) at sowing, anthesis, and harvest in wheat crops in a factorial experiment combining three seeding rates, two soil management practices and four seasons at Wangdong village of Shaanxi Province. Seeding rates are high (HS), medium (MS) and low (LS) and soil management practices are conventional tillage (Con) and straw mulching (SM). Different letters mean significant difference between treatments at a given stage each year (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_26615_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1087"/></fig></p><p id="Par16">Seeding rate significantly affected soil water storage, with high seeding rate reducing soil water content at anthesis and harvest in comparison to medium and low seeding rates (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Under conventional treatment, soil water storage was lower at the high seeding rate than the low seeding rate at anthesis except for the second season (2013&#x02013;14) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). However, under straw mulching soil water storage was mostly at the same level for the three seeding rates at anthesis except for the third season (2014&#x02013;15) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In both conventional treatment or straw mulching, high seeding rate considerably decreased soil water at harvest only in the first season (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par17">Top-soil temperature (5&#x02009;cm) under mulching was 2.8&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (2013&#x02013;14), 0.9&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (2014&#x02013;15) and 1.7&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (2015&#x02013;16) cooler than under conventional practice at re-green stage (GS30), and 1.3&#x02009;&#x000b0;C cooler at jointing (GS35) in 2013&#x02013;2014 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). At other stages, soil temperatures were similar between the two treatments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Soil temperature (0&#x02013;20&#x02009;cm) during the wheat growing period in 2013&#x02013;2014, 2014&#x02013;2015 and 2015&#x02013;2016 at medium seeding rate. Conventional tillage (Con) and straw mulching (SM) treatments are compared at regreen, jointing and anthesis stages. *Represents significant difference between two treatments (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_26615_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1121"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Wheat shoot population dynamics</title><p id="Par18">Wheat shoot population was higher in the second than in the first, third and fourth seasons (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Seeding rate showed season- and practice-dependent effects on population size. Under conventional practice in the first and fourth seasons, shoot population was higher at high and medium than at low seeding rate at seedling and wintering stages; in the second season, high and medium seeding rates showed higher populations than low seeding rates at wintering stage; in the third season, high seeding rate presented higher populations than medium and low seeding rate from seedling to jointing (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> left panels). Under straw mulching, high seeding rate presented higher shoot populations than medium and low seeding rate from seedling to jointing in 2012&#x02013;2013, at wintering and maturity stages in 2013&#x02013;2014, and at seedling and wintering stages in 2014&#x02013;2015 and 2015&#x02013;2016 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> right panels). No difference was observed at other stages.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Dynamics of wheat shoots in a factorial experiment combining three seeding rates (high, HS; medium, MS; low, LS), two soil management practices (conventional tillage, straw mulching) and four seasons at Wangdong village of Shaanxi Province. Crop stages are S, Seedling; W, Winter; J, Jointing; A, Anthesis; M, Maturity. Different letters indicate significant differences between seeding rates (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_26615_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1147"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">There were no significant differences in shoot populations between conventional and straw mulching treatments at any seeding rate in the first and fourth seasons. However compared with conventional practice, populations with straw mulching were lower for all seeding rates at jointing in the second and third seasons, and for medium and low seeding rates at maturity in the second season (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Yield, yield components, ET and WUE of wheat crops in a factorial experiment combining three seeding rates, two soil management practices and four seasons at Wangdong village of Shaanxi Province.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Season</th><th>Soil manage-ment<sup>&#x02020;</sup></th><th>Seeding rate<sup>&#x02021;</sup></th><th>Yield (kg ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th>Biomass (kg ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th>HI</th><th>Ears No. (10<sup>4</sup>&#x02009;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th>No. of grains (grains m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)</th><th>Kernel weight (mg)</th><th>ET (mm)</th><th>WUE (kg ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="6">2012&#x02013;13</td><td rowspan="3">Con</td><td>HS</td><td>3113b<sup>*</sup></td><td>7783a</td><td>0.40b</td><td>287a</td><td>8481ab</td><td>44.4a</td><td>478bcd</td><td>6.58a</td></tr><tr><td>MS</td><td>2962b</td><td>7295a</td><td>0.41b</td><td>251a</td><td>7715b</td><td>44.4a</td><td>462&#x02009;cd</td><td>6.31ab</td></tr><tr><td>LS</td><td>3049b</td><td>7149a</td><td>0.43b</td><td>259a</td><td>7985b</td><td>45.0a</td><td>438d</td><td>6.76a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">SM</td><td>HS</td><td>2851b</td><td>7440a</td><td>0.39b</td><td>288 a</td><td>8332b</td><td>45.9a</td><td>543a</td><td>5.28b</td></tr><tr><td>MS</td><td>3709 a</td><td>7530a</td><td>0.49a</td><td>273a</td><td>9328a</td><td>45.9a</td><td>527ab</td><td>7.27a</td></tr><tr><td>LS</td><td>3317ab</td><td>7516a</td><td>0.44ab</td><td>258a</td><td>8413ab</td><td>45.8a</td><td>500abc</td><td>6.79a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">2013&#x02013;14</td><td rowspan="3">Con</td><td>HS</td><td>6298ab</td><td>16499ab</td><td>0.38ab</td><td>597a</td><td>21924a</td><td>35.1a</td><td>543b</td><td>11.67a</td></tr><tr><td>MS</td><td>6533a</td><td>16895ab</td><td>0.39ab</td><td>596a</td><td>20296abc</td><td>35.8a</td><td>567ab</td><td>11.54a</td></tr><tr><td>LS</td><td>6342ab</td><td>15968b</td><td>0.40a</td><td>600a</td><td>21544ab</td><td>34.3a</td><td>555ab</td><td>11.55a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">SM</td><td>HS</td><td>6157ab</td><td>16720ab</td><td>0.37bc</td><td>581a</td><td>19667bc</td><td>36.4a</td><td>602a</td><td>9.27b</td></tr><tr><td>MS</td><td>6060bc</td><td>17031a</td><td>0.36c</td><td>542b</td><td>20270abc</td><td>34.6a</td><td>594a</td><td>9.42b</td></tr><tr><td>LS</td><td>5664c</td><td>15973ab</td><td>0.35c</td><td>523b</td><td>18443c</td><td>35.8a</td><td>571ab</td><td>9.86b</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">2014&#x02013;15</td><td rowspan="3">Con</td><td>HS</td><td>4180a</td><td>13284a</td><td>0.33a</td><td>512a</td><td>15385a</td><td>36.9b</td><td>414ab</td><td>10.83a</td></tr><tr><td>MS</td><td>4179a</td><td>12878ab</td><td>0.32a</td><td>506a</td><td>13907ab</td><td>41.6a</td><td>412ab</td><td>10.23a</td></tr><tr><td>LS</td><td>4174a</td><td>11842abc</td><td>0.35a</td><td>473a</td><td>13878ab</td><td>41.4a</td><td>390b</td><td>10.48a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">SM</td><td>HS</td><td>3207b</td><td>10538c</td><td>0.30a</td><td>476a</td><td>11078bc</td><td>39.6ab</td><td>433a</td><td>7.47b</td></tr><tr><td>MS</td><td>3023b</td><td>10104c</td><td>0.30a</td><td>461a</td><td>10260c</td><td>40.0ab</td><td>431a</td><td>7.23b</td></tr><tr><td>LS</td><td>3126b</td><td>10739bc</td><td>0.33a</td><td>452a</td><td>10803c</td><td>39.0ab</td><td>398b</td><td>7.80b</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">2015&#x02013;16</td><td rowspan="3">Con</td><td>HS</td><td>6936a</td><td>13888a</td><td>0.53b</td><td>421a</td><td>17090a</td><td>50.9a</td><td>454a</td><td>16.24a</td></tr><tr><td>MS</td><td>6981a</td><td>12467ab</td><td>0.56a</td><td>407a</td><td>15898ab</td><td>51.2a</td><td>455a</td><td>15.35ab</td></tr><tr><td>LS</td><td>6881a</td><td>12237b</td><td>0.56a</td><td>380a</td><td>15649ab</td><td>51.6a</td><td>455a</td><td>15.17ab</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">SM</td><td>HS</td><td>6496a</td><td>12805ab</td><td>0.51c</td><td>364a</td><td>14615bc</td><td>50.8a</td><td>459a</td><td>13.62b</td></tr><tr><td>MS</td><td>6414a</td><td>12769ab</td><td>0.53b</td><td>369a</td><td>14635bc</td><td>50.9a</td><td>471a</td><td>13.49b</td></tr><tr><td>LS</td><td>6506a</td><td>12060b</td><td>0.51c</td><td>366a</td><td>13764c</td><td>51.9a</td><td>454a</td><td>14.62ab</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Con, conventional tillage; SM, straw mulching. <sup>&#x02021;</sup>HS, high seeding rate; MS, medium seeding rate; LS, low seeding rate. *The different lowercase letters represent significant difference between all treatments each season (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Yield and yield components</title><p id="Par20">Wheat yield and its components are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows ANOVA. ANOVA indicated significant seasonal effects on grain yield as follows: season 4&#x0003e; season 2&#x0003e; season 3&#x0003e; season 1. Seasons also affected biomass, HI and yield components (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Across four seasons conventional practice had significantly higher grain yield, ear number and grain number compared with straw mulching. However, mulching significantly interacted with seasons; for example, in the very dry season 2012&#x02013;2013 mulching increased HI and yield compared with conventional practice (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The high seeding rate showed distinctly lower HI than the low seeding rate (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Season, soil management and seeding rate also had significant interaction effect on HI.</p><p id="Par21">Under conventional practice seeding rate had no effect on grain yield for all seasons, and on biomass and harvest index in first three seasons (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). However, high seeding rate increased biomass and reduced HI compared with low seeding rate in the fourth season. Under straw mulching, medium seeding rate presented notably higher HI and yield than high seeding rate in the first season, but seeding rate did not affect HI and yield in the other three seasons, except for a higher HI in the medium seeding rate compared to both high and low seeding rate in fourth season (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). With few exceptions, seeding rate had no effect on grain number and kernel weight under conventional practice or straw mulching in all tested seasons (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). For example, high seeding rate had lower kernel weight than medium and low seeding rate in third season under conventional practice. Under straw mulching, high seeding rate had significantly higher ear number than medium and low seeding rates in the second season; additionally medium seeding rate had significantly higher grain number than high seeding rate in first season.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Water use and water use efficiency</title><p id="Par22">ANOVA indicated significant seasonal effects on ET and WUE (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Straw mulching generally increased ET and reduced WUE with respect to conventional practice. The interaction between straw mulching and season affected ET, but not WUE. Evapotranspiration was higher in crops with high and medium seeding rates compared to their low seeding rate counterparts (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par23">Under conventional practice ET and WUE were statistically similar among seeding rates in all seasons (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Under straw mulching, however, in very dry season (2012&#x02013;2013) the WUE was significantly lower at high seeding rate (5.28&#x02009;kg&#x02009;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) than at medium (7.27&#x02009;kg&#x02009;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and low (6.79&#x02009;kg&#x02009;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) seeding rates (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24">Owing to drier conditions and frost in 2012&#x02013;2013 and frost and hail in 2014&#x02013;2015, yield and WUE were lower in the first and third than in the second and fourth seasons. In addition, grain yield was higher in the fourth season than in the second season despite higher soil water storage at sowing and higher in-crop precipitation in the second season. Higher grain yield was mainly connected to higher kernel weight, which was partially related to precipitation distribution (10&#x02009;mm more post-anthesis) and 5 days longer duration of grain filling in the fourth season than in the second season. Additionally, soil water storage at anthesis was higher in the fourth season than in the second season, and the opposite was true at harvest, which meant post-anthesis water use was more in the fourth than in the second season. The higher water availability after anthesis contributing higher yield has been discussed previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">Straw mulching reduced harvest index, grain yield, and WUE compared to conventional practice in three out of four seasons (wet and favourable condition), but straw mulching increased both harvest index and yield in the very dry season 2012&#x02013;13. Amato <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> reported a similar interaction in a long-term experiment whereby wheat under no-tillage out-yielded its counterpart under conventional tillage under water stress but yield differences were reversed in wetter conditions. The global analysis of Pittelkow <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> showed that no-tillage in combination with residue retention in rainfed systems reduced crop yield in humid climates, but enhanced yield in dry climates. This study did not support our hypothesis that higher soil water availability early in the season under mulch may stimulate tillering and favour early growth at the expense of growth at critical reproductive stages, hence reducing harvest index and grain yield. Instead, we found that population size was generally similar between conventional treatment and straw mulching, and soil water content was consistently higher under straw mulching during the growing season. The reduction in harvest index, grain yield and WUE with mulching in those three seasons was primarily associated with fewer grains per area caused by lower ear numbers. Two factors may have contributed to fewer ears per unit area under mulch: cooler soil during tiller development in spring as found in our study (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) and others under same practice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> or no-tillage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, and pest damage as noticed in our experiment and reported by others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Thus, controlling pests should require more attention under straw mulching to capture the benefits of this practice, especially in wet seasons.</p><p id="Par26">Seeding rate did not affect wheat yield and WUE when averaged across two soil managements over four seasons. Gao <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> found it was not necessary to increase seeding rate over the recommended level during three dry seasons under straw mulching in the same region. Our results highlighted that the higher depletion of water under high seeding rate especially during vegetative stage reduced harvest index compared with that under low seeding rate. Moreover, low seeding rate significantly reduced ET and tended to increase WUE. These results indicate the recommended seeding rate was still higher than needed. Thus, the low seeding rate tested in our study seems suitable for both conventional and straw mulching conditions. In addition, Sunderman<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> has reported seeding rates at 75%, 100% and 125% of the recommended rate for the conventional practice produced similar wheat yield under no tillage, and the seeding rate of 75% of recommended level was suitable for various weather conditions. Our straw mulching treatment fully captured the effect of soil cover, and partially accounted for the reduced soil disturbance in farm-scale no-till systems. With this caveat, the present study showed that reducing seeding rate to 75% of the recommended rate would modulate soil water use and stabilise harvest index to improve the benefits of straw mulching under the prevalent conditions of the Loess Plateau.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was supported by Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31170411, 31672243) and Special-Funds of Scientific Research Programs of State Key Laboratory of Soil Erosion and Dryland Farming on the Loess Plateau (A314021403-C4). Authors also thank the Changwu Agro-ecological Experimental Station on the Loess Plateau, Chinese Academy of Sciences, for providing the climate data and other supports during experimental period.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>S.Z. and X.Y. conceived and designed the experiments, C.H., C.Z. and M.D. conducted the field experiment and analysed the results. C.H. analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. S.Z. and V.S. contributed to data analysis and writing the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par27">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li, S. Chinese Dryland Agriculture [M]. Beijing: Chinese Press of Agriculture, (In Chinese) (2004).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Duan, J., Wang, X., Gao, Z. &#x00026; Zhang, C. Dynamics and trends analysis of annual precipitation in the loess plateau region for 50 years. <italic>J. Soil Water Conserv</italic>. <bold>23</bold>, 143&#x02013;146 (in Chinese) (2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang, R. Analysis of the past 50 years&#x02019; change trend of temperature and precipitation in Pingliang Gully region of Loess Plateau. <italic>J. Anhui Agric. Sci</italic>. <bold>37</bold>, 17564&#x02013;17566 (In Chinese) (2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>PCH</given-names></name><name><surname>Orson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Froud-Williams</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The adoption of non-inversion tillage systems in the United Kingdom and the agronomic impact on soil, crops and environment-a review</article-title><source>Soil Till. Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.still.2010.03.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pittelkow</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Productivity limits and potentials of the principles of conservation agriculture</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>517</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13809</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25337882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25337882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pittelkow</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>When does no-till yield more? A global meta-analysis</article-title><source>Field Crops Res.</source><year>2015</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2015.07.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Simelton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f6;vdahl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grip</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simulated long-term effects of different soil management regimes on the water balance in the loess plateau, China</article-title><source>Field Crops Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2006.08.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of mulching and catch cropping on soil temperature, soil moisture and wheat yield on the Loess Plateau of China</article-title><source>Soil Till. Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.still.2008.07.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water use efficiency of dryland wheat in the Loess Plateau in response to soil and crop management</article-title><source>Field Crops Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2013.07.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water use efficiency of dryland maize in the Loess Plateau of China in response to crop management</article-title><source>Field Crops Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2014.04.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Unger, P. W., Payne, W. A. &#x00026; Peterson, G. A. Water conservation and efficient use. In: Peterson, G.A., Unger, P.W., Payne, W.A. editors Dryland Agriculture. American Society of Agronomy Monograph Series 23. Madison, WI: American Society of Agronomy. pp. 39&#x02013;85 (2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schillinger</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schofstoll</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Alldredge</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Available water and wheat grain yield relations in a Mediterranean climate</article-title><source>Field Crops Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2008.06.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shangguan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water-use efficiency of dryland wheat in response to mulching and tillage practices on the Loess Plateau</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>12225</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep12225</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26192158?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26192158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroup</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crop production and soil water storage in long-term winter wheat-fallow tillage experiments</article-title><source>Soil Till. Res.</source><year>1998</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-1987(98)00151-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of mulch, N fertilizer, and plant density on wheat yield, wheat nitrogen uptake, and residual soil nitrate in a dryland area of China</article-title><source>Nutr. Cycl. Agroecosys.</source><year>2009</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10705-009-9252-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of alternative tillage and residue cover on yield and water use efficiency in annual double cropping system in North China Plain</article-title><source>Soil Till. Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.still.2008.08.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasertsak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Setter</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant spacing, density, and yield of wheat subjected to postanthesis water deficits</article-title><source>Crop Sci.</source><year>1994</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1994.0011183X003400030026x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Grassini, P., Specht, J. E., Tollenaar, M., Ciampitti, I. A. &#x00026; Cassman, K. G. High-yield maize-soybean cropping systems in the US Corn Belt, In: Sadras, V.O., Calderini, D.F. (Eds), Crop Physiology: Applications for genetic improvement and agronomy. Academic Press, San Diego, pp. 17&#x02013;41 (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tokatlidis</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addressing the yield by density interaction is a prerequisite to bridge the yield gap of rain-fed wheat</article-title><source>Ann. Appl. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/aab.12121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isidro-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of seeding rate on durum crop production and physiological responses</article-title><source>Agron. J.</source><year>2017</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj2016.09.0527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tompkins</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hultgreen</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seed rate and row spacing of no-till winter wheat</article-title><source>Agron. J.</source><year>1991</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>684</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj1991.00021962008300040007x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lafond</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of row spacing, seeding rate and nitrogen on yield of barley and wheat under zero-till management</article-title><source>Can. J. Plant. Sci.</source><year>1994</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4141/cjps94-127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sunderman</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response of hard red winter wheat to seed density and seeding rate in no-till</article-title><source>J. Prod. Agric.</source><year>1999</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/jpa1999.0100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hling</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Redozubov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Broll</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of tillage, seeding rate and seeding depth on soil moisture and dryland spring wheat yield in Western Siberia</article-title><source>Soil Till. Res.</source><year>2017</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.still.2017.02.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Soil Survey Staff. Key to Soil Taxonomy, 11th ed. United States department of Agriculture and Natural Resources Conservation Service, Washington, DC (2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liang, Z. J. &#x00026; Meng, Y. M. A new wheat variety Changhan 58 for dry farming. <italic>China Agric. Tech. Ext</italic>. <bold>23</bold>, 17&#x02013;17 (in Chinese) (2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zadoks</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Konzak</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A decimal code for the growth stages of cereals</article-title><source>Weed Res.</source><year>1974</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3180.1974.tb01084.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amato</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term tillage and crop sequence effects on wheat grain yield and quality</article-title><source>Agron. J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>1317</fpage><lpage>1327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj2013.0019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wicks</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crutchfield</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnside</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of wheat (Triticum aestivum) straw mulch and metolachlor on corn (Zea mays) growth and yield</article-title><source>Weed Sci.</source><year>1994</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>147</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manrique</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mulching in potato systems in the tropics</article-title><source>J. Plant Nutr.</source><year>1995</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01904169509364926</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>