<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Theor Appl Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Theor. Appl. Genet</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>TAG. Theoretical and Applied Genetics. Theoretische Und Angewandte Genetik</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5752</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-2242</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6244535</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30232499</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3186</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-018-3186-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Resource allocation optimization with multi-trait genomic prediction for bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) baking quality</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lado</surname><given-names>Bettina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e1;zquez</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quincke</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>Paula</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>Ignacio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>Lucia</given-names></name><address><email>gutierrezcha@wisc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000121657640</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11630.35</institution-id><institution>Department of Statistics, Facultad de Agronom&#x000ed;a, </institution><institution>Universidad de la Rep&#x000fa;blica, </institution></institution-wrap>Garz&#x000f3;n 780, 12900 Montevideo, Uruguay </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2167 3675</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.14003.36</institution-id><institution>Department of Agronomy, </institution><institution>University of Wisconsin&#x02013; Madison, </institution></institution-wrap>1575 Linden Dr, Madison, WI 53706 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0604 4346</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.473327.6</institution-id><institution>Instituto Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Agropecuaria, </institution></institution-wrap>Est. Exp. La Estanzuela, Ruta 50&#x000a0;km 11.5, 70006 Colonia, Uruguay </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0604 4346</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.473327.6</institution-id><institution>Instituto Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Agropecuaria, </institution></institution-wrap>Est. Exp. Las Brujas, Ruta 48&#x000a0;km 10, Rinc&#x000f3;n del Colorado, 90200 Canelones, Uruguay </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Communicated by Hermann Buerstmayr.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>131</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2719</fpage><lpage>2731</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Key Message</title><p id="Par1">Multi-trait genomic prediction models are useful to allocate available resources in breeding programs by targeted phenotyping of correlated traits when predicting expensive and labor-intensive quality parameters.</p></sec><sec><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par2">Multi-trait genomic prediction models can be used to predict labor-intensive or expensive correlated traits where phenotyping depth of correlated traits could be larger than phenotyping depth of targeted traits, reducing resources and improving prediction accuracy. This is particularly important in the context of allocating phenotyping resource in plant breeding programs. The objective of this work was to evaluate multi-trait models predictive ability with different depth of phenotypic information from correlated traits. We evaluated 495 wheat advanced breeding lines for eight baking quality traits which were genotyped with genotyping-by-sequencing. Through different approaches for cross-validation, we evaluated the predictive ability of a single-trait model and a multi-trait model. Moreover, we evaluated different sizes of the training population (from 50 to 396 individuals) for the trait of interest, different depth of phenotypic information for correlated traits (50 and 100%) and the number of correlated traits to be used (one to three). There was no loss in the predictive ability by reducing the training population up to a 30% (149 individuals) when using correlated traits. A multi-trait model with one highly correlated trait phenotyped for both the training and testing sets was the best model considering phenotyping resources and the gain in predictive ability. The inclusion of correlated traits in the training and testing lines is a strategic approach to replace phenotyping of labor-intensive and high cost traits in a breeding program.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1007/s00122-018-3186-3) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100008725</institution-id><institution>Agencia Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n e Innovaci&#x000f3;n</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>POS_NAC_2013_1_11261</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Lado</surname><given-names>Bettina</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100006049</institution-id><institution>Comisi&#x000f3;n Sectorial de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Cient&#x000ed;fica</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Wheat is one of the most important staple food crops of humans (Shewry and Hey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>), providing 18% of the total caloric intake of the world (FAO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2017</xref>). Bread is one of the most important end-use products of wheat; therefore, improving bread quality is a key aspect of wheat improvement. Baking bread quality is a complex trait with quantitative inheritance, derived by several individual traits each one with a different level of environmental influence (Williams et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2008</xref>). One of the traits that determines baking quality is gluten strength, which is a key factor for loaf volume that determines rising and shape maintenance during the baking process (MacRitchie <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1992</xref>). Gluten strength is affected by the proportion of glutenins and gliadins polypeptides (75&#x02013;80% of total proteins) synthetized by each wheat variety (MacRitchie <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1992</xref>). Therefore, the amount and quality of proteins determine gluten strength and can be evaluated with the sedimentation volume value (MacRitchie <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1992</xref>). Protein quantity also determines the stability of the dough to create a network and retain water, which is called wet gluten (WG). There is a complex interaction between proteins and other components such as pentosans (Hamer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2009</xref>) making dough strength predictability from chemical composition very difficult. Therefore, rheological tests are required. The alveograph is used to investigate the stretching properties of the dough. The total energy required for breaking a standardized bubble is called baking strength (<italic>W</italic>). The length of the curve (<italic>L</italic>), or the time required to break it, is the extensibility, and the height of the peak (<italic>P</italic>) represents the tenacity or maximum dough resistance to rupture (Indrani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>). All these traits are used to select varieties with better bread quality (V&#x000e1;zquez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2009</xref>).</p><p id="Par4">Baking quality is a complex quantitative trait, and several breeding strategies have been successfully used to improve complex traits. In the pre-genomic era, common breeding strategies involved the use of classical quantitative genetic approaches (Lynch and Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1998</xref>), including pedigree information to estimate best linear unbiased predictors (BLUPs; Henderson and Quaas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1976</xref>). With the widespread availability of molecular markers, genomic approaches have been used (Lande and Thompson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1990</xref>). One of the most widely used strategies involves using the additive relationship matrix estimated from markers instead of the additive relationship matrix estimated from pedigree with BLUP models. This was the beginning of the genomic selection (GS) era, and the new BLUP model was called a G-BLUP model (Meuwissen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2001</xref>; Habier et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2007</xref>). The G-BLUP model is equivalent to a ridge regression BLUP model (RR-BLUP; Habier et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2007</xref>) and to Bayesian models that assume Gaussian priors for marker effects (i.e., Bayesian ridge regression; VanRaden <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2008</xref>). The latter models compute genetic breeding values (GEBV) adding up all marker effects which were estimated assuming a normal distribution of marker effects with common variance. These models have been the model of choice in most of the prediction scenarios due to their high predictive ability and simple implementation (Heslot et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2015</xref>). However, other models that assume heterogeneity of variances and different distributions for marker effects performing variable selection (de los Campos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2013</xref>) might have higher predictive ability in specific situations (reviewed in Lorenz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2011</xref>).</p><p id="Par5">Classical quantitative genetics theory also provides the necessary framework for selecting multiple traits, and classical approaches used for multi-trait selection include an independent culling approach, tandem and index selection (Falconer and Mackay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1996</xref>). Multi-trait (MT) selection is justified only when traits are genetically correlated (Henderson and Quaas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1976</xref>). This correlation can be the result of pleiotropy or linkage disequilibrium between genes (Falconer and Mackay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1996</xref>). A particular case of selection indices [i.e., Smith&#x02013;Hazel Index (Smith <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">1936</xref>; Hazel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1943</xref>)] uses the correlation and the phenotypic and genotypic variance&#x02013;covariance matrices among traits to estimate the net merit of genotypes. Multi-trait predictions have been extended for the use of genomic information (Calus and Veerkamp <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>; Ceron-Rojas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>). In this case, the correlation among observations is a function of the additive genetic correlation among traits and the additive genetic relationship among individuals (Calus and Veerkamp <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>). This same strategy was applied to predict lines in the context of genotype by environment interaction using the environmental correlation as multi-trait (Burgue&#x000f1;o et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2012</xref>). Similar to single-trait models, multi-trait models could assume different marker distributions to estimate the breeding values. Calus and Veerkamp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>) presented three models: one model estimates all marker effects assuming a unique variance (multi-trait G-BLUP); the other two models perform variable selection; one assumes the same variance for all the SNPs (BayesC&#x003c0;), while the other assumes different variances whether the SNPs were or not associated with a quantitative trait loci (QTL; BayesSSVS). In this study, the differences in performance among methods were small (Calus and Veerkamp <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>). Jia and Jannink (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>) compared three models that were similar to those of Calus and Veerkamp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>), but used different genetic architectures for the traits, and found that the models assuming different variances (BayesA) and performing variable selection (BayesC&#x003c0;) were best when QTL of major effects were simulated. However, for truly quantitative traits, models assuming normal distribution of marker effects and unique variances were similar to more complex models. Therefore, a simple model using additive relationship matrix as variance&#x02013;covariance matrix among individuals seems to perform well for predicting single- (Habier et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2007</xref>) and multi-trait models (Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>; Guo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2014</xref>).</p><p id="Par6">Prediction of new un-phenotyped individuals has been studied using multi-trait and single-trait genomic predictions models (Calus and Veerkamp <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>; Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>; Guo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2014</xref>). Calus and Veerkamp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>) did not find significant differences between both models using simulated data for predicting traits with different but high heritability (<italic>h</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.6 and <italic>h</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.9). However, the multi-trait model showed good performance to predict low heritability traits with the help of correlated traits with high heritability (Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>; Guo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2014</xref>) and was optimal when the genetic architecture was explained by major QTL. Finally, the advantage of multi-trait models to predict new un-phenotyped individuals was not so obvious when using experimental data for diseases resistance in pine (Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>), grain yield and protein content in rice (Schulthess et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2016</xref>), several traits in maize (Dos Santos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2016</xref>) and grain yield in wheat through normalized difference vegetation index (NDVI) and canopy temperature (Sun et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2017</xref>). Therefore, the superiority of multi-trait models for predicting un-phenotyped individuals when using simulated data was not confirmed using experimental data.</p><p id="Par7">On the other hand, simulated and empirical studies show that multi-trait models were useful for predicting traits when individuals were partially phenotyped (Rutkoski et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2012</xref>; Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>; Guo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2014</xref>; Rutkoski et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2016</xref>; Hayes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>; Sun et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2017</xref>). Both Rutkoski et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2012</xref> and Sun et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2017</xref>) found advantages of multi-trait models using correlated traits from high-throughput phenotyping (i.e., NDVI and canopy temperature) in wheat. Jia and Jannink (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>) also found an improvement in predicting rust gall volume and the presence or absence of rust in pine. Finally, Hayes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref> found that end-use quality traits could be better predicted using near-infrared (NIR) or nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR). The results show that multi-trait models could be used to decide the optimal depth of phenotyping for each trait, mainly for expensive or difficult-to-measure traits (Guo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2014</xref>). However, there is no evaluation on how much phenotyping of the labor-intensive and expensive traits could be replaced by evaluating correlated inexpensive traits.</p><p id="Par8">The objective of this work was to evaluate how multi-trait models could be used to optimize phenotyping resource allocation in breeding programs for expensive or labor-intensive traits. Specifically, we evaluated whether the phenotyping of expensive and labor-intensive traits could be replaced by the use of simple-to-measure traits without affecting the predictive ability; and we compared phenotyping strategies including the use of purposefully unbalanced designs that would require phenotyping the same number of individuals for each trait but in an unbalanced manner such that the population evaluated is significantly larger and therefore the predictive ability potentially larger.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par9">Advanced inbred lines from the wheat breeding program from the &#x02018;Instituto Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Agropecuaria&#x02019; (INIA), Uruguay, were used for this study. We used 820 advanced inbred lines for the phenotypic analysis and 1974 advanced inbred lines for the genotypic analyses. Finally, only 495 advanced inbreed lines, having both genotypic and phenotypic information, were used to adjust the genomic selection models.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Phenotyping</title><p id="Par10">The advanced inbred lines from INIA&#x02019;s wheat breeding program were phenotyped for eight baking quality traits. The lines were grown in 82 trials in nine location-year combinations (environment) as part of the wheat breeding program (Table S1). There were trials from different breeding scheme stages in each environment: preliminary and advanced trials, and two maturity groups: short and long maturity. The traits were evaluated in field nurseries located in La Estanzuela (34&#x000b0;20&#x02032;S, 57&#x000b0;42&#x02032;W; 81&#x000a0;m asl), Colonia, Uruguay, over 5&#x000a0;years (2010&#x02013;2014). Additionally, approximately one-third of the lines were also evaluated in Young (32&#x000b0;76&#x02032;S, 57&#x000b0;57&#x02032;W; 85&#x000a0;m asl) and Ruta2 (33&#x000b0;45&#x02032;S, 57&#x000b0;90&#x02032;W; 95&#x000a0;m asl; Table S1). There were two to eight lines that linked the trials within and among environments (Table S2).</p><p id="Par11">Eight baking quality traits were evaluated in 820 experimental advanced inbred lines. Most lines were evaluated in a single environment (~&#x02009;680 lines), while the most promissory lines were evaluated in multiple environments (~&#x02009;140 lines). Grain protein content (Pt) and test weight (TW) were determined with methods 46&#x02013;12 and 55&#x02013;10 of the American Association of Cereal Chemists (AACC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2000</xref>), respectively. Refined flour was obtained using the B&#x000fc;hler Mill (AACC Approved Method 26&#x02013;21A, AACC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2000</xref>) method or equivalent. Flour attributes: wet gluten content (WG), alveograph parameters (<italic>W</italic> and <italic>L</italic>), and mixograph parameters (stability (MH) and time (MT)), were evaluated using the AACC methods 38&#x02013;12, 54&#x02013;30 and 54&#x02013;40 (AACC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2000</xref>), respectively. Sedimentation volume (SV) was measured according to Pe&#x000f1;a et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">1990</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Phenotypic analyses</title><p id="Par12">Best linear unbiased estimation (BLUE) for bread baking quality traits was estimated from data coming from the different trials and environments using the following model:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$y_{ijk} = \mu + g_{i} + e_{j} + t_{k\left( j \right)} + \varepsilon_{ijk}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ijk</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ijk</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$y_{ijk}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ijk</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the phenotypic value of the <italic>i</italic>-th genotype in <italic>j</italic>-th year location for <italic>k</italic>-th trial, <italic>&#x000b5;</italic> is the overall mean, <italic>g</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the fixed effect of the <italic>i</italic>-th genotype, <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> is the fixed effect of <italic>j</italic>-th environment, <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>k</italic>(<italic>j</italic>)</sub> is the random effect of the <italic>k</italic>-th trial nested within <italic>j</italic>-th environment, and <italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub><italic>ijk</italic></sub> is the residual error for the <italic>i</italic>-th genotype in the in <italic>j</italic>-th environment and <italic>k</italic>-th trial, where <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>k</italic>(<italic>j</italic>)</sub> and <italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub><italic>ijk</italic></sub> were random variables being <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>k</italic>(<italic>j</italic>)</sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;<italic>N</italic>(0,<italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub arrange="stack"><italic>t</italic></sub><sup arrange="stack">2</sup>) and <italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub><italic>ijk</italic></sub>&#x02009;~&#x02009;<italic>N</italic>(0, <italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub arrange="stack"><italic>e</italic></sub><sup arrange="stack">2</sup>). The BLUEs were estimated using &#x02018;nlme&#x02019; (Pinheiro and Bates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>) and &#x02018;lsmeans&#x02019; (Lenth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2016</xref>) packages from the R statistical software (R Development Core Team <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2016</xref>).</p><p id="Par14">To evaluate the genotype by environment interaction and the impact of unbalanced designs, Pearson&#x02019;s correlation between environments was estimated using BLUEs computed by environment (as in model 1 but without the environmental effect). Additionally, genotypic, environmental and genotype by environment interaction variance components were estimated. Finally, Pearson&#x02019;s correlation and principal component analysis between traits were estimated to evaluate the correlation among traits using the BLUEs estimated from model 1. The final additive variance&#x02013;covariance matrix between traits was later estimated from the genomic prediction model.</p><p id="Par15">Broad sense heritability for baking quality traits was estimated as follows (Piepho and M&#x000f6;hring <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2007</xref>):<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$H^{2} = \frac{{\sigma_{\text{g}}^{2} }}{{\sigma_{\text{g}}^{2} + {\raise0.7ex\hbox{${\bar{\nu }}$} \!\mathord{\left/ {\vphantom {{\bar{\nu }} 2}}\right.\kern-0pt} \!\lower0.7ex\hbox{$2$}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mpadded><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mpadded><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mpadded><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mpadded></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub arrange="stack"><italic>g</italic></sub><sup arrange="stack">2</sup> is the genotypic variance and <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\bar{\nu }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> the mean variance of the difference of two adjusted means.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Genotyping</title><p id="Par17">Leaf tissue from 1974 lines was collected, and the CTAB method (Saghai-Maroof et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1984</xref>) was used to isolate DNA for genotyping-by-sequencing (Poland et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2012a</xref>). The TASSEL-GBS pipeline (Glaubitz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2014</xref>) was run with modifications for non-reference genomes (Poland et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2012b</xref>). SNPs were filtered setting maximum missing value of 20%. Individuals with more than 50% missing information were also discarded. The initial calling of alleles was conducted on the large number of individuals, and then, marker information for the 495 individuals for which phenotypic information was available was used. Therefore, the remaining 6655 SNPs were those with minor allele frequency larger than 0.05 across the 495 individuals. SNP imputation was conducted using the multivariate normal expectation maximization method (Endelman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2011</xref>; Poland et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2012a</xref>). The additive relationship matrix (<italic>K</italic>) was estimated as <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$K = \frac{WW'}{{2\sum p_{m} q_{m} }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> where <italic>W</italic> is the centered genotypic matrix, <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$W_{im} = X_{im} + \left( {1 - 2p_{m} } \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">im</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">im</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> with <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$X_{im}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">im</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> the genotype of the <italic>i</italic>-th individual for the m-th marker as {&#x02212;&#x02009;1,0,1} and <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p_{m} , q_{m}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> the allelic frequencies where <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$q_{m} = 1 - p_{m}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (Endelman and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2012</xref>). <italic>K</italic> was estimated using the &#x02018;rrBLUP&#x02019; package in R Statistical Software (Endelman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Genomic prediction models</title><p id="Par18">Predictions were obtained from 495 inbreed lines with phenotypic and genotypic information.</p><sec id="Sec8"><title>Single-trait model</title><p id="Par19">Using the single-trait model (ST), the prediction performance values were obtained for the eight baking quality traits using a Bayesian ridge regression (BRR) model by trait.<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$y_{i} = 1\mu + \mathop \sum \limits_{j = 1}^{j = p} x_{ij} \beta_{j} + \varepsilon_{i}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$y_{i}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the adjusted phenotypic mean of individual <italic>i</italic> for a single trait; <italic>&#x003bc;</italic> is the overall mean; <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_{ij}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> the score of the <italic>j</italic>-th SNP in individual <italic>i</italic>; <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\beta_{j}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the effect of <italic>j</italic>-th marker; and <italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the vector of residual errors. The conditional prior distribution is <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varepsilon_{i} \,\sim\,N\left( {0, \sigma^{2} } \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> with <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\sigma^{2} \,\sim\,\chi^{ - 2} (\sigma^{2} |{\text{d}}f,S$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003c7;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) for residuals, and <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\beta_{j} \,\sim\,N\left( {0,\sigma_{\beta }^{2} } \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> with <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\sigma_{\beta }^{2} \,\sim\,\chi^{ - 2} ({\text{d}}f_{\beta } ,S_{\beta }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003c7;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) for genotypic values. Genotypic effects (<italic>g</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>) were predicted as <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$g_{i} = \sum\nolimits_{j = 1}^{j = p} {x_{ij} \hat{\beta }_{j} }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Starting values were set for the degrees of freedom of the inverse Chi-squared distributions (d<italic>f</italic>) as 5 and scale parameters were calculated as <italic>S</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;var(<italic>y</italic>)&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.5 following P&#x000e9;rez and de los Campos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2014</xref>). We used 1500 burn-in and 3000 iterations for the Gibbs sampler algorithm implemented in &#x02018;BGLR&#x02019; package (P&#x000e9;rez and de los Campos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2014</xref>). Prediction accuracies for the ST model were estimated using only one cross-validation approach CV1 (de Leon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2016</xref>), explained below and in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. <fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Predictive strategies for an expensive or difficult-to-measure trait (i.e., Trait 1). ST-CV1: single-trait prediction cross-validation 1 where a trait is predicted at a time; we used 60% of individuals as the training population (phenotyped and genotyped, green) and 40% of the individuals as the testing population (genotyped but not phenotyped, purple) as an example; MT-CV1: multi-trait prediction for new un-phenotyped individuals; we used 60% of individuals as the training population (phenotyped for all traits and genotyped, green) and 40% of the individuals as the testing population (genotyped but not phenotyped for any trait, purple) as an example; MT-CV2: multi-trait prediction with cross-validation 2 where 100% of the information from three correlated traits is available for the individuals to be predicted; we used 60% of individuals as the training population (phenotyped for all traits and genotyped, green) and 40% of the individuals as the testing population (phenotyped for correlated traits but not for the targeted trait, and genotyped, purple) as an example; MT-CV2-50%b: multi-trait prediction cross-validation 2 with 50% of balanced information in three correlated traits where the same 50% of individuals were phenotyped for each correlated traits; MT-CV2-50%u: multi-trait prediction cross-validation 2 with 50% of unbalanced information in three correlated traits where 50% of individuals were phenotyped for each correlated trait but in an unbalanced manner such that each individual is not necessarily phenotyped for all correlated traits. Rectangles represent lines and colors the presence (green) or absence (purple) of phenotypic information (color figure online)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Fig1_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Multi-trait models</title><p id="Par21">Multi-trait models (MT) were estimated fitting a Bayesian multivariate Gaussian model estimating an unstructured variance&#x02013;covariance matrix between traits (&#x02211;) and a residual matrix (<italic>R</italic>). The multi-trait model is:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$y = 1\mu + Zu + \varepsilon$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>y</italic> is a vector of <italic>N&#x02009;</italic>&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>t</italic> length (<italic>N</italic> individuals and <italic>t</italic> traits), <italic>&#x000b5;</italic> is the means vector of length <italic>N&#x02009;</italic>&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>t</italic>; <italic>u</italic> is a vector of predicted genetic values of the individuals for all traits with <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$u\,\sim\,N\left( {0, \sum \otimes K} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02297;</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <italic>&#x003b5;</italic> is a vector of residuals with <inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varepsilon \,\sim\,N\left( {0,R \otimes I} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02297;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <italic>K</italic> is the realized additive relationship matrix among individuals estimated from the markers, and &#x02211; and <italic>R</italic> are the variance&#x02013;covariance matrices for the genetic and residual effects for each individual in all traits, respectively, estimated using a Gibbs sampler algorithm with 1500 burn-in and 3000 iterations. &#x02211; was estimated as an unstructured matrix and <italic>R</italic> as a diagonal matrix. We used a diagonal matrix for <italic>R</italic> instead of an unstructured matrix because the predictive ability was higher with the diagonal matrix. To estimate &#x02211; and <italic>R</italic>, scaled inverse Chi-square prior distributions were assigned to &#x02211;&#x02009;~&#x02009;<inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\chi^{ - 2} \left( {{\text{d}}f_{\varSigma } ,S_{\varSigma } } \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003c7;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003a3;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003a3;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <italic>R</italic>&#x02009;~&#x02009;<inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\chi^{ - 2} \left( {{\text{d}}f_{\text{R}} ,S_{\text{R}} } \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003c7;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, with arbitrary assigned initial scale random matrix <inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$S_{\varSigma }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003a3;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x02009;=&#x02009;I<sub>t</sub>, <inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$S_{R} = 1_{t}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and degrees of freedom <inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{d}}f_{\varSigma }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003a3;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 and <inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{d}}f_{R} = 1_{t}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The predictions were obtained using the &#x02018;MTM&#x02019; package in <italic>R</italic> (de los Campos and Gr&#x000fc;neberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2016</xref>). Finally, a multi-trait model without marker information was evaluated using the same multi-trait model but with an identity matrix for <italic>K</italic> instead of the realized additive relationship matrix.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Cross-validation scheme</title><p id="Par23">Prediction accuracies were estimated using two main strategies of cross-validation also shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The first cross-validation strategy (CV1 following de Leon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2016</xref>) used phenotypic and genotypic information from a random set of the advanced inbred lines to train the model (for example, 60% of the population or 297 individuals). Then, the remaining lines (for example, 40% or 198) were predicted using genotypic data only. Pearson&#x02019;s correlations between the adjusted phenotypic means (model 1) and their predicted values (model 3) were estimated. This process was iterated 100 times selecting different sets of lines each time. This scheme of cross-validation was used for ST and MT models (ST-CV1 and MT-CV1).</p><p id="Par24">The second cross-validation strategy (CV2 following de Leon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2016</xref>) used phenotypic and genotypic information from a random set of lines (for example 60% or 297 individuals) from the trait of interest to train the model. In addition, phenotypic and genotypic information for all lines of correlated traits was used. The trait of interested was predicted in the lines not phenotyped for the trait of interest (for example, 40% or 198 individuals, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Pearson&#x02019;s correlations between adjusted phenotypic means (model 1) and predicted values (model 4) were estimated. This process was iterated 100 times selecting different set of lines each time. This scheme of cross-validation was used only for the MT models (MT-CV2). Multi-trait models were used to predict traits including information from up to three correlated traits which were chosen based on their relationships revealed by principal component analyses and their Pearson&#x02019;s correlations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Improving efficiency of phenotyping</title><p id="Par25">In order to evaluate the possibility to train the models with fewer phenotyped lines, we trained the MT models using 50 to 396 individuals (10 to 80%) from the training population and 100% of the lines phenotyped for the other correlated traits for <italic>W</italic>, <italic>L</italic> and MH. This strategy was used to predict each trait at a time using three correlated traits from the same group of traits (4<italic>T</italic>), two traits from the group (3<italic>T</italic>) or one trait from the group (2<italic>T</italic>). The 2<italic>T</italic> models were constructed with SV for both <italic>W</italic> and MH and with WG for <italic>L</italic>. The 3<italic>T</italic> models were constructed with SV and MH for <italic>W</italic>, SV and TW for MH, and WG and Pt for <italic>L</italic>. We evaluated the accuracy of the predictions using 100 iterations in all traits and CV2.</p><sec id="Sec12"><title>Prediction for alveograph and mixograph parameters (MH, <italic>W</italic> and <italic>L</italic>)</title><p id="Par26">In order to improve the efficiency to predict complex traits such as the parameters from the alveograph or mixograph, we compared the prediction of MH, <italic>W</italic> and <italic>L</italic> using different depth of phenotypic information on correlated traits. The mixograph parameter MT was not evaluated because it is poorly correlated with other traits in its group. First, we evaluated different sizes of this training population for the predicted traits when information on the other three traits was present only in 50% of the lines in a balanced or unbalanced manner. We used the same approach as before with 10&#x02013;80% of the training population for predicting the traits but using phenotypic information for only 50% of the lines for each correlated trait. To mask 50% of the lines, we followed two strategies: designed as balanced (MT-CV2-50%b) or unbalanced (MT-CV2-50%u). The balanced strategy masks the same 50% of the lines in all correlated traits. In the unbalanced strategy, each trait is also phenotyped in 50% of the individuals, but different individuals are phenotyped for different traits. To mask 50% of the lines, both, the training and testing sets were divided in four equal parts. Then, two different sets from the training and two different sets from the testing were masked in each correlated trait. The lines were randomly assigned to each of the four sets. This procedure was conducted for 100 random iterations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Phenotypic characterization of the population</title><p id="Par27">Genotypic means for the multi-environment evaluation were used for genomic predictions since genotype by environment interaction among years was low (i.e., high correlation between environments, large heritability across environments, and relatively low proportion of the total phenotypic variance explained by the genotype by environment interaction; Table S2). Two groups of correlated traits were defined using principal component analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) and Pearson&#x02019;s correlation between traits (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The first and second principal components explained 40 and 20% of the total phenotypic variance, respectively. Both groups were represented by four traits. Group 1 includes MH, SV and <italic>W</italic> with high correlation and TW with intermediate correlation with all other traits (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Group 2 includes Pt, WG, MT and <italic>L</italic>. MT had a low and negative correlation with all traits in this group. The heritability for each trait was medium (0.36&#x02013;0.64, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Principal component analysis for the eight baking bread quality traits where the total phenotypic variance explained by each principal component is indicated</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Fig2_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Scatter plot matrix with Pearson&#x02019;s correlations and phenotypic distributions and trait heritability (on the diagonal) for each group of traits. Group 1 (left) including: TW, test weight; MH, mixograph height; SV, SDS sedimentation volume; <italic>W</italic>, alveograph parameter <italic>W</italic>. Group 2 (right) including: WG, wet gluten; MT, mixing time; Pt, grain protein content; <italic>L</italic>, alveograph <italic>L</italic>. *** indicates significantly different from 0 with <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Fig3_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Multi-trait genomic predictions</title><p id="Par28">Similar predictive ability of ST and MT models was found for predicting new un-phenotype individuals (ST-CV1 and MT-CV1, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The traits with the highest predictive ability were TW and Pt (<inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$r_{{\left( {y,\hat{y}} \right)}} = 0.43$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.43</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> for both), while the trait with the lowest predictive ability was <italic>L</italic> (<inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$r_{{\left( {y,\hat{y}} \right)}} = 0.24$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Predictive ability (<inline-formula id="IEq26"><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$r\left( {y,\hat{y}} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M60"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq26.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) for eight baking bread quality traits. Single-trait prediction model (ST-CV1), and multi-trait prediction model (MT) with two schemes of cross-validation (MT-CV1, predicting new individuals and MT-CV2, predicting individuals phenotyped for correlated traits) with or without genotypic information (CV2<sub>G</sub> and CV2<sub>NG</sub>, respectively). Group 1 of traits (above): TW, test weight; MH, mixograph height; SV, SDS sedimentation volume; W, alveograph parameter W. Group 2 of traits (below): WG, wet gluten; MT, mixograph parameter-mixing time; Pt, grain protein content; L: alveograph parameter <italic>L</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Fig4_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig>
</p><sec id="Sec16"><title>Multi-trait predictions using correlated traits</title><p id="Par29">Using information of correlated traits from predicted individuals increased the predictive ability for all traits (MT-CV1 vs MT-CV2, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The improvement in predictive ability through CV2 was different for each trait and related to the correlation between traits. In the group 1, TW was the trait with the smallest increase in predictive ability (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) due to its low correlation to other traits (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). On the other hand, the increase obtained for highly correlated traits, MT, W and SV, was high. In the group 2, WG was the trait with the largest increase in predictive ability, and this was the trait with the highest correlation with the others three traits in the group (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Replace phenotyping</title><p id="Par30">Using correlated traits from predicted individuals, the training population size can be reduced up to 30% of its size without significantly affecting the predictive ability of the model (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In addition, the inclusion of marker information improved 2&#x02013;14% the predictive ability of multi-trait models for <italic>W</italic> and there was no improvement for <italic>L</italic> trait (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Predictive ability (<inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$r\left( {y,\hat{y}} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M62"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) and standard deviation (shadowed interval) for the alveograph parameters W and L using different sizes of the training population (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;495) on the predicted trait. The traits were predicted using the multi-trait model cross-validation 2 (MT-CV2) with four, three or two traits (4<italic>T</italic>, 3<italic>T</italic> and 2<italic>T</italic>), and single-trait model (ST-CV1) to predict one trait (1<italic>T</italic>). Prediction was assessed using genotypic information (<italic>W</italic><sub>G</sub> and <italic>L</italic><sub>G</sub>) and without genotypic information (<italic>W</italic><sub>NG</sub> and <italic>L</italic><sub>NG</sub>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Fig5_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par31">One highly correlated trait (2<italic>T</italic>) increased more than 50% the predictive ability compared to the single-trait model for both <italic>W</italic> and <italic>L</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Two highly correlated traits (3<italic>T</italic>) increased the predictive ability a 14% for W and a 3% for L compared to the model with one correlated trait (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). TW did not contribute substantially to <italic>W</italic> predictions, while MH and SV improved the predictive ability regardless of the model used (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In addition, MT and Pt did not contribute to L predictions, while WG increased the predictive ability for <italic>L</italic>.</p><p id="Par32">To predict an expensive trait using correlated traits with equal phenotyping cost, a purposefully unbalanced phenotyping design with 50% of each trait was explored (MT-CV2 50%u). In this case, each trait was phenotyped for 50% of the individuals but for different individuals with some overlaps. This strategy yielded higher predictive ability than using even more phenotyping but only in the training population (MT-CV1 vs MT-CV2 50%u, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). For example, 396 individuals phenotyped for <italic>W</italic> on a ST model had a predictive ability of 0.361&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09, while phenotyping 99 individuals for <italic>W</italic> and 495 for SV had a predictive ability of 0.404&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The predictive ability using MT-CV2 50%u for two traits was between 28 and 34% higher than the ST model for MH, <italic>W</italic> and <italic>L</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Deep phenotyping on correlated trait always reached higher predictive ability than reducing the phenotyping to 50% of the lines for these traits. The predictions obtained using an unbalanced strategy were slightly larger than using the balanced strategy. However, there were no differences in the predictive ability of both strategies used to phenotype 50% of the lines.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Predictive ability (<inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$r\left( {y,\hat{y}} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M64"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Article_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) and standard deviation (shadowed interval) of alveograph parameters (<italic>W</italic>, <italic>L</italic>) and mixograph parameter (MH) predictions using different sizes of training population (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;495). Single-trait predictions (ST-CV1) were obtained using the predicted trait to train model (1<italic>T</italic>), or one, two or three correlated traits to train the model (MT-CV2 for 2<italic>T</italic>, 3<italic>T</italic> and 4<italic>T</italic>, respectively). MT-CV2: multi-trait predictions with 100% of information in three correlated traits; MT-CV2-50%u: multi-trait predictions with 50% of unbalanced information in three correlated traits; MT-CV2-50%b: multi-trait predictions with 50% of balanced information in three correlated traits</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="122_2018_3186_Fig6_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par33">Our grouping of traits, where one group was associated with gluten strength and the other one was related to protein quantity, is similar to that found in V&#x000e1;zquez et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2012</xref>). The high correlation we found between MH, <italic>W</italic> and SV was also found in others studies (Pe&#x000f1;a et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">1994</xref>; Ruiz and Carillo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1995</xref>; Indrani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>). Model predictive ability using single-trait prediction through CV1 with 40% of randomly masked individuals (198 individuals) was lower (between 0.24 and 0.43) than previously found in Battenfield et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2016</xref> (between 0.45 and 0.60) predicted using 20% randomly masked individuals. In addition, they were higher than those found in Hayes et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>) although the strategy used to predict performance was different; here, we used cross-validation approaches and Hayes et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>) predicted traits across years and locations.</p><sec id="Sec19"><title>Multi-trait genomic predictions</title><p id="Par34">Predicting new un-phenotyped individuals is always a challenge, and different strategies have been used to improve the predictive ability in those circumstances. The use of correlated trait responses has been effective when the predicted trait is of low heritability and the highly correlated trait is of high heritability (Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>; Guo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2014</xref>; Jiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>). These has been thoroughly studied both theoretically and empirically, within classic quantitative genetic studies (Falconer and Mackay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1996</xref>; Lynch and Walsh <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1998</xref>) and with genomic studies (Calus and Veerkamp <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>; Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>; Guo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2014</xref>; Jiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>). However, for very complex polygenic traits, there is a small advantage of a multi-trait model with correlated responses even with high heritability differences among traits (Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>). Furthermore, studies with real experimental data from quantitative genetics using genomic information did not show a significant improvement of multi-trait models in mice (Jiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>), avocado (He et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2016</xref>), maize (Dos Santos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2016</xref>) or rice (Schulthess et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2016</xref>). We found a similar response, where the multi-trait model (MT-CV1) did not perform better than the single-trait model (ST-CV1). This was somewhat expected because although our traits were correlated, all traits have high heritability and because of the theoretical complexity of the traits (Nelson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2006</xref>; Sun et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2008</xref>; Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2016</xref>).</p><sec id="Sec20"><title>Predictions for partially phenotyped individuals</title><p id="Par35">Correlated traits can also be used to predict a correlated response when the individuals have been phenotyped for other traits (Rutkoski et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2012</xref>; Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>). Some previous work showed high prediction accuracy using highly correlated traits, but not with intermediate to low correlated traits (Calus and Veerkamp <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>; Jia and Jannink <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>; Jiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>). We found the same trend in our study, where the use of correlated responses using information from other traits increased the predictive ability of models, and the predictive ability was directly related to the correlation between traits. Therefore, correlated traits in the lines to be predicted can be used to increase the predictive ability of the models.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Predictions for replace phenotyping</title><p id="Par36">We showed that the use of correlated traits from predicted individuals (MT-CV2) increase the predictive ability of the models, and this was somewhat already shown. The next question we wanted to address was how much could we reduce the depth of phenotyping of an expensive trait (i.e., <italic>W</italic> or <italic>L</italic> in or study based on prices from the Canadian Grain Commission, Wheat Marketing Center, and AIB International), and in consequence the training population size, by using correlated traits without compromising the predictive ability of the model. It has been widely proven that smaller population sizes reduce prediction accuracy (Asoro et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2011</xref>; Heffner et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>; Rincent et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2012</xref>; Akdemir et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>; Rutkoski et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2015</xref>; Cericola et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2017</xref>). However, our hypothesis was that by using correlated traits we could somewhat offset the effect of smaller population sizes. This hypothesis was tested with a range of population sizes (i.e., 50 to 396 individuals or 10 to 80%) and with real data. We found that the training population could be reduced up to 30% of the total population without significantly affecting the predictive ability of the models if correlated traits were used. Our results show that it is possible to effectively design training populations where expensive or difficult-to-phenotype traits are phenotyped at a smaller depth than cheaper or easier-to-phenotype correlated traits. Our results were obtained with individuals from the training population chosen at random. Other studies (Akdemir et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>; Isidro et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2015</xref>; Rincent et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2017</xref>) found that optimizing the training population to select the most predictive individuals instead of using a random sample increases the predictive ability. We would therefore expect that our results are the baseline for the gain that could be achieved by using replaced phenotyping when the training population is optimized.</p><p id="Par37">We found that the increase in predictive ability including marker information was marginal compared to the multi-trait model using phenotypic data from correlated traits when a large number of highly correlated traits were used. However, Crain et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2018</xref>) showed the importance of using marker information to predict traits in a new environment where phenotypic correlation could be lower than expected due to genotype by environment interaction. In our work, we conducted cross-validation using the same population, but this will not be the situation during selection in a breeding program.</p><p id="Par38">We showed that expensive traits could be assessed for fewer individuals without affecting its predictive ability if information of correlated trait is used from all individuals. This requires extensive phenotyping for all correlated traits. Our results showed that the predictive ability using 50% of correlated information (MT-CV2-50%u) was lower than in the full phenotyping (MT-CV2) models. However, the predictive ability was still high. In addition, the use of an unbalanced strategy to reduce phenotyping on correlated traits was slightly better than reducing phenotyping using a balanced strategy (MT-CV2-50%u vs MT-CV2-50%b). Therefore, unbalanced phenotyping of correlated traits could be another approach to predict traits that are expensive or labor-intensive.</p><p id="Par39">Finally, we evaluated whether the inclusion of more than one trait increases the predictive ability of the model if this trait is highly correlated. We found that models with two highly correlated traits are better than models with one highly correlated trait. However, the increase in predictions is low with the addition of a second correlated trait. Therefore, it will be important to evaluate the cost of prediction using two instead of one correlated trait, balancing gain in accuracy with the costs of using another trait to help predictions. The use of mildly correlated traits such as TW, MT, and Pt was not useful.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par40">The use of multi-trait models is useful to improve the predictive ability of partially phenotyped individuals. Expensive or difficult-to-phenotype traits can be phenotyped in smaller population sizes if the predicted individuals are phenotyped fully or partially for less expensive correlated traits. Particularly, we found that the use of only one correlated trait in the model was the most effective way to increase the predictive ability with fewer resources.</p><sec id="d29e2325"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p>DV and MQ designed the phenotyping experiments. BL and PS performed genotyping analyses. BL, LG and IA performed statistical analyses. BL, LG, PS and IA wrote the paper. LG designed the study and hypothesis. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec23"><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="122_2018_3186_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary material 1 (PDF 232&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We express our appreciation for the effort of the technical personnel of INIA La Estanzuela from &#x02018;Laboratorio de calidad industrial de granos.&#x02019; Support for doctoral work of BL was provided by Agencia Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n e Innovaci&#x000f3;n (ANII), Uruguay, through Grant POS_NAC_2013_1_11261 and by Comisi&#x000f3;n Sectorial de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Cient&#x000ed;fica (CSIC), Uruguay, through grants in the program internships abroad. We would like to thank two anonymous reviewers for their comments that improved the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">AACC (2000) AACC International approved methods of analysis, 11th edn. AACC International, St. Paul, MN. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://methods.aaccnet.org/toc.aspx">http://methods.aaccnet.org/toc.aspx</ext-link>. Accessed 23 Jan 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akdemir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of genomic selection training populations with a genetic algorithm</article-title><source>Genet Sel Evol</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>38</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12711-015-0116-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25943105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asoro</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beavis</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy and training population design for genomic selection on quantitative traits in Elite North American Oats</article-title><source>Plant Genome J</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3835/plantgenome2011.02.0007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battenfield</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzm&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaynor</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreisigacker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic selection for processing and end-use quality traits in the CIMMYT spring bread wheat breeding program</article-title><source>Plant Genome</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3835/plantgenome2016.01.0005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgue&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>de los Campos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic prediction of breeding values when modeling genotype&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;environment interaction using pedigree and dense molecular markers</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2011.06.0299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calus</surname><given-names>MPL</given-names></name><name><surname>Veerkamp</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy of multi-trait genomic selection using different methods</article-title><source>Genet Sel Evol</source><year>2011</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>26</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1297-9686-43-26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21729282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cericola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahoor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Orabi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Janss</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimizing training population size and genotyping strategy for genomic prediction using association study results and pedigree information. a case of study in KASP</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0169606</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0169606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28081208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ceron-Rojas</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arief</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Basford</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutkoski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarqu&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyene</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Semagn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLacy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genomic selection index applied to simulated and real data</article-title><source>G3 (Bethesda)</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>2155</fpage><lpage>2164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.115.019869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26290571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutkoski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combining high-throughput phenotyping and genomic information to increase prediction and selection accuracy in wheat breeding</article-title><source>Plant Genome</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>170043</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3835/plantgenome2017.05.0043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Leon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaeppler</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction to a special issue on genotype by environment interaction</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>2081</fpage><lpage>2089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2016.07.0002in</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">de los Campos G, Gr&#x000fc;neberg A (2016) MTM package. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://quantgen.github.io/MTM/vignette.html">http://quantgen.github.io/MTM/vignette.html</ext-link>. Accessed 23 Jan 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de los Campos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pong-Wong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Daetwyler</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Calus</surname><given-names>MPL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome regression and prediction methods applied to plant and animal breeding</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2013</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.112.143313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22745228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>JPR</given-names></name><name><surname>De Castro Vasconcellos</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>LPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Balestre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Pinho</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inclusion of dominance effects in the multivariate GBLUP model</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0152045</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0152045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27074056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endelman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ridge regression and other kernels for genomic selection with R package rrBLUP</article-title><source>Plant Genome</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3835/plantgenome2011.08.0024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endelman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shrinkage estimation of the realized relationship matrix</article-title><source>G3 Genes Genomes Genetics</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>1413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.112.004259</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23173092?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23173092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falconer</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>TFC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Introduction to quantitative genetics</source><year>1996</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ronald Press Company</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">FAO (2017) Food and agriculture organization of the United Nations. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/faostat/en/#home">http://www.fao.org/faostat/en/#home</ext-link>. Accessed 23 Jan 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glaubitz</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Casstevens</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Harriman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Elshire</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckler</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TASSEL-GBS: a high capacity genotyping by sequencing analysis pipeline</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e90346</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24587335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of single-trait and multiple-trait genomic prediction models</article-title><source>BMC Genet</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-15-30</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24593261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernando</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekkers</surname><given-names>JCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of genetic relationship information on genome-assisted breeding values</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2007</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>2389</fpage><lpage>2397</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18073436?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18073436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>MacRitchie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Weegels</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chapter 6: structure and functional properties of gluten</article-title><source>Wheat: chemistry and technology</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>St. Paul</publisher-loc><publisher-name>AACC International, Inc.</publisher-name><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JPCK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kant</surname><given-names>ALCS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accelerating wheat breeding for end- use quality with multi- trait genomic predictions incorporating near infrared and nuclear magnetic resonance-derived phenotypes</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2017</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>2505</fpage><lpage>2519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-017-2972-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28840266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazel</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genetic basis for constructing selection indexes</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1943</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17247099?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17247099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Parida</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel applications of multitask learning and multiple output regression to multiple genetic trait prediction</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>i37</fpage><lpage>i43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27307640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heffner</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic selection accuracy using multifamily prediction models in a wheat breeding program</article-title><source>Plant Genome</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3835/plantgenome2010.12.0029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Quaas</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple trait evaluation using relatives&#x02019; records</article-title><source>J Anim Sci</source><year>1976</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1188</fpage><lpage>1197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas1976.4361188x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heslot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives for genomic selection applications and research in plants</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2014.03.0249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Indrani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Manohar</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajiv</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alveograph as a tool to assess the quality characteristics of wheat flour for parotta making</article-title><source>J Food Eng</source><year>2007</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1202</fpage><lpage>1206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2005.12.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isidro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Akdemir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heslot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Training set optimization under population structure in genomic selection</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-014-2418-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25367380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple-trait genomic selection methods increase genetic value prediction accuracy</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2012</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>1513</fpage><lpage>1522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.112.144246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23086217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Joint prediction of multiple quantitative traits using a Bayesian multivariate antedependence model</article-title><source>Heredity (Edinb)</source><year>2015</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hdy.2015.9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25873147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficiency of marker-assisted selection in the improvement of quantitative traits</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1990</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1968875?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1968875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenth</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Least-squares means: the R package lsmeans</article-title><source>J Stat Softw</source><year>2016</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v069.i01</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single nucleotide polymorphisms linked to quantitative trait loci for grain quality traits in wheat</article-title><source>Crop J</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cj.2015.10.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Asoro</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Heffner</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic selection in plant breeding. Knowledge and prospects</article-title><source>Adv Agron</source><year>2011</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-385531-2.00002-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Genetics and analysis of quantitative traits</source><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>Sunderland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sinauer Associates Inc</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacRitchie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical properties of wheat proteins in relation to functionality</article-title><source>Adv Food Nutr Res</source><year>1992</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1043-4526(08)60104-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meuwissen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of total genetic value using genome-wide dense marker maps</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2001</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>1819</fpage><lpage>1829</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11290733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11290733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreescu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Breseghello</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Finney</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Daisy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Perretant</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Qualset</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative trait locus analysis of wheat quality traits</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2006</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-005-9062-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajaram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in quality characteristics associated with some spring IB/IR translocation wheats</article-title><source>J Cereal Sci</source><year>1990</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0733-5210(09)80092-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarco-Hernandez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaya-Celis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mujeeb-Kazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between chromosome 1B-encoded glutenin subunit composition and bread-making quality characteristic of some durum wheat (Triticum turgidum) cultivars</article-title><source>J Cere</source><year>1994</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>249</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>de los Campos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide regression and prediction with the</article-title><source>Genet Soc Am</source><year>2014</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>495</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piepho</surname><given-names>H-P</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000f6;hring</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computing heritability and selection response from unbalanced plant breeding trials</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2007</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>1881</fpage><lpage>1888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.107.074229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18039886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pinheiro J, Bates D (2017) Linear and nonlinear mixed effects models. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/nlme/nlme.pdf">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/nlme/nlme.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 23 Jan 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of high-density genetic maps for barley and wheat using a novel two-enzyme genotyping-by-sequencing approach</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e32253</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22389690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Endelman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutkoski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Manes</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreisigacker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Villeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic selection in wheat breeding using genotyping-by-sequencing</article-title><source>Plant Genome J</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3835/plantgenome2012.06.0006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Development Core Team (2016) R: the R project for statistical computing. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>. Accessed 23 Jan 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rincent</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalo&#x000eb;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Revilla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Melchinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoen</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Giauffret</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Laborde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Monod</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Flament</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Charcosset</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maximizing the reliability of genomic selection by optimizing the calibration set of reference individuals: comparison of methods in two diverse groups of maize inbreds (Zea mays L.)</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2012</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.112.141473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22865733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rincent</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oury</surname><given-names>EKHMFX</given-names></name><name><surname>Rousset</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of multi-environment trials for genomic selection based on crop models</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2017</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1735</fpage><lpage>1752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-017-2922-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28540573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationships between different prolamin proteins and some quality properties in durum wheat</article-title><source>Plant Breed</source><year>1995</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0523.1995.tb00756.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutkoski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown-guedira</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of genomic prediction methods for fusarium head blight resistance in wheat</article-title><source>Plant Genome</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3835/plantgenome2012.02.0001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutkoski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Huerta-Espino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhavani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient use of historical data for genomic selection: a case study of stem rust resistance in wheat</article-title><source>Plant Genome</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutkoski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Autrique</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canopy temperature and vegetation indices from high-throughput phenotyping improve accuracy of pedigree and genomic selection for grain yield in wheat</article-title><source>G3 (Bethesda)</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2799</fpage><lpage>2808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.116.032888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27402362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saghai-Maroof</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribosomal DNA spacer-length polymorphisms in barley: mendelian inheritance, chromosomal location, and population dynamics</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1984</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>8014</fpage><lpage>8018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.81.24.8014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6096873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulthess</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miedaner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Reif</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple-trait and selection indices genomic predictions for grain yield and protein content in rye for feeding purposes</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-015-2626-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26561306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shewry</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hey</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The contribution of wheat to human diet and health</article-title><source>Food Energy Secur</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fes3.64</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27610232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A discriminant function for plant selection</article-title><source>Ann Eugen</source><year>1936</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-1809.1936.tb02143.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative trait loci (QTLs) for quality traits related to protein and starch in wheat</article-title><source>Prog Nat Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pnsc.2007.12.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutkoski</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multitrait, random regression, or simple repeatability model in high-throughput phenotyping data improve genomic prediction for wheat grain yield</article-title><source>Plant Genome</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3835/plantgenome2016.11.0111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>VanRaden</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient methods to compute genomic predictions</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>4414</fpage><lpage>4423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2007-0980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18946147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">V&#x000e1;zquez D (2009) Aptitud industrial de trigo. In: Inst. Nac. Investig. Agropecu. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.inia.uy/Publicaciones/Documentoscompartidos/18429130709133540.pdf">http://www.inia.uy/Publicaciones/Documentoscompartidos/18429130709133540.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 24 Jan 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e1;zquez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuniberti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bainotti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zavariz de Miranda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheeren</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jobet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Z&#x000fa;&#x000f1;iga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Verges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of cultivar and environment on quality of Latin American wheats</article-title><source>J Cereal Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcs.2012.03.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brien</surname><given-names>LOB</given-names></name><name><surname>Eagles</surname><given-names>HAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Solah</surname><given-names>VAA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayasena</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influences of genotype, environment, and genotype x environment interaction on wheat quality</article-title><source>Aust J Agric Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR07185</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>