<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6361001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6296</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biochemistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Food Science and Technology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Wild edible fool&#x02019;s watercress, a potential crop with high nutraceutical properties</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guijarro-Real</surname><given-names>Carla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prohens</surname><given-names>Jaime</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Burruezo</surname><given-names>Adrian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Adalid-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>Ana Mar&#x000ed;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Gresa</surname><given-names>M Pilar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-6" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fita</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name><email>anfifer@btc.upv.es</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Instituto de Conservaci&#x000f3;n y Mejora de la Agrodiversidad Valenciana (COMAV), Universitat Polit&#x000e8;cnica de Val&#x000e8;ncia</institution>, <city>Valencia</city>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Instituto de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular y Celular de Plantas (IBMCP), Universitat Polit&#x000e8;cnica de Val&#x000e8;ncia</institution>, <city>Valencia</city>, <country>Spain</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Ribeiro-Barros</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2019-02-01"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e6296</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-09-24"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-12-18"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2019 Guijarro-Real et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Guijarro-Real et al.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6296"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Fool&#x02019;s watercress (<italic>Apium nodiflorum</italic>) is an edible vegetable with potential as a new crop. However, little information is available regarding the antioxidant properties of the plant and the individual phenolics accounting for this capacity are unknown.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The antioxidant properties of twenty-five wild populations were analysed and individual phenolics present in the species reported and compared with celery and parsley. The antioxidant activity was measured as the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl hydrate (DPPH) free radical scavenging capacity, and the total phenolics content (TPC) via the Folin-Ciocalteu procedure. The individual phenolics constituents were determined via high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) as aglycones.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The average DPPH and TPC of fool&#x02019;s watercress were 28.1 mg Trolox g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW and 22.3 mg of chlorogenic acid equivalents g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW, respectively, much higher than those of celery and parsley. Significant differences for both DPPH and TPC, which may be explained by either genotype or environmental factors, were detected among groups established according to geographical origin. Quercetin was identified as the major phenolic present in the leaves of the species, unlike parsley and celery, in which high amounts of apigenin and luteolin were determined. Quercetin represented 61.6% of the phenolics targeted in fool&#x02019;s watercress, followed by caffeic acid derivatives as main hydroxycinnamic acids.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The study reports the high antioxidant properties of fool&#x02019;s watercress based on a large number of populations. Results suggest that quercetin accounts for an important share of the antioxidant capacity of this potential new crop. The study also provides a basis for future breeding programs, suggesting that selection by geographical locations may result in differences in the antioxidant properties.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Antioxidants</kwd><kwd><italic>Apium nodiflorum</italic></kwd><kwd>DPPH</kwd><kwd>New crops</kwd><kwd>Total phenolics</kwd><kwd>Quercetin</kwd><kwd>Wild edible plants</kwd><kwd>Flavonoids</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Ministerio de Educaci&#x000f3;n, Cultura y Deporte of Spain (MECD)</funding-source><award-id>FPU14-06798</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>Carla Guijarro-Real is supported by the Ministerio de Educaci&#x000f3;n, Cultura y Deporte of Spain (MECD) with a predoctoral FPU grant (FPU14-06798). There was no additional external funding received for this study. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Wild fruits and vegetables are part of the traditional cuisine in many countries of the Mediterranean region. Besides enriching the cuisine with particular tastes, many of them have also been used in the past as dietary supplements or sources of bioactive compounds, as well as in traditional medicine (<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Shikov et al., 2017</xref>). In the last decades, there has been an increasing interest in wild vegetables by consumers. Consequently, several works have evaluated the nutritional value of wild edible species and also assessed their bioactive health promoting properties (<xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Motamed &#x00026; Naghibi, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Egea-Gilabert et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Garc&#x000ed;a-Herrera et al., 2014</xref>). Moreover, domestication of wild species to be grown as new crops is an opportunity for increasing the offer in food markets. As examples, salad rocket (<italic>Eruca sativa</italic> Mill. and <italic>Diplotaxis tenuifolia</italic> (L.) DC.) and watercress (<italic>Rorippa nasturtium-acquaticum</italic> Hayek) have been adapted and developed as common crops (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Molina, Pardo-de Santayana &#x00026; Tard&#x000ed;o, 2016</xref>).</p><p><italic>Apium nodiflorum</italic> (L.) Lag., commonly known as fool&#x02019;s watercress or water celery, is a perennial herb from <italic>Apiaceae</italic> family. Well adapted to damp soils, it can be easily found, forming clamps, in fresh, shallow water courses such as streams or ditches. The species is broadly distributed along the temperate areas of central and southern Europe, northern Africa and western and central Asia (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Tard&#x000ed;o et al., 2016</xref>). It is widely distributed in Spain, including the Mediterranean coast (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Knees, 2003</xref>), a region with an ancient agricultural tradition. However, the alteration in the irrigation system to drip irrigation in agriculture and the reduction of river flows may negatively affect its natural distribution.</p><p>Wild fool&#x02019;s watercress has been traditionally harvested and consumed in several Mediterranean countries, such as Spain, Italy, Portugal or Morocco (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Tard&#x000ed;o et al., 2016</xref>). The edible parts are the young leaves and tender shoots, which are used as a vegetable and mainly consumed raw in salads, or to a lesser extent boiled or included as a condiment in soups and other dishes (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Parada, Carri&#x000f3; &#x00026; Vall&#x000e8;s, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Guarrera &#x00026; Savo, 2016</xref>). The species has been reported as appetite enhancer, diuretic, intestinal anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial and antifungal (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Menghini et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Maxia et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Guarrera &#x00026; Savo, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Tard&#x000ed;o et al., 2016</xref>). However, the nutritional and bioactive value of the species has not been extensively studied. <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Garc&#x000ed;a-Herrera (2014)</xref> classified fool&#x02019;s watercress as a vegetable with a high content in calcium and sodium, although its consumption should be moderate for people with kidney damage due to the content in oxalic acid, as revealed by <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Morales (2011)</xref>. The plant may be also considered as a source of vitamin E and B<sub>9</sub> (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Tard&#x000ed;o et al., 2016</xref>). But the greatest interest considering its nutritional capacity is probably due to the high content in phenolic compounds together with the strong antioxidant activity that presents (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Morales et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>Phenolic compounds can be included into different categories attending to their chemical composition, being flavonoids and phenolic acids the most common classes in plants (<xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2016</xref>). They commonly appear as glycosides in plants, conjugated to other molecules such as sugars, amines, organic acids or other phenolic compounds (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barba, Esteve &#x00026; Fr&#x000ed;gola, 2014</xref>). Besides the importance of these metabolites for plants defence and survival (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Cartea et al., 2011</xref>), flavonoids and phenolic acids are considered of great importance for human health due to their antioxidant capacity (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Kaushik et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Sahidi &#x00026; Ambigaipalan, 2015</xref>). As antioxidants, they neutralize reactive oxygen species, which in excess can produce molecular and cellular disorders causing several diseases (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Prasad, Gupta &#x00026; Tyagi, 2017</xref>). However, this capacity is greatly dependent on the chemical structure of each molecule (<xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Zaluski, Ciesla &#x00026; Janeczko, 2015</xref>).</p><p>Flavonoids and phenolic acids are commonly found in <italic>Apiaceae</italic> (<xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Sayed-Ahmad et al., 2017</xref>) and daily used spices and aromatic herbs of the family have been studied for these compounds. For instance, leaves of parsley (<italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> (Mill.) Nyman) and celery (<italic>Apium graveolens</italic> L. var. <italic>dulce</italic>) are good sources of apigenin (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">P&#x000e1;pay et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2017</xref>), with levels that can reach 630 mg 100 g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> FW (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Justesen &#x00026; Knuthsen, 2001</xref>) and 970 mg 100 g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> FW (<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Yao &#x00026; Ren, 2011</xref>), respectively. Polyphenol glycosides including apigenin, quercetin, chlorogenic acid, caffeic acid or ferulic acid derivatives have been detected in fennel (<italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> Mill.) (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Salami, Rahimmalek &#x00026; Ehtemam, 2016</xref>). And <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al. (2012)</xref> determined that coriander leaves (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.) are rich in quercetin derivatives, with a total value of 494 mg 100 g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW, and also present relevant contents of <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid derivatives. However, we have not found references to the phenolic constituents of the edible organs of fool&#x02019;s watercress.</p><p>We consider that there is a need to evaluate the antioxidant properties and phenolic composition of fool&#x02019;s watercress since this edible species has potential as a source of antioxidants. So far, little information on the diversity for phenolics content and antioxidant activity in the species is available (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Morales et al., 2012</xref>). The study of several populations may offer more accurate information for the antioxidant properties and phenolic content of the species. Thus, in the present study we evaluated the antioxidant activity of a set of populations of fool&#x02019;s watercress. We also determined the main phenolic compounds in an attempt to correlate them with the antioxidant properties of this species. We included two related crops with similar uses in the analysis (celery and parsley) in order to compare data of wild and related cultivated species. The results obtained may be also useful for considering the domestication of fool&#x02019;s watercress.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Plant material and sample preparation</title><p>The Horta Nord of Valencia (Spain), an area with many irrigation ditches used for centuries by the farmers, was prospected. The prospection took place in the spring season of 2015 and was focused on the locations where ditches are still in use and a regular water flow is provided (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). A total of twenty-five wild isolated masses of fool&#x02019;s watercress were sampled. Samples were grouped by their geographical origin and seven groups were established according to the following geographical areas: Puerto de Sagunto (FW1), Puzol-El Puig (FW2), Masamagrell (FW3), Albuixech-Albalat dels Sorells (FW4), Foios-Meliana town (FW5), Meliana beach-Alboraya-Valencia (FW6) and Pueblo Nuevo-Alfara del Patriarca (FW7) (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Plant of fool&#x02019;s watercress.</title><p>(A) Wild population growing in an irrigation ditch. (B) Sample representing the edible part of this plant. Author: C. Guijarro-Real</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6296-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Geographical situation of the wild populations of fool&#x02019;s watercress harvested in the region of Valencia (Spain) and identification of the groups established by their origin.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6296-g004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Geographical group</bold><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Population</bold><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Location</bold></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Coordinates</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puerto de Sagunto</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;37&#x02032;36&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;16&#x02032;49&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puerto de Sagunto</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;37&#x02032;55&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;16&#x02032;11&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puzol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;36&#x02032;08&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;18&#x02032;08&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">El Puig</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;35&#x02032;09&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;17&#x02032;45&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">El Puig</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;36&#x02032;00&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;18&#x02032;05&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">El Puig</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;35&#x02032;33&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;16&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Masamagrell</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;34&#x02032;04&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;42&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Masamagrell</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;33&#x02032;59&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;48&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Masamagrell</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;33&#x02032;42&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;18&#x02032;25&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albuixech</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;33&#x02032;04&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;39&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albuixech</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;32&#x02032;37&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;55&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albuixech</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;32&#x02032;29&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;27&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albuixech</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;32&#x02032;43&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;07&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albalat dels Sorells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;32&#x02032;04&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;26&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foios</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;31&#x02032;59&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;20&#x02032;31&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foios</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;32&#x02032;16&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;20&#x02032;49&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meliana (town)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;31&#x02032;26&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;20&#x02032;52&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meliana (beach)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;31&#x02032;01&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;36&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alboraya</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;30&#x02032;59&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;19&#x02032;37&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valencia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;28&#x02032;57&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;20&#x02032;11&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pueblo Nuevo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;30&#x02032;39&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;22&#x02032;57&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pueblo Nuevo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;30&#x02032;39&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;23&#x02032;10&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pueblo Nuevo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;31&#x02032;19&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;23&#x02032;17&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alfara del Patriarca</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;31&#x02032;37&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;22&#x02032;36&#x02033;W</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alfara del Patriarca</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b0;32&#x02032;21&#x02033;N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b0;23&#x02032;06&#x02033;W</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1"><label>a</label><p>Codes FW1 to FW7 refer to the seven geographical groups in which the populations of fool&#x02019;s watercress have been clustered.</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn2"><label>b</label><p>Nod-001 to Nod-025 refer to the codes given to the twenty-five populations of fool&#x02019;s watercress analysed in the study.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The aerial part was air-dried in oven at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, with low humidity conditions, for three days, in order to prevent water activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). Dried samples were powdered with a commercial grinder and used for the determinations, which were carried out in triplicates. For comparison of results, celery and parsley species were also analysed. Thus, two commercial samples of celery, and two commercial samples of parsley, each one coming from different local markets, were acquired and processed in the same way than samples of fool&#x02019;s watercress.</p></sec><sec><title>Evaluation of the antioxidant activity and total phenolics content</title><p>The antioxidant activity was measured as the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl hydrate (DPPH) free radical scavenging capacity as described by <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Rufino et al. (2007)</xref>. Subsamples of 0.1 g were extracted with 5 mL methanol (50% v/v) plus 5 mL acetone (70% v/v), then samples of fool&#x02019;s watercress diluted (1:2). Absorbance was measured at 515 nm after 25&#x000a0;min of incubation with DPPH (Sigma-Aldrich, Sant Louis, MO, USA) solution (0.025 g/L in methanol). The antioxidant Trolox (Scharlab S.L., Sentmenat, Barcelona, Spain) was used as standard and results were expressed as milligrams of Trolox equivalents per gram of dry weight (mg Trolox g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW).</p><p>Total phenolics were extracted from subsamples of 0.125 g with 5 mL acetone (70% v/v) containing glacial acetic acid (0.5% v/v) and determined according to the Folin-Ciocalteu procedure (<xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Singleton &#x00026; Rossi, 1965</xref>) as indicated in <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Plazas et al. (2014)</xref>. Absorbance was measured at 750 nm after 95&#x000a0;min of incubation with the diluted Folin-Ciocalteu reagent (10% v/v) (Scharlab S.L.). Chlorogenic acid (Sigma-Aldrich) was used as standard and results were expressed as milligrams of chlorogenic acid equivalents per gram of dry weight (mg CAE g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW).</p></sec><sec><title>Phenolics profile</title><p>Phenolic compounds were extracted from subsamples of 0.1 g with 1.5 mL methanol (80% v/v) including 0.1% (w/v) 2,6-di-<italic>tert</italic>-butyl-4-methylphenol (BHT) (Sigma-Aldrich) (<xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Plazas et al., 2014</xref>). Then, an hydrolysis was performed by adding 1.2 M HCl for two hours at 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for fool&#x02019;s watercress and celery, and 2 M HCl for four hours for parsley (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Justesen &#x00026; Knuthsen, 2001</xref>), to a final methanol solution of 50% (v/v).</p><p>Samples were analysed on a HPLC 1220 Infinity LC System (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). A BRISA C18 column (150 mm &#x000d7;&#x000a0;4.6 mm i.d., 3 &#x000b5;m particle size; Teknokroma, Barcelona, Spain) was used and the injection volume was 10 &#x000b5;l. Mobile phase consisted of two solvents, (A) 0.1% formic acid in water and (B) methanol with gradient elution. Hydroxycinnamic acids profile was studied under the following conditions (<xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Yildiz et al., 2008</xref>): starting with 7% (B) the first 8 min, raising up to 30% (B) at 13 min, 66% (B) at 48 min, 75% (B) at 50 min, 100% (B) at 54 min and maintained for 2 min, then decreasing to initial conditions of 7% (B) at 60 min and equilibrated for 5&#x000a0;min. Flow rate was 1 mL min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and the absorbance was fixed at 320 nm. The study of flavonoids was performed as described by <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Bae et al. (2012)</xref> with a flow rate of 0.8 mL min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and a fixed absorbance of 360 nm, using the same solvents as above. The gradient elution started with 40% (B) following to 100% (B) at 10 min and maintained for 5&#x000a0;min, then decreasing to the initial conditions at 20 min and equilibrated for 5&#x000a0;min.</p><p>A tentative identification of the compounds was performed by comparison of the retention time from the peaks with commercial standards (Sigma-Aldrich), and with published data. Standards from common phenolics described in <italic>Apiaceae</italic> were selected and used in this study (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), which their general chemical structures are represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>. Due to the possible partial hydrolysis of chlorogenic acid to caffeic acid under the above cited conditions, concentration of both compounds were added and considered together as caffeic acid derivatives.</p><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Phenolic aglycones commonly cited in the literature for the family <italic>Apiaceae</italic>.</title><p>It is indicated the class classification according to the chemical structure as well as the retention time in the current conditions (Rt, min).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6296-g005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Rt</bold><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Compound</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Class</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>References</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quercetin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Justesen (2000)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Justesen &#x00026; Knuthsen (2001)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al. (2012)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Vallverd&#x000fa;-Queralt et al., (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Salami, Rahimmalek &#x00026; Ehtemam (2016)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luteolin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Crozier et al. (1997)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Justesen (2000)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Justesen &#x00026; Knuthsen (2001)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Vi&#x000f1;a &#x00026; Chaves (2007)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Yildiz et al., (2008)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al. (2012)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaempferol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Justesen, Knuthsen &#x00026; Leth (1998)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Justesen (2000)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Justesen &#x00026; Knuthsen (2001)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Yao et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Yao &#x00026; Ren (2011)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al., (2012)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apigenin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Crozier et al. (1997)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Justesen &#x00026; Knuthsen (2001)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Yildiz et al. (2008)</xref><xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Hossain et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al. (2012)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorogenic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydroxycinnamic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Vi&#x000f1;a &#x00026; Chaves (2007)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al., (2012)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Vallverd&#x000fa;-Queralt et al. (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Salami, Rahimmalek &#x00026; Ehtemam (2016)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caffeic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydroxycinnamic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al. (2010)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Hossain et al. (2011)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Yao &#x00026; Ren (2011)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Vallverd&#x000fa;-Queralt et al. (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Salami, Rahimmalek &#x00026; Ehtemam (2016)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p-</italic> Coumaric acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydroxycinnamic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al. (2010)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Yao &#x00026; Ren (2011)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al. (2012)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Vallverd&#x000fa;-Queralt et al. (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Salami, Rahimmalek &#x00026; Ehtemam (2016)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferulic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydroxycinnamic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al. (2010)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Yao &#x00026; Ren (2011)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al. (2012)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Vallverd&#x000fa;-Queralt et al., (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Salami, Rahimmalek &#x00026; Ehtemam (2016)</xref></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1"><label>a</label><p>Rt obtained in the conditions described by <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Yildiz et al. (2008)</xref> (hydroxycinnamic acids) or <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Bae et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref> (flavones and flavonols).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Chemical structure of the phenolic compounds evaluated in the samples of fool&#x02019;s watercress, celery and parsley.</title><p>The phenolics targeted included the following hydroxycinnamic acids (A): caffeic acid (<italic>R</italic><sup>1</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;OH), chlorogenic acid (<italic>R</italic><sup>1</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;OH plus the carboxylic group esterified with quinic acid), <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid (<italic>R</italic><sup>1</sup>&#x000a0;= OH, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;= H) and ferulic acid (<italic>R</italic><sup>1</sup>&#x000a0;= OH, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;= OCH<sub>3</sub>); and the flavonoids (B): apigenin (<italic>R</italic><sup>1</sup>&#x000a0;= OH, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sup>3</sup>&#x000a0;= H), kaempferol (<italic>R</italic><sup>1</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sup>3</sup>&#x000a0;= OH, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;= H), luteolin (<italic>R</italic><sup>1</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;= OH, <italic>R</italic><sup>3</sup> = H) and quercetin (<italic>R</italic><sup>1</sup>&#x000a0;= <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sup>3</sup>&#x000a0;= OH).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6296-g002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>The average values of DPPH and total phenolics content (TPC) in each sample were used to obtain the mean value and the average standard error of the seven geographical groups of fool&#x02019;s watercress (FW1-FW7), celery (GRAV, as average of two samples, Grav-01 and Grav-02), and parsley (CRI, as average of two samples, Cri-01 and Cri-02). Data were analysed using a one-way factorial analysis of variance (ANOVA) considering the groups as a factor and significant differences between groups were calculated with the Student-Newman-Keuls test. Ten selected populations of fool&#x02019;s watercress with low and high antioxidant activities and overall representing four geographical groups, plus the two samples of celery and the two of parsley, were analysed for phenolic profile by HPLC, in triplicates. Finally, Pearson pairwise comparisons were performed in order to evaluate correlations between DPPH, TPC and the content in phenolics determined as sum of the individual phenolics targeted.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>DPPH radical-scavenging activity and TPC</title><p>A highly significant variation (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001) between fool&#x02019;s watercress and celery and parsley was found for the DPPH scavenging capacity (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The average DPPH capacity of fool&#x02019;s watercress was 28.12 mg Trolox g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW. This value was 3.5-fold higher than the DPPH value for celery (8.09 mg Trolox g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW) and 12.8-fold higher compared to parsley (2.20 mg Trolox g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW). Values of the seven geographical groups considered in fool&#x02019;s watercress ranged from 15.17 to 36.97 mg Trolox g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW (FW2 and FW7, respectively; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;0.01), with continuous variation among them (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Mean values and range for DPPH radical-scavenging activity and TPC for fool&#x02019;s watercress, celery, and parsley groups.</title><p><italic>N</italic> is the number of populations included in each group. Statistics includes the mean squares values (MS) for group and residuals, and the value of the <italic>F</italic>-test for differences among groups.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6296-g006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>(mg Trolox g</italic><sup>&#x02212;1</sup><italic>DW)</italic></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>(mg CAE g</italic><sup>&#x02212;1</sup><italic>DW)</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Group</bold><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>N</italic></bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DPPH</bold><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Range</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TPC</bold><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Range</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.19 cd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(22.84&#x02013;33.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.16 c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(23.12&#x02013;25.21)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.17 bc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.34&#x02013;18.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.90 ab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13.26&#x02013;18.91)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.61 cd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(19.95&#x02013;36.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.73 c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.31&#x02013;26.97)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.29 cd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(19.86&#x02013;38.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.73 c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(18.58&#x02013;27.56)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.67 cd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.14&#x02013;29.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.82 bc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(18.55&#x02013;21.82)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.23 d</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30.74&#x02013;33.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.89 c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(23.17&#x02013;24.39)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.97 d</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.96&#x02013;43.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.19 c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(21.19&#x02013;28.91)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GRAV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.09 ab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.47&#x02013;8.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.32 a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12.71&#x02013;13.93)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.87&#x02013;2.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.98 ab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12.58&#x02013;17.38)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MS group</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>373.28</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>64.28</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MS residual</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>36.98</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>7.02</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prob <italic>F-</italic> test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-3fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-3fn1"><label>a</label><p>Groups FW1 to FW7 refer to the seven geographical groups in which the populations of fool&#x02019;s watercress have been clustered (see <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). GRAV refers to the celery group, including Grav-01 and Grav-02 samples. CRI refers to the parsley group, including Cri-01 and Cri-02 samples.</p></fn><fn id="table-3fn2"><label>b</label><p>Different letters indicate significant differences according to the Student-Newman-Keuls test (confidence level 95.0%).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the case of TPC, differences were less remarkable in absolute values but also highly significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001) (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Celery and parsley presented similar average values of 13.32 mg of chlorogenic acid equivalents (CAE) g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW and 14.98 mg CAE g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW, respectively, while the average content determined for fool&#x02019;s watercress was 22.35 mg CAE g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW. However, the variation in this species ranged from 15.90 (FW2) to 26.19 mg CAE g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW (FW7), which meant that geographical groups with the lowest content were comparable to celery and parsley. As in the DPPH radical-scavenging activity, a continuous variation was observed for the total of groups established with significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01).</p></sec><sec><title>Phenolic profile of fool&#x02019;s watercress, celery, and parsley</title><p>Ten populations of fool&#x02019;s watercress from diverse geographical groups (FW2, FW4, FW5 and FW7) and overall representing samples with low and high antioxidant capacity and TPC were used for analysing the phenolic profile of the species and comparing it with those of celery and parsley (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-1">Fig. S1</xref>). The content in phenolics of fool&#x02019;s watercress, obtained as sum of individual phenolics, ranged from 1.20 to 7.12 mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW (for populations Nod-004 and Nod-021, respectively), with a mean value of 4.19 mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW (<xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Samples with the highest values corresponded to the geographical group FW7 (mean value 6.71 mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW) while those with low content belonged to the geographical groups FW2 and FW5 (mean values 1.92 and 2.76 mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW, respectively). Populations from geographical group FW4 showed intermediate content (mean value 4.15 mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW). On the other hand, the mean values for celery and parsley were 7.63 and 4.76 mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW, respectively.</p><table-wrap id="table-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296/table-4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Mean values for the content of individual phenolics targeted, DPPH radical-scavenging activity and TPC in individual samples of fool&#x02019;s watercress, celery, and parsley.</title><p>The content of each phenolic targeted is expressed as &#x000b5;g g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW, the sum of the individual phenolics targeted (&#x003a3; i.p.) as mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW, the DPPH as mg Trolox g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW and the TPC as mg CAE g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW. Statistics includes the mean squares values (MS) for species and residuals, and the value of the <italic>F</italic>-test for differences among species.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6296-g007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CF der</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CMA</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FRA</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AP</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>KM</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>LT</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>QR</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003a3;<bold>i.p.</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DPPH</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TPC</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-003<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-4fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">640.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">214.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1478.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">203.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">751.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2232.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">935.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2567.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1100.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">490.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2729.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">449.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">184.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1920.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">703.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1407.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1178.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">652.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4684.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1041.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">228.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">295.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">448.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4004.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nod-024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1299.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">747.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4252.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mean</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">799.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">368.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2602.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cri-01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3828.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cri-02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4815.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">319.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mean</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4321.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">249.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grav-01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">511.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">287.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2742.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3593.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grav-02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2695.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5058.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mean</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">329.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2718.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4325.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>species</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#x022c5;10<sup>6</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1&#x022c5;10<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9&#x022c5;10<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9&#x022c5;10<sup>7</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8&#x022c5;10<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#x022c5;10<sup>7</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6&#x022c5;10<sup>6</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6&#x022c5;10<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>residual</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#x022c5;10<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9&#x022c5;10<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7&#x022c5;10<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5&#x022c5;10<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8&#x022c5;10<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4&#x022c5;10<sup>5</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4&#x022c5;10<sup>6</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1&#x022c5;10<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P. <italic>F-</italic> test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.712</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.454</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-4fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-4fn1"><label>a</label><p>Samples Nod-003 to Nod-024 refer to the ten samples of species fool&#x02019;s watercress evaluated. Samples Cri-01 and Cri-02 refer to the two samples of parsley evaluated. Samples Grav-01 and Grav-02 refer to the two samples of celery evaluated.</p></fn><fn id="table-4fn2" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl1"><def-head>TITLE</def-head><def-item><term> CF der</term><def><p>caffeic acid derivatives</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> CMA</term><def><p><italic>p-</italic>coumaric acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> FRA</term><def><p>ferulic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> AP</term><def><p>apigenin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> KM</term><def><p>kaempferol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> LT</term><def><p>luteolin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> QR</term><def><p>quercetin</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In addition, the relative content of each compound against the sum of the phenolics targeted was determined (%, indicating mg of each compound mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of total compounds) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>). In general, flavonoid compounds comprised the most representative group considering the total identified, with an average relative abundance of 76.4%, 92.7% and 97.0% for fool&#x02019;s watercress, celery and parsley, respectively. Nevertheless, the profile of individual phenolics varied considerably between species, both qualitatively and quantitatively. Quercetin was the major flavonoid in fool&#x02019;s watercress (61.6%), while this flavonoid represented less than 0.3% in celery and parsley. On the contrary, apigenin was found as the major phenolic in parsley (90.7%) but it only represented 0.8% in fool&#x02019;s watercress. This flavonoid ranked second in concentration in celery (35.8%), after luteolin (56.3%). Compared to celery, luteolin abundance was 6.6-fold lower in fool&#x02019;s watercress and 11-fold lower in parsley. Finally, kaempferol was present in fool&#x02019;s watercress in a relative abundance of 4.3% in contrast with parsley, in which represented only 0.9%. This compound was not detected in celery.</p><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Relative abundance and standard error (&#x000b5;g compound &#x000b5;g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> total) of individual phenolics identified.</title><p>(A) Phenolics identified in the samples of fool&#x02019;s watercress. (B) Phenolics identified in the samples of celery. (C) Phenolics identified in the samples of parsley. The abbreviations correspond to: caffeic acid derivatives (CF der), <italic>p-</italic> coumaric acid (CMA), ferulic acid (FRA), apigenin (AP), kaempferol (KM), luteolin (LT) and quercetin (QR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6296-g003"/></fig><p>Differences in the composition of phenolic acids were also determined. The only hydroxycinnamic acid detected in leaves of parsley was <italic>p-</italic>coumaric and represented 3.0% of the total phenolics. On the contrary, the four hydroxycinnamic acids targeted were detected in fool&#x02019;s watercress and celery. The relative concentration of these compounds in leaves of celery ranged from 0.5% for ferulic acid to 4.5% for caffeic acid derivatives. Ferulic acid was also the minor phenolic acid detected in fool&#x02019;s watercress (1.2%), followed by <italic>p-</italic>coumaric acid (4.2%). Caffeic acid derivatives were determined as the main hydroxycinnamic acids of fool&#x02019;s watercress (19.4%).</p></sec><sec><title>Correlation between antioxidant parameters</title><p>The Pearson linear correlation coefficient (r) between the DPPH radical-scavenging activity and TPC in fool&#x02019;s watercress populations was <italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.903 (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001). For those samples of fool&#x02019;s watercress that were analysed by HPLC, correlation coefficient values between DPPH, TPC and the content in targeted phenolics were also studied. The content in targeted phenolics as sum of the individual compounds presented high correlation coefficients with both the DPPH scavenging activity and TPC (<italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.924 and <italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.933, respectively; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The present study highlights the antioxidant capacity of fool&#x02019;s watercress in terms of DPPH scavenging activity and TPC. These results are in agreement with published data. For example, <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Morales et al. (2012)</xref> analysed four wild leafy vegetables (<italic>A. nodiflorum, F.&#x000a0;vulgare</italic>, <italic>Montia fontana</italic> L. and <italic>Silene vulgaris</italic> (Moench) Garcke.) and obtained the highest values for DPPH and TPC in fool&#x02019;s watercress. In addition, fool&#x02019;s watercress also has high antioxidant activity compared to other common aromatic herbs and spices from the same family. <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Hossain et al. (2011)</xref> evaluated those parameters for fennel, celery, cumin and parsley. Values of DPPH-radical scavenging activity in these spices were 1.7 to 9.7-fold lower than the antioxidant capacity of fool&#x02019;s watercress. On the contrary, the TPC calculated there for the four spices were quite similar to the range determined in fool&#x02019;s watercress.</p><p>Comparison among different geographical groups of fool&#x02019;s watercress revealed moderate differences for the TPC and the DPPH radical scavenging activity. The production and accumulation of these secondary metabolites can be affected by the environmental conditions and stress situations as well as by genetic diversity (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Kaulmann et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Galieni et al., 2015</xref>). Thus, differences between geographical groups may result from genotypic differences or by divergence of particular environmental conditions. The evaluation of genetic and environmental effects needs to be studied in future selection programmes aimed at the development of fool&#x02019;s watercress as a new crop with high antioxidant properties as added value.</p><p>Our results also reveal differences in the phenolic profile of the three species. Fool&#x02019;s watercress displayed low amounts of apigenin and luteolin in contrast to parsley and celery, vegetables described as sources of these compounds (<xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2016</xref>). On the contrary, quercetin was detected as the main flavonoid of fool&#x02019;s watercress. Quercetin has been also detected within the <italic>Apiaceae</italic> in fresh herbs such as coriander, dill or fennel (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Salami, Rahimmalek &#x00026; Ehtemam, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">El-Zaeddi et al., 2017</xref>). Regarding to the hydroxycinnamic acids studied (caffeic acid, chlorogenic acid, <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid and ferulic acid), the four of them have been previously detected in fennel (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Salami, Rahimmalek &#x00026; Ehtemam, 2016</xref>); these authors found that chlorogenic acid was the main phenolic acid. Chlorogenic acid is rapidly hydrolysed to caffeic acid in alkaline conditions (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Mattila &#x00026; Kumpulainen, 2002</xref>), while it is considered more stable at low pH. However, we noted a partial hydrolysis of chlorogenic acid to caffeic acid under the current conditions. Due to this reason, we considered both hydroxycinnamic acids, that is, chlorogenic and caffeic acids, together as caffeic acid derivatives, and the individual values were not given.</p><p>In agreement with our results, positive, strong correlation between DPPH and TPC has been previously established in other vegetables, including common spices and wild species (<xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Morales et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Skotti et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2015</xref>). However, in other cases this correlation was not so clear (<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Albano &#x00026; Miguel, 2011</xref>). Discrepancies may be explained in part by the composition of the evaluated matrix, as well as the possible interferences of different compounds others than phenolics with the reagents, as they could be tocopherols, aminoacids or, commonly to many fruits, ascorbic acid (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Craft et al., 2012</xref>). However, the ascorbic acid is an unstable metabolite highly sensitive that can be easily degraded with the consequence of losing the antioxidant capacity. Conditions such as exposure to oxygen (e.g., during the extraction step and storage of extracts), humidity, or temperature of drying and store can affect the stability of ascorbic acid (e.g., <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Kaya, Aydin &#x00026; Kolayli, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Van Bree et al., 2012</xref>). Moreover, this molecule is commonly stabilized with <italic>meta</italic>-phosphoric, in order to preserve it from degradation during storage of the extract (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Chebrolu et al., 2012</xref>). On the contrary, phenolic compounds are stable molecules, not affected by the drying process (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Bianchi &#x00026; Lo Scalzo, 2018</xref>). Our results suggest that the antioxidant capacity of the dried leaves in this species is mainly due to the phenolic compounds, according to the high correlation established between the two parameters. In the same way, the high correlation between the sum of the individual phenolics of fool&#x02019;s watercress detected by HPLC and both the DPPH radical-scavenging activity and TPC indicated that the compounds identified account for the antioxidant activity of the species.</p><p>Although celery presented the highest values of phenolics measured by HPLC and contents determined in parsley were also remarkable, the antioxidant capacity measured in these species was lower than the obtained in fool&#x02019;s watercress, especially in the case of DPPH radical-scavenging activity. A possible reason may be found in the chemical structure of the major compounds detected in the different species, as well as the synergistic effects of different phenolic compounds present in specific species. The number and position of hydroxyl groups affect the antioxidant capacity of polyphenols (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Cartea et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Zaluski, Ciesla &#x00026; Janeczko, 2015</xref>). The antioxidant capacity of these compounds would decrease in the following order: quercetin &#x0003e;luteolin &#x0003e;apigenin (<xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Yildiz et al., 2008</xref>), which could explain the relatively poor DPPH activity of parsley in comparison with the two other species. In celery, both apigenin and luteolin would account for an important share of the antioxidant capacity. Finally, the highly remarkable DPPH radical-scavenging activity of fool&#x02019;s watercress would be correlated to the content in quercetin, which is in addition a molecule that has been related with a protective and inhibition action against several cancers, in cellular models but also <italic>in vivo</italic> in mammals (<xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Sharmila et al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our results reveal that fool&#x02019;s watercress is a leafy vegetable with high antioxidant activity, especially in comparison to the related cultivated parsley and celery. The high correlation between DPPH radical scavenging activity and TPC suggested that the antioxidant activity of this species is mainly caused by the phenolic compounds accumulated in the leaves. When the phenolic profile was analysed, we observed that, unlike celery and parsley, quercetin was the main compound present in the species. This finding may explain the greatest antioxidant activity of fool&#x02019;s watercress, resulting from the higher antioxidant capacity of this flavonoid compared to apigenin and luteolin, the main compounds detected in parsley and celery, respectively (<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Rice-Evans, Miller &#x00026; Paganga, 1996</xref>). In addition, results revealed differences among the geographical groups established for the total of populations of fool&#x02019;s watercress, indicating that selection among geographical origins may result in differences in bioactive properties. Although these differences may be caused by either genetic variation or environmental conditions, our results offer a starting point for future domestication and breeding programs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title> Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296/supp-1</object-id><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title>Representative chromatograms of fool&#x02019;s watercress, celery and parsley</title><p>(A) Chromatogram obtained with the conditions described by <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Yildiz et al. (2008)</xref>, and identification of the hydroxycinnamic acids targeted. Peaks correspond to: 1 chlorogenic acid, 2 caffeic acid, 3<italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid, and 4 ferulic acid. (B) Chromatogram obtained with the conditions described by <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Bae et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref>, and identification of the flavonoids (aglycones) targeted. Peaks correspond to: 5 quercetin, 6: luteolin, 7: kaempferol, and 8: apigenin. Note that different chromatograms may have different scales.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-6296-s001.png"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6296/supp-2</object-id><label>Data S1</label><caption><title>Raw data of the analyses performed</title><p>Raw data file includes the content in total phenolics (mg of chlorogenic acid equivalents per gram of dry matter), and the DPPH value (mg of Trolox equivalents per gram of dry matter), for the twenty-five populations of fool&#x02019;s watercress (Nod-001 to Nod-025), two of parsley (Cri-01 and Cri-02), and two of celery (Grav-01 and Grav-02). The file also includes the content of individual phenolics (micrograms per gram of dry matter) targeted by HPLC for the selected samples. Each data correspond to one individual measurement.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-6296-s002.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>Authors thank Mr. Manuel Figueroa for his help in the botanical identification of the plant.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Carla Guijarro-Real</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Jaime Prohens</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Adrian Rodriguez-Burruezo</xref> and <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-6">Ana Fita</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-4" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-4">Ana Mar&#x000ed;a Adalid-Mart&#x000ed;nez</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-5" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-5">M Pilar L&#x000f3;pez-Gresa</xref> performed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The raw data is available in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-1">Supplemental File</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Albano &#x00026; Miguel (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albano</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miguel</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Biological activities of extracts of plants grown in Portugal</article-title><source>Industrial Crops and Products</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2010.11.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Bae et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayaprakasha</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jifon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Extraction efficiency and validation of an HPLC method for flavonoid analysis in peppers</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>130</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.07.041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Barba, Esteve &#x00026; Fr&#x000ed;gola (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barba</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Esteve</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fr&#x000ed;gola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Bioactive components from leaf vegetable products</article-title><volume>Vol. 41</volume><source>Studies in natural products chemistry</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Atta-ur Rahman</surname><given-names>FRS</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Elsevier Inc.</publisher-name><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-444-63294-4.00011-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Barros et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Due&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos-Buelga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>ICFR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Phenolic profiles of <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> grown <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.11.048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Bianchi &#x00026; Lo&#x000a0;Scalzo (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo&#x000a0;Scalzo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Characterization of hot pepper spice phytochemicals, taste compounds content and volatile profiles in relation to drying temperature</article-title><source>Journal of Food Biochemistry</source><volume>2018</volume><elocation-id>e12675</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jfbc.12675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Cartea et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cartea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Francisco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soengas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Phenolic compounds in <italic>Brassica</italic> vegetables</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/Molecules16010251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Chebrolu et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chebrolu</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayaprakasha</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun&#x000a0;Yoo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jifon</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>An improved sample preparation method for quantification of ascorbic acid and dehydroascorbic acid by HPLC</article-title><source>LWT&#x02014;Food Science and Technology</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2012.02.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Craft et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craft</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerrihard</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Amarowicz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pegg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Phenol-based antioxidants and the <italic>in vitro</italic> methods used for their assessment</article-title><source>Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1541-4337.2011.00173.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Crozier et&#x000a0;al. (1997)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crozier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lean</surname><given-names>MEJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Quantitative analysis of the flavonoid content of commercial tomatoes, onions, lettuce, and celery</article-title><source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf960339y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Egea-Gilabert et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egea-Gilabert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni&#x000f1;irola</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Candela</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Agronomical use as baby leaf salad of <italic>Silene vulgaris</italic> based on morphological, biochemical and molecular traits</article-title><source>Scientia Horticulturae</source><volume>152</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2013.01.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>El-Zaeddi et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Zaeddi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cal&#x000ed;n-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowicka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Tom&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguera-Artiaga</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Burl&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojdy&#x00142;o</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonell-Barrachina</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Preharvest treatments with malic, oxalic, and acetylsalicylic acids affect the phenolic composition and antioxidant capacity of coriander, dill and parsley</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>226</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.01.067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28254010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Galieni et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galieni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Di&#x000a0;Mattia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Gregorio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Speca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastrocola</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pisante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stagnari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Effects of nutrient deficiency and abiotic environmental stresses on yield, phenolic compounds and antiradical activity in lettuce (<italic>Lactuca sativa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Scientia Horticulturae</source><volume>187</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2015.02.036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Garc&#x000ed;a-Herrera (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Herrera</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Plantas silvestres de consumo tradicional. Caracterizaci&#x000f3;n de su valor nutricional y estimaci&#x000f3;n de su actividad antif&#x000fa;ngica</article-title><source>D Pharm. Thesis</source><institution>Universidad Complutense de Madrid</institution></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Garc&#x000ed;a-Herrera et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Herrera</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Mata</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e1;mara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Ruiz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;ez-Marqu&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tard&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Nutrient composition of six wild edible Mediterranean <italic>Asteraceae</italic> plants of dietary interest</article-title><source>Journal of Food Composition and Analysis</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfca.2014.02.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Guarrera &#x00026; Savo (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guarrera</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Savo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Perceived health properties of wild and cultivated food plants in local and popular traditions of Italy: a review</article-title><source>Journal of Ethnopharmacology</source><volume>146</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2013.01.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23395624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Guarrera &#x00026; Savo (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guarrera</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Savo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Wild food plants used in traditional vegetable mixtures in Italy</article-title><source>Journal of Ethnopharmacology</source><volume>185</volume><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2016.02.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26944238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Hossain et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Patras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry-Ryan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin-Diana</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunton</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Application of principal component and hierarchical cluster analysis to classify different spices based on in vitro antioxidant activity and individual polyphenolic antioxidant compounds</article-title><source>Journal of Functional Foods</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2011.03.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Justesen (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Justesen</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Negative atmospheric pressure chemical ionisation low-energy collision activation mass spectrometry for the characterisation of flavonoids in extracts of fresh herbs</article-title><source>Journal of Chromatography A</source><volume>902</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9673(00)00861-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11192169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Justesen &#x00026; Knuthsen (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Justesen</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Knuthsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Composition of flavonoids in fresh herbs and calculation of flavonoid intake by use of herbs in traditional Danish dishes</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0308-8146(01)00114-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Justesen, Knuthsen &#x00026; Leth (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Justesen</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Knuthsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Quantitative analysis of flavonols, flavones, and flavanones in fruits, vegetables and beverages by high performance liquid chromatography with photo-diode array and mass spectrometric detection</article-title><source>Journal of Chromatography A</source><volume>799</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9673(97)01061-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9550103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Kaulmann et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaulmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonville</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Carotenoids, polyphenols and micronutrient profiles of <italic>Brassica oleraceae</italic> and plum varieties and their contribution to measures of total antioxidant capacity</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>155</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.01.070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24594181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Kaushik et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>And&#x000fa;jar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilanova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Plazas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramazio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Herraiz</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brar</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Prohens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Breeding vegetables with increased content in bioactive phenolic acids</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>18464</fpage><lpage>18481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules201018464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26473812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Kaya, Aydin &#x00026; Kolayli (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolayli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Effect of different drying conditions on the vitamin C (ascorbic acid) content of Hayward kiwifruits (<italic>Actinidia deliciosa</italic> Planch)</article-title><source>Food and Bioproducts Processing</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fbp.2008.12.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Knees (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knees</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title><italic>Apium</italic> L</article-title><series>Vol. X: Araliaceae-Umbelliferae</series><source>Flora Ib&#x000e9;rica: Plantas Vasculares de La Pen&#x000ed;nsula Ib&#x000e9;rica E Islas Baleares</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Castroviejo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Real Jard&#x000ed;n Bot&#x000e1;nico-CSIC</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>275</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Mattila &#x00026; Kumpulainen (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattila</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumpulainen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Determination of free and total phenolic acids in plant-derived foods by HPLC with diode-array detection</article-title><source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>3660</fpage><lpage>3667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf020028p</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12059140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Maxia et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maxia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Falconieri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Piras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Porcedda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marongiu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Frau</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavaleiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Salgueiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Chemical composition and antifungal activity of essential oils and supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> extracts of <italic>Apium nodiflorum</italic> (L.) lag</article-title><source>Mycopathologia</source><volume>174</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11046-011-9519-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22237925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Menghini et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menghini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Leporini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tirillini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Epifano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Genovese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Chemical composition and inhibitory activity against <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> of the essential oil of <italic>Apium nodiflorum</italic> (<italic>Apiaceae</italic>)</article-title><source>Journal of Medicinal Food</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jmf.2009.0010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20136461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Molina, Pardo-de Santayana &#x00026; Tard&#x000ed;o (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo-de Santayana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tard&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Natural production and cultivation of Mediterranean wild edibles</article-title><source>Mediterranean wild edible plants: ethnobotany and food composition tables</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Mata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tard&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>107</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Morales (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Vegetales silvestres de uso alimentario: determinaci&#x000f3;n de compuestos bioactivos y capacidad antioxidante</article-title><source>D Pharm. Thesis</source><institution>Universidad Complutense de Madrid</institution></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Morales et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Mata</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e1;mara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>ICFR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Tocopherol composition and antioxidant activity of Spanish wild vegetables</article-title><source>Genetic Resources and Crop Evolution</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10722-011-9726-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Morales et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>ICFR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Mata</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e1;mara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Ruiz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo-de Santayana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tard&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Mediterranean non-cultivated vegetables as dietary sources of compounds with antioxidant and biological activity</article-title><source>LWT&#x02014;Food Science and Technology</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2013.08.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Motamed &#x00026; Naghibi (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motamed</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Naghibi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Antioxidant activity of some edible plants of the Turkmen Sahra region in northern Iran</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>119</volume><fpage>1637</fpage><lpage>1642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2009.09.057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>P&#x000e1;pay et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e1;pay</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000e1;llai-Szab&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lud&#x000e1;nyi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Klebovich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Antal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Development of oral site-specific pellets containing flavonoid extract with antioxidant activity</article-title><source>European Journal of Pharmaceutical Science</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejps.2016.10.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Parada, Carri&#x000f3; &#x00026; Vall&#x000e8;s (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carri&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Ethnobotany of food plants in the Alt Empord&#x000e0; region (Catalonia, Iberian Peninsula)</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Botany and Food Quality</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Plazas et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plazas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Prohens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cu&#x000f1;at</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilanova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramazio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Herraiz</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>And&#x000fa;jar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Reducing capacity, chlorogenic acid content and biological activity in a collection of scarlet (<italic>Solanum aethiopicum</italic>) and gboma (<italic>S. macrocarpon</italic>) eggplants</article-title><source>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>17221</fpage><lpage>17241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms151017221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25264739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Prasad, Gupta &#x00026; Tyagi (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) and cancer: role of antioxidative nutraceuticals</article-title><source>Cancer Letters</source><volume>387</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2016.03.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27037062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Rice-Evans, Miller &#x00026; Paganga (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice-Evans</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Paganga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Structure-antioxidant activity relationships of flavonoids and phenolic acids</article-title><source>Free Radical Biology &#x00026; Medicine</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>933</fpage><lpage>956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0891-5849(95)02227-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8743980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>Rufino et&#x000a0;al. (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rufino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Morais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saura-Calixto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Determina&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da atividade antioxidante total em frutas pela captura do radical livre ABTS</article-title><source>Comunicado T&#x000e9;cnico 127</source><institution>Embrapa Agroind&#x000fa;stria Tropical, Fortaleza</institution></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Sahidi &#x00026; Ambigaipalan (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahidi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambigaipalan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Phenolics and polyphenolics in foods, beverages and spices: antioxidant activity and health effects&#x02014;a review</article-title><source>Journal of Functional Foods</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>820</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2015.06.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Salami, Rahimmalek &#x00026; Ehtemam (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimmalek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehtemam</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Inhibitory effect of different fennel (<italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic>) samples and their phenolic compounds on formation of advanced glycation products and comparison of antimicrobial and antioxidant activities</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>213</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.06.070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27451172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Sayed-Ahmad et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sayed-Ahmad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Talou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hijazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Merah</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>The <italic>Apiaceae</italic>: ethnomedicinal family as source for industrial uses</article-title><source>Industrial Crops and Products</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2017.09.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Sharmila et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharmila</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Athirai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiruthiga</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Elumalai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arunkumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arunakaran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Chemopreventive effect of quercetin in MNU and testosterone induced prostate cancer of Sprague-Dawley rats</article-title><source>Nutrition and Cancer</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01635581.2014.847967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24320139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Shikov et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shikov</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsitsilin</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozharitskaya</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></name><name><surname>Makarov</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Traditional and current food use of wild plants listed in the Russian Pharmacopoeia</article-title><source>Frontiers in Pharmacology</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>841</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2017.00841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29209213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Singleton &#x00026; Rossi (1965)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1965</year><article-title>Colorimetry of total phenolics with phosphomolybdic phosphotungstic acid reagents</article-title><source>American Journal of Enology and Viticulture</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>158</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Skotti et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skotti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Anastasaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanellou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Polissiou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarantilis</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Total phenolic content, antioxidant activity and toxicity of aqueous extracts from selected Greek medicinal and aromatic plants</article-title><source>Industrial Crops and Products</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2013.12.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Tang et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>ELH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajarajeswaran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanthimathi</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title><italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> has antioxidant properties, protects against DNA damage and inhibits proliferation and migration of cancer cells</article-title><source>Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>2763</fpage><lpage>2771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.7078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25582089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Tard&#x000ed;o et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tard&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Mata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Herrera</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;ez-Marqu&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Ruiz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e1;mara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo-de Santayana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matallana-Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Mata</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Torija-Isasa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guil-Guerrero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boussalah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Ethnobotanical and food composition monographs of selected Mediterranean wild edible plants</article-title><source>Mediterranean wild edible plants: ethnobotany and food composition tables</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Mata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tard&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>470</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Vallverd&#x000fa;-Queralt et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vallverd&#x000fa;-Queralt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Regueiro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Hu&#x000e9;lamo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi&#x000a0;Alvarenga</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Neto&#x000a0;Leal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamuela-Raventos</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>A comprehensive study on the phenolic profile of widely used culinary herbs and spices: rosemary, thyme, oregano, cinnamon, cumin and bay</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>154</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2013.12.106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24518346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Van&#x000a0;Bree et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van&#x000a0;Bree</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Baetens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Samapundo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Devlieghere</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Laleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandekinderen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Noseda</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xhaferi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Baets</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Meulenaer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Modelling the degradation kinetics of vitamin C in fruit juice in relation to the initial headspace oxygen concentration</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2012.02.096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Vi&#x000f1;a &#x00026; Chaves (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vi&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Respiratory activity and phenolic compounds in pre-cut celery</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>1654</fpage><lpage>1660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2005.12.060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Yao &#x00026; Ren (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Effect of thermal treatment on phenolic composition and antioxidant activities of two celery cultivars</article-title><source>LWT&#x02014;Food Science and Technology</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2010.07.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Yao et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Phenolic composition and antioxidant activities of 11 celery cultivars</article-title><source>Journal of Food Science</source><volume>75</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2009.01392.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Yildiz et&#x000a0;al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ba&#x0015f;kan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>T&#x000fc;tem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Apak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Combined HPLC-CUPRAC (cupric ion reducing antioxidant capacity) assay of parsley, celery leaves, and nettle</article-title><source>Talanta</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.Talanta.2008.06.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18804638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Zaluski, Ciesla &#x00026; Janeczko (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaluski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciesla</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Janeczko</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>The structure&#x02013;activity relationships of plant secondary metabolites with antimicrobial, free radical scavenging and inhibitory activity toward selected enzymes</article-title><source>Studies in Natural Products Chemistry</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-444-63473-3.00007-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>Zhou et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Apigenin: a current review on its beneficial biological activities</article-title><source>Journal of Food Biochemistry</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>e12376</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jfbc.12376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>Zhou et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Natural polyphenols for prevention and treatment of cancer</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>515</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu8080515</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>