<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Anim Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Anim. Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jansci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Animal Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-8812</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1525-3163</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6313133</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30346551</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jas/sky408</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">sky408</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Animal Health and Well Being</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Heat stress abatement during the postpartum period: effects on whole lactation milk yield, indicators of metabolic status, inflammatory cytokines, and biomarkers of the oxidative stress</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Safa</surname><given-names>Soroush</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn-0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kargar</surname><given-names>Shahryar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn-0001"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>skargar@shirazu.ac.ir</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moghaddam</surname><given-names>Gholam Ali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ciliberti</surname><given-names>Maria Giovanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Caroprese</surname><given-names>Mariangela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Department of Animal Science, Faculty of Agriculture, University of Tabriz, Tabriz, Iran</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Department of Animal Science, School of Agriculture, Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran</aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>Department of the Sciences of Agriculture, Food and Environment (SAFE), University of Foggia, Via Napoli, Foggia, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding author: <email>skargar@shirazu.ac.ir</email></corresp><fn id="fn-0001"><p>These two authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-10-20"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>97</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the American Society of Animal Science.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="sky408.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The objective of this study was to determine the effect of cooling upon calving in alleviating the adverse effects of heat stress in Holstein lactating cows. Production performance, indicators of metabolic status, immune response, and biomarkers of oxidative stress were measured. Based on mature equivalent milk production, parity, and calving date, 46 multiparous lactating cows were allotted to groups of equal sizes (<italic>n</italic> = 23); heat stressed (<bold>HS</bold>; BW = 658 &#x000b1; 28 kg [mean &#x000b1; SD]; BCS = 2.7 &#x000b1; 0.18; parity = 3 &#x000b1; 0.12) and cooled (<bold>CL</bold>; BW = 668 &#x000b1; 23 kg; BCS = 2.8 &#x000b1; 0.14; parity = 3 &#x000b1; 0.25). Cows were housed in sand-bedded individual stalls equipped with misters and fans which were on from 1000 to 1800 hours for CL group. DMI and milk yield were measured from calving for 7 wk. Body condition score and BW were recorded weekly. Blood samples were collected weekly to measure the metabolic and antioxidant status, inflammatory cytokines, and immunoglobulins. Rectal temperature was measured daily at 1400 hour. Mean daily maximum temperature, minimum relative humidity, and maximum temperature&#x02013;humidity index was 37.0 &#x000b0;C, 31.9%, and 83.4 for HS and 27.3 &#x000b0;C, 44.9%, and 75.7 for CL, respectively. Heat-stressed cows exhibited greater rectal temperature (39.8 vs. 39.1 &#x000b0;C) and lower feed intake (19.8 vs. 21.3 kg/d) relative to CL cows. Milk yield, including raw (31.2 vs. 38.6 kg/d) and fat- and protein-corrected (32.1 vs. 35.7 kg/d) milk, was lower in HS vs. CL cows, respectively. The percentages of milk protein (3.25 vs. 3.06), lactose (4.73 vs. 4.58), and solids-not-fat (8.63 vs. 8.38) but not milk fat (4.31 vs. 3.59) were higher in HS cows than in CL cows, respectively. Somatic cell score was greater in HS cows as compared with CL cows. Cooled cows lost less body condition as compared with HS cows. Blood plasma concentrations of glucose, non-esteri&#x0fb01;ed fatty acids, and &#x003b2;-hydroxybutyric acid were lower in HS cows. Blood plasma concentrations of malondialdehyde (2.13 vs. 1.84 nmol/mL), reactive oxygen species (579 vs. 561 U/mL), and total antioxidant capacity (4.49 vs. 4.06 U/mL) were greater in HS cows than in CL cows. Blood plasma concentrations of the inflammatory cytokines (tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1;, interleukin-1&#x003b1;, and interleukin-2) and immunoglobulins (IgA, IgM, and IgG) were lower in HS cows than in CL cows. These findings demonstrated that cooling dairy cows during the early postpartum improved the production performance, indicators of metabolic status, immune response, and antioxidant capacity.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>antioxidant status</kwd><kwd>cooling</kwd><kwd>metabolic response</kwd><kwd>summer</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>High ambient temperature, especially when associated with high relative humidity, alters metabolism and hormonal secretions, and decreases milk production in lactating cows as a consequence of lower feed intake, reduced nutrient uptake by the mammary glands, and changes in nutrient partitioning to regulate thermal balance (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">West, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Kargar et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karimi et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>Periparturient dairy cows exhibit important endocrine, metabolic, and immune changes to the extent that cows are unable to respond properly (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Bradford et al., 2015</xref>). The ability of cows to increase their feed intake at the beginning of lactation is much lower than milk yield rise, resulting in a marked negative energy balance and considerable lipomobilization (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Drackley et al., 2001</xref>) due to increased ratio of growth hormone to insulin secretion (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Ingvartsen, 2006</xref>). As a result, cows in their first 2 mo of lactation experience higher frequency of metabolic disturbances (e.g., milk fever, ketosis, and liver lipidosis) and infectious diseases (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Goff and Horst, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">LeBlanc et al., 2006</xref>). Metabolic demands, associated with late pregnancy, parturition, and initiation of lactation, would be expected to increase production of reactive oxygen species (<bold>ROS</bold>) and blood non-esterified fatty acids (<bold>NEFA</bold>) and &#x003b2;-hydroxy butyric acid (<bold>&#x003b2;HBA</bold>) concentrations (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Contreras et al., 2012</xref>). Excessive production of ROS results in increased oxidative stress, lipid peroxidation, cellular damage, and inflammatory responses (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Sordillo, 2005</xref>). Pro-inflammatory cytokines (e.g., interleukin [<bold>IL</bold>]-1&#x003b1;; IL-6, tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1; [<bold>TNF-&#x003b1;</bold>]) are presumed to be responsible for postpartum inflammation. Elevated secretions of these cytokines during the periparturient period can further decrease the appetite, cause fever, and increase energy expenditure and fat mobilization (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Elsasser et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Sordillo et al., 1995</xref>). The inflammatory responses might be suppressed by the secretion of anti-inflammatory cytokines (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Dinarello, 2000</xref>); but if not promptly controlled, extensive and long-term inflammation response would deteriorate the lactation performance (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Bradford et al., 2015</xref>). However, there is no convincing demonstration on in vivo relation between oxidative stress and systemic inflammation in the periparturient cow. These events can trigger new and more serious pathologies as well as many endocrine-metabolic modifications. Heat stress during the postpartum period may further exacerbate the endocrine, metabolic, and immune alterations which have not been researched extensively in dairy cows (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karimi et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Lamp et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al., 2016</xref>). Furthermore, the mechanism(s) underlying the reduced immune function in heat-stressed dairy cows is not fully understood, particularly in terms of cytokine profiles.</p><p>Different strategies are used to alleviate the possible adverse effect of heat stress on production performance of dairy cows. Among which, using cooling systems have found to be beneficial for dairy cows together with the provision of high-quality diet (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karimi et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Kargar et al., 2015</xref>). Furthermore, the mechanism of adaptation to heat is a challenge lasting several weeks (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Cook et al., 2007</xref>). There is not much information on the effect of postpartum cooling on whole lactation milk production, biomarkers of metabolic and oxidative stress, and immune status; therefore, the present study aimed at investigating the production performance, indicators of metabolic status (glucose, NEFA, and &#x003b2;HBA), immune response, and oxidative stress in heat-stressed and cooled Holstein dairy cows. We hypothesized that cooling may alleviate the negative impact of heat stress during the postpartum period.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>The experiment was conducted (June to September 2013) at a local dairy farm in Kashaf river valley (36&#x000b0;18&#x002b9;56&#x002ba; N latitude and 59&#x000b0;34&#x002b9;04&#x002ba; E longitude), Quchan, Mashhad, Iran, with a mean elevation of 1,003 m above sea level. The experimental procedures and details, previously reported by <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karimi et al. (2015)</xref>, are briefly described here. The University of Tabriz Laboratory Animal Care Advisory Committee approved all animal procedures.</p><sec id="s3"><title>Animals, Housing, Experimental Design, and Environment</title><p>Forty-six multiparous Holstein dairy cows, similar in calving date, parity, and mature-equivalent (<bold>MEq</bold>) milk production during their previous lactation, were randomly and concurrently allotted to two treatments (23 cows per treatment) after calving. Treatments were imposed for 7 wk postpartum and included either cooling [<bold>CL</bold>; BW = 668 &#x000b1; 23 kg (mean &#x000b1; SD); BCS = 2.8 &#x000b1; 0.14; parity = 3 &#x000b1; 0.25; previous (305 d) MEq milk yield = 10,650 &#x000b1; 350 kg] or heat stress (<bold>HS</bold>; BW = 658 &#x000b1; 28 kg; BCS = 2.7 &#x000b1; 0.18; parity = 3 &#x000b1; 0.12; previous (305 d) MEq milk yield = 10,320 &#x000b1; 313 kg). All cows were subjected to the same photoperiod (~15 h of light and 9 h of dark), with barn lighting installed over the stall areas, and controlled manually (between 0530 and 0600 and 2000 to 2030 hours). Cows were housed in individual sand-bedded stalls (4 m &#x000d7; 4 m), each equipped with a concrete feed bunk (0.8 m &#x000d7; 0.6 m &#x000d7; 0.4 m; length &#x000d7; width &#x000d7; height) and automatic water troughs. The pen contained a corrugated sheet metal shade structure oriented north&#x02013;south with an oscillating evaporatively cooled mister and fan (3 m distance from the floor; model HU-100; Isfahan Havasaz Co., Isfahan, Iran) located at the middle of each stall. The fans (one for two cows) were 0.5 m in diameter with a 1,300-W motor which circulated the air at a rate of 90 m<sup>3</sup>/min. Water was distributed at a maximum rate of 45 L/h. The air velocity and water temperature were 9 m/s and 18 to 20 &#x000b0;C, respectively. The stall barns for the CL and HS cows were 50 m apart. The misters and fans operated from 1000 to 1800 hours during the cooling of the CL cows. At the end of the experimental period, all cows were transferred to the herd in a cooling barn equipped with misters and fans.</p><p>Dietary ingredients and chemical composition are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Diets were formulated to meet or exceed the <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">NRC (2001)</xref> nutrient allowance for the lactating dairy cow with a forage to concentrate ratio of 40:60 (DM basis). The forage component of the diet was a mixture of corn silage and chopped alfalfa hay. Ingredients were mixed for ~8 min in a horizontal TMR mixer wagon and offered twice daily at 0800 and 1800 hours in amounts that allowed 5% refusals. Cows had ad libitum access to feed and fresh water. The amounts of TMR offered and refused were recorded daily for each cow for calculation of the daily feed intake. Cows were milked three times daily at 8-h intervals (0300, 1100, and 1900 hours) in a herringbone milking parlor followed by 20 min of exercise in an outdoor lot (without cooling) after each milking. Milk yield was recorded daily and averaged on a weekly basis until 50 DIM, and then followed monthly until the end of lactation. Body condition score was recorded at the beginning of the trial and then weekly up to 50 DIM by the same trained observer, unaware of the treatment, using a scale from 1 to 5, including 0.25 points, where 1 = thin and 5 = extremely fat (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al., 1994</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Ingredients and chemical composition of postpartum TMR diet fed to Holstein dairy cows</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ingredient composition, % of DM</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alfalfa hay<sup>1</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn silage<sup>1</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole cottonseed</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beet pulp</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.93</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground barley grain</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground corn grain</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat bran</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molasses</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Megalac<sup>2</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin&#x02013;mineral premix<sup>3</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium bicarbonate</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oyster shell</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Di-calcium phosphate</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemical composition, % of DM</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM, %</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organic matter</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-fibrous carbohydrate (NFC)<sup>4</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral detergent fiber (NDF)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ether-extract (EE)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ash</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca<sup>5</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sup>5</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE<sub>L</sub>,<sup>5</sup> Mcal/kg of DM</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>Alfalfa hay and corn silage contained: 17.34% and 7.12% CP, 44.88% and 55.28% NDF, 32.73 and 34.11 acid detergent fiber, respectively.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0002"><p>
<sup>2</sup>The product contained: 17.4 g/100g FA of palmitic acid (C16:0), 2.1 g/100 g FA of stearic acid (C18:0), 33.6 g/100 g FA of oleic acid (C18:1), 30.5 g/100 g FA of linoleic acid (C18:2), and 2.4 g/100 g FA of linolenic acid (C18:3).</p></fn><fn id="fn-0003"><p>
<sup>3</sup>Vitamin&#x02013;mineral premix contained (DM basis) 1,00,000 IU/kg of vitamin A; 360,000 IU/kg of vitamin D3; 15,000 IU/kg of vitamin E; 10 g/kg of Mn; 16 g/kg of Zn; 4 g/kg of Cu; 0.15 g/kg of I; 0.12 g/kg of Co; 0.8 g/kg of Fe; and 0.08 mg/kg of Se.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0004"><p>
<sup>4</sup>NFC = 100 &#x02212; (CP + NDF + EE + ash).</p></fn><fn id="fn-0005"><p>
<sup>5</sup>Calculated from <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">NRC (2001)</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Air temperature and relative humidity for each stall area were recorded hourly, using a temperature and humidity data-logger (model ST-172; Fotronic Co., Melrose, MA) which was installed at cow level within stalls, and used to compute the temperature-humidity index (<bold>THI</bold>) according to the following equation (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Kargar et al., 2015</xref>):</p><disp-formula><mml:math id="D01"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>THI&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.</mml:mn><mml:mtext>8&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;maximum&#x02009;temperature</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>minimum&#x02009;relative&#x02009;humidity/1</mml:mtext><mml:mn>00</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>&#x02003;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>maximum&#x02009;temperature</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>14</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>4</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;46</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>4</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>The THI categories developed for high-yielding lactating cows by <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Zimbelman et al. (2009)</xref> were used: thermal neutral (&#x0003c;68), threshold heat stress (68 to 71), mild-to-moderate heat stress (72 to 79), moderate-to-severe heat stress (80 to 89), severe heat stress (90 to 98), and extremely severe heat stress (&#x0003e;100). Rectal temperature was measured daily at 1400 hour using a rectal thermometer (Digital Thermometer MT101, Sejoy, Hangzhou, China).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Sample Collection and Laboratory Analyses</title><p>Milk samples were taken weekly at three consecutive milkings until 50 d postpartum, composited in proportion to the milk yield, preserved with potassium dichromate, and stored at 4 &#x000b0;C for determination of fat, protein, lactose, and SNF contents using an infrared analyzer (MilkoScan FT6000 [Foss Electric, Hiller&#x000f8;d, Denmark]; <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">AOAC International, 2002</xref>; method 972.16). The amount of fat- and protein-corrected milk (<bold>FPCM</bold>) was calculated as follows: FPCM yield = (0.337 + 0.116 &#x000d7; fat % + 0.06 &#x000d7; protein %) &#x000d7; milk yield (kg/d) (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Heuer, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Kargar et al., 2014</xref>). Feed efficiency was computed as kilogram raw milk per kilogram DMI. Somatic cell count (<bold>SCC</bold>) was determined using an automated optical SCC analyzer (Model Fossomatic 4000; Foss Electric, Hiller&#x000f8;d, Denmark). Somatic cell score (<bold>SCS</bold>) was calculated according to the following equation (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karimi et al., 2015</xref>): SCS = [log<sub>10</sub> (SCC/12.5)]/log<sub>10</sub> (2).</p><p>Blood was sampled weekly (up to 50 DIM) in 10-mL EDTA vacutainer tubes (Becton Dickinson Vacutainer System, Rutherford, NJ) by puncture of the coccygeal vein immediately before morning feeding and placed on ice. Blood samples were centrifuged at 3,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 15 min at 4 &#x000b0;C, the plasma sample was divided into three aliquots and frozen at &#x02212;20 &#x000b0;C until analysis. Concentrations of plasma glucose (Bio Systems Reagents and Instruments, Barcelona, Spain), &#x003b2;HBA, NEFA, and total antioxidant capacity (<bold>T-AOC</bold>) (Randox Laboratories Ltd., Ardmore, UK) were determined by commercial colorimetric kits using an ALCYON 300i automatic analyzer (Abbott Laboratories Ltd., Chicago, IL). The analyzer was calibrated and controls assayed daily according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions to ensure acceptable assay performance. Plasma malondialdehyde (<bold>MDA</bold>) levels were measured using the thiobarbituric acid reactive substances method (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Kargar et al., 2015</xref>). Plasma concentrations of ROS were determined by enzymatic colorimetry using an ELISA plate reader FL<sub>X</sub>800 Fluorescence Microplate (Bio-Tek Instruments Inc., Winooski, VT) according to <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al. (2004)</xref>. Plasma concentrations of TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b1;, and IL-2 were measured using commercial ELISA kits (Pierce Biotechnology Inc., Rockford, IL) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Plasma concentrations of IgA, IgM, and IgG were determined using commercial ELISA kits (Bethyl Laboratories Inc., Montgomery, TX). The intra- and inter-assay coefficients of variations were 5.9 and 7.1% for TNF-&#x003b1;, &#x0003c;10 and &#x0003c;12% for IL-1&#x003b1;, &#x0003c;12 and &#x0003c;10% for IL-2, 5.5% and 11.5% for IgA, 8.7 and 10.7 for IgM, and 5.7 and 8.0 for IgG, respectively. The lower limits of detection were 0.002, 0.006, 0.2, 0.2, 0.5, and 5 ng/mL for TNF-&#x003b1;, IL-1&#x003b1;, IL-2, IgA, IgM, and IgG, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>The data were evaluated for normality of residual distribution before analysis (PROC UNIVARIATE; <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">SAS Institute, 2003</xref>) and all blood variables that were not normally distributed were logarithmically transformed. Data on production variables, plasma metabolites, BCS, and rectal temperature were analyzed using the MIXED MODEL procedure (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">SAS Institute, 2003</xref>) for repeated measures according to the following model:</p><disp-formula><mml:math id="D02"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000b5;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Cow</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Treatment</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Time</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Treatment</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Time</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>in which, <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>ijklm</italic></sub> is the dependent variable, <italic>&#x000b5;</italic> is the average experimental value, Cow<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the random effect of cow, Treatment<sub><italic>j</italic></sub> is the fixed effect of treatment <italic>j</italic> (<italic>j</italic> = CL or HS), Time<sub><italic>k</italic></sub> is the fixed effect of time <italic>k</italic> (<italic>k</italic> = number of day or week), (Treatment <italic>&#x000d7;</italic> Time)<sub><italic>jk</italic></sub> represents the effect of the interaction between treatment and time, <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>ijkl</italic></sub> is the sampling error and <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>ijklm</italic></sub> is the error term.</p><p>Time (day or week) was modeled as a repeated measurement by using a first-order autoregressive covariance structure which was determined by the lowest Bayesian information criterion. When the interaction between treatment and time was significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05), pair-wise comparisons of the individual means were performed using the Tukey&#x02013;Kramer test. Differences between treatments were declared significant at <italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 and differences from <italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05 to <italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.10 were considered as trends.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s6"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s7"><title>Meteorological and Production Data</title><p>Mean daily maximum temperature and minimum relative humidity were 37.0 &#x000b0;C and 31.9% for HS, and 27.3 &#x000b0;C and 44.9% for CL, respectively. The maximum THI in the pens of cows exposed to heat stress was often higher than 80 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), which is the lower limit for moderate-to-severe heat stress, for cows exposed to cooling was always below 79, indicating mild&#x02013;to-moderate heat stress (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Zimbelman et al., 2009</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Temporal patterns of minimum (min) and maximum (max) temperature-humidity index (THI) during the experimental period. Mean daily maximum temperature, minimum relative humidity, and maximum THI were 37.0 &#x000b0;C, 31.9%, and 83.4 for HS group and 27.3 &#x000b0;C, 44.9%, and 75.7 for CL group, respectively. THI categories developed for high-yielding lactating cows by <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Zimbelman et al. (2009)</xref> were used: thermal neutral (&#x0003c;68), heat stress threshold (68 to 71), mild-to-moderate heat stress (72 to 79), moderate-to-severe heat stress (80 to 89), severe heat stress (90 to 98), and extremely severe heat stress (&#x0003e;100).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sky40801"/></fig><p>Heat-stressed cows exhibited higher rectal temperature (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04), lower DMI (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>), and NE<sub>L</sub> intake (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>) than CL cows (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In particular, CL cows had an increased DMI during weeks 3 and 4 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.03; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). Heat-stressed cows yielded 1,442 kg less milk over whole lactation period (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) which corresponded to reduction in average yield of raw milk (19%; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>), FPCM (10%; <italic>P</italic> = 0.03; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>), milk fat (12%; <italic>P</italic> = 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2E</xref>), protein (15%; <italic>P</italic> = 0.006), lactose (18%; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2F</xref>), and SNF (18%; <italic>P</italic> = 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2G</xref>). In HS cows, milk yield was reduced at weeks 1 and 2 postpartum (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>). Heat-stressed cows had greater milk constituents [fat (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2H</xref>), protein, lactose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2I</xref>), and SNF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2J</xref>) percentages] as compared with CL cows (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Feed efficiency expressed as raw milk/DMI but not as FPCM/DMI was lower in HS cows (<italic>P</italic> = 0.002). SCS was greater (39%) in HS cows than in CL cows (3.49 vs. 2.13; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2K</xref>) over the experimental period. In addition, HS cows showed, on average, a 0.26 unit reduction in BCS as compared with CL cows (<italic>P</italic> = 0.06). Body condition score of HS cows was lower than that of CL cows during the weeks 4 to 7 of the study period (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2L</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Rectal temperature, feed intake, milk yield and milk composition, feed efficiency, and tissue gain of cows exposed to either heat stress (HS) or cooling (CL) during the postpartum period</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Item</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Treatment (T)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week (W)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T &#x000d7; W</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>N</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rectal temperature, &#x000b0;C</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMI, kg/d</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE<sub>L</sub> intake, Mcal/d</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yields of milk and milk composition, kg/d</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole lactation milk, kg</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,615</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raw milk</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPCM<sup>1</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fat</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Milk composition, %</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fat</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.73</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCS<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feed efficiency</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raw milk/DMI</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPCM/DMI</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tissue gain</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0006"><p>
<sup>1</sup>FPCM yield = fat- and protein-corrected milk [(0.337 + 0.116 &#x000d7; fat % + 0.06 &#x000d7; protein %) &#x000d7; milk yield (kg/d)] (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Heuer, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Kargar et al., 2014</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="fn-0007"><p>
<sup>2</sup>Somatic cell score = [log<sub>10</sub>(SCC/12.5)]/log<sub>10</sub>(2) (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karimi et al., 2015</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>DMI [(kg/d; A) (SE = 0.26. Effects in model: treatment (T): <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; week (W): <italic>P</italic> = 0.07; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.03)], net energy for lactation intake [(NE<sub>L</sub> intake; Mcal/d; B) (SE = 0.43. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.07; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.03)], raw milk yield [(kg/d; C) (SE = 1.28. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.04)], fat- and protein-corrected milk yield [(FPCM; kg/d; D) (SE = 1.18. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> = 0.03; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.02)], milk fat yield [(kg/d; E) (SE = 0.04. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> = 0.01; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.009; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.01)], milk lactose yield [(kg/d; F) (SE = 0.05. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.01)], milk SNF yield [(kg/d; G) (SE = 0.11. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> = 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.03)], milk fat percentage [(%; H) (SE = 0.04. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001)], milk lactose percentage [(%; I) (SE = 0.02. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001)], milk SNF percentage [(%; J) (SE = 0.04. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.05; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001)], somatic cell score [(SCS; K) (SE = 0.06. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.003)], and body condition score [(BCS; L) (SE = 0.09. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> = 0.06; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.04)] response following early-lactation exposure to either heat stress (HS) or cooling (CL). For each time point, * denotes significant difference at <italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 and &#x02020; a tendency at <italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sky40802"/></fig></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Metabolic Data, Oxidant Status, and Immune Responses</title><p>The CL cows showed higher plasma glucose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>), NEFA, and &#x003b2;HBA levels than HS cows (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Heat-stressed cows showed a higher plasma T-AOC than CL cows (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), and in particular at weeks 6 and 7 postpartum (<italic>P</italic> = 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). The concentration of plasma MDA was higher in HS cows at weeks 4, 5, and 6 postpartum (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). Analogously, the concentration of plasma ROS was greater in HS cows at week 1, and then at weeks 5, 6, and 7 postpartum (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Blood plasma metabolic and antioxidant parameters, and concentrations of inflammatory cytokines and immunoglobulins of cows exposed to either heat stress (HS) or cooling (CL) during the postpartum period</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Item</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Treatment (T)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HS</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week (W)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T &#x000d7; W</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>N</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic parameters</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose, mg/dL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEFA, mEq/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;HBA, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.810</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.864</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antioxidant parameters</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-AOC<sup>1</sup>, U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA<sup>1</sup>, nmol/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ROS<sup>1</sup>, fluorescence intensity/Ml</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">579</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">561</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflammatory cytokines</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-&#x003b1;<sup>1</sup>, ng/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interleukin-1&#x003b1;, ng/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interleukin-2, ng/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immunoglobulins</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgA, ng/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM, ng/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgG, ng/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0008"><p>T-AOC = total antioxidant capacity; MDA = malondialdehyde; ROS = reactive oxygen species; and TNF-&#x003b1; = tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1;.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Blood plasma glucose [(mg/dL; A) (SE = 1.03. Effects in model: treatment (T): <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; week (W): <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.09)], total antioxidant capacity [(<bold>T-AOC</bold>; U/mL; B) (SE = 0.07. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.05)], malondialdehyde [(<bold>MDA</bold>; nmol/mL; C) (SE = 0.10. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> = 0.06; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.04)], reactive oxygen species [(ROS; fluorescence intensity/Ml; D) (SE = 2.00. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001)], tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1; [(TNF-&#x003b1;; ng/mL; E) (SE = 0.01. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.001)], interleukin-1&#x003b1; [(ng/mL; F) (SE = 0.01. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> = 0.01; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.10)], and immunoglobulin A [(Ig A; ng/mL; G) (SE = 0.04. Effects in model: T: <italic>P</italic> = 0.006; W: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; T &#x000d7; W: <italic>P</italic> = 0.03)] response following early-lactation exposure to either heat stress (HS) or cooling (CL). For each time point, * denotes significant difference at <italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 and &#x02020; a tendency at <italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sky40803"/></fig><p>Decreased concentrations of TNF-&#x003b1; (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), IL-1&#x003b1; (<italic>P</italic> = 0.01), and IL-2 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.03) were observed in HS cows compared with CL cows (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Production of TNF-&#x003b1; in HS cows first started to decrease at first week postpartum and was low at weeks 2, 5, and 6 postpartum (<italic>P</italic> = 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3E</xref>). Cooled cows produced greater IL-1&#x003b1; at weeks 6 and 7 postpartum as compared with HS cows (<italic>P</italic> = 0.10; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3F</xref>). Blood plasma concentrations of IgM (<italic>P</italic> = 0.03) and IgG (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) were higher in CL cows; however, IgA concentration was only higher at weeks 5 and 6 postpartum as compared with HS cows (<italic>P</italic> = 0.03; <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3G</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s9"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The present experiment demonstrated that cooling of heat-stressed dairy cows during the postpartum period was beneficial in controlling and sustaining the homeorhetic shifts in metabolism necessary for the onset of lactation, and at the same time guaranteed an appropriate control of inflammation and production of oxidative metabolites. Conventionally, the reduction in milk yield during the heat stress condition is attributed to the reduced feed intake and blood flow to mammary glands which has been observed in cows fed ad libitum under thermal stress and in restricted-fed cows under thermal comfort (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Collier et al., 1982</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Lough et al, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">West, 2003</xref>). In the current study, HS cows exhibited a reduction in DMI and in milk yield as compared with CL cows throughout the experiment. The present data are in line with those of <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Lamp et al. (2015)</xref> where decreased milk yield during early lactation in heat-stressed cows was primarily a consequence of decreased DMI. <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Rhoads et al. (2009)</xref> reported that decreased DMI accounted only for about 35% of the heat stress-induced decrease in milk bio-synthesis during established lactation. Therefore, the prioritization of milk bio-synthesis is higher in the early vs. established lactation phases which may lead to neutralization of the additional heat stress-related reduction in milk bio-synthesis. However, as an important result of the present experiment, cooling succeeded in increasing the whole lactation milk by about 16% or 1,442 kg.</p><p>During heat stress, several adaptive mechanisms become activated to modify the post-absorptive metabolism and energetics to prioritize the cow&#x02019;s thermal balance (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Baumgard and Rhoads, 2013</xref>). Lipid mobilization is suppressed and glucose utilization is increased as an evolutionary mechanism to increase efficiency of thermoregulation and reduce metabolic heat load; the &#x003b2;-oxidation of NEFA produces more metabolic load than glucose oxidation, generating 1,814.0 vs. 472.3 kcal energy (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Wheelock et al., 2010</xref>). Therefore, glucose is preferentially utilized to sustain thermo-regulation rather than milk bio-synthesis. The reduction in plasma glucose in HS throughout the experimental period further supported the hypothesis of the utilization of glucose for thermo-regulatory purpose. However, decreased DMI (to alleviate heat production) cannot be excluded as factor in lowering the plasma glucose in HS cows. The decrease in adipose tissue mobilization and NEFA availability is sustained by a complex perturbation in the somatotropic axis and a change in insulin secretion (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Baumgard and Rhoads, 2013</xref>). Therefore, the reduction in milk production in HS cows could be attributed to both the inability in activating the glucose-sparing mechanisms to sustain milk production via NEFA utilization and the reduction in volatile fatty acid concentration, especially acetate, induced by decreased feed intake (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Rhoads et al., 2009</xref>). As a result of cooling, the cows produced more milk and mobilized more adipose tissue with increased production of NEFA and &#x003b2;HBA, thus contrasting the observed shift in macronutrient utilization toward glucose rather than lipid oxidation during heat stress. Therefore, cooling during early lactation seemed to help cows in better coping with heat stress, as observed by the maintenance of greater BCS in CL cows than in HS cows throughout the experiment. Indeed, adipose tissue mobilization in CL cows during the first 2 wk of lactation, measured as NEFA level, was lower than 0.7 mEq/L suggested by <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Chapinal et al. (2012)</xref> as a threshold for predicting lower milk yield.</p><p>The severity of heat stress effects on production depends on the stage of lactation, with mid lactation phase being the most sensitive stage of lactation. It was reported that milk yield in heat-stressed cows decreased by 14% during early, and by 35% during mid-lactation stages (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Basiric&#x000f2; et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Bernabucci et al., 2010</xref>). Dairy cows have different nutritional and metabolic conditions during the different stages of lactation. Particularly, the tissues that are mobilized during early lactation to sustain milk production have higher efficiency when compared with the metabolic utilization of feed, primarily used during mid-lactation to sustain milk production (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Bernabucci et al., 2010</xref>). In addition, substrate utilization in the liver and skeletal muscles is altered according to the stage of lactation, and a number of changes to reduce heat production are activated in early but not in mid lactation (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al., 2016</xref>). Based on the findings of previous experiments (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Basiric&#x000f2; et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Bernabucci et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al., 2016</xref>), cooling, initiated at early lactation, may be beneficial to milk production and could help in preventing the most negative effect of heat stress during mid-lactation as hypothesized by <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karimi et al. (2015)</xref>. The increase in milk production during whole lactation observed in the present experiment supported the previous findings and our hypothesis that CL cows exhibited the typical metabolic state of transition cows that are not under heat stress.</p><p>Increased oxidative stress, indicated by increased level of blood MDA, in the transition cows during hot seasons has been reported (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Johnson, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Bernabucci et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Sakatani et al., 2012</xref>). Similarly, HS cows in the present experiment recorded higher levels of plasma oxidants as indicated by increased levels of plasma MDA and ROS, particularly starting from the third week of parturition; however, HS cows also showed a greater plasma T-AOC than CL cows during the last 2 wk. The concomitant increase in T-AOC, and MDA and ROS is not easy to explain; however, the activation of the antioxidant responses could be a mechanism to limit the endogenous production of the reactive metabolites. From this perspective, data in the present experiment suggested that the concomitant increase in both oxidants and antioxidants in HS cows may be a reaction to balance the oxidant production, and a compensatory mechanism, which is under homeostatic control (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Barja de Quiroga et al., 1992</xref>). Consequently, in the present experiment, the increase in T-AOC, subsequent to increases in MDA and ROS, can be considered a protective mechanism activated by HS cows in order to control the risk of oxidative damage. Moreover, as suggested by others (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Celi, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Chauhan et al., 2016</xref>), it would be important to define a biomarker of the balance between oxidants and antioxidants because it seems that neither the increase in the level of plasma oxidation alone nor the reduction of the antioxidant capacity alone can be considered undesirable conditions responsible for oxidative stress. The necessity of balancing the heat-induced changes in oxidative stress, although not the only mechanism, might have a role in mediating the inflammatory status and milk production. The increase in antioxidant response to oxidant production has been suggested to reduce the utilization of energy for milk production, being a metabolic process with high energetic costs (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Sordillo and Raphael, 2013</xref>).</p><p>Oxidative stress is one of the contributing factors to the impairment of the immune responses under heat stress (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Beckman and Ames 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Mujahid et al., 2005</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Sordillo and Raphael, 2013</xref>). In the present experiment, the alteration of oxidative metabolites in HS cows, though not showing a clear oxidative stress, influenced the cytokine production. A reduction in immune responses during heat stress has been documented (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Lacetera et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Caroprese et al., 2009</xref>). The lower production of TNF-&#x003b1;, observed in HS cows compared with CL cows, may be an indication of the impairment in inflammatory responses, which are required in support of parturition and during the physiological adaptation from transition state to milk production (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Bradford et al., 2015</xref>). The response of TNF-&#x003b1; was coupled with the IL-1&#x003b1; production in HS cows, decreasing at weeks 6 and 7 postpartum as compared with the CL cows. During transition from parturition to lactation, a moderate inflammation has a fundamental role in eradicating the pathogens, resolving infections, regulating the metabolic changes and controlling nutrient partitioning and energetic (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Bradford et al., 2015</xref>). It has been hypothesized that endogenous inflammation in early lactation is also important in promoting insulin resistance in support of copious milk production (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Bradford et al., 2015</xref>). The concomitant reduction in MDA, ROS, T-AOC, and increases in TNF-&#x003b1;, and IL-1&#x003b1; in the present experiment suggested that CL cows experienced a moderate and controlled inflammation in the last part of the experiment. Production of IL-2, an important factor in T-cell activation, is suppressed in heat stressed dairy cow (<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2018</xref>). As a confirmation of the previous assessment, cooling dairy cows resulted in a greater production of IL-2, and greater competence in humoral immune responses as demonstrated by higher concentrations of plasma IgA, IgM, and IgG. The observed immune reactivity of the adaptive responses in the cows benefiting from cooling perfectly matched with milk production data. A proper degree of endogenous inflammation in early lactation is needed to activate the adaptive mechanisms ensuring nutrient requirements for the mammary gland in order to support a copious milk synthesis (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Bradford et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>Results of the present experiment demonstrated that cooling during postpartum enhances the ability of dairy cows to counteract the negative effects of heat stress on health and performance, thus maintaining feed intake, reducing MDA and ROS, and ensuring the adequate activation of the immune responses and milk production. Cooling during early postpartum can be considered a proper management strategy to sustain dairy cow production under heat stress and to reduce economic losses due to the negative influence of heat stress on milk production.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>The authors express their kind appreciation to the farm staffs for diligent animal care. The authors also express their appreciation to Mohammad Javad Zamiri (Emeritus Professor, Shiraz University) for editing the final English version of this manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>LITERATURE CITED</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>AOAC International</collab></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<source>Official methods of analysis</source>. <edition>17</edition>th ed. <publisher-loc>Arlington, VA:</publisher-loc><publisher-name>AOAC International</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barja de Quiroga</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Torres</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Campo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Relationship between antioxidants, lipid peroxidation and aging</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emerit</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="given-only"><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chance</surname></name></person-group>, editors, <source>Free radicals and aging</source>. <publisher-loc>Basel:</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Birkh&#x000e4;user</publisher-name>; p. <fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basiric&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernabucci</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morera</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lacetera</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nardone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Gene expression and protein secretion of apolipoprotein B100 (ApoB100) in transition dairy cows under hot or thermoneutral environments</article-title>. <source>Ital. J. Anim. Sci</source>. <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>592</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>584</lpage>. doi: 10.4081/ijas.2009.s2.592</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgard</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhoads</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Effects of heat stress on postabsorptive metabolism and energetics</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Anim. Biosci</source>. <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>337</lpage>. doi: 10.1146/annurev-animal-031412-103644<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25387022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckman</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>B. N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>The free radical theory of aging matures</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Rev</source>. <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>581</lpage>. doi: 10.1152/physrev.1998.78.2.547<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9562038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tymoczko</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Stryer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<source>Biochemistry</source>. <edition>6</edition>th edn. <publisher-loc>New York:</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Freeman Custom Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernabucci</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lacetera</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgard</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhoads</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronchi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nardone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Metabolic and hormonal acclimation to heat stress in domesticated ruminants</article-title>. <source>Animal</source><volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1183</lpage>. doi: 10.1017/S175173111000090X<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22444615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernabucci</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronchi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lacetera</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nardone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Markers of oxidative status in plasma and erythrocytes of transition dairy cows during hot season</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>2173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2179</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(02)74296-3<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12362449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farney</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mamedova</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Invited review: inflammation during the transition to lactation: new adventures with an old flame</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>6631</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6650</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2015-9683<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26210279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caroprese</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marzano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Entrican</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wattegedera</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albenzio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Sevi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Immune response of cows fed polyunsaturated fatty acids under high ambient temperatures</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>2796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2803</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2008-1809<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19448013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Celi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Biomarkers for oxidative stress in ruminant medicine</article-title>. <source>Immunopharmacol. Immunotoxicol</source>. <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>. doi: 10.3109/08923973.2010.514917<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20849293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapinal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Godden</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Capel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J. E. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Overton</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffield</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The association of serum metabolites in the transition period with milk production and early-lactation reproductive performance</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>1301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1309</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2011&#x02013;4724<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22365212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ponnampalam</surname><given-names>E. N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Celi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leury</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunshea</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>High dietary vitamin E and selenium improves feed intake and weight gain of finisher lambs and maintains redox homeostasis under hot conditions</article-title>. <source>Small Rumin. Res</source>. <volume>137</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. doi: 10.1016/j.smallrumres.2016.02.011</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doelger</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Head</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thatcher</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1982</year>
<article-title>Effects of heat stress during pregnancy on maternal hormone concentrations, calf birth weight and postpartum milk yield of Holstein cows</article-title>. <source>J. Anim. Sci</source>. <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>319</lpage>. doi: 10.2527/jas1982.542309x<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7076593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raphael</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattmiller</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gandy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Sordillo</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Nonesterified fatty acids modify inflammatory response and eicosanoid biosynthesis in bovine endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>5011</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5023</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2012&#x02013;5382<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22916905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mentink</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>T. B.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Burgi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The effect of heat stress and lameness on time budgets of lactating dairy cows</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1674</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1682</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2006-634<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinarello</surname><given-names>C. A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Proinflammatory cytokines</article-title>. <source>Chest</source><volume>118</volume>:<fpage>503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>508</lpage>. doi: 10.1378/chest.118.2.503<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10936147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drackley</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Overton</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>G. N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Adaptations of glucose and long chain fatty acid metabolism in liver of dairy cows during the periparturient period</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>84</volume> (<issue>E Suppl</issue>):<fpage>E100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E112</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(01)70204-4</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elsasser</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Fayer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Cytokines, stress, and growth modulation</article-title>. in <source>Cytokines in animal health and disease</source>. <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="given-only"><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murtaugh</surname></name></person-group>, editors. <publisher-loc>New York:</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Marcel Dekker Inc</publisher-name>; p. <fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>290</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galligan</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Principal descriptors of body condition score in Holstein cows</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>2695</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2703</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(94)77212-X<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7814740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Physiological changes at parturition and their relationship to metabolic disorders</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>1260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1268</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(97)76055-7<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9241588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heuer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The use of test day information to predict energy intake of dairy cows in early lactation</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>601</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(04)73201-4<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15202643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingvartsen</surname><given-names>K. L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Feeding- and management-related diseases in the transition cow: physiological adaptations around calving and strategies to reduce feeding-related diseases</article-title>. <source>Anim. Feed Sci. Technol</source>. <volume>126</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>. https: //doi.org/10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2005.08.003</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>H. D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Bio-climate effects on growth, reproduction and milk production</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="given-only"><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Bioclim. Adapt Livest</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam:</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> p. <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kargar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghorbani</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fievez</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Schingoethe</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Performance, bioenergetic status, and indicators of oxidative stress of environmentally heat-loaded Holstein cows in response to diets inducing milk fat depression</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>4772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4784</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2014-9100<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25981062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kargar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghorbani</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khorvash</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghi-Sefidmazgi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Schingoethe</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Reciprocal combinations of barley and corn grains in oil-supplemented diets: feeding behavior and milk yield of lactating cows</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>7001</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7011</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2013-7850<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25200781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghorbani</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kargar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Drackley</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Late-gestation heat stress abatement on performance and behavior of Holstein dairy cows</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>6865</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6875</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2014-9281<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26233442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>T. Y.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Selenium attenuates lipopolysaccharide-induced oxidative stress responses through modulation of p38 MAPK and NF-kappaB signaling pathways</article-title>. <source>Exp. Biol. Med. (Maywood)</source>. <volume>229</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:10.3168/jds.2014&#x02013;9281<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14734799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamp</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eslamizad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weitzel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhla</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Metabolic response to heat stress in late-pregnant and early lactation dairy cows: implications to liver-muscle crosstalk</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0160912</fpage>. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0160912<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27513961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacetera</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernabucci</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scalia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronchi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzminsky</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nardone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Lymphocyte functions in dairy cows in hot environment</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Biometeorol</source>. <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>110</lpage>. doi: 10.1007/s00484-005-0273-3<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15991017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamp</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Derno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otten</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mielenz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>N&#x000fc;rnberg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhla</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Metabolic heat stress adaption in transition cows: differences in macronutrient oxidation between late-gestating and early-lactating German Holstein dairy cows</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0125264</fpage>. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0125264<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25938406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lissemore</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelton</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffield</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Major advances in disease prevention in dairy cattle</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1279</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(06)72195-6<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16537959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lough</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beede</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Effects of feed intake and thermal stress on mammary blood flow and other physiological measurements in lactating dairy cows</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>332</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(90)78677-8<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2329200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mujahid</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshiki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akiba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Toyomizu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Superoxide radical production in chicken skeletal muscle induced by acute heat stress</article-title>. <source>Poult. Sci</source>. <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>314</lpage>. doi: 10.1093/ps/84.2.307<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15742968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>NRC</collab></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<source>Nutrient requirements of dairy cattle</source>. <edition>7</edition>th rev. ed., <publisher-loc>Washington, DC:</publisher-loc><publisher-name>National Academic Science</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhoads</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhoads</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>VanBaale</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crooker</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgard</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Effects of heat stress and plane of nutrition on lactating Holstein cows: I. Production, metabolism, and aspects of circulating somatotropin</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1986</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1997</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2008-1641<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19389956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakatani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>N. V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Consequences of physiological heat shock beginning at the zygote stage on embryonic development and expression of stress response genes in cattle</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>3080</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3091</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2011-4986<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22612944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>SAS Institute</collab></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<source>SAS user&#x02019;s guide. Version 9.1</source>. <publisher-loc>Cary, NC:</publisher-loc><publisher-name>SAS Institute Inc</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sordillo</surname><given-names>L. M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Factors a&#x0fb00;ecting mammary gland immunity and mastitis susceptibility</article-title>. <source>Livest. Prod. Sci</source>. <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>. doi: 10.1016/j.livprodsci.2005.10.017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sordillo</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pighetti</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Enhanced production of bovine tumor necrosis factor-alpha during the periparturient period</article-title>. <source>Vet. Immunol. Immunopathol</source>. <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>270</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8746700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sordillo</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Raphael</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Significance of metabolic stress, lipid mobilization, and inflammation on transition cow disorders</article-title>. <source>Vet. Clin. North Am. Food Anim. Pract</source>. <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage>. doi: 10.1016/j.cvfa.2013.03.002<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23809891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Protective effects of zymosan on heat stress-induced immunosuppression and apoptosis in dairy cows and peripheral blood mononuclear cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Stress Chaperones</source><volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1069</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1078</lpage>. doi: 10.1007/s12192-018-0916-z<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29860708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>J. W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Effects of heat-stress on production in dairy cattle</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>2131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2144</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(03)73803-X<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12836950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheelock</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhoads</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanbaale</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgard</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Effects of heat stress on energetic metabolism in lactating Holstein cows</article-title>. <source>J. Dairy Sci</source>. <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>655</lpage>. doi: 10.3168/jds.2009-2295<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20105536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimbelman</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhoads</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhoads</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumguard</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>A re-evaluation of the impact of temperature humidity index (THI) and black globe temperature humidity index (BGHI) on milk production in high producing dairy cows</article-title>. In <conf-name>Proceedings of 24th Southwest Nutrition and Management Conference, Tempe, AZ</conf-name>
<publisher-loc>Tucson:</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Arizona</publisher-name>; p. <fpage>158</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>168</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>