<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6232877</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.01599</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Functional Characterization of BoaMYB51s as Central Regulators of Indole Glucosinolate Biosynthesis in <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> var. <italic>alboglabra</italic> Bailey</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Congxi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Wenxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>Huiying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Mingdan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Mengyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/633998/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Jiayao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Qiaomei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/578284/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Agriculture Ministry Laboratory of Horticultural Crop Growth and Development</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Zhejiang Provincial Key Laboratory of Horticultural Plant Integrative Biology</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>School of Horticulture and Plant Protection, Yangzhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Yangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Xiaoya Chen, Institute of Plant Physiology and Ecology, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Gaojie Hong, ZheJiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, China; Wansheng Chen, Second Military Medical University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Qiaomei Wang <email>qmwang@zju.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Metabolism and Chemodiversity, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1599</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Cai, Yuan, Miao, Deng, Wang, Lin, Zeng and Wang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cai, Yuan, Miao, Deng, Wang, Lin, Zeng and Wang</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>R2R3-MYB transcription factor MYB51 is known to control indole glucosinolate (indole GSL) biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Here, two copies of <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> have been isolated in Chinese kale (<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> var. <italic>alboglabra</italic> Bailey), designated <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> and <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic>, which exhibit overlapping but distinct expression levels among different organs and respond to signaling molecules in a similar pattern. It has been demonstrated a structural and functional conservation between BoaMYB51s and AtMYB51 by phylogenetic analysis, complementation studies and transient expression assay. To further investigate the transcriptional mechanism, we identified the transcriptional activation domain (TAD) and putative interacting proteins of BoaMYB51s by means of yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) two hybrid. Using tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>) transient expression assay, we confirmed that the carboxy-end is required for transcriptional activation activity of BoaMYB51s. In addition, several BoaMYB51-interacting proteins have been identified by yeast two-hybrid screening. These results provide important insights into the molecular mechanisms by which MYB51 transcriptionally regulates indole GSL biosynthesis.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>BoaMYB51</kwd><kwd>Chinese kale</kwd><kwd>indole glucosinolate</kwd><kwd>protein-protein interaction</kwd><kwd>transcription regulation</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">31270343</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">China Postdoctoral Science Foundation<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100002858</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn004">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="9"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="54"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="8332"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Chinese kale (<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> var. <italic>alboglabra</italic> Bailey), a biennial vegetable belonging to the family of <italic>Brassicaceae</italic>, is widespread in southern China and Southeast Asia, with a large growing area and a marketable supply in these regions. Generally, Chinese kale is consumed for its bolting stems as common edible parts, and the tender rosette leaves and sprouts are also widely consumed (Wang et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In addition to good flavor, numerous studies indicate that Chinese kale has abundant glucosinolates (GSLs) (Sun et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Qian et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>GSLs are a class of nitrogen- and sulfur-containing amino acid-derived secondary metabolites, which are common in members of the <italic>Brassicaceae</italic> family including the model plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and agriculturally important <italic>Brassica</italic> crops such as Chinese cabbage (<italic>Brassica rapa</italic> ssp. <italic>pekinensis</italic>), broccoli (<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> var. <italic>italica</italic>), and cauliflower (<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> var. <italic>botrytis</italic>) (Halkier and Gershenzon, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Mithen et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Cai et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Seo et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Capriotti et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In recent years, GSL have evolved as a model system for study of secondary metabolite in plants. Depending on the origin of the core amino acid, GSLs are generally classified into three groups: aliphatic GSL derived from methionine, leucine, isoleucine or valine; indole GSL derived from tryptophan; and benzolic GSL derived from tyrosine or phenylalanine (Fahey et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Kliebenstein et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Wittstock and Halkier, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>), of which more than 200 different GSLs have been identified (Clarke, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). It is known that GSLs and their breakdown products contribute to the protective effects against cancer (Gross et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Mithen et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Grubb and Abel, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Besides the benefits to the human health, these compounds also play an active role in plant defense against microbial pathogens (Clay et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) as well as herbivorous insects (Kliebenstein et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Levy et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), and therefore, it will be a potential strategy for improvement of <italic>Brassica</italic> vegetables by regulating GSL.</p><p>Over the past two decades, indole GSL biosynthetic pathway has been well elucidated, with the almost complete characterization of enzymes involved (Halkier and Gershenzon, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). The composition and content of GSLs vary drastically in response to environmental stimuli, and GSL biosynthesis can be controlled by multiple signals. An understudied aspect of GSL research is to illustrate this regulatory machinery. Recent observations have begun to provide evidence that transcriptional regulation plays a central role in biosynthesis of secondary metabolites (Stracke et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Gonzalez et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). R2R3-MYB transcription factors have been shown to function in a variety of plant-specific processes, which control development, primary and secondary metabolism and response to biotic and abiotic stresses (Dubos et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). In <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, six R2R3-MYB transcription factors having a characteristic &#x0201c;[L/F]LN[K/R]VA&#x0201d; motif (Stracke et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>) are known to be involved in transcriptional regulation of aliphatic GSL (MYB28, MYB29, and MYB76), and indole GSL (MYB34, MYB51, and MYB122) (Gigolashvili et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2007a</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Malitsky et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; S&#x000f8;nderby et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Among them, MYB51 controls indole GSL biosynthesis mainly in the shoots and have been demonstrated to exclusively trans-activates the expression of indole GSL biosynthetic genes and differentially respond to phytohormone signaling molecules such as abscisic acid (ABA), jasmonate (JA), ethylene (ETH), and salicylate (SA) (Gigolashvili et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2007a</xref>; Frerigmann and Gigolashvili, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), but the underlying transcriptional mechanism remains relatively poorly defined.</p><p>A class of JA-signaled bHLH transcription factors (MYC2, MYC3, and MYC4) has been shown to interact with the six GSL-related MYB transcription factors, respectively (Schweizer et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Frerigmann et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). These MYB-bHLH protein complexes have been linked to GSL biosynthesis regulating, and similar scenarios can also be found in other plant secondary metabolites (Gonzalez et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Xu et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Since previous analyses of the reference genome sequence of <italic>B. oleracea</italic> identified a whole-genome triplication (WGT) event after its divergence from a common ancestor of <italic>A. thaliana</italic> in the <italic>Brassica</italic> ancestor, most genes in Chinese kale were found to be duplicated or triplicated (Cheng et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Thus, construction of Chinese kale cDNA prey library for yeast two-hybrid screening will be enriched for cDNAs of naturally co-occurring proteins, which will increase the possibility to identify novel GSL-related MYB interactors and enable us to seek other types of MYB-bHLH protein complex regulating GSL biosynthesis.</p><p>Despite the identification of aliphatic GSL biosynthesis regulator MYB28 and MYB29 in <italic>Brassica rapa ssp. pekinensis</italic> (Kim et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), <italic>B. juncea</italic> (Augustine et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and <italic>B. oleracea</italic> (Araki et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Yin et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), none of the transcription factors regulating indole GSL in <italic>Brassica</italic> crops have been well investigated to date. Previous study only identified one BoMYB51 from broccoli (Yu et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Here, we report that both two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes have been isolated with identification of their transcriptional activation domain (TAD) and novel protein interactors. Our results highlight the importance of BoaMYB51s in regulating indole GSL biosynthesis in Chinese kale, which could be potential in improvement of pest and pathogen resistance as well as health benefits of <italic>B. oleracea</italic> by metabolic engineering.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Plant material and cultivation conditions</title><p>Chinese kale cultivar &#x0201c;DSCH&#x0201d; germinated and grown in Zhejiang University (Hangzhou, China) was used as material in this study. Chinese kale seeds were sterilized for 30 s in 75% ethanol and washed with sterile water twice, and then immersed in 10% bleach for 2 min, followed by washing with sterile water five times. They were then soaked in sterile-distilled water for 48 h at 25&#x000b0;C in dark. Chinese kale sprouts were cultured in petri dishes with three pieces of wet filter paper in a plant growth chamber at 25&#x000b0;C with a 16-h-light/8-h-dark photoperiod. Five-day-old sprouts and six-month-old Chinese kale plants were used to collect different organs to analyze <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> expression patterns. For epi-brassinolide (eBL) (Sigma), methyl-jasmonate (MeJA) (Sigma), SA (Sigma), and flagelin22 (flg22) (Chinese Peptide, Hangzhou, China) treatment, 5-day-old Chinese kale sprouts were grown in sterile half-strength Murashige and Skoog (MS) media at 25&#x000b0;C with a 16-h-light/8-h-dark photoperiod.</p><p><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutant <italic>myb34myb51</italic> (Frerigmann and Gigolashvili, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) was used for functional complementation studies. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds were sterilized for 12 min in 10% bleach and washed with sterile water 5 times, and then were stratified for 3 days at 4&#x000b0;C. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants were grown in sterile half-strength Murashige and Skoog (MS) media at 22&#x000b0;C with a 16-h-light/8-h-dark photoperiod.</p></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p>Multiple protein sequence alignments were performed using Clustal W. The phylogenetic tree was produced based on the amino acid sequences of MYB34, MYB51, and MYB122 proteins from <italic>B. rapa, B. oleraceae</italic>, and <italic>A. thaliana</italic> by applying the NJ (Neighbor-joining) method with MEGA v.7.0 software (Kumar et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and bootstrap values with 1,000 replicates were calculated.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA extraction and qRT-PCR analysis</title><p>Plant samples were ground using Tissuelyser-24 (Jingxin, Shanghai, China). Total RNA was isolated as described previously with minor modifications (Guo et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Reverse transcription was performed using the PrimeScript&#x02122; RT reagent Kit with gDNA Eraser (Takara). qRT-PCR was performed on ABI StepOne Real-time PCR System (Thermo Fisher). <italic>BoaACTIN2</italic> gene was used as an endogenous control and the expression of other genes was computed using the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>CT</italic></sup> method. Primers used are listed in Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>. Data were analyzed from three independent sets of biological replicates.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA constructs and plant transformation</title><p>Constructs for plant transformation were generated using Gateway system (Invitrogen). The full-length coding DNA sequences (CDS) of <italic>BoaMYB51</italic>.1 and <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> were amplified with Gateway-compatible primers (see Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">2</xref>). The PCR product was cloned using pENTR/D-TOPO CLONING KIT (Invitrogen) and then recombined with the binary vector pGWB2 (Nakagawa et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) to generate the <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.1</italic> and <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.2</italic> constructs. For the generation of <italic>BoaMYB51</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:GUS</italic> constructs, the promoter regions (~2 kb) of the two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes were isolated from genomic DNA of and cloned into the gateway binary vector pGWB3 (Nakagawa et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Histochemical analysis was performed as previously described (Sun et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Primers are tabulated in Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">2</xref>. The above constructs were then transformed into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101, which was used for transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants by floral dip method.</p></sec><sec><title>GSL assay</title><p>GSL were extracted and analyzed as previously described (Guo et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Extract was applied to a DEAE-Sephadex A-25 (35 mg) column (Pyridine acetate form) (Sigma). ONPG (Sigma) was used as an internal standard for HPLC analysis. The GSL concentration was expressed as &#x003bc;mol g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>fresh weight (FW).</p></sec><sec><title>Transient expression assay</title><p>The transient expression assays were carried out in tobacco leaves as previously described (Zhai et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The promoters of <italic>BoaCYP79B2.1, BoaCYP83B1, BoaSOT16.1, BoaCYP79F1</italic>, and <italic>AtCYP83B1</italic> were amplified and cloned into entry vector using the pENTR/D-TOPO CLONING KIT (Thermo Fisher). Then promoters were fused with the luciferase reporter gene <italic>LUC</italic> into pGWB35 and pGreenII 0800-LUC to generate the reporter constructs <italic>BoaCYP79B2.1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC, BoaCYP83B1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC, BoaSOT16.1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC, BoaCYP79F1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic>, and <italic>AtCYP83B1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic>. Effector constructs <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.1-YFP, 35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.2-YFP</italic>, and <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB28.1-YFP</italic> were generated using ClonExpress II One Step Cloning Kit (Vazyme Biotech). We used a low-light cooled CCD imaging apparatus (NightOWL II LB983) to capture the LUC image and to count luminescence intensity. The leaves were sprayed with 100 mM luciferin (Promega) and were placed in darkness for 3 min before luminescence detection.</p></sec><sec><title>Transactivation activity assay in yeast</title><p>Full-length CDS of <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> and <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> and their derivatives were amplified with listed primers (see Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">2</xref>). PCR products were recombined with the pGBKT7 vector using ClonExpress II One Step Cloning Kit (Vazyme Biotech) for fusion with the BD domain at their N terminal. The resulting constructs were then transformed into the yeast strain <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> AH109, and the presence of the transgenes was verified by PCR and growth on an SD/-Trp plate. The Matchmaker GAL4 two-hybrid systems (Clontech) was used for the transactivation activity assay. Each yeast liquid culture was serially diluted to OD<sub>600</sub> = 1.0, and 5 &#x003bc;l of each dilution was spread on the plates containing SD/-Ade/-His/-Trp synthetic dropout medium.</p></sec><sec><title>Y2H assays</title><p>The TAD deletion constructs of BoaMYB51.1 and BoaMYB51.2 were used for the Y2H screening of the pGADT7-based Chinese kale cDNA library, which was generated with mRNAs isolated from Chinese kale sprouts, leaves, roots, stems and flowers. Y2H assays were based on Matchmaker GAL4 two-hybrid systems (Clontech). Yeast transformants were exhaustively selected on SD/-Ade/-His/-Leu/-Trp/X-&#x003b1;-Gal medium. Putative BoaMYB51 interacting clones were characterized and sequenced.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed using the SPSS package program version 11.5 (SPSS inc. Chicago, IL, USA). For Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>, Data was analyzed by one-way ANOVA, followed by Turkey's HSD multiple comparison test. The values are reported as means with their standard error for all results. Differences were considered significant at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec><sec><title>Accession numbers</title><p>Chinese kale sequence information can be found in the <italic>Brassica</italic> database (BRAD, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brassicadb.org">http://brassicadb.org</ext-link>) under the following accession numbers: <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Bol013207">Bol013207</ext-link>), <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Bol030761">Bol030761</ext-link>), <italic>BoaMYB28.1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Bol017019">Bol017019</ext-link>), <italic>BoaCYP79B2.1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Bol018585">Bol018585</ext-link>), <italic>BoaCYP83B1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Bol033477">Bol033477</ext-link>), <italic>BoaSOT16.1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Bol026200">Bol026200</ext-link>), <italic>BoaCYP79F1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Bol038222">Bol038222</ext-link>), <italic>BoaBIM1.1</italic> (Bol043819), <italic>BoaBIM1.2</italic> (Bol008832), and <italic>BoaACTIN2</italic> (Bol030974). All <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes used in this article are referenced in the Arabidopsis Genome Initiative under the following accession numbers: <italic>AtMYB51</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="At1G18570">At1G18570</ext-link>), <italic>AtCYP83B1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="At4G31500">At4G31500</ext-link>) and <italic>AtSOT16</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="At1G74100">At1G74100</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Isolation of the two BoaMYB51 homologs from Chinese kale</title><p>According to <italic>Brassica</italic> database (BRAD, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brassicadb.org">http://brassicadb.org</ext-link>), in <italic>B. oleracea</italic> genome, there are two <italic>MYB51</italic> homologs distributed in different chromosomes, namely <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> (Bol013207, C08) and <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> (Bol030761, C05). First, primers based on reference sequences from BRAD were used to isolate the two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes from Chinese kale cultivar &#x0201c;DSCH.&#x0201d; Next, the full-length coding sequences of two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes were confirmed with multiple amplifications in other Chinese kale cultivars. As a result, the length of CDS of <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> is 1002 bp encoding a protein of 333 aa, whereas the CDS of <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> is 990 bp encoding a protein of 329 aa (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Compared with reference sequences from BRAD, the coding sequence of <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> isolated from Chinese kale has three different nucleotides and three different amino acids (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>), while <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> has eight different nucleotides and six different amino acids (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">2</xref>). Comparison of the coding sequence with their corresponding genomic sequences revealed that both <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes consisted of three exons and two introns (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of the BoaMYB51 gene sequences.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene ID</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Coding sequence (bp)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Protein (aa)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. of exons (size in bp)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. of introns (size in bp)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> (Bol013207)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (136,130,736)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (101,429)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> (Bol030761)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">990</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">329</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (136,130,724)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (114,234)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The amino acid sequences of two BoaMYB51 proteins are 76% identical and share 74 and 70% similarity with AtMYB51, respectively (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">3</xref>). We also found that BoaMYB51.1 protein sequence shares maximum identity (97%) with BrMYB51.2 (Bra016553), and BoaMYB51.2 protein sequence showed the highest level of identity (94%) with BrMYB51.3 (Bra025666) (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">3</xref>). Furthermore, amino acid sequence alignment of two BoaMYB51s with AtMYB51 demonstrated a conserved N-terminal region (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), containing R2R3-MYB domain which was predicated to serve as DNA binding domain (Dubos et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Nuclear localized signal (NLS) and characteristic &#x0201c;[L/F]LN[K/R]VA&#x0201d; motif belonging to R2R3-type MYB subgroup 12 were also found in BoaMYB51s (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Compared with the highly conserved N-terminal domain, the C-terminal region of BoaMYB51 exhibited conservation in patches (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Multiple alignments of the BoaMYB51 and AtMYB51 protein sequences. Multiple alignments were performed using CLC Main Workbench software (QIAGEN). Nuclear localized signal (NLS) and characteristic &#x0201c;[L/F]LN[K/R]VA&#x0201d; motif were marked with yellow and red rectangle, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01599-g0001"/></fig><p>To investigate the evolutionary relationship, we identified all indole GSL-related <italic>MYB</italic> genes (<italic>MYB34, MYB51</italic>, and <italic>MYB122</italic>) in <italic>B. rapa, B. oleracea</italic> and <italic>A. thaliana</italic>. We constructed a phylogenetic tree of all deduced MYB amino acid sequences using the neighbor-joining method (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Phylogenetic analyses revealed that in <italic>B. rapa</italic> genome there are three <italic>MYB51</italic> orthologs, four <italic>MYB34</italic> orthologs, and two <italic>MYB122</italic> orthologs, while in <italic>B. oleracea</italic> genome, there are two <italic>MYB51</italic> orthologs, one <italic>MYB34</italic> ortholog, and one <italic>MYB122</italic> ortholog (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Evolutionary relationships of MYB34, MYB51, and MYB122 proteins in <italic>A. thaliana, B. rapa</italic> and <italic>B. oleracea</italic>. Phylogenetic analysis was performed using the neighbor-joining method (bootstrap test with 1000 replicates). Triangle indicates MYB51, square indicates MYB122, and circle indicates MYB34. <italic>A. thaliana</italic> proteins are labeled with red, <italic>B. rapa</italic> proteins are labeled with green, and <italic>B. oleracea</italic> proteins are labeled with yellow.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01599-g0002"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes exhibit overlapping but distinct expression profiles in Chinese kale</title><p>Distinct expression profiles among homologous genes in <italic>Brassica</italic> crops have been observed in many studies (Augustine et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Nour-Eldin et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). To test if two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes are differentially expressed, qRT-PCR analysis was performed to measure the expression levels of the two genes during different developmental stages and among different tissues in Chinese kale. In general, two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes showed overlapping expression profiles in Chinese kale and <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> was more highly expressed (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A,B</xref>). At seedling stage, <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> as well as <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> was expressed in both shoots and roots, and <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> exhibited a higher expression level than <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). At reproductive stage, <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> gene expression levels differed among different tissues. <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> was highly expressed in roots, leaves and flowers with the highest level in leaves while lowest level in siliques. However, <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> was expressed abundantly only in roots and flowers, and a trace accumulation of <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> transcript was detected in leaves and siliques (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). In order to confirm the result of qRT-PCR analysis, we performed the GUS histochemical analysis of <italic>BoaMYB51</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:GUS</italic> transgenic lines in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. As shown in Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">3</xref>, both two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes were expressed in aerial part and underground part, and a higher GUS staining was observed in <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:GUS</italic>.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Relative gene expression of <italic>BoaMYB51s</italic> in Chinese kale organs at the seedling stage (5 day) <bold>(A)</bold> and reproductive stage (6 month) <bold>(B)</bold>. Each data point represents the mean of three independent biological replicates (mean &#x000b1; SE). <bold>(A)</bold> Values are shown compared with expression level of <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> in below ground tissues. <bold>(B)</bold> Values are shown compared with expression level of <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> in siliques.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01599-g0003"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>BoaMYB51s</italic> respond to signaling molecules</title><p>The transcript level of <italic>MYB51</italic> varies in response to phytohormones (Frerigmann and Gigolashvili, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). To address whether two <italic>BoaMYB51s</italic> respond to signaling molecules such as eBL, MeJA, SA, and flg22, we examined the expression patterns of both two genes in Chinese kale sprouts, which had been treated with corresponding signaling molecules. Generally, eBL and MeJA treatment caused a repression of <italic>BoaMYB51s</italic>, whereas SA and flg22 treatment induced the expression of <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A&#x02013;H</xref>). eBL and MeJA repressed the expression of <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> in a similar mode, which differed from the expression pattern of <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic>. The expression level of <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> was reduced at 6 h under eBL treatment while at 1h with MeJA treatment (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A&#x02013;D</xref>). In contrast, SA and flg22 treatment caused a significant induction of both <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> and <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> in a similar pattern. BoaMYB51s reached the highest level at 3 h with SA treatment while the peak time was 1 h after treatment with flg22 (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4E&#x02013;H</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Time-course expression of <italic>BoaMYB51s</italic> in response to eBL, MeJA, SA, and flg22 treatments. Five-day-old Chinese kale sprouts were treated with 1 &#x003bc;M eBL <bold>(A,B)</bold>, 100 &#x003bc;M MeJA <bold>(C,D)</bold>, 100 &#x003bc;M SA <bold>(E,F)</bold>, and 100 nM flg22 <bold>(G,H)</bold> for indicated times before total RNAs were extracted for real time-qPCR assays. Values are shown compared with gene expression level at 0 h. Each data point represents the mean of three independent biological replicates (mean &#x000b1; SE).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01599-g0004"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Carboxy-end is required for transcriptional activation activity of BoaMYB51s</title><p>To investigate the biological function of BoaMYB51s in Chinese kale, we analyzed the transcriptional activation ability of the two transcription factors using transient assays. <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves were infiltrated with Agrobacteria strain GV3101 carrying the <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51</italic> or <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB28.1</italic> construct as effector expression and reporter constructs containing the promoter of indole GSL biosynthetic genes (<italic>BoaCYP79B2.1, BoaCYP83B1</italic>, and <italic>BoaSOT16.1</italic>) or aliphatic GSL biosynthetic gene (<italic>BoaCYP79F1</italic>) fused with <italic>LUC</italic>. We showed that all tested promoters of indole GSL biosynthetic genes were activated by two BoaMYB51s but not affected by BoaMYB28.1 (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A&#x02013;L</xref> and Supplementary Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">4A&#x02013;D</xref>). On the contrary, co-transformation of <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51</italic> with <italic>BoaCYP79F1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic> failed to cause an obvious increase of luminescence intensity (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A&#x02013;D</xref> and Supplementary Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">5A,B</xref>). These results implicated that BoaMYB51s are specifically involved in the transcriptional regulation of indole GSL biosynthesis in Chinese kale.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Tobacco transient expression assays showing that BoaMYB51 trans-activates the expressions of Chinese kale indole glucosinolate biosynthetic genes. <bold>(A&#x02013;D)</bold> Co-infiltration of <italic>BoaCYP79B2.1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic> and <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:YFP, 35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB28.1, 35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.1</italic> or <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.2</italic>, respectively. <bold>(E&#x02013;H)</bold> Co-infiltration of <italic>BoaCYP83B1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic> and <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:YFP, 35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB28.1, 35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.1</italic> or <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.2</italic>, respectively. <bold>(I&#x02013;L)</bold> Co-infiltration of <italic>BoaSOT16.1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic> and <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:YFP, 35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB28.1, 35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.1</italic> or <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.2</italic>, respectively. Representative images of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves 72 h after infiltration are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01599-g0005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Tobacco transient expression assays showing that BoaMYB51 fail to trans-activates the expressions of <italic>BoaCYP79F1</italic>. <bold>(A&#x02013;D)</bold> Co-infiltration of <italic>BoaCYP79F1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic> and <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:YFP, 35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB28.1, 35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.1</italic> or <italic>35S</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:BoaMYB51.2</italic>, respectively. Representative images of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves 72 h after infiltration are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01599-g0006"/></fig><p>To substantiate the functional contribution of each BoaMYB51 to the regulation on indole GSL biosynthesis, two <italic>BoaMYB51s</italic> were over-expressed in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutant <italic>myb34myb51</italic>. Three independent homozygous lines of each <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> were analyzed for total as well as individual indole GSL contents in 6-week old rosette leaves. We showed that both two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes complemented not only the accumulation of total indole GSL contents but also individual indole GSL fractions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). The increased indole GSL accumulation in transgenic lines correlated with increased mRNA levels of the indole GSL pathway genes of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. As shown in Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">6</xref>, the gene expression levels of <italic>CYP79B2, CYP79B3, CYP83B1</italic>, and <italic>SOT16</italic> were considerably increased in complementation lines compared with mutants. Moreover, transient assay revealed that both two BoaMYB51 transcription factors were able to activate the expression of <italic>AtCYP83B1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic> (Supplementary Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">7A&#x02013;D</xref>). Collectively, these results clearly suggested that both two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes are active and positively regulate the indole GSL biosynthesis.</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Functional complementation analyses of <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana myb34myb51</italic>. The glucosinolate content and profile were determined in 6-week-old rosette leaves. Three independent mutant-complemented lines for each <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> gene were analyzed. Each data point represents the mean of three independent biological replicates (mean &#x000b1; SE).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01599-g0007"/></fig><p>Next, to better understand the transcriptional activation mechanism of BoaMYB51, we defined the transcriptional activation domain (TAD) of two BoaMYB51s using the MATCHMAKER GAL4-based Two-Hybrid System 3 (Clontech). In these assays, we found that both two BoaMYB51s had strong transcriptional activation activity whereas BoaMYB51.1 derivative containing amino acids from 1 to 274, and BoaMYB51.2 derivative containing amino acids from 1 to 270, do not, which suggested that the carboxy-end domain of both BoaMYB51.1 and BoaMYB51.2 could be the TAD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref>). To validate this <italic>in planta</italic>, we co-expressed construct encoding full-length BoaMYB51s or TAD-deleted BoaMYB51 derivatives with reporter <italic>BoSOT16.1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic> in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves. Our results showed that BoaMYB51s&#x00394;TAD led to a substantial decrease of luminescence intensity when compared with full-length BoaMYB51s, suggesting that deletion of C-end strongly weakened the transcriptional activation activity of BoaMYB51s (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref> and Supplementary Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">8A&#x02013;D</xref>). Taken together, these data indicated that C-end is required for transcriptional activation activity of BoaMYB51s.</p><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>C-end is the TAD of BoaMYB51. <bold>(A)</bold> Yeast assay shows the deletion of C-end abolishes the transcriptional activity of BoaMYB51s. Yeast clones were grown on yeast synthetic dropout lacking Trp or on selective media lacking Ade, His, and Trp. one-tenth and one-hundred dilution yeast growth in media were also shown. <bold>(B)</bold> Tobacco transient expression assays show C-end is required for the transcriptional activity of BoaMYB51s. Representative images of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves 72 h after infiltration are shown. Each experiment was repeated at least three times with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01599-g0008"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Interactome of BoaMYB51s identified by yeast two-hybrid screening</title><p>To identify proteins that function in cooperation with BoaMYB51, a yeast two-hybrid assay with a Chinese kale complementary DNA (cDNA) library as prey was performed. To circumvent the problem that full-length BoaMYB51s have autoactivation activity, we used BoaMYB51&#x00394;TAD as bait. In total, we analyzed plasmids from 52 (BoaMYB51.1&#x00394;TAD as bait) and 82 (BoaMYB51.2&#x00394;TAD as bait) yeast colonies by sequencing. Using the basic local alignment search tool (BLAST) of BRAD, we identified a total of 34 unique inserts, most of which represent full length or nearly full-length coding sequences. Duplicates and sequences unambiguously belonging to proteins of the photosynthetic and the ribosomal machinery were excluded from further analysis, leaving a curated list of 30 candidate interactors (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>List of proteins interacting with BoaMYB51 in the yeast two-hybrid screen.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Code</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Clones</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Name</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Description</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol036079</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AKINBETA1, KIN&#x003b2;1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes AKINbeta1, a subunit of the SnRK1 kinase (Sucrose non-fermenting-1-related protein kinase). Involved in regulation of nitrogen and sugar metabolism.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol026500</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-5 exonuclease domain-containing protein/K homology domain-containing protein/KH domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol025605</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARGININE AMIDOHYDROLASE 1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes an arginase, likely to be involved in polyamine biosynthesis in pollen</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol034826</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-loop containing nucleoside triphosphate hydrolases superfamily protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol031300</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BFN1, BIFUNCTIONAL NUCLEASE I, ENDO1, ENDONUCLEASE 1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes a bifunctional nuclease that acts on both RNA and DNA involved in nucleic acid degradation to facilitate nucleotide and phosphate recovery during senescence. It has mismatch-specific endonuclease activity with wide recognition of single base mismatches as well as the ability to cleave indel types of mismatches</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol014189</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYC2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes a MYC-related transcriptional activator with a typical DNA binding domain of a basic helix-loop-helix leucine zipper motif. Binds to an extended G-Box promoter motif and interacts with Jasmonate ZIM-domain proteins.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol034555</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Translation elongation factor EF1B/ribosomal protein S6 family protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol040078</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PATL3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sec14p-like phosphatidylinositol transfer family protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol025181</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transducin/WD40 repeat-like superfamily protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol035576</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PME3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes a pectin methylesterase, targeted by a cellulose binding protein (CBP) from the parasitic nematode Heterodera schachtii during parasitism.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol037760</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLANT U-BOX 23, PUB23</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes a cytoplasmically localized U-box domain containing E3 ubiquitin ligase that is involved in the response to water stress and acts as a negative regulator of PAMP-triggered immunity.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol030761</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB51</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes a member of the R2R3-MYB transcription family. Involved in indole glucosinolate biosynthesis.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol025647</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RABG3A, RAB GTPASE HOMOLOG G3A, RABG3A</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAB GTPase homolog G3A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol044700</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALTERED SEED GERMINATION 1, ASG1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP-dependent DNA helicase</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol019812</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APG5, ATG5, AUTOPHAGY 5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autophagy protein ATG5. Forms a conjugate with ATG12 with an essential role in plant nutrient recycling. Mutants missing ATG5 display early senescence and are hypersensitive to nitrogen or carbon starvation, accompanied by a more rapid loss of organellar and cytoplasmic proteins.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol029372</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPPA, TREHALOSE-6-PHOSPHATE PHOSPHATASE A</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homologs to the C-terminal part of microbial trehalose-6-phosphate phosphatases</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol024700</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HOMOLOG OF HUMAN UAP56 B, UAP56B</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">One of two genes encoding an ATP-dependent RNA helicase that localizes predominantly to euchromatic regions of nuclei, and associates with genes transcribed by RNA polymerase II independently from the presence of introns. It is not detected at non-transcribed loci. It interacts with ssRNA, dsRNA and dsDNA, but not with ssDNA. Its ATPase activity is stimulated by RNA and dsDNA and its ATP-dependent RNA helicase activity unwinds dsRNA but not dsDNA.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol026069</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERAT1;1, SAT-52, SAT5, SERAT1;1, SERINE ACETYLTRANSFERASE 1;1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes a cytosolic serine O-acetyltransferase involved in sulfur assimilation and cysteine biosynthesis. Expressed in the vascular system</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol030585</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POLYUBIQUITIN 10, UBI10, UBIQUITIN 10, UBQ10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">These genes encode the highly conserved 76-amino acid protein ubiquitin that is covalently attached to substrate proteins targeting most for degradation. Polyubiquitin genes are characterized by the presence of tandem repeats of the 228 bp that encode a ubiquitin monomer. Induced by salicylic acid. Independent of NPR1 for their induction by salicylic acid. The mRNA is cell-to-cell mobile.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol032979</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc ion binding protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol026467</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGO4, ARGONAUTE 4, OCP11,</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGO4 is a member of a class of PAZ/PIWI domain containing proteins involved in siRNA mediated gene silencing.Loss of function mutations have reduced site specific CpNpG and CpHpH methylation and increased susceptibility to bacterial pathogens including Tobacco rattle virus</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol008799</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyruvate kinase family protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol038054</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PUX7, PLANT UBX DOMAIN-CONTAINING PROTEIN 7, PUX7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes a nuclear UBX-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol022070</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unkonwn</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol044051</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RING/U-box superfamily protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol036269</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REPLICATION PROTEIN A 1D, RPA1D, RPA70D</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Replication factor-A protein 1-like protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol028834</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FK506-BINDING PROTEIN 16-2, FKBP16-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FK506-BINDING PROTEIN 16-2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol005163</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium-binding EF-hand family protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol013491</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZW10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homologs to Drosophila ZW10, a centromere/kinetochore protein involved in chromosome segregation</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bol043819</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BIM1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encodes a basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) family protein BIM1 (BES1-INTERACTING MYC-LIKE 1)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Among the proteins interacting with MYB51 were transcription factors (Bol014189, Bol030761, and Bol043819), other nuclear-localized regulatory proteins (Bol044700, and Bol024700, and Bol026467), protein regulatory proteins (Bol037760, Bol030585, and Bol044051), and a protein with unassigned functions (Bol022070). In the current study, we further analyzed the interaction between BoaMYB51 and BoaBIM1.1 (Bol043819), because previous studies demonstrated that MYB-bHLH protein complex is important for transcriptional regulation of GSL biosynthesis (Schweizer et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Frerigmann et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>BoaMYB51s interact with BoaBIMs</title><p>BES1-interacting Myc-like1 (BIM1), a basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) transcription factor, was first identified by yeast two-hybrid assay using BES1 as bait in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. BIM1 was reported to be involved in brassinosteroid responses such as hypocotyl elongation (Yin et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). There are two BIM1 paralogs in Chinese kale, namely <italic>BoaBIM1.1</italic> (Bol043819) and <italic>BoaBIM1.2</italic> (Bol008832), and <italic>BoaBIM1.2</italic> showed a higher expression level than <italic>BoaBIM1.1</italic> (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">9</xref>). Screened by yeast two-hybrid assay, BoaBIM1.1 was identified to be a protein interactor of BoaMYB51s. To verify this new identified MYB-bHLH complex, we cloned full-length <italic>BoaBIM1.1</italic> and <italic>BoaBIM1.2</italic> from Chinese kale and fused them to the GAL4-activation domain. We found that both BoaBIM1.1 and BoaBIM1.2 showed interaction with two BoaMYB51s (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). Next, we mapped the interaction domain of BoaBIM1.1 with BoaMYB51s using yeast two-hybrid assays. We found that C-end but not N-end of BoaBIM1.1 was required for its interaction with BoaMYB51s (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9B</xref>).</p><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>BoaMYB51s interact with BoaBIMs. <bold>(A)</bold> A yeast two-hybrid assay shows the interaction between BoaMYB51s and BoaBIMs. <bold>(B)</bold> C-end of BoaBIM1.1 was sufficient for its interaction with BoaMYB51s. BoaBIM1.1-C, C-terminal domain of BoaBIM1.1 (332&#x02013;545), BoaBIM1.1-bHLH+C, bHLH and C-terminal domain of BoaBIM1.1 (278&#x02013;545), and BoaBIM1.1-N, N-terminal domain of BoaBIM1.1 (1&#x02013;277). Yeast clones were grown on yeast synthetic dropout lacking Trp and Leu or on selective media lacking Ade, His, Trp, and Leu. One-tenth and one-hundred dilution yeast growth in media were also shown. Each experiment was repeated at least three times with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01599-g0009"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Chinese kale is abundant in GSL accumulation and MYB51 acts as an important regulator of indole GSL biosynthesis. Here, we isolated both two <italic>MYB51</italic> homologs for the first time in <italic>Brassica</italic> crops. BoaMYB51s exhibited overlapping but distinct expression profiles in Chinese kale and <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> exhibited a higher expression level than <italic>BoaMYB51.2</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Previous study in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> indicated that MYB51 seems to be the major regulator of indole GLS biosynthesis in shoots, while MYB34 is decisive for the production of indole GLS in roots (Frerigmann and Gigolashvili, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In our current research, <italic>BoaMYB51.1</italic> has a higher transcript level in shoots when compared to roots (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>), which was in line with the study in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Next, we found that two <italic>BoaMYB51</italic> genes responded to signaling molecules in a similar pattern, which were repressed by MeJA while induced by SA and flg22 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the expression level of <italic>MYB51</italic> has also been demonstrated to be activated by SA and flg22 (Millet et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Frerigmann and Gigolashvili, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), while was decreased upon MeJA and eBL treatment (Guo et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Frerigmann and Gigolashvili, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). However, <italic>MYB34</italic> gene expression was repressed by SA but triggered by MeJA (Frerigmann and Gigolashvili, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). To analyze whether these signaling molecules affect indole GSL accumulation, we measure the GSL content of Chinese kale sprouts after signaling molecules treatment. Our results revealed that flg22 and SA treatment elevated the content of indole GSL, while eBL treatment reduced the accumulation of indole GSL, thus demonstrating the importance of BoaMYB51.1 for signal-mediated indole GSL regulation (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">10</xref>). However, MeJA treatment also increased the content of indole GSL, substantiating the importance of MYB34 upon JA signaling (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">10</xref>). Collectively, it seems that BoaMYB51.1 act as a major regulator of indole GSL biosynthesis while BoaMYB51.2 perform as an accessory role. To obtain insights into BoaMYB51s, we analyzed their transcriptional activation mechanisms, defined their transcriptional activation domains, and identified BoaMYB51-interacting proteins.</p><sec><title>MYB51-mediated regulation on indole GSL biosynthesis is conserved</title><p>In the present study, complementation experiments in <italic>A. thaliana myb34myb51</italic> double mutants and tobacco transient expression assay demonstrated that both two BoaMYB51 proteins are involved in controlling indole GSL biosynthesis in Chinese kale. Two BoaMYB51 proteins were shown to exclusively trans-activate the indole GSL biosynthetic genes including <italic>BoaCYP79B2, BoaCYP83B1</italic> and <italic>BoaSOT16</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) while they failed to induce the aliphatic GSL biosynthetic gene <italic>BoaCYP79F1</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), which is in consistency with previous report of AtMYB51 (Gigolashvili et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2007b</xref>). Moreover, it has been revealed that two BoaMYB51s also activates <italic>AtCYP83B1</italic> (Supplementary Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">7A&#x02013;D</xref>), implying that MYB51-mediated transcription regulation of indole GSL biosynthesis is conserved. Amino acid sequence alignment of two BoaMYB51 and AtMYB51 proteins showed conserved N-terminal domain among them (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). It is known that N-terminal domain of R2R3-MYB is responsible for its DNA binding function (Dubos et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), which explains the conservation of MYB51-mediated regulation on GSL biosynthesis. Besides, when promoter sequences of <italic>BoaSOT16.1</italic> and <italic>AtSOT16</italic> genes were aligned, a conserved <italic>cis-</italic>element was observed (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">11</xref>), which is a putative binding site of MYB51. In addition to indole GSL regulator, we also found that BoaMYB28 positively regulates aliphatic GSL biosynthetic gene without directly affecting indole GSL biosynthesis in Chinese kale, which is in line with the results in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and other <italic>Brassica</italic> crops (Gigolashvili et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2007a</xref>; Augustine et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), suggesting that the MYB-mediated regulatory mechanism of aliphatic GSL and indole GSL biosynthesis is conserved in <italic>Brassicaceae</italic>. To further study the MYB-mediated specific regulation on GSL biosynthesis, we swapped the N-terminal fragments of BoaMYB28 for the N-terminal domain of BoaMYB51.1 and co-expressed this chimeric protein with <italic>BoaSOT16.1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic> and <italic>BoaCYP79F1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic>, respectively in tobacco leaves (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">12</xref>). Our results revealed that BoaMYB51.1<sup>N&#x02212;SWAP</sup> protein failed to activate the promoter of <italic>BoaSOT16.1</italic>, whereas co-transfomation with <italic>BoaCYP79F1</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub><italic>:LUC</italic> led to a significant increase of luminescence intensity (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">12</xref>). We also generated another chimeric protein with N-terminal fragments of BoaMYB51.1 and C-terminal fragments of BoaMYB28 and this BoaMYB51.1<sup>C&#x02212;SWAP</sup> protein showed an opposite pattern in tobacco transient assay when compared with BoaMYB51.1<sup>N&#x02212;SWAP</sup> (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">12</xref>). Collectively, these results suggest that the N-terminal domain is critical for the specific regulation of GSL biosynthesis.</p></sec><sec><title>C-end is the transcriptional activation domain (TAD) of BoaMYB51s</title><p>Typically, a TF consists of a DNA-binding domain (DBD) and a transcription regulatory domain. It is generally considered that plant R2R3-MYB TFs share a conserved N-terminal MYB DBD, and C-terminal part of the protein usually harbors an activation or repression domain (Dubos et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). However, the experimentally proven details about TAD in R2R3-MYB TFs is limited. From studies by Goff et al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>), the TAD of the ZmC1 is located in a carboxy-terminal acidic region. Moreover, the C-terminal acidic region of AtMYB2 and AtMYB12 was found to be able to activate transcription (Urao et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Stracke et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Here, we identified the TAD of BoaMYB51, which is also located in the C-terminal region, by using yeast two-hybrid system and tobacco transient assay (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A,B</xref>). According to previous reports, the TAD of a TF often contains acidic, glutamine-rich, or proline-rich stretches of amino acids (Stracke et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The TAD of BoaMYB51 defined in this study is enriched in acidic amino acids, but proline-rich or glutamine-rich amino acid stretches were not identified, which is in good accordance with the features of the TADs of above-mentioned R2R3-MYB TFs. It is a general phenomenon that the acidic TADs of TFs overlap closely with the destruction elements (Salghetti et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). Whether the acidic TAD of BoaMYB51 also functions as a degron which may account for the unstable characteristic of MYB51 protein needs further analysis. Since the amino sequences between AtMYB51 and BoaMYB51 are highly conserved, we also identified the TAD of AtMYB51 based on sequence alignment which is located in the amino acid region 294 to 352, and the result was validated by yeast two-hybrid system (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">13</xref>). Furthermore, we also found that the TAD of AtMYB28 and BoaMYB28.1 are localized to C-end (data not shown), indicating that the C-terminally localized TAD is shared as a conserved feature by GSL-related MYBs.</p></sec><sec><title>MYB51-BIM1 protein complex might be involved in regulating indole GSL biosynthesis</title><p>The bHLH protein BIM1 is a brassinosteroid signaling component involved in mediating BR-responsive gene expression. It has been demonstrated that BIM1 regulates hypocotyl elongation, embryo patterning, and UVR8-mediated photomorphogenesis via interacting with the atypical bHLH protein BES1, AP2 protein DRN and UV-B light photoreceptor UVR8, respectively (Yin et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Chandler et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Liang et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Here, BoaBIM1.1 was identified from a two-hybrid screen using BoaMYB51.1&#x00394;TAD as bait (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), and protein-protein interaction between BoaBIM1s and BoaMYB51s has been further confirmed. Gene expression analysis revealed that both <italic>BoaBIM1.1</italic> and <italic>BoaBIM1.2</italic> are expressed in Chinese kale leaves at a relatively high level (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">9</xref>), in which BoaMYB51s are also highly expressed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). To study the role of BIM1 on GSL biosynthesis, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> triple mutant <italic>bim123</italic> was used for GSL and qRT-PCR analysis. We found that indole GSL content and expression levels of indole GSL biosynthetic genes <italic>AtCYP79B2, AtCYP79B3</italic>, and <italic>AtCYP83B1</italic> were decreased (Supplementary Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">14A,B</xref>), implicating that BIM1 is a putative regulator of indole GSL biosynthesis. Besides, it has also been showed that the transcript level of <italic>AtMYB51</italic> was not affected in <italic>bim123</italic>, suggesting that BIM1 interact with MYB51 and regulate the transcription of indole GSL biosynthetic genes.</p><p>Protein-protein interaction between MYB and bHLH transcription factors is a well-known paradigm of combinatorial gene regulation in plants and are instrumental in various biological processes (Feller et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). MYB-bHLH protein complex has been revealed to regulate anthocyanin biosynthesis (Gonzalez et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and trichome morphogenesis (Zhao et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Besides, the bHLH protein MYC2, known as a component of JA signaling pathway, and its close homologs MYC3 and MYC4 were shown to interact with GSL-related MYBs and affect thereby the GSL biosynthesis (Schweizer et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Frerigmann et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In this study, we identified another MYB-bHLH protein complex involved in the GSL biosynthesis regulation. It is known that the three MYCs bind to GSL-related MYBs via an N-terminal domain, the so-called JID domain (JAZ interaction domain). However, the C-terminal domain of BoaBIM1 show interaction with BoaMYB51 in yeast two-hybrid assays (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9B</xref>), suggesting that the interaction mechanism between these two MYB-bHLH protein complexes is different.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Author contributions</title><p>CC and QW designed the research, CC and WY conducted the experiments. WY, HM, MD, MW, JL, and WZ analyzed the data. CC and QW wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by a grant from National Science Foundation of China (NO. 31270343, 31470385, 31801864) and China Postdoctoral Science Foundation (NO. 2017M621943).</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01599/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01599/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasumi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishizawa</surname><given-names>O. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwahara</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Novel bioresources for studies of <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic>: identification of a kale MYB transcription factor responsible for glucosinolate production</article-title>. <source>Plant Biotechnol. J.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>1017</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1027</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12095</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23910994?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23910994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Augustine</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majee</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisht</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Four genes encoding MYB28, a major transcriptional regulator of the aliphatic glucosinolate pathway, are differentially expressed in the allopolyploid <italic>Brassica juncea</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>4907</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4921</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert280</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24043856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24043856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>C. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Effects of industrial pre-freezing processing and freezing handling on glucosinolates and antioxidant attributes in broccoli florets</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source>
<volume>210</volume>, <fpage>451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>456</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.04.140</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27211670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27211670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capriotti</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavaliere</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>La Barbera</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montone</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piovesana</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenezini Chiozzi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Chromatographic column evaluation for the untargeted profiling of glucosinolates in cauliflower by means of ultra-high performance liquid chromatography coupled to high resolution mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Talanta</source>
<volume>179</volume>, <fpage>792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>802</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2017.12.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29310309?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29310309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Werr</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>BIM1, a bHLH protein involved in brassinosteroid signalling, controls <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> embryonic patterning via interaction with DORNROSCHEN and DORNROSCHEN-LIKE</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-008-9405-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18830673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18830673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Genome triplication drove the diversification of <italic>Brassica</italic> plants</article-title>. <source>Hortic. Res.</source>
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>14024</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hortres.2014.24</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26504539?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26504539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Glucosinolates, structures and analysis in food</article-title>. <source>Anal Methods UK.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>325</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b9ay00280d</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adio</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Denoux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Glucosinolate metabolites required for an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> innate immune response</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>323</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1164627</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19095898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19095898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubos</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stracke</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grotewold</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisshaar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepiniec</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>MYB transcription factors in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>581</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2010.06.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20674465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20674465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zalcmann</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Talalay</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The chemical diversity and distribution of glucosinolates and isothiocyanates among plants</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(00)00316-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11198818?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11198818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machemer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grotewold</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Evolutionary and comparative analysis of MYB and bHLH plant transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04459.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21443626?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frerigmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gigolashvili</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>bHLH05 is an interaction partner of MYB51 and a novel regulator of glucosinolate biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>166</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>369</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.240887</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25049362?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25049362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frerigmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gigolashvili</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>MYB34, MYB51, and MYB122 distinctly regulate indole glucosinolate biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol. Plant</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>814</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>828</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssu004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24431192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gigolashvili</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisshaar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flugge</surname><given-names>U. I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007a</year>). <article-title>The transcription factor HIG1/MYB51 regulates indole glucosinolate biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>886</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>901</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03099.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17461791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gigolashvili</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engqvist</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yatusevich</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flugge</surname><given-names>U. I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>HAG2/MYB76 and HAG3/MYB29 exert a specific and coordinated control on the regulation of aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>177</volume>, <fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>642</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02295.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18042203?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18042203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gigolashvili</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yatusevich</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flugge</surname><given-names>U. I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007b</year>). <article-title>The R2R3&#x02013;MYB transcription factor HAG1/MYB28 is a regulator of methionine-derived glucosinolate biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>261</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03133.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17521412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17521412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Functional analysis of the transcriptional activator encoded by the maize <italic>B</italic> gene: evidence for a direct functional interaction between two classes of regulatory proteins</article-title>. <source>Gene Dev.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>864</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>875</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.6.5.864</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1577278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1577278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leavitt</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Regulation of the anthocyanin biosynthetic pathway by the TTG1/bHLH/Myb transcriptional complex in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>814</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>827</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03373.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18036197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18036197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalebout</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grubb</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Functional detection of chemopreventive glucosinolates in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>159</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9452(00)00354-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11074279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11074279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grubb</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Glucosinolate metabolism and its control</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2005.12.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16406306?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16406306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>C. X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>BZR1 and BES1 participate in regulation of glucosinolate biosynthesis by brassinosteroids in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>2401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2412</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert094</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23580754?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23580754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halkier</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Biology and biochemistry of glucosinolates</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Plant Bio.</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>333</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.57.032905.105228</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16669764?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16669764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>MYB transcription factors regulate glucosinolate biosynthesis in different organs of Chinese cabbage</article-title> (<source>Brassica rapa ssp. pekinensis). Molecules</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>8682</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8695</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules18078682</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23881053?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23881053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kliebenstein</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambrix</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichelt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell-Olds</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Gene duplication in the diversification of secondary metabolism: tandem 2-oxoglutarate&#x02013;dependent dioxygenases control glucosinolate biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>681</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>693</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.13.3.681</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11251105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11251105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kliebenstein</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell-Olds</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Comparative analysis of quantitative trait loci controlling glucosinolates, myrosinase and insect resistance in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>161</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>332</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12019246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12019246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>MEGA7: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 7.0 for bigger datasets</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1870</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1874</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw054</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27004904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27004904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaspi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrella</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> IQD1, a novel calmodulin-binding nuclear protein, stimulates glucosinolate accumulation and plant defense</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02435.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15960618?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15960618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>UVR8 interacts with BES1 and BIM1 to regulate transcription and photomorphogenesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Dev Cell.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>512</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>523</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2017.12.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29398622?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29398622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malitsky</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Less</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venger</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elbaz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The transcript and metabolite networks affected by the two clades of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> glucosinolate biosynthesis regulators</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>148</volume>, <fpage>2021</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2049</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.124784</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18829985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18829985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danna</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Songnuan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Werck-Reichhart</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Innate immune responses activated in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> roots by microbe-associated molecular patterns</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>973</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>990</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.069658</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20348432?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20348432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mithen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Glucosinolate biochemical diversity and innovation in the <italic>Brassicales</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>71</volume>, <fpage>2074</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2086</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2010.09.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20971483?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20971483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mithen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magrath</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Development of isothiocyanate-enriched broccoli, and its enhanced ability to induce phase 2 detoxification enzymes in mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>734</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-002-1123-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12596003?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12596003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurose</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hino</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamukai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Development of series of gateway binary vectors, pGWBs, for realizing efficient construction of fusion genes for plant transformation</article-title>. <source>J. Biosci. Bioeng.</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1263/jbb.104.34</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17697981?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17697981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nour-Eldin</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Reduction of antinutritional glucosinolates in <italic>Brassica</italic> oilseeds by mutation of genes encoding transporters</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>382</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3823</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28288105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28288105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>C. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Effects of light quality on main health-promoting compounds and antioxidant capacity of Chinese kale sprouts</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source>
<volume>196</volume>, <fpage>1232</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1238</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.10.055</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26593611?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26593611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salghetti</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muratani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijnen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Futcher</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tansey</surname><given-names>W. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Functional overlap of sequences that activate transcription and signal ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>97</volume>, <fpage>3118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3123</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.7.3118</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10706616?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10706616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schweizer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Calvo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zander</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diez-Diaz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glauser</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> basic helix-loop-helix transcription factors MYC2, MYC3, and MYC4 regulate glucosinolate biosynthesis, insect performance, and feeding behavior</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>3117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3732</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.113.115139</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23943862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23943862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shon</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Functional analysis of three BrMYB28 transcription factors controlling the biosynthesis of glucosinolates in <italic>Brassica rapa</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>90</volume>, <fpage>503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>516</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-016-0437-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26820138?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26820138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000f8;nderby</surname><given-names>I. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kliebenstein</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halkier</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A complex interplay of three R2R3 MYB transcription factors determines the profile of aliphatic glucosinolates in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>153</volume>, <fpage>348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>363</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.149286</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20348214?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20348214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stracke</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huep</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barsch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrtens</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niehaus</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Differential regulation of closely related R2R3&#x02013;MYB transcription factors controls flavonol accumulation in different parts of the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seedling</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>660</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>677</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03078.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17419845?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17419845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stracke</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turgut-Kara</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisshaar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The AtMYB12 activation domain maps to a short C-terminal region of the transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Z. Naturforsch. C</source>
<volume>72</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/znc-2016-0221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28284041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28284041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stracke</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Werber</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisshaar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The R2R3-MYB gene family in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>456</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(00)00199-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11597504?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11597504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Variation of glucosinolates in three edible parts of Chinese kale (<italic>Brassica alboglabra</italic> Bailey) varieties</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source>
<volume>124</volume>, <fpage>941</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>947</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2010.07.031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>S. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Arabidopsis ASA1 is important for jasmonate-mediated regulation of auxin biosynthesis and transport during lateral root formation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1511</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.108.064303</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19435934?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19435934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noji</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A transcriptional activation domain of ATMYB2, a drought-inducible <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Myb-related protein</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1148</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1996.10061145.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9011094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9011094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of the nutritional quality of Chinese kale (<italic>Brassica alboglabra</italic> Bailey) using UHPLC-Quadrupole-Orbitrap MS/MS-based metabolomics</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1262</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules22081262</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28749430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28749430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wittstock</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halkier</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Glucosinolate research in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> era</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>270</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(02)02273-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grain</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Gourrierec</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Th&#x000e9;venin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelemen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Complexity and robustness of the flavonoid transcriptional regulatory network revealed by comprehensive analyses of MYB-bHLH-WDR complexes and their targets in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seed</article-title>. <source>New Phytol.</source>
<volume>202</volume>, <fpage>132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>144</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12620</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24299194?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24299194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Molecular characterization of MYB28 involved in aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis in Chinese kale <italic>(Brassica oleracea</italic> var</article-title>. <source>alboglabra Bailey). Front. Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1083</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.01083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28680435?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28680435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vafeados</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A new class of transcription factors mediates brassinosteroid-regulated gene expression</article-title> in <source>Arabidopsis. Cell.</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>259</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2004.11.044</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15680330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15680330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evivie</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Identification and expression pattern analysis of BoMYB51 involved in indole glucosinolate biosynthesis from broccoli (<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> var</article-title>. <source>italica). Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
<volume>501</volume>, <fpage>598</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>604</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2018.05.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29753738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Q. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Transcriptional mechanism of jasmonate receptor COI1-mediated delay of flowering time in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>2814</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2828</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00619</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26410299?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26410299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Three genes encoding AOP2, a protein involved in aliphatic glucosinolate biosynthesis, are differentially expressed in <italic>Brassica rapa</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>6205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6218</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erv331</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26188204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26188204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morohashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatlestad</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grotewold</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The TTG1-bHLH-MYB complex controls trichome cell fate and patterning through direct targeting of regulatory loci</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>1991</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1999</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.016873</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18434419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18434419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>