<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6024020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.00853</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><sup>15</sup>N Natural Abundance Evidences a Better Use of N Sources by Late Nitrogen Application in Bread Wheat</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal</surname><given-names>Teresa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/474438/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Estavillo</surname><given-names>Jos&#x000e9; M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Du&#x000f1;abeitia</surname><given-names>Miren K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu&#x000e9;rfano</surname><given-names>Ximena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/524856/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castell&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>Ander</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Murua</surname><given-names>Carmen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aizpurua</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moro</surname><given-names>Mar&#x000ed;a Bego&#x000f1;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/291015/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Plant Biology and Ecology, University of the Basque Country (UPV/EHU)</institution>, <addr-line>Bilbao</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>NEIKER-Tecnalia, Basque Institute for Agricultural Research and Development</institution>, <addr-line>Derio</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Karl H. M&#x000fc;hling, Christian-Albrechts-Universit&#x000e4;t zu Kiel, Germany</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Laura Ercoli, Scuola Sant&#x02019;Anna di Studi Avanzati, Italy; Bahar Yildiz Kutman, Gebze Technical University, Turkey</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Teresa Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal, <email>teresa.fuertes@ehu.eus</email> Mar&#x000ed;a Bego&#x000f1;a Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moro, <email>mariabegona.gonzalez@ehu.eus</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Nutrition, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>853</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal, Estavillo, Du&#x000f1;abeitia, Hu&#x000e9;rfano, Castell&#x000f3;n, Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Murua, Aizpurua and Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moro.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal, Estavillo, Du&#x000f1;abeitia, Hu&#x000e9;rfano, Castell&#x000f3;n, Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Murua, Aizpurua and Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moro</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>This work explores whether the natural abundance of N isotopes technique could be used to understand the movement of N within the plant during vegetative and grain filling phases in wheat crop (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) under different fertilizer management strategies. We focus on the effect of splitting the same N dose through a third late amendment at flag leaf stage (GS37) under humid Mediterranean conditions, where high spring precipitations can guarantee the incorporation of the lately applied N to the soil-plant system in an efficient way. The results are discussed in the context of agronomic parameters as N content, grain yield and quality, and show that further splitting the same N dose improves the wheat quality and induces a better nitrogen use efficiency. The nitrogen isotopic natural abundance technique shows that N remobilization is a discriminating process that leads to an impoverishment in <sup>15</sup>N of senescent leaves and grain itself. This technique also reflects the more efficient use of N resources (fertilizer and native soil-N) when plants receive a late N amendment.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>bread quality</kwd><kwd>bread wheat</kwd><kwd>humid Mediterranean conditions</kwd><kwd><sup>15</sup>N natural abundance</kwd><kwd><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Instituto Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n y Tecnolog&#x000ed;a Agraria y Alimentaria<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100007652</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">RTA2005-00219-CO3-02</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Instituto Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n y Tecnolog&#x000ed;a Agraria y Alimentaria<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100007652</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">RTA2013-00057-CO5-02</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003">Ekonomiaren Garapen eta Lehiakortasun Saila, Eusko Jaurlaritza<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100005004</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn003">IT-932-16</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="2"/><ref-count count="58"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Nitrogen is one of the essential nutrients required for crop productivity, which is mainly provided in form of fertilizers. However, the overuse of fertilizers in nowadays agriculture is often associated with a low nitrogen use efficiency (NUE) by the crop, since most crop plants absorb only 30&#x02013;50% of the N fertilizer supplied, depending on the soil or the environment (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Tilman et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Ladha et al., 2005</xref>). This N overapplication of fertilizer derives in a risk of negative impacts to the environment.</p><p>During the last decades, innovative approaches such as quantitative genetics or different agronomic strategies are being introduced in order to increase crops NUE. Among agronomic practices, an adequate distribution of the fertilizer rate is fundamental in order to assure that the N applied is available at the right time, especially in early growth stages. In wheat crop, two amendments of N fertilizer are traditionally applied in Mediterranean areas. The first and second amendments are applied, according to Zadoks growth scale for cereals, at tillering stage (GS20) and at stem elongation stage, respectively (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Zadoks et al., 1974</xref>). However, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Gate (1995)</xref> and <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Oury et al. (2003)</xref> proposed the application of a third amendment in the flag leaf stage (GS37), which would extend the vegetative growth of the plant and enhance the N content of the vegetative organs. This would lead to a higher N availability in the vegetative organs to be later remobilized within the plant at the reproductive stage, eventually improving grain protein concentration. This fertilizer management strategy is commonly used in European regions of the United Kingdom, Germany, Netherlands, or Denmark, where high spring rains result in higher availability of N fertilizer to crop plants. Nevertheless, under Mediterranean climatic conditions a late N application has led to very different results regarding grain yield (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Alcoz et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Garrido-Lestache et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Ercoli et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Blandino et al., 2015</xref>) and grain quality in terms of N concentration (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Ayoub et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Garrido-Lestache et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Brown and Petrie, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2010a</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Blandino et al., 2015</xref>). These contrasting results are probably explained by the different climatic conditions under which field experiments have been carried out.</p><p>In the Basque Country cereal production is conducted under humid Mediterranean conditions. Under these climatologic conditions a late N amendment at GS37 could be relevant due to high spring precipitations can lead to higher grain N content, as a result of an efficient incorporation of the lately applied N (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2010a</xref>), in contrast to other drier Mediterranean areas. In fact, under irrigated conditions wheat plants grown in pots are able to efficiently use the N lately applied in GS37 (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2010b</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The physiological basis of this agronomic behavior is based on the fact that in wheat, grain N is not only determined by the amount of N reserves accumulated in the vegetative organs during pre-anthesis, but also largely determined by the amount of N taken after anthesis, since both N sources contribute to storage protein accumulation in the grain (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Dupont and Altenbach, 2003</xref>). In order to design N fertilization schedules tailored to a specific agroclimatic region, it is mandatory to get a better knowledge of the NUE by identifying the critical moments of requirements of N fertilizer by the crop during vegetative stages and those of N reallocation from source to sink organs.</p><p>An interesting tool to understand and interpret the efficiency of the different N fertilization regimes is the use of isotopic markers. The use of stable isotopes, particularly the analysis of N isotope natural abundance (&#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N), is promising in agriculture. This technique has the advantage that it is relatively accessible, as it can be measured in different plant organs or growth stages without any extra design in the trials and at a reasonable price.</p><p>The patterns of &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N in the plant integrate, on one side, processes occurring in the soil (N cycling and loss), reflecting the isotopic fractionation during transformations of soil N; at the same time, &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N represents an indicator of which source, soil vs. fertilizer, is the main one for the plant. Specifically in agricultural soils, soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N signature is strongly affected by that of the N fertilizer (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2017</xref>); the large difference in &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N among soil and N fertilizer allows the usage of <sup>15</sup>N isotope composition as a tracer. Synthetic fertilizers are normally depleted or enriched in <sup>15</sup>N. On the other side, plant values of &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N also reflect the different physiological mechanisms occurring inside the entire plant system, mainly N uptake, nitrate reduction and N assimilation at different crop stages, as well as remobilization to the grain, or even N losses to the atmosphere or rhizosphere (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Coomstock, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Evans, 2001</xref>). Thus, the application of different N fertilizer doses and in different moments to match the N requirements of the crop along the growing season is foreseeable to influence the <sup>15</sup>N plant composition, thus reflecting the N use by the plant. Under this assumption, the time-integrated character regarding biological processes makes &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N is considered as a potential tool to be taken into account in order to address the understanding of the processes responsible for NUE under different climatic and agronomic management conditions. This technique has been used, for instance, to understand the ecosystem N status (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>), as indicator of the fertilization regime (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bateman et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">In&#x000e1;zio et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2017</xref>), as a potential tool to guarantee the authenticity of organic products (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Flores et al., 2007</xref>) or for estimating the relative contribution of the different N sources to a sink (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Kolb and Evans, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Serret et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Flores et al., 2010</xref>). Nevertheless, the use of <sup>15</sup>N natural abundance still demands of a deeper theoretical basis and technical advances in order to be correctly interpreted in the soil-plant system (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Robinson, 2001</xref>), according to the farming system or agricultural practices.</p><p>The present work has been carried out under the following hypothesis: firstly, the &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N in wheat is expected to deplete with increasing application of synthetic nitrogen fertilizer (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Austin and Jones, 1975</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bateman et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Bol et al., 2005</xref>), secondly, the third late amendment allows to increase the N content in grain in some wheat varieties (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2010b</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The specific objectives of the present work were: firstly, to explore whether the natural abundance of N isotopes technique could be used to understand the movement of N within the plant during vegetative and grain filling phases in wheat crop and, secondly, to evaluate the potentiality of &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value in tissues as a physioagronomic indicator to assess the effect of different fertilizer managements on NUE by wheat. The work has been done under humid Mediterranean conditions in the Northern Spain. Results are discussed in relation with N content in plant organs as well as with agronomic and (breadmaking) quality parameters of wheat grain and will help to provide scientific basis for a rational fertilization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Experimental Design</title><p>A field trial was established in Northern Spain in Arkaute (42&#x000b0;51&#x02032;N, 2&#x000b0;41&#x02032;W, and 513 m above sea level) in the province of Alava, on a clay loam soil, type Aquertic Etrudept (<bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>). The preceding crop was winter wheat. Mechanical tillage (disk, mouldboard plow) was used for seed bed preparation. Winter bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) Cezanne variety was sown at a density of 220 kg seeds ha<sup>-1</sup> in November 2006 and harvested in July 2007. At pre-seeding 90 kg ha<sup>-1</sup> of P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and 90 kg ha<sup>-1</sup> of K<sub>2</sub>O were applied as basal fertilization. The experimental design consisted in four N fertilizer treatments applied as ammonium nitrate (33.5% N w/w, with a &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of 1.56 &#x000b1; 0.17&#x02030;) at rates of 0, 140, and 180 kg N ha<sup>-1</sup>, splitted in two or three amendments at the beginning of tillering stage (GS20), the beginning of stem elongation stage (GS30) and flag leaf stage (GS37), as stated in <bold>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></bold>. The trial consisted of a completely randomized block experimental design with four replications (number of total plots = 16), the size of each plot being 50 m<sup>2</sup> (5 m &#x000d7; 10 m). Regarding the weather conditions, <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold> shows monthly rainfall and temperatures at the trial location along the field campaign (2006&#x02013;2007) and mean values of monthly rainfall and temperatures for the last 25 years (1991&#x02013;2016). The rainfall during 2006&#x02013;2007 growing season was slightly lower than the average values for the last 25 years, and temperatures fall within the region&#x02019;s average annual.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Physical and chemical properties of the clay loam soil (0&#x02013;30 cm depth) for the location at Arkaute (Alava, Spain).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Soil texture<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Soil chemical properties<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sand (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silt (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clay (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organic matter (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C/N</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbonate (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P (ppm)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca (meq/100)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mg (meq/100)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K (meq/100)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Total rates and splitting of the different N-fertilization treatments, and soil and plant samplings on different growth stages (GS) along the crop cycle.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GS20</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GS30</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GS36</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GS37</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GS60</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GS90</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatments</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/>Beginning of tillering</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/>Beginning of stem elongation</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/>Flag leaf stage</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/>Anthesis</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/>Maturity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fertilization (kg N ha<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil sampling</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;30 cm</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;30 cm</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;30 cm</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant sampling</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flag leaf fourth leaf</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ear flag leaf fourth leaf</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grain ear flag leaf fourth leaf</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>GS according to the Zadoks scale.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Mean monthly and total rainfall and minimum and maximum temperatures for the location at Arkaute (Alava, Spain) during the field trial in 2006&#x02013;2007, and mean values for the last 25 years (1991&#x02013;2016) (data source: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.euskalmet.euskadi.eus">www.euskalmet.euskadi.eus</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00853-g001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sampling and Analyses</title><p>Soil was collected and wheat plants were harvested at different developmental stages. Soil was collected by mixing four subsamples taken individually from the 0&#x02013;30 cm depth zone in each plot, just before the flag leaf (GS36), anthesis (GS60), and maturity (GS90) stages (<bold>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></bold>). Fifteen wheat plants per treatment and plot were harvested and separated into fourth leaf (bottom leaf), flag leaf and ear, just before flag leaf (GS36), flowering (GS60), and maturity (GS90) stages. Values for mature grain corresponded to GS90 and were determined by harvesting the 1.5 m width central belt along each plot row. Both soil and plant samples were oven-dried at 70&#x000b0;C for 72 h and homogenized into fine powder for further analyses. In the case of the grain, the material was later sieved through a 1 mm screen. Breadmaking quality was determined using the standard alveogram procedure (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">AACC-Approved methods of the American Association of Cereal Chemists, 1993</xref>) and given as Chopin&#x02019;s alveogram parameters: extensibility (L), tenacity (P), equilibrium (P/L), and strength (W). Nitrogen concentration and &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N in soil and plant material were determined using a Delta Plus Continuous Flow Stable Isotope Ratio Mass Spectrometer (Thermo Finnigan, Bremen, Germany) coupled to a Carlo Erba elemental analyzer (CHNSO EA1108, Carlo Erba, Milan, Italy). Grain protein concentration was calculated as the product of total N concentration multiplied by 5.7 (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Teller, 1932</xref>).</p><p>Nitrogen harvest index (NHI) was calculated accordingly to <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Austin and Jones (1975)</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>NHI</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Where <italic>Y</italic> is the yield of grain (G) and straw (S), and <italic>N</italic> is the N concentration. The values of the isotope ratio were expressed as &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N (&#x02030;), according to the formula</p><disp-formula id="E2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>15</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02030;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>standard</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where R<sub>sample</sub> is <sup>15</sup>N/<sup>14</sup>N of the soil or plant material. Following international convention, the R<sub>standard</sub> used was the N isotope ratio in the atmosphere air (<italic>R</italic> = 0.0036765, <sup>15</sup>N<sub>air</sub> = 0&#x02030;<sub>;</sub>
<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Robinson, 2001</xref>). For <sup>15</sup>N<sub>air</sub>, the samples were referenced against acetanilide. The &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N of the material may be either positive if it is enriched in <sup>15</sup>N relative to the standard, or negative if it is depleted.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>Measurements were taken from four experimental replications. Data on N concentration and &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values were subjected to a two-factor ANOVA for soil data and three-factor ANOVA for plant data (SPSS version 20.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, United States). The variance was related to the three main treatments (fertilizer treatment, organ and sampling date) and to the interactions between them. Duncan&#x02019;s multiple-range test was used to evaluate significantly different means (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) between treatments.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Grain Yield, Protein Content, and Breadmaking Quality Parameters</title><p>Wheat grain yield ranged from 3.20 tons/ha in the non-fertilized plants to 5.64 tons/ha in treatment 180+ (<bold>Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref></bold>). The three-time splitted 180 kg N ha<sup>-1</sup> rate maintained the yield as the same rate twice splitted. The non-fertilized plants showed a grain protein concentration of 7.3%, which increased to 10.3% and 10.9% by applying 140 and 180 kg N ha<sup>-1</sup> two-times splitted, respectively, with no significant difference between them. However, the third splitting of the highest rate of 180 kg N ha<sup>-1</sup> at GS37 led to a further increase in grain protein concentration of 7.8% respect to the same twice-splitted dose (<bold>Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref></bold>). Besides, this increase in grain protein content due to the third split (180+) was accompanied by a significant increase (10%) in the NHI. The most determinant parameters of breadmaking quality, extensibility (L) and strength (W), were increased by 103% and 143%, respectively, on average when applying 140 and 180 kg N ha<sup>-1</sup> (<bold>Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref></bold>) with respect to the non-fertilized treatment. A further improvement in the dough strength (24%) occurred when the highest fertilizer dose was three times splitted in compared to treatment receiving two fertilizer amendments.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Grain yield, grain protein content, Nitrogen Harvest Index (NHI) and breadmaking quality of dough, according to the Chopin&#x02019;s alveogram parameters in wheat (L: extensibility; P: tenacity; P/L: tenacity/extensibility ratio or equilibrium; W: strength).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kg N ha<sup>-1</sup></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yield (kg ha<sup>-1</sup>)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grain protein (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NHI (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Alveogram parameters<hr/></th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L (mm)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P (mm)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P/L</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W (&#x000d7;10<sup>-4</sup> J)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Test</italic> (0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3196 &#x000b1; 235 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30 &#x000b1; 0.11 c</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.3 ab</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0 &#x000b1; 2.3 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.7 &#x000b1; 4.9 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 &#x000b1; 0.17 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.7 &#x000b1; 8.9 c</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5441 &#x000b1; 160 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.32 &#x000b1; 0.28 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.4 ab</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.7 &#x000b1; 7.7 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.2 &#x000b1; 3.7 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 &#x000b1; 0.18 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216.3 &#x000b1; 1.9 b</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5412 &#x000b1; 198 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.94 &#x000b1; 0.45 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.5 b</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.0 &#x000b1; 1.1 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.0 &#x000b1; 4.0 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#x000b1; 0.05 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.5 &#x000b1; 0.3 b</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5639 &#x000b1; 72 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.80 &#x000b1; 0.17 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.8 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.0 &#x000b1; 11.9 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.7 &#x000b1; 9.6 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#x000b1; 0.27 a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261.7 &#x000b1; 4.8 a</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>Nitrogen fertilization treatments: 0 (test), 140, 180, and 180+ (kg N ha<sup>-<italic>1</italic></sup>) dispensed as indicated in <bold>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></bold>. Values in the same column followed by the same letter are not significantly different at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Soil N Content and &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N</title><p>Soil N content remained stable independently of the fertilizer treatment along growth stages (<bold>Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4A</xref></bold>). The fertilizer applied (ammonium nitrate 33.5%) showed a low &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of 1.56 &#x000b1; 0.17&#x02030;, accordingly to the range of -1.4 to 2.6&#x02030; described for NH<sub>4</sub>NO<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Bateman and Kelly, 2007</xref>). Thus, the application of inorganic N fertilizer significantly decreased the soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N in all fertilized treatments (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>) at GS36 compared to the non-fertilized soil, which showed a &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of 6.7&#x02030;. The soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N remained stable at the different wheat growth stages (<bold>Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4A</xref></bold>).</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Summary of Factorial ANOVA.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(A) Soil factorial ANOVA</th><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Soil N (%)</bold><hr/></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N (&#x02030;)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>F</italic></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Significance level</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>F</italic></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Significance level</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.351</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.384</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth stage</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.302</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.840</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment &#x000d7; growth stage</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>(B) Plant organs factorial ANOVA</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Plant N (%)</bold><hr/></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Plant &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N (&#x02030;)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.051</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.697</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth stage</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178.799</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.595</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241.727</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment &#x000d7; growth stage</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.383</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.981</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment &#x000d7; organ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.742</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth stage &#x000d7; organ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.738</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.557</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment &#x000d7; growth stage &#x000d7; organ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.114</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><bold>(A)</bold> Two-way ANOVA for the effect of N fertilization treatment and growth stage sampled on soil N content and &#x003b4;<sup><italic>15</italic></sup>N. <bold>(B)</bold> Three-way ANOVA for the effect of the N fertilizer treatment, growth stage and organ on plant N concentration and &#x003b4;<sup><italic>15</italic></sup>N. Treatments as in <bold>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></bold>. Asterisks indicate significance level at <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 and <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Effect of N fertilization on the N concentration and N isotopic composition (&#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N) of soil and plant organs at different growth stages. Fertilization treatments: 0, 140, 180, and 180+ (kg N ha<sup>-1</sup>) dispensed as indicated in <bold>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></bold>. For each growth stage, different letters indicate significant differences between treatments at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 according to Duncan&#x02019;s test. Absence of letters indicates no differences. Asterisk indicates significant differences between treatments 180 and 180+, according to the <italic>t</italic>-test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00853-g002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Plant N Content and &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N</title><p>Plant N concentration significantly changed with fertilizer application, along growth stages and among organs in wheat (<bold>Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4B</xref></bold>). In addition, an interaction between the growth stage and the organ was also observed. The &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values also showed differences with the fertilized treatments, growth stages and organs, without any interaction between these factors (<bold>Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4B</xref></bold>).</p><p>The N concentration of vegetative organs (fourth and flag leaves) showed a trend to diminish along the wheat crop lifecycle (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). Concomitantly, a N remobilization toward the grain occurred. Thus, an average decrease of 40% in the N concentration of the fourth leaf was observed between GS36 and GS60 in all treatments as a whole, while the flag leaf showed a higher decrease later (60%), from anthesis at GS60 to maturity at GS90. During this period, when it&#x02019;s well known that the ear actively accumulates biomass, the N concentration remained stable. Regarding the effect of fertilization, the N concentration of vegetative organs increased in fertilized respect to non-fertilized plants, although no differences were found among fertilized treatments within the different stages. However, at harvest, grain N concentration was significantly increased with the three-time splitting (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>).</p><p>Concerning the <sup>15</sup>N isotope composition, as observed by other authors (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Kolb and Evans, 2003</xref>) a decreasing trend of &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values within the different plant organs was observed as lifecycle draws on, decreasing in the non-fertilized plant organs from a mean 6&#x02030; at GS36 and GS60 to 3.5&#x02030; at GS90 and from a mean 4&#x02030; to 2&#x02030; in the fertilized plants (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). The &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of the grain in fertilized plants was significantly lower than their respective leaf and ear values (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>).</p><p>Nitrogen fertilization induced changes in &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values, leading to enrichment in the heavy <sup>15</sup>N isotope in non-fertilized plants (average &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of 5&#x02030;) with respect to the fertilized plants (average &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of 2.9&#x02030;), whatever the organ sampled (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). Increasing the N rate from 140 to 180 kg N ha<sup>-1</sup>, but maintaining the splitting at the same moments (GS20 and GS30) led to equal plant natural N isotopic composition (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). On the contrary, a late splitting of the 180 kg N ha<sup>-1</sup> rate (three-times splitted) raised &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N in the flag leaf at GS60 and GS90 and in the ear at GS90 with respect to the two-time splitting.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Further Splitting the N Rate Is Effective in Maintaining Wheat Yield and Improving Grain Quality Under Humid Mediterranean Conditions</title><p>The right rate and timing of fertilizer application must meet the nutrient crop necessity in order to optimize the plant N uptake and avoid N losses to the environment. In this sense, a third late N-fertilizer application in wheat crop at GS37 has been proposed as an agronomic management aimed to increase the NUE by the crop; and this application results particularly interesting in our region (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2010a</xref>), with a monthly average rainfall of 70 mm from March to May in the last 25 years (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold>). In fact, when there is no water limitation this late amendment is able to raise the photosynthetic capacity and the carbohydrate accumulation in leaves and to stimulate the wheat canopy development during the vegetative stages; thus, achieving higher grain yields in Soissons wheat variety (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2010b</xref>) and higher grain protein contents in Cezanne variety (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2013</xref>). The present experiment confirms that, the rainy spring of our region allows the incorporation of the N supplied lately at GS37 (in May) in Cezanne variety. Actually, similarly to what happens in other regions of Northern Europe, further splitting of the N dose at the flag leaf stage (GS37) maintains the crop yield, what means it can correct a possible decrease in yield because of a limiting second application of only 100 kg N ha<sup>-1</sup> at the beginning of stem elongation (GS30).</p><p>Regarding grain quality, it is widely known that the increment in grain protein content is usually translated into a better breadmaking quality of the flour. In this sense, dough strength (W) and extensibility (L) have been described as the most sensitive alveogram parameters to N management and the most dependent properties on grain protein content (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Ames et al., 2003</xref>). Thus, under Mediterranean climate conditions, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Garrido-Lestache et al. (2005)</xref> described improvements in grain quality after the splitting of the N rate, although this effect has not been clearly stated in other studies (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Ayoub et al., 1994</xref>). In our study the increment in grain protein content by three-time splitting of the same N rate (180 Kg N ha<sup>-1</sup>) was translated into an improvement of the dough strength of Cezanne variety (<bold>Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref></bold>). According to <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Borghi et al. (1995)</xref>, the flours obtained from the fertilized treatments of the present experiment (W &#x0003e; 210. 10<sup>-4</sup> J) can be classified inside class 2, e.g., suitable for &#x0201c;direct breadmaking quality.&#x0201d; A better behavior of W is reached, with values up to 261.7 10<sup>-4</sup> J, when the fertilizer is three-times splitted, which categorizes this flour into class 1 and enables its use as an &#x0201c;improver wheat.&#x0201d; Whereas on the contrary, when no fertilizer was applied the low values of W and L makes this flour is classified as &#x0201c;bread for biscuit,&#x0201d; with a quality not appropriate for breadmaking. So, we conclude that, similarly to what was described for Soissons variety under the same climatic conditions by <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al. (2010a</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), the management of N fertilization through a third late splitting at GS37 also improves grain quality in Cezanne variety destined to breadmaking.</p></sec><sec><title>Fertilization Depletes the Soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N</title><p>The soil is considered as a dynamic system where many N transformation processes occur, as mineralization, immobilization, nitrification, volatilization, or plant assimilation. All these processes are viewed as reciprocal and, taken as a whole, they would have none or little effect on total soil N and &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N. Total soil N and &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N are dominated by soil stable N (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Johannisson and H&#x000f6;gberg, 1994</xref>) and by both N inputs and outputs fluxes (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>); possible changes in these parameters would be originated from the N input&#x02013;output balance in the soil system, such as fertilizer application or N losses to the environment. Provided different studies show that mineral fertilization can either decrease (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Serret et al., 2008</xref>), increase (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Senbayram et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>) or even have none (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Kriszan et al., 2009</xref>) or little effect (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2011</xref>) on soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N, in our study, we monitored the soil N content in combination with soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N to attain a better interpretation of possible variations in the N source available for the plant due to fertilizer management. The soil of our study presented a N content of 0.16% previous to N fertilization (<bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>), and was not affected by the input of mineral N fertilizer (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold> and <bold>Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4A</xref></bold>). In fact, the only expected changes in soil &#x0201c;N fractions&#x0201d; after mineral fertilization would be a transient increase in soil ammonium and nitrate contents (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Hu&#x000e9;rfano et al., 2016</xref>), whereas no clear dependence of top-soil N content and the amount of applied fertilizer is expected (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Watzka et al., 2006</xref>). Regarding soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N, the initial value of 6.7&#x02030; (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>) is in the range of cultivated soils (+1 and +12&#x02030;) (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2017</xref>), which is normally higher than in natural soils due to the fertilization input. Thus, the &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N of cultivated soils is susceptible to be affected by the &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N of the fertilizer after long periods applying N. In the same line of evidences, soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values even below 0&#x02030; (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Broadbent et al., 1980</xref>) and a strong depletion in soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N, with a lowering of 2.9&#x02030; (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Gerzabek et al., 1999</xref>) have been registered. The slight downward shift of 0.31&#x02030; units observed after fertilization in our short-time study would be explained by the low signature value of the mineral nitrogen fertilizer applied (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2017</xref>), which showed a &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of 1.56 &#x000b1; 0.17&#x02030;, e.g., close to that of atmospheric N<sub>2</sub> (0&#x02030;).</p><p>More interestingly, the lowering shift effect of &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N was distinguishable among the different fertilization strategies in GS36, just before the application of the third amendment. Thus, the impoverishment trend in the soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value observed in the treatment 180 reflected that the amount of fertilizer dispensed until that very moment was the highest rate (<bold>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></bold> and <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). Treatments 140 and 180+ showed identical soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values, accordingly to the fact that both plots had received equal N fertilizer rate and timing (40 kg ha<sup>-1</sup> at GS 20 and 100 kg ha<sup>-1</sup> at GS30).</p></sec><sec><title>Plant &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N Reflects the N Source Signature and Shows Isotope Discrimination During N Remobilization Toward the Grain</title><p>The interpretation of <sup>15</sup>N natural abundance in plant tissues is generally complex because &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N signatures can differ from those of the original source due to isotope fractionation during physiological processes within the plant, mainly during N uptake, nitrate reduction and assimilation (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Evans et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Robinson, 2001</xref>), as well as during remobilization to the grain. Therefore, the combination of &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N signature with other agrophysiological parameters becomes necessary to better understanding of the N movement within the plant, as modulated by the different fertilizer management strategies.</p><p>During pre-anthesis, up to GS60, leaves act overall as photosynthetic N sinks where N uptake and assimilation take place. It is during this phase when the wheat crop assimilates most of its N, in such a way the total N content in the plant at GS60 becomes sometimes as high as 90% of the total N at maturity (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Heitholt et al., 1990</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Hocking and Staper, 2001</xref>). Between GS36 and GS60, the fourth leaf strongly contributes to N remobilization, as indicated by its depletion in N content (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>); Meanwhile, the flag leaf would still be growing (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Gustavsson, 2011</xref>) and maintaining its assimilatory capacity, acting thus overall as a photosynthetic N sink. At GS60 the ear is completely developed (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Zadoks et al., 1974</xref>) and can take up N directly from the soil, but it also behaves as a sink receiving N remobilized from leaves (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Kichey et al., 2007</xref>). The lower &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values in leaves of the fertilized plants during pre-anthesis (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>) indicate that more N was available for the plant directly from the fertilizer applied. In fact, the always higher &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values in organs of non-fertilized plants (with mean values of around 6.2&#x02030;) mirror more closely the soil &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value (with mean values of around 6.6&#x02030;), whereas fertilized plants show a mean drop of 2.5&#x02030; units in the &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values respect to fertilized soils (with values between 3 and 4&#x02030; with respect to 6.324&#x02030; of the soil). This impoverishment in the heavy isotope in fertilized plants is interpreted in the sense that they were fed by a mixed source consisting of both soil N (with a &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of 6.324&#x02030;) and the inorganic N fertilizer (with a low &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of 1.56&#x02030;). Discrimination against the heavy <sup>15</sup>N isotope occurs during the primary assimilation of inorganic nitrogen within the plant, nitrate reductase and glutamine synthetase being the main enzymes responsible for this isotope discrimination (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Kalcsits et al., 2014</xref>). So, the impoverishment in &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N of the fertilized plants induced by the uptake of inorganic fertilizer (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>) was surely enhanced by an also higher N assimilation rate with respect to the non-fertilized plants.</p><p>During the grain filling period, from GS60 to GS90, the ear is the main sink organ and vegetative organs behave as sources remobilizing N in a type of senescence process characterized by a sequential death from bottom-to-upper leaves. In fact, this senescence process was formerly started in the pre-anthesis phase in the oldest fourth leaf. From GS60 to GS90 the contribution of the already senescent fourth leaf to N remobilization was minimal, upper leaves taking their turn successively jointly with leaf sheaths or even root, to supply N reserves to the ear (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2012</xref>). Thus, it would be the youngest flag leaf the one providing N reserves for N recycling, as indicated by the strong depletion of more than 50% in its N content from GS60 to GS90 (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). Therefore, during the post-anthesis period it is the ear the plant organ that accumulates N. However, a dilution effect due to its continuous growth would be the responsible factor for counteracting the expected increase in N content due to the import of nitrogenous compounds, thus making the ear N concentration remains unchanged until maturity.</p><p>As leaves suffer the source-sink transition, ammonium is released from protein degradation (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Kichey et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bernard and Habash, 2009</xref>). In theory, the lighter isotope <sup>14</sup>N is often incorporated for the biosynthesis of the products destined to translocation (e.g., amino acids), whereas the heavier <sup>15</sup>N isotope is concentrated in the remaining cell solution, since <sup>15</sup>N-bearing molecules or ions react slower than isotopically lighter analogs (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Dawson and Brooks, 2001</xref>). According to that, we would expect that the remaining leaves as source organs were enriched in <sup>15</sup>N-bearing molecules non-used for remobilization. But interestingly, the remobilization of N from the fourth and flag leaves was concurrent with a significant impoverishment in the heavy <sup>15</sup>N isotope as leaves senesced. Related to this, a general isotopic impoverishment of plant organs along the plant lifecycle was previously reported (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Flores et al., 2007</xref>), although the physiological basis remains to be understood. The cytosolic isoform of glutamine synthetase (GS1) has been specifically involved in the reassimilation of ammonium released during senescence. <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Kichey et al. (2006)</xref> reported its accumulation in the mesophyll cytosol in the flag leaf. Glutamate dehydrogenase is also induced in senescent leaves probably to deaminate leaf proteins (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Kichey et al., 2005</xref>). Whatever the enzyme is contributing to the recycling of ammonium, a discrimination effect against <sup>15</sup>NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> occurs, the lighter <sup>14</sup>NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> being preferentially incorporated by N-reassimilating enzymes for amino acid translocation. According to that, we suggest that ammonium peaks occurring in senescing leaves will be proportionally <sup>15</sup>N-enriched. Several authors have reported that ammonia emissions peak related to N remobilization take place during late leaf senescence (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Schjoerring, 2012</xref>). Thus, the impoverishment in <sup>15</sup>N observed in senescent organ biomass might be explained by <sup>15</sup>N-enriched ammonia losses from the plant body to the atmosphere when N remobilization occurs.</p><p>The dynamics of &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values in the ear must be interpreted in function of the dual role of this structure both as sink and source of N for remobilization. The ear &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values are concomitant with changes in N contents of the leaves as N remobilizing organs. In fact, the strong correlations between the ear &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values at G60 and GS90 with changes in N concentration of fourth and flag leaves, respectively (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>) support that fourth leaf provides the ear with N from G36 to GS60 whereas flag leaf provides more directly N to the ear from the anthesis (GS60) to maturity (GS90). On the other hand, the extremely low values of &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N in the non-fertilized ear at GS90 respect to GS60 indicate that during grain filling the N previously carried-over from leaves is isotopically discriminated in the same ear structures, and also that the remobilization process would predominate over a direct N uptake from soil by this organ. The fact that grain &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N signature of non-fertilized plants shows similar values to the ear and flag leaf at GS90 (around 4&#x02030;), indicates: firstly, the ear structures contribute to grain filling, playing an intermediate role during the development of mature grain. In fact, practically all the N remobilized is temporarily accumulated in the glumes, which act as a sink of N before its further remobilization to the grain (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Lopes et al., 2006</xref>). In the same line of evidence, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Sanchez-Bragado et al. (2016)</xref> have reported that ammonium turnover happens actively in different structures of the ear (glumes, awns, grains) as well as in the flag leaf. The remobilization process could explain the strong impoverishment in <sup>15</sup>N observed in the non-fertilized ear between GS60 and GS90, as well as in the grain in fertilized plants (with &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N of 1.7&#x02013;2.0&#x02030;) in relation to their respective ears (&#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N of 2.6&#x02013;3.2&#x02030;) or flag leaves at GS60 (&#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N of 2.8&#x02013;4.2&#x02030;). Secondly, the discrimination against <sup>15</sup>N is minimal in the non-fertilized ear compared to the fertilized one, surely due to the N limitation prevents the discrimination and promotes a simultaneously higher efficiency in the N remobilization process (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>) (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Gaju et al., 2014</xref>). The larger amount of N carried over to the grain, the higher the discrimination against <sup>15</sup>N becomes in this structure. This fact is supported by the strong depletion in &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values for grain in fertilized plants regarding non-fertilized plants, which is not evident in the ear at GS90, and the improvement in N content in the fertilized treatments (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). And also by the inverse correlations observed between ear &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values and the changes in N concentration of vegetative organs acting as N source along the wheat crop cycle (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>). Thus, we can interpret these relationships in the sense that discrimination within the plant is lower in the non-fertilized ear because the ratio between plant demand versus the N available is high (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Serret et al., 2008</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Correlation between ear &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values at GS60 and decreases in the fourth leaf N concentration from GS36 to GS60 <bold>(A)</bold>; and between ear &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values at GS90 and decreases in the flag leaf N concentration from GS60 to GS90 <bold>(B)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-00853-g003"/></fig><p>A third late N fertilizer application at the flag leaf stage (GS37) attains a better behavior of dough as consequence of the increment in grain protein. Nevertheless, no effect of the third late amendment was evident in terms of N concentration in the ear, as was neither observed in general for the rest of vegetative organs along the crop cycle. According to previous work (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2012</xref>), splitting the same dose into three amendments did not increase the N reserves in tissues but remobilize them more efficiently. The late N application would have more impact on N metabolism and its remobilization to the grain than on biomass accumulation or N partitioning in the plant (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal et al., 2010b</xref>). The &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N signature reveals itself as a physioagronomic marker able to reflect the effect of a late N amendment in treatment 180+ in certain organs and moments. Thus, the &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N in the flag leaf and the ear at GS60 allows tracking the effect of the application of this third N amendment. Besides, the higher &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values were determined in the flag leaf and ear in treatment 180+ at GS60, which confirms the period between GS36 and GS60 is critical for N uptake by the crop under humid Mediterranean conditions. Moreover, once the third amendment is dispensed it would be expected the plant uses preferably the N coming directly from the fertilizer, however the higher &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N value of the flag leaf and ear at GS60 in treatment 180+ is also maintained respect to the values of the previous growth stage GS36. Interestingly, this indicates that the plant from treatment 180+ is taking proportionally a higher amount of N coming from the soil than in the case of 140 and 180 plants. In other words, the &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N parameter allows to illustrate that after applying a late N amendment the plant takes up an extra quantity of N coming from soil at this late growth stage, which would contribute to the increase in grain N content and dough quality observed, thus implying a more efficient use of the N sources compared to a twice amendment management.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, the use of the nitrogen isotopic natural abundance technique in wheat plants revealed that N remobilization is a discriminating process leading to an impoverishment in the heavy isotope of senescent leaves and grain. The analysis of &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N values also reflected how wheat plants are able to use nitrogen resources (native soil-N versus fertilizer-N) in a more efficient way when N application is further splitted into a late N amendment under humid Mediterranean conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>TF-M, JME, and MBG-M designed the experiments, developed the structure and arguments for the paper, made critical revisions, and had primary responsibility for the final content. AA and AC managed the field experiments. XH and MKD helped in analyzing the data. JME, CG-M, and MKD supervised the experiments and complemented the manuscript writing and its discussion. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This research was supported by IT-932-16, RTA2005-00219-CO3-02 and RTA2013-00057-CO5-02.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>The authors thank technicians of SAI, Universidade da Coru&#x000f1;a for their technical support in &#x003b4;<sup>15</sup>N determinations.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>AACC-Approved methods of the American Association of Cereal Chemists</collab> (<year>1993</year>). <source><italic>Method 54-30A.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AACC</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alcoz</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hons</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haby</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Nitrogen-fertilization timing effect on wheat production, nitrogen uptake efficiency and residual soil-nitrogen.</article-title>
<source><italic>Agron. J.</italic></source>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>1198</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1203</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj1993.00021962008500060020x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dexter</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Selles</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchylo</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Effects of nitrogen fertilizer on protein quantity and gluten strength parameters in durum wheat (<italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> L. var. <italic>durum</italic>) cultivars of variable gluten strength.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cereal Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/CCHEM.2003.80.2.203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>The physiology of wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cambridge Annual Report, Plant Breeding Institute</italic></source>
<fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayoub</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guertin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fregeau-Reid</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Nitrogen fertilizer on bread-making quality of hard red spring wheat in eastern Canada.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>1346</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1352</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1994.0011183X003400050038x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Fertilizer nitrogen isotope signatures.</article-title>
<source><italic>Isotopes Environ. Health Stud.</italic></source>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>247</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10256010701550732</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17786669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17786669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jickells</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Nitrogen isotope relationships between crops and fertilizer: implications for using nitrogen isotope analysis as an indicator of agricultural regime.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>5760</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5765</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf050374h</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15998145?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15998145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Habash</surname><given-names>D. Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The importance of cytosolic glutamine synthetase in nitrogen assimilation and recycling.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>182</volume>
<fpage>608</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>620</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02823.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19422547?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19422547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blandino</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyneri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Late-Season nitrogen increases improver common and durum wheat quality.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Fertil. Crop Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>680</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>690</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/agronj14.0405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bol</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnett</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>B. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The natural abundance of 13C, 15N, 34S and 14C in archived (1923&#x02013;2000) plant and soil samples from the Askov long-term experiments on animal manure and mineral fertilizer.</article-title>
<source><italic>Rap. Commun. Mass Spectrom.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>3216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3226</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rcm.2156</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16220463?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16220463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borghi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordani</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbellini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guermandi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toderi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Influence of crop rotation and fertiliser treatments on wheat bread-making quality.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Agron.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1161-0301(14)80015-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broadbent</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauschkolb</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>G. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Spatial variability of nitrogen-15 and total nitrogen in some virgin and cultivated soils.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>524</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>527</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2136/sssaj1980.03615995004400030017x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Irrigated hard winter wheat response to fall, spring, and late season applied nitrogen.</article-title>
<source><italic>Field Crops Res.</italic></source>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2005.07.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittert</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Soil total nitrogen and natural 15Nitrogen in response to long-term fertilizer management of a maize-wheat cropping System in Northern China.</article-title>
<source><italic>Commun. Soil Sci. Plant Anal.</italic></source>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>322</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00103624.2011.538883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Synthetic fertilizer and livestock manure differently affect &#x003b4;15N in the agricultural landscape: a review.</article-title>
<source><italic>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>237</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2016.12.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ro</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobbie</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Patterns of natural 15N in soils and plants from chemically and organically fertilized uplands.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Biol. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>1493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1500</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0038-0717(03)00246-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coomstock</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Steady-state isotopic fractionation in branched pathways using plant uptake of NO3- as an example.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>214</volume>
<fpage>220</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>234</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250100602</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11800386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11800386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Fundamentals of stable isotope chemistry and measurement,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Application of Stable Isotope Techniques to Study Biological Processes and Functioning of Ecosystems</italic></source>
<role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Unkovich</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic</publisher-name>) <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altenbach</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Molecular and biochemical impacts of environmental factors on wheat grain development and protein synthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Cereal Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>146</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0733-5210(03)00030-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ercoli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pampana</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariotti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arduini</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>As durum wheat productivity is affected by nitrogen fertilisation management in Central Italy.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Agron.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eja.2012.08.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Physiological mechanisms influencing plant nitrogen isotope composition.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trends Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>126</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(01)01889-1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11239611?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukrapanna</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehleringer</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Nitrogen isotope composition of tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> Mill. cv. T-5) grown under ammonium or nitrate nutrition.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1323</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.1996.tb00010.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenoll</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The feasibility of using &#x003b4;15N and &#x003b4;13C values for discriminating between conventionally and organically fertilized pepper (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>5740</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5745</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf0701180</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17567025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17567025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenoll</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aparicio-Tejo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Isotopic evidence of significant assimilation of atmospheric-derived nitrogen fixed by <italic>Azospirillum brasilense</italic> co-inoculated with phosphate-solubilising Pantoea dispersa in pepper seedling.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Soil Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>340</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2010.10.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aizpurua</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moro</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estavillo</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010a</year>). <article-title>Improving wheat breadmaking quality by splitting the N fertilizer rate.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Agron.</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eja.2010.03.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seti&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estavillo</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moro</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010b</year>). <article-title>Late nitrogen fertilization affects carbohydrate remobilization in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>173</volume>
<fpage>907</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>919</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jpln.200900262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Murua</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moro</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estavillo</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Late nitrogen fertilization affects nitrogen remobilization in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Soil Sci. Plant Nutr.</italic></source>
<volume>175</volume>
<fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>124</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcn124</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18660494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18660494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Torralba</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arregui</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Murua</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Moro</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estavillo</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Ammonium as sole N source improves grain quality in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sci. Food. Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>2162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2171</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.6022</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23339023?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23339023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaju</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martre</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Gouis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Nitrogen partitioning and remobilization in relation to leaf senescence, grain yield and grain nitrogen concentration in wheat cultivars.</article-title>
<source><italic>Field Crops Res.</italic></source>
<volume>155</volume>
<fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>223</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2013.09.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrido-Lestache</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Bellido</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Bellido</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Durum wheat quality under Mediterranean conditions as affected by N rate, timing and splitting, N form and S fertilization.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Agron.</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eja.2004.12.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gate</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source><italic>Ecophysiologie du bl&#x000e9;.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lavoisier</publisher-name>
<volume>429</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerzabek</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haberhauer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichlmayer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The response of soil nitrogen and 15N natural abundance to different amendments in a long-term experiment at Ultuna, Sweden.</article-title>
<source><italic>Agronomie</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>466</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/agro:19990603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A developmental scale for perennial forage grasses based on the decimal code framework.</article-title>
<source><italic>Grass Forage Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>108</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2494.2010.00767.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heitholt</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croy</surname><given-names>L. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maness</surname><given-names>N. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Nitrogen partitioning in genotypes of winter-wheat differing in grain N-concentration.</article-title>
<source><italic>Field Crop Res.</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>144</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-4290(90)90108-N</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hocking</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staper</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Effects of sowing time and nitrogen fertiliser on canola and wheat, and nitrogen fertiliser on Indian mustard. I. Dry matter production, grain yield, and yield components.</article-title>
<source><italic>Aust. J. Agric. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>52</volume>
<fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>634</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR00113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu&#x000e9;rfano</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuertes-Mendiz&#x000e1;bal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-D&#x000ed;ez</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estavillo</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Murua</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Men&#x000e9;ndez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The new nitrification inhibitor 3,4-dimethylpyrazole succinic (DMPSA) as an alternative to DMPP reducing N2O emissions from wheat crops under humid Mediterranean conditions.</article-title>
<source><italic>Eur. J. Agron.</italic></source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eja.2016.07.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>In&#x000e1;zio</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Urquinaga</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalk</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>M. G. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>P. O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Identifying N fertilizer regime and vegetable production system in tropical Brazil using 15N natural abundance.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Sci. Food Agric.</italic></source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>3025</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3032</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.7177</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25800588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25800588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johannisson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;gberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>15N of soils and plants along an experimentally induced forest nitrogen supply gradient.</article-title>
<source><italic>Oecologia</italic></source>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>322</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00317321</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28313626?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28313626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalcsits</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buschhaus</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Nitrogen isotope discrimination as an integrated measure of nitrogen fluxes, assimilation and allocation in plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Physiol. Plant.</italic></source>
<volume>151</volume>
<fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppl.12167</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24512444?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24512444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kichey</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heumez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocholle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pageau</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanacker</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Combined agronomic and physiological aspects of nitrogen management in wheat highlight a central role for glutamine synthetase.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>169</volume>
<fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01606.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16411930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16411930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kichey</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heumez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Gouis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Wheat genetic variability for postanthesis nitrogen absorption and remobilization revealed by 15N labeling and correlations with agronomic traits and nitrogen physiological markers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Field Crops Res.</italic></source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2007.01.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kichey</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Gouis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangwan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Changes in the cellular and subcellular localization of glutamine synthetase and glutamate dehydrogenase during flag leaf senescence in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>964</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>974</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pci105</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15840646?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15840646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Influence of N source and concentration on nitrogen isotopic discrimination in two barley genotypes (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>1431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1440</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3040.2003.01066.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kriszan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amelung</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schellberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebbing</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhbauch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Long-term changes of the &#x003b4;15N natural abundance of plants and soil in a temperate grassland.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>325</volume>
<fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>169</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-009-9965-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladha</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupnik</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Six</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessel</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Efficiency of fertilizer nitrogen in cereal production: retrospects and prospects.</article-title>
<source><italic>Adv. Agron.</italic></source>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>156</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2113(05)87003-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Effect of nitrogen addition on the variations in the natural abundance of nitrogen isotopes of plant and soil components.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>412</volume>
<fpage>453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>464</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-016-3081-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortadellas</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kichey</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Habash</surname><given-names>D. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araus</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Wheat nitrogen metabolism during grain filling: Comparative role of glumes and the flag leaf.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>225</volume>
<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-006-0338-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16804706?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16804706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oury</surname><given-names>F. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;rad</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brancourt-Hulmel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Depatureaux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doussinault</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galic</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Yield and grain protein concentration in bread-wheat: a review and a study of multi-annual data from a French breeding program.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Genet. Breed.</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>&#x003b4;15N as an integrator of the nitrogen cycle.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trends Ecol. Evol.</italic></source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(00)02098-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11179580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Bragado</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Serret</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araus</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The nitrogen contribution of different plant parts to wheat grains: exploring genotype, water, and nitrogen effects.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>1986</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.01986</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28119703?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28119703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senbayram</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>K. W. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bol</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Long- term influence of manure and mineral nitrogen applications on plant and soil 15N and 13C values from the Broadbalk Wheat Experiment.</article-title>
<source><italic>Rapid Commun. Mass Spectrom.</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>1735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1740</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rcm.3548</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18438763?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18438763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serret</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz-Monasterio</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araus</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The effects of urea fertilisation and genotype on yield, nitrogen use efficiency, &#x003b4;15N and &#x003b4;13C in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Appl. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>153</volume>
<fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7348.2008.00259.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teller</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1932</year>). <article-title>Non-protein nitrogen compounds in cereals and their relation to the nitrogen factor for protein in cereals and bread.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cereal Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>274</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tilman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Agricultural sustainability and intensive production practices.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>418</volume>
<fpage>671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>677</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01014</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12167873?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12167873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schjoerring</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Seasonal variation in nitrogen pools and 15N/13C natural abundances in different tissues of grassland plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biogeosciences</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>1583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1595</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/bg-9-1583-2012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schjoerring</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Seasonal variation in ammonia compensation point and nitrogen pools in beech leaves (<italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>343</volume>
<fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-010-0693-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watzka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchgraber</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanek</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Natural 15N abundance of plants and soils under different management practices in a montane grassland.</article-title>
<source><italic>Soil Biol. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>1564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1573</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2005.11.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zadoks</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Konzak</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <article-title>A decimal code for the growth stages of cereals.</article-title>
<source><italic>Weed Res.</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>421</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3180.1974.tb01084.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>