<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur. J. Med. Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Journal of Medical Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0949-2321</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2047-783X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5622480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">277</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40001-017-0277-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Developing a risk prediction model for breast cancer: a Statistical Utility to Determine Affinity of Neoplasm (SUDAN-CA Breast)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Salih</surname><given-names>Alaaddin M.</given-names></name><address><phone>00 249 (9) 00 14 71 333</phone><email>alaaddin_salih@biari.brown.edu</email><email>alaaddinsalih@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alam-Elhuda</surname><given-names>Dafallah M.</given-names></name><address><email>dafoua@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alfaki</surname><given-names>Musab M.</given-names></name><address><email>musabnoor946@live.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yousif</surname><given-names>Adil E.</given-names></name><address><email>aeyousif@qu.edu.qa</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nouradyem</surname><given-names>Momin M.</given-names></name><address><email>mumatb@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442398.0</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>International University of Africa, </institution></institution-wrap>Khartoum, Sudan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>National Academy of Health Sciences, Khartoum, Sudan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 7988</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4305.2</institution-id><institution>College of Medicine and Veterinary Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Edinburgh, </institution></institution-wrap>Edinburgh, EH8 9YL UK </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 6207</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9763.b</institution-id><institution>Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Khartoum, </institution></institution-wrap>Khartoum, Sudan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.449328.0</institution-id><institution>National Ribat University and Central Police Hospitals, National Ribat University, </institution></institution-wrap>Khartoum, Sudan </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0634 1084</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412603.2</institution-id><institution>Department of Statistics, College of Arts and Sciences, </institution><institution>Qatar University, </institution></institution-wrap>Doha, Qatar </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.449328.0</institution-id><institution>Department of OB/GYN, </institution><institution>Ribat University and Central Police Hospitals, National Ribat University, </institution></institution-wrap>Khartoum, Sudan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><elocation-id>35</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Breast cancer risk prediction models are widely used in clinical settings. Although most of the well-known models were designed based on data collected from western population, yet they have been utilized for surveillance purposes in many limited-resource countries. Given the genetic variations in risk factors that exist between different races, we therefore aimed to develop and validate a tool for breast cancer risk assessment among Sudanese women.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Using cross-sectional design, 153 subjects were eligible to participate in our study. Data were collected from the only couple of tertiary centers in Sudan. They underwent multiple logistic regression using purposeful selection method to build the model. Various adjustments were made to determine significant predictors. Overall performance, calibration and discrimination were assessed by <italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>, <italic>O</italic>/<italic>E</italic> ratio and c-statistic, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">SUDAN predictors of breast cancer were: age, menarche, family history, vegetables and fruits weekly servings, and type of cereals that traditional cuisine is made of. Both Nagelkerke <italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup> (0.495) and <italic>O</italic>/<italic>E</italic> ratio (0.78) were good. c-statistic expressed the excellent discriminatory power of the model (0.864, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001, 95% CI 0.81&#x02013;0.92).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Our findings suggest that SUDAN provides a simple, efficient and well-calibrated tool to predict and classify women&#x02019;s lifetime risks of developing breast cancer. Input from our model could be deployed to guide utilization of the more advanced screening modalities in resource-limited settings to maximize cost effectiveness. Consequently, this might improve the stage at which the diagnosis is usually made.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Breast cancer</kwd><kwd>Prediction model</kwd><kwd>Risk assessment</kwd><kwd>SUDAN</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par11">Breast cancer (BC) is the world&#x02019;s most common malignancy with a constantly increasing incidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Risk prediction models assess either: [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] group odds of developing breast cancer over time as BCRAT (Gail) model, or individual risks of inheriting a mutant <italic>BRCA1/2</italic>like BRCAPRO, BOADICEA, and the Myriad II prevalence tables [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. A practical overlap between the two objectives is present in some models. For instance, IBIS (Cuzick-Tyrer) mainly estimates the risk of breast cancer over time; furthermore, readouts of inheriting a mutant <italic>BRCA</italic>-<italic>1/2</italic> are there. BRCAPRO serves the two goals inversely. Cuzick-Tyrer represents the most accurate prediction tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par12">Modern empirical models are used mainly in defining individual risk to develop breast cancer. Their use is limited to clinical settings since they require detailed family history and genetic analysis for some of them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Applying them in population screening is not fully understood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">As group risk prediction models are used in anticipating breast cancer probability in a wide scale of population, they can help in offering benefits-harms weighted screening recommendations, managing patients, and improving risk reduction strategies. Women with 20&#x02013;25% lifetime risk of BC are advised to undergo breast MRI according to American Cancer Society guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. US Preventive Services Task Force guidelines recommend BRCA1/2 mutation testing for women at a high risk of CA breast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. FDA recommends prophylactic tamoxifen for women with 1.67% 5-years risk of BC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">Most of the known models represent analysis of data retrieved from American and British studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. This is not inclusive of other populations&#x02019; circumstances and may contradict with its generalization over other communities that differ. Moreover, models like Gail and Cuzick-Tyrer consider findings of invasive and costly interventions as biopsies to improve the overall accuracy. Inconsistently, a proven major risk factor, breast density, that could be detected by simple, cheap and non-invasive mammographic scan is not incorporated in any model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This study is trying to identify the risk factors for BC among Sudanese patients.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design and subjects</title><p id="Par15">This is a multicenter, observational, retrospective, cross-sectional study conducted in breast clinics of Bashaier University Hospital (BUH) and Khartoum Center for Radiation and Isotopes (RICK), Khartoum, Sudan. Both are leading tertiary centers highly specialized in managing breast conditions among Sudanese and east African nationals. From October 2014 to September 2015, all eligible patients referred to either of the study facilities were considered. Inclusion criteria were: being a Sudanese female who had menarche, confirmed diagnosis with a standard triple assessment, cases of BC should be of primary type, and accepting participation without compensation. Uncertain diagnoses, breast metastasis from another primary focus, and comparison subjects with proliferative tumors were excluded. A total of 153 patients aged 32&#x02013;74&#x000a0;years were enrolled for this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Variables and outcome</title><p id="Par16">Data were collected using structured data forms. Height and weight were measured using stadiometer of 1&#x000a0;mm accuracy and calibrated 0.01&#x000a0;kg sensitive medical weight scale, respectively. The investigated 34 defined risk factors include demographic (age, education, ethnicity, etc.); medical (past history of benign or malignant breast disease); family history of BC; reproductive (e.g., menarche, age of marriage and birth of the first live child, durations of pregnancy and lactation, and menopause); pharmacological (either usage of hormonal contraception or risk reducing like aspirin, tamoxifen, and raloxifene); nutritional (traditional food cereals, meat and animal products; vegetables and fruits, and sugar servings); and lifestyle risks like physical exercise, smoking and alcohol intake.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par17">Statistical analysis was performed using the Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS), version 23.0 (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Categorical variables were reported in numbers and percentages (<italic>N</italic>, %). Whereas, continuous variables were expressed as mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation (SD) at 95% confidence interval (CI).</p><p id="Par18">Using SPSS, a dataset of the 153 participants was made. 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;2 contingency and frequency tables for the categorical and numerical variables were created to ensue occupancy of each cell. No empty cell was present. SUDAN CA Breast was built according to purposeful selection method. All risk factors individually underwent univariate analysis once-at-a-time using simple binary logistic regression. Only 13 with significant Wald <italic>&#x003c7;</italic>
<sup>2</sup> at <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.25 were qualified for a second phase analysis using multivariate logistic regression. Five variables with <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 were selected as predictors of the initial logit model. Parameter estimates of age, menarche, family history, and vegetables and fruits, and sorghum and millets were changed by 14.78, 8.88, 14.72, 7.67, 18.42, and 10.99%, respectively. Such levels exclude confoundings as none exceeded the 20% ceiling. Moreover, they changed insignificantly when variables dropped in phase 1 were subsequently added to the main effects model. All predictors fulfilled the assumptions of normality, absence of multicollinearity, and linearity between probability logit and age, menarche, and weekly servings of fruits and vegetables. Overall performance, discrimination and calibration of the final model were assessed for using <italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>, c-statistic, and Hosmer&#x02013;Lemeshow test, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Ethical concerns</title><p id="Par19">Ethical clearance of the Research Ethics Committee in National Academy of Health Sciences was obtained. Institutional approvals were also received prior to commencement of the research. Our study strictly followed Declaration of Helsinki. Informed consents were obtained from all participants after ensuring anonymity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Demographic and clinical features of participants</title><p id="Par20">A total of 184 patients were referred to our facilities during study period. After assessing eligibility, 153 females were incorporated in the model (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). 63 (41.2%) subjects were diagnosed with the cancer. The median age of our sample was 37.00 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.30) years. It was 46.89 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.99) years for breast cancer patients and 32.64 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.41) years for those who did not have the disease. Patients who were illiterate were more than those who had not BC, 34.92% compared to 17.78%. Low socioeconomic status was invariably predominant among respondents (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;132; 86.27%). 120 (78.43%) of our sample came from central Sudan, whereas only 4 were from eastern states. Almost half of our African subjects had breast cancer (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;26; 48.15%), compared to 37 (37.37%) of the remaining ethnicities.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Likelihood measures of SUDAN. <bold>1</bold> ROC curve showing the AUC c-statistic. <bold>2</bold> Scatter plots of continuous data. 2a age in a polynomial relationship; 2b and 2c menarche and weekly serving of vegetables and fruits. Showing wide scattering, weak relation and negative direction of the polynomial regression line</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40001_2017_277_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par21">Interestingly, a positive past history of breast diseases was seen in one-third of the comparison group, close to the 26.98% BC patients. Twenty (31.75%) of cancer patients had a familial pattern of the disease which existed in 12 (13.33%) of the counter group. Menarche of BC patients was significantly earlier than others mean, 14.77&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.70 compared to 14.05&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.92 (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.016). Conversely, menopause of the former at 48.09 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.49) years was insignificantly delayed from counterparts&#x02019; mean (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;26.11&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.57, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.312). Married BC patients were 56 (88.89%), making the figure eightfold the number of singles (7, 11.11%). They experience marriage at 20.73 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.98) years, one and half year prior to unaffected participants 22.14 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.21, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.245) years. Most participants with cancer have given birth to single or multiple offspring (52; 82.54%) at the age of 21.25 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.28) years.</p><p id="Par22">Contraception was used by only 18 (28.57%) patients, 14 of them received contraceptive pills. This was even less than those used contraception and do not gain the disease (28; 31.11%). Regular use of the prophylactic acetylsalicylic acid was used by only 4 (6.35%) and 5 (5.56%) subjects with and without malignancy. Tamoxifen and raloxifene were taken by none.</p><p id="Par23">Two of the four nutritional patterns that have been studied were significant factors for breast cancer, cereals and fruits and vegetables servings. Sudanese frequently eat their traditional meals that are rich in starchy ingredients. Types of cereals, meals are made of, were investigated. Among the 23 (15.03%) subjects who consume millet, 69.57% harbor BC. Most of our samples eat vegetables and fruits throughout the week with an indiscriminate mean between healthy and ill individuals, 6.62 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.958) and 6.79 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.679) servings per week, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Uni- and multivariate analysis</title><p id="Par24">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> contains the results of the univariate analysis of the 34 known risk factors resulted in only 13 significant at <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.25. When incorporated into a single multivariate logistic regression, the 5 with <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 were the predictors (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Main effects model containing significant factors (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.25) underwent univariate analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Factors</th><th align="left">Mean (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD)/<italic>N</italic> (%)</th><th align="left">
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>
</th><th align="left">S.E.</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic> value</th><th align="left">OR</th><th align="left">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Demographic risks</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Age (years)</td><td char="(" align="char">38.5 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.3)</td><td char="." align="char">0.093</td><td char="." align="char">0.018</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td><td align="left">1.098</td><td align="left">1.06&#x02013;1.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">&#x000a0;Educational level</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Illiterate</td><td char="(" align="char">38 (24.8%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.909</td><td char="." align="char">0.382</td><td char="." align="char">0.017</td><td align="left">2.482</td><td align="left">1.17&#x02013;5.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Literate</td><td char="(" align="char">115 (75.2%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">(Reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">&#x000a0;Occupational status</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Unemployed</td><td char="(" align="char">111 (72.5%)</td><td char="." align="char">1.073</td><td char="." align="char">0.409</td><td char="." align="char">0.009</td><td align="left">2.924</td><td align="left">1.31&#x02013;6.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Employed</td><td char="(" align="char">42 (27.5%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">(Reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">&#x000a0;Ethnicity</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;African</td><td char="(" align="char">54 (35.3%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.442</td><td char="." align="char">0.343</td><td char="." align="char">0.197</td><td align="left">1.556</td><td align="left">0.80&#x02013;3.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Non-African</td><td char="(" align="char">99 (64.7%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">(Reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Family</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">&#x000a0;Family history of BC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;NA</td><td char="(" align="char">121 (79.1%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">(Reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;YA</td><td char="(" align="char">32 (20.9%)</td><td char="." align="char">1.106</td><td char="." align="char">0.412</td><td char="." align="char">0.007</td><td align="left">3.023</td><td align="left">1.35&#x02013;6.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Reproductive</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Menarche (years)</td><td char="(" align="char">14.5 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.8)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.227</td><td char="." align="char">0.096</td><td char="." align="char">0.018</td><td align="left">0.797</td><td align="left">0.66&#x02013;0.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">&#x000a0;Marital status</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Single</td><td char="(" align="char">33 (21.6%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">(Reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Married/have married</td><td char="(" align="char">120 (78.4%)</td><td char="." align="char">1.179</td><td char="." align="char">0.463</td><td char="." align="char">0.011</td><td align="left">3.250</td><td align="left">1.31&#x02013;8.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">&#x000a0;Birth history</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Nulliparous</td><td char="(" align="char">43 (28.1%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">(Reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Parous</td><td char="(" align="char">110 (71.9%)</td><td char="." align="char">0.959</td><td char="." align="char">0.398</td><td char="." align="char">0.016</td><td align="left">2.608</td><td align="left">1.20&#x02013;5.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Nutritional</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">&#x000a0;Traditional food cereals (servings/week)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Wheat</td><td char="(" align="char">107 (69.9%)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">(Reference)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Sorghum/Milo</td><td char="(" align="char">23 (15.0%)</td><td char="." align="char">1.249</td><td char="." align="char">0.476</td><td char="." align="char">0.009</td><td align="left">3.488</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Millet</td><td char="(" align="char">23 (15.0%)</td><td char="." align="char">1.634</td><td char="." align="char">0.499</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td><td align="left">5.126</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Vegetables &#x00026; fruits (servings/week)</td><td char="(" align="char">5.4 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.2)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.212</td><td char="." align="char">0.078</td><td char="." align="char">0.007</td><td align="left">0.809</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Sleep</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Nocturnal sleeping (h)</td><td char="(" align="char">7.19 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.7)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.143</td><td char="." align="char">0.101</td><td char="." align="char">0.157</td><td align="left">0.867</td><td align="left">0.71&#x02013;1.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Measurements</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Weight (kg)</td><td char="(" align="char">66.0 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;16.1)</td><td char="." align="char">0.014</td><td char="." align="char">0.010</td><td char="." align="char">0.188</td><td align="left">1.014</td><td align="left">0.99&#x02013;1.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="(" align="char">24.6 (&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.6)</td><td char="." align="char">0.041</td><td char="." align="char">0.030</td><td char="." align="char">0.166</td><td align="left">1.042</td><td align="left">0.98&#x02013;1.11</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Five predictors of SUDAN CA Breast with their parameter estimates</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Predictors</th><th align="left">
<italic>&#x00392;</italic>
</th><th align="left">S.E.</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>-value</th><th align="left">
<italic>OR</italic>
</th><th align="left">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td char="." align="char">0.098</td><td char="." align="char">0.021</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td><td align="left">1.103</td><td align="left">1.057&#x02013;1.150</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Menarche(years)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.318</td><td char="." align="char">0.124</td><td char="." align="char">0.010</td><td align="left">0.727</td><td align="left">0.571&#x02013;0.926</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">Family history of BC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;NA</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">1 (Ref)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;YA</td><td char="." align="char">1.141</td><td char="." align="char">0.504</td><td char="." align="char">0.024</td><td align="left">3.130</td><td align="left">1.166&#x02013;8.406</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vegetables &#x00026; fruits (servings/week)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.265</td><td char="." align="char">0.112</td><td char="." align="char">0.018</td><td align="left">0.767</td><td align="left">0.616&#x02013;0.956</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">Traditional food cereals (servings/week)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Wheat</td><td char="." align="char">0.000</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">1 (Ref)</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Sorghum/Milo</td><td char="." align="char">1.098</td><td char="." align="char">0.599</td><td char="." align="char">0.067</td><td align="left">2.997</td><td align="left">0.927&#x02013;9.688</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Millet</td><td char="." align="char">1.676</td><td char="." align="char">0.659</td><td char="." align="char">0.011</td><td align="left">5.345</td><td align="left">1.468&#x02013;19.463</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par25">A logistic regression was performed to assess the effects of age, menarche, family history, vegetables and fruits weekly servings, and type of cereals that traditional cuisine is made of in causing BC. The logistic regression model was statistically significant (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;70.027, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001). SUDAN had successfully classified 49.5% of variance existed between the two groups (Nagelkerke <italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.495). Age has a significant positive relation with breast cancer. An increase in age by 1&#x000a0;year increases the odds of BC by 1.103 compared to the preceding year. Conversely, menarche is inversely related to the disease with each year of delay that minimizes lifetime risks by 0.273. Positive family history of BC triples likelihood of developing malignancy during lifetime. Increasing the number of weekly servings of vegetables and fruits by a single digit reduces the risk of BC by 0.232. Classical Sudanese gastronomy is based on three main cereals. Using wheat as a reference point, subjects who depend on sorghum had a threefold increase in their odds of breast cancer. Even more, millet tops risk up by five times.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Model performance</title><p id="Par26">SUDAN was assessed in terms of overall performance, discrimination and calibration using <italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>, c-statistic, and Hosmer&#x02013;Lemeshow Goodness of fit (GOF) test, respectively. With a Nagelkerke <italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup> of 0.495, the model is capable of justifying almost half of the variance in breast cancer. Discriminatory power measured by c-statistic of AUC equals to 0.864 (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001, 95% CI 0.81&#x02013;0.92). Hosmer&#x02013;Lemeshow GOF test showed an insignificant difference between observed and predicted probabilities making the model well calibrated (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.159, 8&#x000a0;df, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.520). Internal validation of the model revealed an <italic>O</italic>/<italic>E</italic> ratio of 0.78.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par27">To the best of our knowledge, SUDAN is the pioneering tool to assess risk of developing BC in Sudan, Africa, and Middle East. Moreover, it is the first ever of its kind been built using purposeful selection technique. It represents a multivariate logistic regression analysis of data collected in a cross-sectional study, which specified five predictors of breast cancer: age, menarche, family history, vegetables and fruits weekly servings, and type of cereals used. The former three are shared by Gail and Cuzick-Tyrer models. Claus, BRCAPRO, and BOADICEA have the same triad except menarche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. None of our nutritional factors was a predictor in any of the previous models. However, the relationship between nutrition and BC has been established in many studies. Kamath et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] stated that strict vegetarians are three times less likely to have the disease (OR 2.80, 95% CI 1.15&#x02013;6.81). Another study found a significant association between starchy food, like cereals, and certain categories of BC, ER-ve subtypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. By increasing weekly servings of vegetables and fruits and replacing millet and sorghum by wheat, risks get minimized in favor of primary prevention.</p><p id="Par28">The two most important predisposing factors for BC are increasing age and positive family history [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The presence of menarche among predictors can be expressed molecularly. Association between reproductive risk factors of BC, including menarche, and ER+ tumors, has been previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Fadl Elmoula et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] reported a similar prevalence of ER+ among Sudanese and western women. On the contrary, since ER+ status is much less among Asians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], risk prediction model for Thai appeared without menarche. Exceptionally, as receptor status of Koreans and western women are comparable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], four out of KoBCRAT predictors were reproductive risks.</p><p id="Par29">With an OR of 3.13, familial factors appear to play a key role in causing breast cancer. Genetically, breast cancer has autosomal dominant inheritance, predominantly for BRCA1/2 genes. Elnour et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] found that BRCA1/2 mutations to be common in Sudan. Awadelkarim et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] reached similar conclusions; moreover, they highlighted that 28% of their patients&#x02019; germline mutations to be novel. Furthermore, 24.3% of identified point mutations studied by Biunno et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] poses unknown clinical significance, and 42.4% of them are unique to Africa.</p><p id="Par30">The significance of family history and consequently BRCA1/2 predisposition may be attributed to the widespread consanguineous marriages in Sudan. The nation has the highest global rate of matrimonies involving couples who are first degree cousins (45%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. This was even higher in Saha et al.&#x02019;s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] study (49.5%), with additional 13% of participants married to relative husbands of further degrees.</p><p id="Par31">SUDAN has a concordance index of 0.864, which is described as excellent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. This was much higher than the reported c-statistic of Gail Model in a study among western women
(meta-analyzed c-statistic&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.63; 95% CI 0.59&#x02013;0.67) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. KoBCRAT has a c-statistics of 0.63 for &#x0003c;&#x000a0;50&#x000a0;year women and 0.65 for others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. This high discriminatory accuracy qualifies our model to meet screening purposes and define population at high-risk, which better redirect our limited resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p id="Par32">SUDAN model <italic>O</italic>/<italic>E</italic> ratio of 0.78 makes it second to Cuzick-Tyrer only (0.81; 95% CI 0.62&#x02013;1.08), according to Amir et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Corresponding values for Claus, BRCAPRO, and Gail were 0.56 (95% CI 0.43&#x02013;0.75), 0.49 (95% CI 0.37&#x02013;0.65), and 0.48 (95% CI 0.37&#x02013;0.64), respectively. Since our overall <italic>O</italic>/<italic>E</italic> ratios of less than 1.00, subjects that really had the disease were less than expected. This raises false positives; however, it is acceptable as it increases catchment and, consequently, screening purposes which represent the principle aim of our model. <italic>O</italic>/<italic>E</italic> ratio will improve with an increase in the sample size as it better assesses predictors.</p><sec id="Sec12"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par33">This study has some limitations which are addressed here. Firstly, since the cross-sectional design was used, causality relationship for significant variables could not be proven. Secondly, the model offers group predictions in the form of OR. Individual relative risks (RR) could not be calculated as the study design was not longitudinal follow-up. Thirdly, although regression sample size is an issue that is not agreed upon, however, it is relatively small though fulfilling rule of ten.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusion and recommendations</title><p id="Par34">Breast cancer constitutes a real problem in Sudan. Early onset, late presentation, and limited resources are the characteristics unique to our national context of BC. This triad could be better dealt with by inventing a prediction tool. SUDAN considers risk factors in women of different ages and ranks them accordingly. This makes them aware of their odds and subsequently improves early detection. Cost effectiveness will be enhanced further by recommending screening measures for high-risk individuals. Our model showed good calibration and excellent discriminatory power.</p><p id="Par35">Factors influence the role of family history and the prevalent BRCA1/2 predisposition are results of the high rates of consanguineous marriage. However, further genetic studies on the penetrance of BRCA1/2 and predisposition to other mutant genes should be considered. Utilization of purposeful selection method is advisable particularly when sample size used is relatively small. The authors support previous recommendations on establishing a national registry for cancer in Sudan. This will offer a potential data source for externally validating this model and developing it further to better fit Sudanese women.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>BC</term><def><p id="Par5">breast cancer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KoBCRAT</term><def><p id="Par6">Korean Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>O/E ratios</term><def><p id="Par7">observed/expected ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p id="Par8">odd ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RR</term><def><p id="Par9">risk ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SUDAN-CA Breast</term><def><p id="Par10">Statistical Utility to Determine Affinity of Neoplasm (SUDAN Model)</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>AS conceptualized and designed the study, analyzed and interpreted data, and drafted the manuscript. AY helped with statistical interpretation. DA, MA, AY, and MN revised the draft. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par36">The authors would like to thank Prof. Mustafa Numairi, Professor of Biostatistics, Faculty of Medicine, Neelain University, for his endless scientific contributions.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par37">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par38">Authors will keep data as they are working on it to develop an application software.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par39">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par40">None received.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par41">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pisani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global cancer statistics, 2002</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2005</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/canjclin.55.2.74</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15761078?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15761078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer risk-assessment models</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/bcr1750</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17888188?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17888188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Deffenbaugh</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of individuals with germline mutations in BRCA1 and BRCA2: analysis of 10,000 individuals</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1480</fpage><lpage>1490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2002.20.6.1480</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11896095?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11896095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellcross</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Approaches to applying breast cancer risk prediction models in clinical practice</article-title><source>Comm Oncol</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1548-5315(11)70263-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Huffman</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic risk assessment and BRCA mutation testing for breast and ovarian cancer susceptibility: systematic evidence review for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>143</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-143-5-200509060-00012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16144895?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16144895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saslow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Boetes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>American Cancer Society guidelines for breast screening with MRI as an ad- junct to mammography</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2007</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/canjclin.57.2.75</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17392385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17392385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>US Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF)</collab></person-group><article-title>Genetic Risk Assessment and BRCA Mutation Testing for Breast and Ovarian Cancer Susceptibility</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-143-5-200509060-00011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16144894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickerham</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tamoxifen for prevention of breast cancer: report of the National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project P-1 study</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1998</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1371</fpage><lpage>1388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/90.18.1371</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9747868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9747868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gail</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing breast cancer risk assessment models</article-title><source>JNCI</source><year>2010</year><volume>102</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djq141</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20427429?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20427429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedenson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing and managing breast cancer risk: clinical tools for advising patients</article-title><source>Med Gen Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashok</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanal</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study on risk factors of breast cancer among patients attending the tertiary care hospital, Udupi district</article-title><source>Indian J Community Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0970-0218.112440</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23878422?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23878422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laious</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutron-Ruault</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Clavel-Chapelon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Romieu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbohydrate intake, glycemic index, glycemic load, and risk of postmenopausal breast cancer in a prospective study of French women</article-title><source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2008</year><volume>87</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1384</fpage><lpage>1391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumitrescu</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotarla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding breast cancer risk-where do we stand in 2005?</article-title><source>J Cell Mol Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1582-4934.2005.tb00350.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15784178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15784178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Althuis</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fergenbaum</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Closas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinton</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Madigan</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etiology of hormone receptor&#x02014;defined breast cancer: a systematic review of the literature</article-title><source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1558</fpage><lpage>1568</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15466970?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsakountakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanidas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stathopoulos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kafousi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anogiannaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgoulias</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsiftsis</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation of breast cancer risk factors with HER-2/neu protein overexpression according to menopausal and estrogen receptor status</article-title><source>BMC Women&#x02019;s Health</source><year>2005</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6874-5-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15694000?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15694000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fadl Elmoula</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farag Alla</surname><given-names>HEH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association of ki67 proliferation marker with estrogen, progesterone and HER2 markers among Sudanese females with breast cancer</article-title><source>J Biomed Pharmaceut Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuthapisith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Permsapaya</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Warnnissorn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Akewanlop</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirivatanauksorn</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Osoth</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer subtypes identified by the ER, PR and HER-2 status in Thai women</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7314/APJCP.2012.13.2.459</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22524806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22524806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Telli</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurian</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Keegan</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtensztajn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asian ethnicity and breast cancer subtypes: a study from the California Cancer Registry</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2011</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-010-1173-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20957431?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20957431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiechmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stempel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacks</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presenting features of breast cancer differ by molecular subtype</article-title><source>Ann Surg Oncol</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2705</fpage><lpage>2710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-009-0606-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19593632?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19593632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hormone receptor expression in invasive breast cancer among Korean women and comparison of 3 antiestrogen receptor antibodies: a multi-institutional retrospective study using tissue microarrays</article-title><source>Am J Surg Pathol</source><year>2012</year><volume>36</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1817</fpage><lpage>1825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PAS.0b013e318267b012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23154769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23154769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elnour</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elderdery</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>ElbietAbdelaal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhassan</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hady</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BRCA 1 &#x00026; 2 mutations in Sudanese secondary school girls with known breast cancer in their families</article-title><source>Int J Health Sci (Qassim)</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12816/0005974</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23267305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awadelkarim</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Aceto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Veschi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhaj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamedani</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltayeb</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abuidris</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Dioacchino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Battista</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Verginelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Elwali</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariani-Costantini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BRCA1 and BRCA2 status in a Central Sudanese series of breast cancer patients: interactions with genetic, ethnic and reproductive factors</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2007</year><volume>102</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-006-9303-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17333343?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17333343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biunno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Aceto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Awadelkarim</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhaj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltayeb</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abuidris</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Elwali</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>De Blasio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rovida</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariani-Costantini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BRCA1 point mutations in premenopausal breast cancer patients from Central Sudan</article-title><source>Fam Cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10689-014-9717-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24729269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24729269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Gazali</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamamy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Arrayad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic disorders in the Arab world</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2006</year><volume>333</volume><issue>7573</issue><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.38982.704931.AE</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17053236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17053236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamad</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inbreeding Effects on Reproductive Outcome in a Sudanese Population</article-title><source>Hum Hered</source><year>1990</year><volume>40</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000153932</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2379925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2379925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosmer</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemeshow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturdivant</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name></person-group><source>Applied logistic regression</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Inc.</publisher-name><fpage>177</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meads</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of breast cancer incidence risk prediction models with meta-analysis of their performance</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2012</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-011-1818-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22037780?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22037780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Korean risk assessment model for breast cancer risk prediction</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e76736</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076736</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24204664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24204664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gail</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Twenty-five Years of Breast Cancer Risk Models and Their Applications</article-title><source>JNCI J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2015</year><volume>107</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djv042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amir</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shenton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalloo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boggis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation of breast cancer risk assessment packages in the family history evaluation and screening programme</article-title><source>J Med Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jmg.40.11.807</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14627668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14627668</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>