<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6206275</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.01536</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Contributions of Three Starch Branching Enzyme Isozymes to the Fine Structure of Amylopectin in Rice Endosperm</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>Takayuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>Mizuho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Yasunori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/465810/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Faculty of Bioresource Sciences, Akita Prefectural University</institution>, <addr-line>Akita</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Akita Natural Science Laboratory</institution>, <addr-line>Akita</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Miyako Kusano, University of Tsukuba, Japan</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Yan Lu, Western Michigan University, United States; Futoshi Taura, University of Toyama, Japan</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Yasunori Nakamura, <email>nakayn@silver.plala.or.jp</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>&#x02020;Present address: Takayuki Sawada, TDK Corporation, Akita, Japan</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Metabolism and Chemodiversity, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1536</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Sawada, Itoh and Nakamura.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sawada, Itoh and Nakamura</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Three starch branching enzyme (BE) isozymes, BEI, BEIIa, and BEIIb, are involved in starch biosynthesis in rice endosperm. Past <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have suggested that each BE isozyme plays a distinct role in forming the fine structure of amylopectin. To elucidate more details of their roles, we prepared DNA constructs in which all the possible combinations of the expressions of these three isozymes were suppressed in developing rice endosperm. Analysis of the chain-length distributions of amylopectin produced under these various conditions confirmed the contributions of the individual BE isozymes to the fine structure of amylopectin in rice endosperm. Among these isozymes, the impact of loss of BEIIb activity on amylopectin fine structure was most remarkable and indicated that it plays a specific role in the synthesis of short chains with a 6&#x02013;13 degree of polymerization (DP). The contribution of BEI to the amylopectin synthesis was unclear when only BEI activity was reduced. It was clear, however, when both BEI and BEIIb activities were substantially inhibited. The DP11-22 intermediate chains were markedly reduced in the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line compared with the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line, indicating that BEI plays a distinct role in the synthesis of these intermediate chains. Although no substantial change in amylopectin chain profile was detected in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic> line, the role of BEIIa could be deciphered by analyzing amylopectin fine structure from the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line in comparison to that from &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line. This strongly suggests that BEIIa compensates for the role of BEI, rather than that of BEIIb, by forming intermediate chains of DP11-22. In addition, the new possibility that BEIIa is involved in the formation of starch granules in rice endosperm was suggested because the onset temperature for gelatinization of starch granules in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line was significantly higher than that in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line. In summary, the present study highlights the distinct roles of BEI, BEIIa, and BEIIb in the synthesis of amylopectin in developing rice endosperm.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>amylopectin</kwd><kwd>chain-length distribution</kwd><kwd>endosperm</kwd><kwd>rice</kwd><kwd>starch</kwd><kwd>starch biosynthesis</kwd><kwd>starch branching enzyme</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Akita Prefectural University<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100007574</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="48"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Starch branching enzyme (BE) is the only enzyme capable of forming the branch linkages in amylopectin, a major starch component, that usually comprises 65&#x02013;85% of starch. BEs in higher plants belong to glycoside hydrolase family 13 (GH13) in the Carbohydrate-Active Enzymes Database (CAZy; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Stam et al., 2006</xref>), and are further classified into two types: BEI and BEII (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Boyer and Preiss, 1978</xref>; also see the review by <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Preiss and Levi, 1980</xref>). In addition, cereals contain BEIIa- and BEIIb-type isozymes, the latter being specifically expressed in their endosperms. The functional properties of BEI, BEIIa, and BEIIb were at first extensively studied using maize plants, mainly by Preiss and his colleagues. They showed that BEI plays a role in the formation of the intermediate and long chains of amylopectin whereas BEIIa and BEIIb preferentially form its short chains in maize endosperm (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Guan and Preiss, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Takeda et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 1997</xref>). Later, by using high-performance anion-exchange chromatography- pulsed amperometric detection (HPAEC-PAD) or fluorophore-assisted carbohydrate electrophoresis (FACE), the contribution of each BE isozyme to the fine structure of amylopectin was analyzed by precisely measuring the chain-length distribution of amylopectin formed in mutants and transformants in which the activities of BE isozymes were singly or multiply modified (see the review by <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Tetlow and Emes, 2017</xref>). In these analyses, the lengths of &#x003b1;-1,4 chains [i.e., their degree of polymerization (DP) values] liberated after debranching the &#x003b1;-1,6 glucosidic linkages (branches) of amylopectin with isoamylase (ISA) were measured by the FACE method. Chain-distribution analysis of glucans formed by <italic>in vitro</italic> BE enzymatic reactions also confirmed the chain-length specificity of each isozyme and characterized its enzymatic properties, such as substrate specificity toward branched and linear glucans and malto-oligosaccharides (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Sawada et al., 2014</xref>; also see the review by <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2015</xref>).</p><p>The roles of individual BE isozymes in starch biosynthesis in rice endosperm have been examined by many groups worldwide using mutants and transformants prepared from both <italic>japonica</italic>-type and <italic>indica</italic>-type rice cultivars. It has been reported that although the relative activities of BEI, BEIIa, and BEIIb in both cultivars are reported approximately 60&#x02013;80%, 10&#x02013;20%, and 10&#x02013;20%, respectively (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Yamanouchi and Nakamura, 1992</xref>), the impacts of the three BE isozymes on the starch synthesis and structure greatly differ among them (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2002</xref>). Mutations in the <italic>BEIIb</italic> gene resulted in the <italic>amylose-extender</italic> (<italic>ae</italic>) phenotype of the caryopses, which had a floury appearance and reduced weight (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Mizuno et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Nishi et al., 2001</xref>). The <italic>ae</italic> mutant starch contained modified amylopectin with fewer short chains of with DP &#x02264; 17 (mostly A chains) and more long B chains (see Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>) and an elevated amylose content, which caused changes to the starch granular structure and physicochemical properties, such as a switch in X-ray diffraction pattern from A-type to B-type and a higher resistance to thermal gelatinization (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Nishi et al., 2001</xref>). These results are consistent with those of <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Butardo et al. (2011)</xref>, who showed that RNA silencing of <italic>BEIIb</italic> expression in rice kernels led to the <italic>ae</italic> phenotypes similar to those described above. Elimination of BEI activity led to only slight phenotypic changes in amylopectin structure, such as the elevation of short chains and a reduction in long B chains, while no significant change in the appearance and weight of the caryopsis were found (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Satoh et al., 2003</xref>). No detectable alterations in the amylopectin chain profile and caryopsis phenotypes were detected when the <italic>BEIIa</italic> gene was defective (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2002</xref>). These results are basically consistent with the view proposed by the Preiss&#x02019; group that BEI and BEIIb play crucial roles in the formation of short and long chains of amylopectin in maize endosperm (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Guan and Preiss, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Takeda et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>Biochemical, molecular biological, and genetic approaches using additional mutants or transformants in which two or three BE isozymes are simultaneously eliminated would be very useful in precisely defining the contributions of the three BE isozymes to amylopectin biosynthesis. Wei and his group have extensively studied the starch phenotypes of mainly the <italic>be1</italic>/<italic>be2b</italic> mutants of both <italic>japonica</italic>- and <italic>indica</italic>-type rice lines, thereby revealing the roles of both BEs in amylopectin fine structure, amylose content, and starch structure, and starch functional properties including resistance to enzyme-catalyzed hydrolysis (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Man et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>; see also the review by <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). However, the contribution of BEIIa in starch biosynthesis is still uncertain, perhaps because its role overlaps that of BEIIb and/or BEI to large extent. In this study, we prepared transformed lines in which all the possible combinations of BE isozymes were eliminated by RNAi technology, namely the seven lines: &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic>, and &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic>. By comparing the starch phenotypes among these lines, with a particular emphasis on precisely analyzing amylopectin chain-length distributions by the FACE method (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Shea et al., 1998</xref>), the contributions of the three BE isozymes to amylopectin biosynthesis in rice endosperm have been clarified, and in particular the role of BEIIa on the amylopectin structure and the starch gelatinization properties.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Preparation of cDNA Fragments for Rice BE Isozymes</title><p>The cDNA fragments of rice BEI, BEIIa, and BEIIb used for preparation of RNAi constructs were generated by PCR using cDNA prepared from mRNA of developing seeds of the <italic>japonica</italic>-type rice cultivar Kinmaze, as described previously (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura et al., 2005</xref>). The forward and reverse primers used were: BEI, 5&#x02032;- ggggacaagtttgtacaaaaaagcaggctATGCTGTGTCTCACCTCCTCTTCCTCCTC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;- ggggaccactttgtacaagaaagctgggtATATATAGGAAGGTGGTCGACCTCCTCCAC-3&#x02032;; BEIIa, 5&#x02032;- ggggacaagtttgtacaaaaaagcaggctGCCGTCGGTGCTCTTCAGGAGGAAGGACTCC -3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;- ggggaccactttgtacaagaaagctgggtTGCCACTGCTGGAATCTCTTCCTCCTCCTC -3&#x02032;; BEIIb, 5&#x02032;- ggggacaagtttgtacaaaaaagcaggctACGGGATGCCGGTTTCAGCAGGTTCAGACG -3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;- ggggaccactttgtacaagaaagctgggtCTGTTGGTGGGACAACTCGTGGTTTCTGC -3&#x02032; (Note that small and large letters represent tags and coding regions of <italic>BE</italic> genes, respectively). The PCR reaction products were separated by agarose gel (1.5% agarose, w/v) electrophoresis and the corresponding bands were excised from the gels.</p><p>For the preparation of cDNA fragments of <italic>BEI</italic> plus <italic>BEIIa</italic> cDNA by PCR, the forward primer used for preparation of the BEI cDNA (see above), the reverse primer used for preparation of the BEIIa cDNA (see above) and a BEI-BEIIa connection primer (5&#x02032;- TTGTGGAGGAGGTCGACCACCTTCCTATATATgccgtcggtgctcttcaggaggaaggac-3&#x02032;) were used. The cDNA fragments of <italic>BEI</italic> and <italic>BEIIa</italic> that were used for the PCR were prepared using 5&#x02032;-ATGCTGTGTCTCACCTCCTCTTCCTCCTC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;- ATATATAGGAAGGTGGTCGACCTCCTCCAC-3&#x02032;, and 5&#x02032;-GCCGTCGGTGCTCTTCAGGAGGAAGGACTCC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-TGCCACTGCTGGAATCTCTTCCTCCTCCTC-3&#x02032;, respectively. PCR reaction products were separated by agarose gel (1.5% agarose, w/v) electrophoresis and the corresponding bands were excised from the gel and used for the subsequent reaction.</p><p>For preparation of cDNA fragments of <italic>BEI</italic> and <italic>BEIIb</italic> cDNA by PCR, the forward primer used for preparation of the BEI cDNA (see above), the reverse primer used for preparation of the BEIIb cDNA (see above) and the BEI-BEIIb connection primer (5&#x02032;- GTTGTGGAGGAGGTCGACCACCTTCCTATATATacgggatgccggtttcagcaggttcag-3) were used. The cDNA fragment of <italic>BEI</italic> used for PCR was prepared as above, and that of <italic>BEIIb</italic> was prepared by using 5&#x02032;-ACGGGATGCCGGTTTCAGCAGGTTCAGACG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-CTGTTGGTGGGACAACTCGTGGTTTCTGC-3&#x02032;. PCR reaction products were separated by agarose gel (1.5% agarose, w/v) electrophoresis and the corresponding bands were excised from the gel and used for the subsequent reaction.</p><p>For preparation of cDNA fragments of <italic>BEIIa</italic> and <italic>BEIIb</italic> cDNA by PCR, the forward primer used for preparation of the BEIIa cDNA (see above), the reverse primer used for preparation of the BEIIb cDNA (see above) and the BEIIa-BEIIb connection primer (5&#x02032;- TCTGAACCTGCTGAAACCGGCATCCCGTtgccactgctggaatctcttcctcctcctc-3&#x02032;) were used. The cDNA fragments of <italic>BEIIa</italic> and <italic>BEIIb</italic> that were used for the PCR were prepared. The DNA fragments were purified with an agarose gel, as described above.</p><p>For preparation of cDNA fragments for <italic>BEI</italic>, <italic>BEIIa</italic>, and <italic>BEIIb</italic> cDNA by PCR, the forward primer used for preparation of the BEI cDNA (see above), the reverse primer used for preparation of the BEIIb cDNA (see above) and the BEIIa-BEIIb connection primers (see above) were used. The cDNA fragments of <italic>BEI</italic> plus <italic>BEIIa</italic> and <italic>BEIIb</italic> used as templates for the PCR were prepared as above, and DNA fragments were purified from agarose gels, as described above.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of DNA Constructs for Silencing the Expression of Rice <italic>BE Isozyme</italic> Genes</title><p>The RNAi constructs were designed by including oligonucleotides for cDNA fragments encoding rice BEI, BEIIa, and BEIIb, respectively, as illustrated in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. The binary vector pINDEX 4 (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ouwerkerk et al., 2001</xref>) was used as the basic plasmid DNA for the RNAi construct. The rice polyubiquitin 2 promoter (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2000</xref>), Gateway system fragments A and B, and the pdk intron fragment were prepared using the pHELLSGATE 8 vector (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Helliwell et al., 2002</xref>; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). For preparation of the rice polyubiquitin 2 promoter fragment by PCR, 5&#x02032;-atgtctagaCTGCAGAAATGCAAATTTCATAAAAC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-atgtctagaCTCGAGGGTGATAGTCTTGCCGGTC-3&#x02032; were used as forward and reverse primers, respectively. An <italic>Xba</italic>I site was added to both ends of the fragment during this PCR. The fragment was then prepared by restriction enzyme treatment with <italic>Xba</italic>I, while the pHELLSGATE 8 vector was treated with <italic>Xba</italic>I and <italic>Xho</italic>I to prepare three fragments; the Gateway system fragments A and B and pdk intron fragment (<italic>Xba</italic>I&#x02013;<italic>Xho</italic>I). These four fragments were introduced into the binary vector pINDEX 4, which had been digested with <italic>Xba</italic>I and <italic>Xho</italic>I. The final plasmid construct was designated as pCRUBQ-SV. Seven kinds of cDNA fragments for BEs were then inserted into the pCRUBQ-SV plasmid using the Gateway system (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Katzen, 2007</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Representation of DNA constructs used for RNAi-suppression of <italic>BEI</italic>, <italic>BEIIa</italic>, and <italic>BEIIb</italic> gene expression in rice endosperm (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Helliwell et al., 2002</xref>). <bold>(A)</bold> The rice polyubiquitin 2 promoter (rice Pub2 promoter) was used and attR1 and attR2 are recombination recognition sites of the target gene. The ccdB protein selectively inhibits <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DNA topoisomerase type II and inhibits the growth of most <italic>E. coli</italic> strains such as OmniMAX<sup>TM</sup> 2-T1R, DH5&#x003b1;<sup>TM</sup>, TOP10. This was used for selection for recombination of the target gene. The pdk intron was used to construct the hairpin loop RNA of the RNAi. The CaMV 35S-driven hygromycin resistance gene (hpt intron) was used for selection of transgenic plants. <bold>(B)</bold> The DNA fragments for the target <italic>BE</italic> genes used for the seven different RNAi.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01536-g001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Generation and Selection of Transgenic Plants</title><p>A total of seven different DNA constructs were used to transform competent <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> EHA105 cells (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Hood et al., 1993</xref>). Transformants were selected on LB-agar plates containing 50 &#x003bc;g/ml kanamycin.</p><p>Calli of <italic>japonica</italic>-type rice cultivar Kinmaze were generated from sterile seeds and transformed with recombinant <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> EHA105 carrying the plasmid pCRUB2-SV/&#x00394;BEs. Selection of transformants and callus regeneration were as described previously (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Sawada et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>For each construct, a total of about 30 independent T<sub>0</sub> progeny lines were grown in a greenhouse which was controlled at 30&#x000b0;C and 60% relative humidity. One to three developing T<sub>1</sub> seeds were randomly chosen. Crude enzyme extracts were prepared from each kernel and separated by native polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) to detect BE activities (see below). Six to nine lines were then selected for every construct, in which BE activities were judged as having been greatly inhibited as expected, and seeds from these lines were further analyzed.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of Enzyme Extracts and Native-PAGE of BE Isozymes From Developing Rice Endosperm</title><p>A single developing kernel at the mid-milking stage was homogenized using a plastic pestle in a microtube on ice in 100 &#x003bc;l of 50 mM imidazole-HCl (pH 7.4), 8 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, and 12.5% (v/v) glycerol. The homogenate was centrifuged at 10,000 <italic>g</italic> at 4&#x000b0;C for 20 min, and the supernatant was used as the crude enzyme extract. Ten &#x003bc;l of each extract was applied onto a native-polyacrylamide gel and native PAGE/staining of BE isozyme activity was performed as described previously (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Yamanouchi and Nakamura, 1992</xref>). Native PAGE was performed on a slab gel prepared of 7.5% (w/v) resolving gel with 3.3% (w/v) stacking gel using a modified version of the method described by <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Davis (1964)</xref>. Electrophoresis was carried out at 4&#x000b0;C at a constant current of 20 mA. After electrophoresis, the gel was rinsed with 20 ml of a solution of 50 mM HEPES-NaOH buffer (pH 7.4) containing 20% (v/v) glycerol for 2&#x02013;3 min on ice and then incubated for 5&#x02013;6 h at 30&#x000b0;C in 20 ml of the BE reaction mixture, which consisted of 50 mM HEPES-NaOH buffer (pH 7.4), 50 mM glucose 1-phosphate, 2.5 mM AMP, 10% (v/v) glycerol, and rabbit muscle phosphorylase a (Pho-a; about 60 units; Sigma, St. Louis, MO, United States). The gel was then placed in a solution of 0.1% (w/v) I<sub>2</sub> and 1% (w/v) KI. BE activity bands were detected by their reddish purple color due to the formation of branched glucans by BE and Pho-a or the plastidial phosphorylase (Pho1). Although BEIIb and Pho1 bands overlapped, while Pho1 activity itself was visualized as a blue band from the presence of linear glucans when BEIIb activity was absent, as described previously (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Yamanouchi and Nakamura, 1992</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Observation of Rice Kernel Morphology</title><p>Cross-sections were prepared from the middle part of mature caryopses using a razor blade and images were captured with a digital camera under suitable lighting.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurements of Mature Kernel Weights</title><p>The weight of a mature kernels was determined as the average value of 15 arbitrarily chosen mature caryopses.</p></sec><sec><title>Thermal Properties of Starch Granules</title><p>Thermal properties of starch granules were analyzed using a differential scanning calorimeter (DSC), as described previously (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Fujita et al., 2003</xref>). For the DSC measurement of thermal properties of endosperm starch, rice powder prepared from a half portion of each kernel by de-hulling, crushing with pliers, and hand-homogenization using a mortar and pestle. The weighed starch (about 3 mg) was placed in an aluminum sample cup (SSC000C009; Seiko Instrument, Tokyo, Japan), mixed with 9 &#x003bc;l of distilled water and sealed. Gelatinization properties of the starch were analyzed by DSC-6100 (Seiko Instrument, Tokyo, Japan). The heating rate was 3&#x000b0;C per min in a temperature range of 5&#x02013;90&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of Chain-Length Distribution of Amylopectin</title><p>The chain-length distribution of amylopectin was determined by the FACE method (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Shea et al., 1998</xref>), as described by <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura et al. (2002)</xref>. Starch samples from the other half of the kernel remaining after analysis of starch thermal properties by DSC, as described above, were homogenized in a mortar and pestle. The powder was suspended in 5 ml of methanol and heated in a boiling water bath for 10 min. The suspension was centrifuged at 2,000 <italic>g</italic> for 5 min, and the precipitate was washed twice with 5 ml of 90% (v/v) methanol and centrifuged again at 2,000 <italic>g</italic> for 5 min. The supernatant was removed and the precipitate was dried in air. The rice powder (1 mg) was suspended in 1 ml of distilled water and heated in a boiling water bath for 5 min to gelatinize starch. An aliquot (100 &#x003bc;l) was placed into a microtube and added by 4 &#x003bc;l of 100% acetic acid, 4 &#x003bc;l of 600 mM Na-acetate buffer (pH 4.4), and 91 &#x003bc;l of distilled water. To debranch the amylopectin, 1 &#x003bc;l of a <italic>Pseudomonas amyloderamosa</italic> ISA solution (PaISA; about 59 units; Hayashibara Biochemical Laboratories, Inc., Okayama, Japan) was added and the sample was incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 3 h. The debranched sample was heated in a boiling water bath for 5 min to stop the enzymatic reaction. The solution was then deionized with ion exchange resin [15 mg; AG 501-X8(D) Resin; Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc.] for 30 min by rotating the microtube at 10 rpm at room temperature. Fluorescence labeling of &#x003b1;-1,4-glucan chains at their reducing ends with 8-amino-1,3,6-pyrenetrisulfonic acid (APTS) was performed using an APTS Labeling Dye kit according to the instruction manual (SCIEX; Tokyo, Japan). The APTS-labeled &#x003b1;-1,4-glucans were analyzed using a capillary electrophoresis system equipped with a laser-induced fluorescence detector (P/ACE MDQ Carbohydrate System; Beckman Instruments/AB SCIEX, Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>DNA Construct for Suppression of the <italic>BE Isozyme</italic> Gene Expression</title><p>In the present investigation, gene expression of BEI, BEIIa, and/or BEIIb was selectively suppressed by using RNAi constructs containing specific regions of cDNA coding for BE isozymes. The lengths of regions used for BEI, BEIIa, and BEIIb cDNA were 237 bp (coding region, 1&#x02013;237; Accession number, <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="D10752">D10752</ext-link>), 220 bp (115&#x02013;324; AB023498), and 183 bp (242&#x02013;424; D16201), respectively.</p><p>Out of about 30 lines regenerated from each RNAi construct, 6&#x02013;9 in which enzyme activities were suppressed as assessed by zymogram (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) were selected: #1, 2, 8, 12, 14, 19, and 25 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic> lines; #2, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, and 14 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic> lines; #2, 5, 6, 8, 12, 13, 15, and 27 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> lines; #3, 11, 14, 17, 27, and 29 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa</italic> lines; #2, 5, 6, 9, 11, 13, 16, 22, and 27 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> lines; #4, 6, 7, 11, 12, and 27 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> lines; and #4, 7, 9, 12, 24, and 28 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> lines. Since T<sub>1</sub> seeds were unable to germinate, biochemical analyses were performed using T<sub>1</sub> seeds generated from one of the representative T<sub>0</sub> progeny lines exhibiting the most similar kernel morphology and starch-related phenotypes among them in each construct.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Native-PAGE/activity staining of BEs in crude enzyme extracts from developing kernels of the transformed lines, wild-type (cv. Kinmaze), and the <italic>be2b</italic> mutant line, EM10. The developing T<sub>1</sub> kernels of transformed lines from which the enzyme extracts were prepared are (from left to right): #2 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic>; #8 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic>; #6 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic>; #11 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa</italic>; #5 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic>; #11 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic>; and #9 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic>. Note that in the BEIIb suppression lines, the BEIIb-corresponding bands exhibited a blue color, which was due to the activity of plastidial phosphorylase 1 (Pho1) only present in rice endosperm, while in the other lines, these bands exhibited dark reddish purple colors, indicating the presence of branched glucans formed by BEIIb and Pho-a as well as Pho1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01536-g002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>BE Isozyme Activity Levels in Transformed Lines</title><p>To examine to what extent BE isozyme activities were suppressed in the transformed lines by the RNAi constructs, the crude enzyme extracts prepared from developing kernels were separated by native PAGE to determine the activities of BEI, BEIIa, and BEIIb by an activity-staining method. BEIIb activity band is known to overlap with Pho1 band on the native PAGE (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Yamanouchi and Nakamura, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Nishi et al., 2001</xref>). When BEIIb activity is high, these bands are a reddish purple color due to the formation of branched glucans. However, when BEIIb activity is lost, the band color turns blue because only linear glucans are synthesized by Pho1 in the presence of glucose 1-phosphate (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Yamanouchi and Nakamura, 1992</xref>). Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> shows that all the BE activities were greatly reduced in endosperms from the representative lines (#2 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic> line; #8 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic> line; #6 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line; #11 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa</italic> line; #5 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line; #11 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line; and #9 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line). Although a small amount of BEI activity remained in the &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic>-related transformants, almost all of BEIIa activity was lost in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic>-related transformants. BEIIb activity was largely suppressed in &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic>-related transformants. Together, these results show that all the RNAi constructs, for the most part, successfully silenced the appropriate <italic>BE</italic> genes, as they were designed to.</p></sec><sec><title>Transformed Line Kernel Morphology</title><p>Three lines each for every construct were chosen from those having kernels of the consistent size and morphology, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Light micrographs of cross-sections of mature kernels from the transformants, their host wild-type <italic>japonica</italic> cultivar Kinmaze, and a <italic>be2b</italic> mutant line, EM10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01536-g003"/></fig><p>Wild-type cultivars of <italic>japonica</italic>-type rice have the plump seeds with translucent kernels, whereas some mutants, such as <italic>ae</italic> mutant, have a floury kernel phenotype (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Nishi et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2018</xref>). The &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic>, and &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa</italic> lines had plump translucent kernels, and their appearances were the same as the wild-type (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> kernels had a floury kernel phenotype that were not shriveled, although their size was somewhat smaller than the wild-type (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). This phenotype was the same that of the <italic>ae</italic> mutant line, EM10 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). However, most of kernels from the double and triple &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic>-related transformants such as &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb/BEIIa</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb/BEIIa</italic>, and &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb/BEIIa/BEI</italic> were severely shrunken and had a floury phenotype (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p><p>One representative line was chosen from the three selected T<sub>0</sub> progeny lines: #2 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic>; #8 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic>; #6 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic>; #11 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa</italic>; #5 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic>; #11 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic>; and #9 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic>. A single T<sub>1</sub> kernel was chosen from these lines, cut in half, and each half used for analysis of starch thermal properties or amylopectin chain-length distribution so that the relationship between amylopectin fine structure and thermal properties of starch granules could be assessed.</p></sec><sec><title>Mature Kernel Weights of Transformed Lines</title><p>The <italic>be2b</italic> mutant of <italic>japonica</italic>-type rice has a reduced kernel weight (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Nishi et al., 2001</xref>), while that of the <italic>be1</italic> mutant is similar to wild-type (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Satoh et al., 2003</xref>). The kernel weights of the &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic> or the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic> transformant was similar or slightly lower than wild-type (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). However, the kernel weight of the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line was significantly lower than that of wild-type, and similar to a <italic>be2b</italic> mutant line EM10 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). Although kernel weight was unaffected by silencing of the <italic>BEIIa</italic> or <italic>BEI</italic> gene, it was significantly lower in the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa</italic> line than that in the &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic> or &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic> line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). The kernel weight of the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line was significantly lower than that of the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). These results show that BEIIa plays a role in amylopectin biosynthesis in the absence of BEI or BEIIb. Similarly, even though the &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic> line had the same kernel weight as the wild-type, the kernel weight of the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line was markedly decreased and significantly lower than that of the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). These results indicate that the BEI&#x02019;s role in amylopectin synthesis is more important than that of BEIIa, particularly when BEIIb activity is very low or missing. The kernel weight of the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line was similar to the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line and the lowest among all of the suppression lines (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). These results suggest that the residual activities of all the three BE isozymes were too low to support starch biosynthesis in rice endosperm, and that any BE can support synthetic activity, at least to some extent, especially when any of the other isozymes are defective.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>The average weight of a single kernel in each transformed line, the host wild-type <italic>japonica</italic> cultivar Kinmaze, or a <italic>be2b</italic> mutant line, EM10. Values are the averages measured from 15 arbitrarily chosen mature caryopses and standard deviations are presented. The lines used were the same as those in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>. Values indicated by the same letter above the column are not significantly different as calculated by the Tukey&#x02013;Kramer method (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01536-g004"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Chain-Length Distribution of Amylopectin of Transformed Line Kernels</title><p>To examine the contribution of each BE isozyme to the fine structure of amylopectin, we determined the chain-length distribution of amylopectin after debranching the insoluble glucans with PaISA followed by labeling with APTS at their non-reducing ends, according to the FACE method (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Shea et al., 1998</xref>).</p><p>The chain profiles of amylopectin produced in endosperm of the &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic> or &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic> line was very similar to that from wild-type (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), suggesting that the contributions of BEI and BEIIa to amylopectin fine structure are unspecific and that, in the absence of either isozyme, the remaining BE isozymes can complement their functions. Our previous study indicated that amylopectin in the <italic>be1</italic> mutant contains more DP &#x02264; 10 chains and fewer DP &#x02265; 37 and DP12-21 chains, although the extents of these changes are much less significant compared with those in the <italic>be2b</italic> mutant (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Nishi et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Satoh et al., 2003</xref>). The &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic> line still contained a small amount of BEI activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), suggesting that the apparent discrepancy between the <italic>be1</italic> mutant and the &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic> line was due to the difference in the residual BEI activity level between them; i.e., none or extremely low in the mutant versus very low but still at a functional level in the transformant. In contrast, amylopectin in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line had fewer short chains of DP &#x02264; 13 with a peak at DP9 and 10 and more intermediate B1 and long B2-3 chains than in the wild-type; these changes were consistent with those in the <italic>be2b</italic> (<italic>ae</italic>) mutant (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and Supplementary Figures <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>) (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Nishi et al., 2001</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Chain-length distribution of amylopectin in mature endosperm from the rice transformants, their host cultivar Kinmaze, or the <italic>be2b</italic> mutant line, EM10. Values are the averages calculated from three replicate measurements. Standard deviations were too small to be shown in the figure. The mature T<sub>1</sub> kernels of transformed lines from which starches were prepared are (from left to right): #2 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic>; #8 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic>; #6 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic>; #11 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa</italic>; #5 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic>; #11 for &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic>; and #9 for &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01536-g005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p>Difference in chain-length distributions of amylopectin from each transformant compared to &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic>, as shown in figures <bold>(A&#x02013;C)</bold>. Data are the same as those shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01536-g006"/></fig><p>When the expression of both <italic>BEI</italic> and <italic>BEIIb</italic> genes was simultaneously suppressed, as in the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line, the crosspoint of the difference graph shifted from DP13/14 in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line to DP18/19 in the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). In addition, long chains with DP &#x02265; 30 were significantly higher in the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line compared to &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic>. This strongly suggests that BEI plays an important role in the synthesis of a wide range of longer A chains with DP up to 14&#x02013;18 and B chain external segments with chain-lengths up to DP18, while BEIIb is only involved in the synthesis of short A chains and short B chain external segments with DP &#x02264; 13. On the other hand, the chain-length distribution pattern of amylopectin in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line was almost the same as in &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>), indicating that BEIIa cannot compensate for the role of BEIIb in amylopectin synthesis. Interestingly, however, amylopectin in the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line had fewer chains of DP6-18 and more chains of DP &#x02265; 30 compared with &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). One simple explanation of these results is that BEIIa can complement, at least to some extent, the role of BEI rather than that of BEIIb.</p></sec><sec><title>Thermal Properties of Starch in Transformed Line Kernels</title><p>The thermal properties of starch granules in various BE transformants were compared with those in wild-type or the <italic>ae</italic> (<italic>be2b</italic>) mutant using DSC (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). As reported previously (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Nishi et al., 2001</xref>), the <italic>be2b</italic> mutation caused starch granules to be highly resistant to thermal gelatinization (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In accordance with this result, the starch granules in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line had markedly higher DSC parameters compared with wild-type starch granules (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). It is interesting that the DSC parameters of the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic> starch granules were slightly higher than those of wild-type (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), although the chain-length distribution of amylopectin in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic> line was similar to that in the wild-type, as described above (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). It is also notable that the starch granules were much more resistant to thermal gelatinization when expression of both <italic>BEIIa</italic> and <italic>BEIIb</italic> genes was suppressed (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In contrast, the thermal properties of starch granules were unchanged by suppression of the <italic>BEI</italic> gene expression. Together, these results suggest that BEIIa plays some role in the formation of starch granule structure despite its direct contribution to chain-length distribution being seemingly low.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Thermal properties of native starches from mature kernels of &#x00394;<italic>BE</italic>-transformed lines, their host wild-type <italic>japonica</italic> cultivar Kinmaze, and a <italic>be2b</italic> mutant line EM10.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Line</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To (&#x000b0;C)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tp (&#x000b0;C)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tc (&#x000b0;C)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;H (J/g)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kinmaze</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.7 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.3 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.0 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 &#x000b1; 1.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>be2b</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.1 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.6 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.8 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 &#x000b1; 0.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>BEI</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.7 &#x000b1; 1.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.3 &#x000b1; 1.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.6 &#x000b1; 2.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 &#x000b1; 1.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>BEIIa</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.2 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.6 &#x000b1; 1.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 &#x000b1; 1.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.1 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.7 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.1 &#x000b1; 1.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 &#x000b1; 1.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.2 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.4 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.8 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 &#x000b1; 0.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">nd</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.0 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.3 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.1 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 &#x000b1; 0.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">nd</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>T<sub>0</sub>, Tp, Tc, and &#x00394;H are onset, peak, conclusion temperature, and enthalpy change, respectively. Values are the averages calculated from three replicate measurements with standard deviations. nd, not determined. In this study, we focused on the relationship between the chain-length distribution of amylopectin and the thermal properties of starch granules from the same kernel. However, starch contents of the kernels from &#x00394;BEI/BEIIb and &#x00394;BEIIa/BEIIb lines were too low to measure by DSC.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Role of Each BE Isozyme in Amylopectin Biosynthesis</title><p>We have performed a detailed analysis of the changes in the chain-length distribution of amylopectin produced in rice endosperm when the activities of a single or all the possible combinations of the three BE isozymes were inhibited. The pattern of changes largely depended on the BE isozyme(s) that was (were) deficient in the endosperm. To ascertain clearly the contribution of BEI and BEIIa to the amylopectin fine structure, the differences between the chain-length distribution of amylopectin between the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line and the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic>, or &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line was compared (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), because this might clarify the additional effect of the reduction of BEI activity and/or BEIIa activity.</p><p>The contribution of BEI to amylopectin synthesis could be conceived from the difference of the chain-length pattern between the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line and the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). The intermediate DP11-21 chains of amylopectin from the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> line were significantly lower than those from the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line, indicating that BEI plays a distinct role in the synthesis of the intermediate chains. It is interesting to note that intermediate chains of DP13-20 were also slightly reduced in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line compared with the <italic>BEIIb</italic> line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). This suggests that BEIIa plays a part in the synthesis of these chains. The amylopectin from the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line had markedly fewer intermediate chains of DP11-22 than the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>), and the difference in amylopectin chain-length distribution between the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> lines was much larger than that between the &#x00394;<italic>BEI/BEIIb</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>BEIIb</italic> lines (c.f. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref> with Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). These results also support the view that both BEI and BEIIa play an important role in the synthesis of intermediate chains. Thus, a distinct role of BEIIa in amylopectin synthesis in rice endosperm has been assigned for the first time in this study, because it was impossible to determine the contribution of BEIIa to the amylopectin structure in the past since no significant effect of BEIIa on the amylopectin fine structure was observed in the <italic>be2a</italic> mutant (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2002</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Comparison of the Roles of BE Isozymes Among Cereal Endosperms</title><p>There have been numerous studies that have examined the roles of BE isozymes in endosperm of cereals such as maize, rice, wheat, and barley (see the review by <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Tetlow and Emes, 2017</xref>). The impact of the loss of each BE isozyme on endosperm starch structure has been reported to be similar between maize and rice. A deficiency of either BEI or BEIIa results in no detectable or only small changes in endosperm starch phenotypes and kernel morphology in maize and rice (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Blauth et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Satoh et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2004</xref>). In contrast, a number of groups worldwide have reported on the specific impact of BEIIb on the fine structure, starch granule morphology, and starch physicochemical properties in endosperms from maize (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Shi and Seib, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Klucinec and Thompson, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2007</xref>) and rice (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Nishi et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Butardo et al., 2011</xref>; see also reviews by <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2018</xref>).</p><p>It is interesting that the effects of BEII isozyme inhibition on starch structure and properties seem to differ largely among four major crops: maize, rice, wheat, and barley. Regina and her colleagues have revealed that suppression of BEIIa expression greatly affects starch structure, amylose content, and starch physicochemical and functional properties of starch granules in wheat and barley endosperm, and its influences are more severe than the loss of BEIIb activity (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Regina et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The results contrast strikingly with the observation that a single mutation of BEIIa produces no significant effect on starch structure and properties in both maize (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Blauth et al., 2001</xref>) and rice (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2002</xref>) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) endosperm. It is known that BEIIb is present at lower levels in wheat endosperm than that in maize and rice endosperm (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Regina et al., 2005</xref>). On the other hand, the observation that starch structure and properties are largely controlled by varying BEIIb levels under constant BEIIa levels in rice endosperm (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka et al., 2004</xref>) clearly indicates that these changes in starch are caused by a specific role of BEIIb, but not BEIIa, in amylopectin biosynthesis. The molecular mechanism for the discrepancy in the functions of BEIIa and BEIIb found among cereals remains to be elucidated in the future.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In the present study, the contributions of all three BE isozymes, namely BEI, BEIIa, and BEIIb, to amylopectin biosynthesis in rice endosperm were comprehensively examined by analyzing amylopectin chain-length distribution in seven lines in which all the combinations of BE expressions were singly or multiply silenced with RNAi. Thus, the present study could clarify the distinct and overlapping roles of these individual isozymes. Lack of BEIIb led to the most striking changes in starch-related phenotypes in rice endosperm, indicating that this isozyme plays a crucial role in the starch biosynthesis, particularly, in the formation of amylopectin short chains. These results are consistent with <italic>in vivo</italic> studies with BEIIb suppressed lines (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Butardo et al., 2011</xref>), and <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments with purified enzyme, showing that BEIIb forms external short chains of DP7 and 6 (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>A previous study with a rice <italic>be1</italic> mutant suggested that BEI is involved in the synthesis of intermediate amylopectin chains (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Satoh et al., 2003</xref>). However, its role was unclear because the chain-length of amylopectin was only slightly altered by the <italic>be1</italic> mutation. In the present study, the role of BEI could be identified by comparing all the BEI-related transformants (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> distinctly indicates that BEI is involved in the synthesis of intermediate amylopectin chains.</p><p>Up to now, no distinct role of BEIIa in developing rice endosperm has been proposed because no significant change in amylopectin chain-profile was detected in the <italic>be2a</italic> mutant (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura, 2002</xref>), as also seen in the BEIIa-suppressed line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). The present study, however, shows that BEIIa plays a substantial role in starch biosynthesis in rice endosperm. Detailed analysis of the chain-length distribution of amylopectin clearly indicates that BEIIa compensates for role of BEI, rather than BEIIb, by forming intermediate chains (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). The result is rather surprising in terms of amino acid sequence homology among three BE isozymes, because BEIIa is more alike to BEIIb, rather than BEI (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Sawada et al., 2014</xref>). However, the result seems to be consistent with our previous report that the amylopectin chain-profile was only controlled by levels of BEIIb activity when BEIIa levels were constant, and therefore it was unaffected by relative activities of BEIIa and BEIIb (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka et al., 2004</xref>). The additional striking observation in the present study was that loss of BEIIa resulted in an increase in the onset temperature of thermal gelatinization (T<sub>0</sub>), and this effect was more pronounced in the &#x00394;<italic>BEIIa/BEIIb</italic> line (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The results strongly suggest that BEIIa is more significantly involved in the construction of starch granules than previously appreciated.</p><p>In summary, the present investigation provides concrete evidence on the distinct contributions of three BE isozymes to the synthesis of amylopectin fine structure, the formation of starch granules, and starch properties in rice endosperm.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>TS and MI conducted experiments. TS also summarized data and prepared Figures and Table. YN designed the experiments and wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was funded by the Ministry of Education, Sports, Science and Technology [Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research (A), 20248002].</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank Dr. Satoh, Kyushu University, for providing us with the rice <italic>ae</italic> mutant line EM10.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01536/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01536/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Image_1.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Image_2.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><media xlink:href="Image_3.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><media xlink:href="Image_4.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blauth</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klucinec</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiltinan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Identification of Mutator insertional mutations of starch-branching enzyme 1 (sbe1) in <italic>Zea mays</italic> L.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1013335217744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11855730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blauth</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klucinec</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiltinan</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Identification of Mutator insertional mutants of starch-branching enzyme 2a in corn.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>125</volume>
<fpage>1396</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1405</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.125.3.1396</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11244119?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11244119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Multiple forms of (1,4)-&#x003b1;-D-glucosyl transferase from developing <italic>Zea mays</italic> L. kernels.</article-title>
<source><italic>Carbohydr. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>334</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0008-6215(00)84492-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butardo</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gidley</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larroque</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Impact of down-regulation of starch branching enzyme IIb in rice by artificial microRNA- and hairpin RNA-mediated RNA silencing.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>4927</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4941</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err188</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21791436?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21791436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>). <article-title>Disc electrophoresis II. Method and application of human serum proteins.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>121</volume>
<fpage>404</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>427</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.1964.tb14213.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14240539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jane</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Antisense inhibition of isoamylase alters the structure of amylopectin and the physicochemical properties of starch in rice endosperm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>607</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>618</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcg079</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12826626?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12826626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imparl-Radosevich</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Comparing the properties of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> branching enzyme and maize branching enzyme.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</italic></source>
<volume>342</volume>
<fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/abbi.1997.0115</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9185617?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9185617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Differentiation of the properties of the branching isozymes from maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>1269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1273</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.102.4.1269</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12231902?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12231902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helliwell</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varsha</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wielopolska</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>High-throughput vectors for efficient gene silencing in plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Funct. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>1217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/FP02033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hizukuri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Polymodal distribution of the chain lengths of amylopectin, and its significance.</article-title>
<source><italic>Carbohydr. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>147</volume>
<fpage>342</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>347</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0008-6215(00)90643-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelvin</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melchers</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoekema</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>New agrobacterium helper plasmids for gene transfer to plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Transgenic Res.</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>218</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01977351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katzen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Gateway recombinational cloning: a biological operating system.</article-title>
<source><italic>Expert Opin. Drug Discov.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>571</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>589</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/17460441.2.4.571</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23484762?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23484762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klucinec</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Structure of amylopectins from ae-containing maize starches.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cereal Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2016.06.029</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27296443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27296443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiltinan</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Mutation of the maize sbe1a and ae genes alters morphology and physical behavior of wx-type endosperm starch granules.</article-title>
<source><italic>Carbohydr. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>342</volume>
<fpage>2619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2627</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carres.2007.07.019</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17765880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17765880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Different structures of heterogeneous starch granules from high-amylose rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>11254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11263</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf503999r</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25373551?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25373551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Effect of simultaneous inhibition of starch branching enzymes I and IIb on the crystalline structure of rice starches with different amylose contents.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>9930</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9937</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf4030773</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24063623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24063623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Morphology and structural characterization of high-amylose rice starch residues hydrolyzed by porcine pancreatic &#x003b1;-amylase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Hydrocoll.</italic></source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodhyd.2012.11.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okumura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Alteration of the structural properties of starch components by the lack of an isoform of starch branching enzyme in rice seeds.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>268</volume>
<fpage>19084</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19091</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8360192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8360192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Towards a better understanding of the metabolic system for amylopectin biosynthesis in pants: rice endosperm as a model tissue.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>718</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>725</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcf091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12154134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Biosynthesis of reserve starch,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Starch: Metabolism and Structure</italic></source>, <role>ed.</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Rice starch biotechnology: rice endosperm as a model of cereal endosperms.</article-title>
<source><italic>Starch</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>:<issue>1600375</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/star.201600375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Francisco</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Hosaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Essential amino acids of starch synthase IIa differentiate amylopectin structure and starch quality between japonica and indica rice varieties.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-005-6507-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16027975?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16027975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagamine</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The fine structure of amylopectin in endosperm from Asian cultivated rice can be largely classified into two classed.</article-title>
<source><italic>Starch</italic></source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1521-379X(200204)54:3/4&#x0003c;117::AID-STAR117&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Utsumi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Utsumi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Characterization of the reactions of starch branching enzyme from rice endosperm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>776</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>794</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcq035</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20305271?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20305271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Biochemical and genetic analysis of the effects of amylose-extender mutation in rice endosperm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>127</volume>
<fpage>459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>472</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.010127</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11598221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11598221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Shea</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Konik</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morell</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Fluorophore-assisted carbohydrate electrophoresis (FACE) of oligosaccharides: efficiency of labeling and high-resolution separation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Carbohydr. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>307</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0008-6215(97)10085-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouwerkerk</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Kam</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoge</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Glucocorticoid-inducible gene expression in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>213</volume>
<fpage>370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>378</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250100583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11506359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1952</year>). <article-title>Evidence of multiple branching in waxy maize starch.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Chem. Soc.</italic></source>
<fpage>4546</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4548</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Starch biosynthesis and degradation,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>The Biochemistry of Plants, Carbohydrate: Structure and Function</italic></source>
<volume>Vol. 3</volume>
<role>ed.</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>), <fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>423</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berbezy</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosar-Hashemi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cmiel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larroque</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>A genetic strategy generating wheat with very high amylose content.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Biotechnol. J.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>1276</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1286</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12345</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25644858?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25644858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Topping</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barsby</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>High-amylose wheat generated by RNA interference improves indices of large-bowel health in rats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>3546</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3551</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0510737103</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16537443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16537443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosar-Hashemi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Control of starch branching in barley defined through differential RNAi suppression of starch branching enzyme IIa and IIb.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>1469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1482</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq011</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20156842?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20156842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosat-Hashemi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Starch branching enzyme IIb in wheat is expressed at low levels in the endosperm compared to other cereals and encoded at a non-syntenic locus.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>222</volume>
<fpage>899</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>909</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-005-0032-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16172866?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16172866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Starch-branching enzyme I-deficient mutation specifically affects the structure and properties of starch in rice endosperm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>133</volume>
<fpage>1111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1121</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.021527</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 14526120?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14526120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Francisco</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Utsumi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Chlorella starch branching enzyme II (BEII) can complement the function of BEIIb in rice endosperm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>1062</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1074</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcp058</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19380351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19380351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohdan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Francisco</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Diversity of reaction characteristics of glucan branching enzymes and the fine structure of &#x003b1;-glucan from various sources.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</italic></source>
<volume>562</volume>
<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2014.07.032</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25107532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25107532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seib</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Fine-structure of maize starches of from 4 wx-containing genotypes of the w64a inbred line in relation to gelatinization and retrogradation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Carbohydr. Polym.</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0144-8617(94)00059-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stam</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danchin</surname><given-names>E. G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rancured</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Dividing the large glycoside hydrolase family 13 into subfamilies: towards improved functional annotations of &#x003b1;-amylase-related proteins.</article-title>
<source><italic>Protein Eng. Des. Sel.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>562</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/protein/gzl044</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17085431?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17085431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Branching of amylose by the branching isozymes of maize endosperm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Carbohydr. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>240</volume>
<fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>263</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0008-6215(93)84188-C</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The structure of starch can be manipulated by changing the expression levels of starch branching enzyme IIb in rice endosperm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Biotechnol. J.</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>516</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-7652.2004.00097.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17147623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17147623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tetlow</surname><given-names>I. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emes</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Starch biosynthesis in the developing endosperms of grasses and cereals.</article-title>
<source><italic>Agronomy</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>81</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agronomy7040081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Progress in high-amylose cereal crops through inactivation of starch branching enzymes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>469</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00469</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28421099?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28421099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Gradually decreasing starch branching enzyme expression is responsible for the formation of heterogeneous starch granules.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>176</volume>
<fpage>582</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>595</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.01013</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29133372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29133372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oard</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Structure, expression and promoter activity of two polyubiquitin genes from rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>156</volume>
<fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9452(00)00255-7</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10936527?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10936527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Microstructure and ultrastructure of high-amylose rice resistant starch granules modified by antisense RNA inhibition of starch branching enzyme.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Agric. Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>1224</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1232</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf9031316</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20030326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20030326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamanouchi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Organ specificity of isoforms of starch branching enzyme (Q-enzyme) in rice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>985</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>991</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2008.00714.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18844776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18844776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiltinan</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Maize starch-branching enzyme isoforms and amylopectin structure. In the absence of starch-branching enzyme IIb, the further absence of starch-branching enzyme Ia leads to increased branching.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>136</volume>
<fpage>3515</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3523</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.043315</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15516514?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15516514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Fine-structure of amylopectin in relation to gelatinization and retrogradation behavior of maize starches from 3 wx-containing genotypes in 2 inbred lines.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cereal Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>