<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6232684</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.01498</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>On the Roles of Wheat Endosperm ADP-Glucose Pyrophosphorylase Subunits</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrero</surname><given-names>Danisa M. L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/620720/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Asencion Diez</surname><given-names>Matias D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/315087/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>Misty L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/583273/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Falaschetti</surname><given-names>Christine A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Piattoni</surname><given-names>Claudia V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/570273/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>Alberto A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/28235/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>Miguel A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/289103/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Laboratorio de Enzimolog&#x000ed;a Molecular, Instituto de Agrobiotecnolog&#x000ed;a del Litoral (CONICET &#x02013; UNL), Facultad de Bioqu&#x000ed;mica y Ciencias Biol&#x000f3;gicas, Universidad Nacional del Litoral</institution>, <addr-line>Santa Fe</addr-line>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Loyola University Chicago</institution>, <addr-line>Chicago, IL</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Yasunori Nakamura, Akita Prefectural University, Japan</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Jos&#x000e9; Juan Ordaz-Ortiz, Centro de Investigaci&#x000f3;n y de Estudios Avanzados (CINVESTAV), Mexico; Sam T. Mugford, John Innes Centre (JIC), United Kingdom; Tom W. Okita, Washington State University, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Alberto A. Iglesias, <email>iglesias@fbcb.unl.edu.ar</email> Miguel A. Ballicora, <email>mballic@luc.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Present address: Misty L. Kuhn, Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, San Francisco State University, San Francisco, CA, United States; Christine A. Falaschetti, Jenner &#x00026; Block LLP, Chicago, IL, United States; Claudia V. Piattoni, Institut Pasteur de Montevideo, Montevideo, Uruguay</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p><sup>&#x02021;</sup>These authors have contributed equally to the work</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn004"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Metabolism and Chemodiversity, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1498</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Ferrero, Asencion Diez, Kuhn, Falaschetti, Piattoni, Iglesias and Ballicora.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ferrero, Asencion Diez, Kuhn, Falaschetti, Piattoni, Iglesias and Ballicora</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase from wheat endosperm controls starch synthesis in seeds and has unique regulatory properties compared to others from this family. It comprises two types of subunits, but despite its importance little is known about their roles. Here, we synthesized <italic>de novo</italic> the wheat endosperm ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase small (S) and large (L) subunit genes, heterologously expressed them in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, and kinetically characterized the recombinant proteins. To understand their distinct roles, we co-expressed them with well characterized subunits from the potato tuber enzyme to obtain hybrids with one S subunit from one source and an L subunit from the other. After kinetic analyses of these hybrids, we concluded that the unusual insensitivity to activation of the wheat endosperm enzyme is caused by a pre-activation of the L subunit. In addition, the heat stability and sensitivity to phosphate are given by the S subunit.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>starch synthesis</kwd><kwd>allosteric regulation</kwd><kwd>3-phosphoglycerate</kwd><kwd>heat stability</kwd><kwd>crop improvement</kwd><kwd>inorganic phosphate</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Agencia Nacional de Promoci&#x000f3;n Cient&#x000ed;fica y Tecnol&#x000f3;gica<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100003074</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">PICT 2015 1767</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Universidad Nacional del Litoral<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100005746</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">CAID 2016</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003">National Science Foundation<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100000001</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn003">MCB 1024945</award-id><award-id rid="cn003">MCB 1616851</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="37"/><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Nearly one-fifth of all calories consumed in the world come from wheat. In order to meet the caloric needs of our growing population, it is estimated that the yield of this crop must substantially increase in the near future (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Altman, 1999</xref>). Crop yield is influenced by starch synthesis (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Smidansky et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Tuncel and Okita, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Zi et al., 2018</xref>), which in higher plants and unicellular algae is controlled to a large extent by ADP-glucose (ADP-Glc) pyrophosphorylase (EC: 2.7.7.27; ADP-Glc PPase). This regulatory enzyme catalyzes the conversion of ATP and glucose-1-phosphate (Glc-1P) to form ADP-Glc and pyrophosphate (PP<sub>i</sub>) (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Iglesias and Preiss, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). The wheat endosperm enzyme, like other plant ADP-Glc PPases, comprises two distinct homologous subunits, small (S) and large (L), which form an S<sub>2</sub>L<sub>2</sub> heterotetramer. However, this endosperm form presents unique regulatory properties compared with enzymes from other sources. Despite the relevance of this particular enzyme, its impact on the agricultural importance of wheat, and its peculiar properties, little is known about their relationship to structure.</p><p>The majority of plant ADP-Glc PPases are allosterically activated by 3-phosphoglycerate (3-PGA) and inhibited by orthophosphate (P<sub>i</sub>) (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Iglesias and Preiss, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Although the main activator is 3-PGA, the enzymes may be slightly promiscuous toward low affinity secondary activators (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Iglesias et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Casati and Iglesias, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Kuhn et al., 2013</xref>). It has been established that dicot L subunits influence the different sensitivities to allosteric effectors based on their tissue localization (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Kavakli et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Crevillen et al., 2003</xref>). Since the divergence of monocots and dicots, dicot L subunits have duplicated and diversified into three separate branches of the phylogenetic tree, whereas monocot endosperm L subunits belong to a fourth distinct branch (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). It is known that monocot endosperm ADP-Glc PPases display unique responses to allosteric effectors (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Plaxton and Preiss, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Kleczkowski et al., 1993</xref>). For instance, the wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) enzyme purified from endosperm is insensitive to 3-PGA activation in absence of P<sub>i</sub> (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Casati and Iglesias, 2002</xref>).</p><p>To reveal whether the unique regulatory properties of the wheat endosperm ADP-Glc PPase are determined by one subunit, or the combination of both, we constructed hybrid proteins mixing S and L subunits from different sources. We chose potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>) tuber and wheat endosperm enzymes because of their distinct responses to allosteric effectors (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Casati and Iglesias, 2002</xref>). The potato tuber ADP-Glc PPase is highly sensitive to activation by 3-PGA, unlike the wheat endosperm enzyme. We analyzed the allosteric properties of the enzymes by combining the recombinant potato tuber S subunit (StuS) with either the potato tuber L subunit (StuL) or the wheat endosperm L subunit (TaeL) by heterologous expression in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> of artificially synthesized genes. In addition, we studied the combinations of the wheat endosperm S subunit (TaeS) with either the wheat endosperm L subunit (TaeL) or the potato tuber L subunit (StuL).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Reagents</title><p>D-[<sup>14</sup>C]Glc-1P was purchased from GE Healthcare (Piscataway, NJ, United States). All other reagents were purchased at the highest quality available. The genes encoding the wheat endosperm ADP-Glc PPase small (TaeS) and large (TaeL) subunits were synthesized <italic>de novo</italic> (Bio Basic Inc., Markham, ON, Canada) (sequences in <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">1</xref></bold>)</p></sec><sec><title>Subcloning Procedures</title><p>TaeS and TaeL subunit genes, as well as genes encoding S and L subunits from potato tuber ADP-Glc PPase, were subcloned using <italic>Nde</italic>I and <italic>Sac</italic>I restriction sites in pET28c vectors, thus rendering proteins with an N-term His-tag after overexpression. In addition, all genes encoding the different S and L subunits were subcloned from the pET28c plasmid into the pCDFduet vector using <italic>Nde</italic>I and <italic>Xho</italic>I (downstream the <italic>SacI</italic> in the pET28 multi cloning sites). This construct overexpresses this construction overexpress the target protein but without any tag. By combining the pCDE and pET28 constructs, we obtained the different ADP-Glc PPases characterized in this work, with a His-tag on only one subunit. Although we obtained the entire set of combinations, we report here kinetic and regulatory data only from those heteromeric S/L enzymes where the His-tag was in the L subunit (using pET28c) and the S subunit was untagged (by using pCDFduet). All sequences were confirmed by the University of Chicago DNA Sequencing Facility (Chicago, IL, United States).</p></sec><sec><title>Enzyme Expression and Purification</title><p>Proteins were over-expressed using <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) as a host. Cells were transformed with single pET28 or pCDFduet constructs for independent subunit production, or a combination of plasmids (pCDFduet/<italic>small-subunit</italic> with pET28c/<italic>large-subunit</italic>) as stated above. Transformed cells were grown in LB medium at 37&#x000b0;C until OD<sub>600</sub> reached 0.6 and then cultures were induced with 0.5 mM IPTG for 16 h at 18&#x000b0;C. After induction, cells were harvested, resuspended in buffer A (50 mM MOPS pH 8.0, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1 mM EDTA, 10% sucrose, 10 mM imidazole and 4 mM &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol), disrupted by sonication and then centrifuged twice (10 min) at 30,000 &#x000d7;<italic>g.</italic> Proteins were purified by immobilized metal ion affinity chromatography (IMAC) and all purification steps were performed at 4&#x000b0;C. Supernatants were loaded on a 1 ml His-Trap column (GE Healthcare) previously equilibrated with buffer A and proteins were eluted with a 10&#x02013;300 mM imidazole linear gradient in buffer A (50 column volumes). Fractions containing the highest activity were pooled and concentrated. The resulting enzyme samples were &#x0003e;90% pure (according to densitometry of SDS-PAGE gels, not shown) and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until use. The recombinant wheat endosperm enzymes (TaeS/TaeL as well as single TaeS or TaeL subunits) remained fully active for 12 months.</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular Mass Determination</title><p>Protein molecular mass was determined by gel filtration using a Tricorn 5/200 column (GE Healthcare) loaded with Superdex G200 resin (GE Healthcare). A Gel Filtration Calibration Kit-High Molecular Weight (GE Healthcare) with protein standards including thyroglobulin (669 kDa), ferritin (440 kDa), aldolase (158 kDa), conalbumin (75 kDa), and ovalbumin (44 kDa) was used. The column void volume was determined using a Dextran Blue loading solution (Promega, Fitchburg, WI, United States).</p></sec><sec><title>Enzyme Activity Assays and Kinetic Analysis</title><p>A radiometric enzyme assay was employed to measure the synthesis of ADP-[<sup>14</sup>C]Glc from [<sup>14</sup>C]Glc-1P and ATP, as described before (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Yep et al., 2004</xref>). The standard reaction mixture had 50 mM HEPPS (pH 8.0), 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 4 mM dithiothreitol, 1.5 mM [<sup>14</sup>C]Glc-1P (100&#x02013;1000 cpm/nmol), 2.5 mM ATP, 10 mM 3PGA (unless otherwise stated), 0.75 U/ml inorganic pyrophosphatase, 0.2 mg/ml bovine serum albumin, and enzyme in a total reaction volume of 0.2 ml. The reaction proceeded for 10 min at 37&#x000b0;C and was stopped in a boiling water bath for 1 min. The amount of ADP-[<sup>14</sup>C]Glc formed was quantified as described (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Yep et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>We also measured ADP-Glc PPase activity by analyzing ADP-Glc synthesis in a highly sensitive colorimetric method by following P<sub>i</sub> formation after hydrolysis of PP<sub>i</sub> by inorganic pyrophosphatase (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Fusari et al., 2006</xref>). Reaction mixtures contained (unless otherwise specified) 50 mM MOPS pH 8.0, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 4 mM dithiothreitol, 2 mM ATP, 0.2 mg/ml bovine serum albumin, 0.5 U/ml yeast inorganic pyrophosphatase and a proper enzyme dilution. Assays were initiated by addition of 2 mM Glc-1P in a total volume of 50 &#x003bc;l. Reactions were incubated for 10 min at 37&#x000b0;C and terminated when the Malachite Green reagent was added. The complex formed with the released P<sub>i</sub> was measured at 630 nm in an ELISA EMax detector (Molecular Devices).</p><p>One unit of activity (U) is defined as the amount of enzyme catalyzing the formation of 1 &#x003bc;mol of product per min, under conditions described above in each case.</p><p>Saturation curves were performed by assaying enzyme activity at different concentrations of the variable substrate or effector while the others remained constant. To avoid interference with any potential presence of S subunit homotetramers the saturation curves for 3-PGA were performed up to 1 mM. These homotetrameric S forms are not active until much higher concentrations of 3-PGA (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Doan et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Crevillen et al., 2003</xref>) or Fru-6P (unpublished). Experimental data were plotted as enzyme activity (U/mg) versus substrate (or effector) concentration (mM) and kinetic constants were determined by fitting the data to the Hill equation as described elsewhere (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Crevillen et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kuhn et al., 2009</xref>). Fitting was performed with the Levenberg-Marquardt non-linear least-squares algorithm provided by the computer program Origin<sup>TM</sup> 8.0. Hill plots were used to calculate the Hill coefficient (<italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub>), the maximal velocity (<italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>), and the kinetic constants that correspond to the activator, substrate or inhibitor concentrations giving 50% of the maximal activation (<italic>A</italic><sub>0.5</sub>), velocity (<italic>S</italic><sub>0.5</sub>), or inhibition (<italic>I</italic><sub>0.5</sub>). All kinetic constants are the mean of at least three independent sets of data, which were reproducible within a range of &#x000b1; 10%.</p></sec><sec><title>Protein Methods</title><p>Protein concentration was determined using the bicinchoninic acid reagent from Pierce Chemical Company (Rockford, IL, United States) as described previously (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 1985</xref>). Samples were desalted using Bio-Rad 10 DG columns and concentrated with Centricon-30 devices (Amicon Inc., Billerica, MA, United States)). Recombinant proteins and purification fractions were defined by sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) according to Laemmli (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Laemmli, 1970</xref>). Gels were loaded with 5&#x02013;50 &#x003bc;g of protein per well and stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue.</p></sec><sec><title>Heat Stability</title><p>Heat stability of the recombinant constructs was measured as follows. Half milliliter of purified (by IMAC) TaeS/TaeL, StuS/TaeL, TaeS/StuL, StuS/StuL proteins were placed into individual 1.7 ml microcentrifuge tubes and centrifuged at 20,000 &#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C. The enzyme samples were diluted to give the same final protein concentration (&#x0223c;2 mg/ml). Then, 50 &#x003bc;l of the supernatant was aliquoted into five 1.7 ml microcentrifuge tubes and then placed at 0, 25, 37, 42, and 55&#x000b0;C for 5 min. Samples were immediately placed on ice for 2 min, centrifuged at 20,000 &#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C and the supernatant was diluted with 50 mM MOPS buffer pH 8.0, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1 mM EDTA, 0.5 mg/ml bovine serum albumin. The activity of 10 &#x003bc;l samples was assayed in duplicate as described above.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Recombinant Wheat ADP-Glc PPase Expression and Characterization</title><p>To deepen the study of the regulatory properties of wheat endosperm ADP-Glc PPase, it was necessary to obtain a recombinant version of the enzyme. We artificially synthesized the respective genes coding for the S and L subunits with the codon usage for <italic>E. coli</italic> to maximize the heterologous expression in this bacterium. Our first attempts for kinetic analyses were based on a strategy where the subunits were obtained without a His-tag. The kinetic properties of the recombinant wild type wheat endosperm enzyme (untagged) were comparable to the native enzyme purified from wheat seeds, although this enzyme was unstable as previously described (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Casati and Iglesias, 2002</xref>). Then, we overexpressed the recombinant S and L subunits from wheat endosperm ADP-Glc PPase with an N-term His-tag, which allowed us to purify the proteins to high levels of purity (&#x0003e;90%), as shown in <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">2A</xref></bold>. Interestingly, when we co-expressed the TaeS/TaeL heteromer with the His-tag in the L subunit, the enzyme became stable and remained active for several months. We confirmed that this stabilization effect could be ascribed to the N-term His-tag on the TaeL subunit, since, when we removed it the enzyme became unstable again (not shown). Thus, we decided to use this strategy (untagged S subunit; His-tagged L subunit) to produce the recombinant wheat endosperm ADP-Glc PPase and the hybrid S/L proteins characterized in this work. Gel filtration on Superdex-G200 revealed that in all the cases the purified recombinant enzymes had a quaternary structure of homo- (S<sub>4</sub>) or hetero-tetramers (S<sub>2</sub>L<sub>2</sub>) of about 200 kDa (see <bold>Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">2B</xref></bold>). Also, the L subunits expressed alone were not active and thus not further characterized.</p><p>The purified homotetrameric TaeS exhibited a relatively low specific activity (see <bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref></bold>) and it was activated up to 3.5-fold by 3-PGA (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold> and <bold>Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref></bold>). Conversely, the heterotetrameric TaeS/TaeL showed insensitivity to 3-PGA (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold>). However, this metabolite increased by nearly twofold the apparent affinity of the enzyme toward Glc-1P and mainly affected the sigmoidal saturation curve for this substrate (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). The kinetic parameters of recombinant TaeS/TaeL detailed in <bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold> are similar (in the same order of magnitude) to those previously reported for the ADP-Glc PPase purified from wheat seeds (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Casati and Iglesias, 2002</xref>). As a whole, these results indicate that the TaeL subunit significantly contributes to form a heterotetramer with relatively high catalytic capacity and also insensitivity to 3-PGA. These properties of the wheat endosperm ADP-Glc PPase agree with reports on the characterization of the enzyme from barley (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Kleczkowski et al., 1993</xref>) and maize (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Plaxton and Preiss, 1987</xref>) endosperm.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Saturation curves for 3-PGA of wheat ADP-Glc PPase. Black circles black circles belongs to homotetrameric TaeS enzyme, whilst in open circles belong to the heterotetrameric TaeL/TaeS. Relative activity was calculated considering activities of 0.04 and 4.7 U/mg for the homo- and heterotetrameric enzymes, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01498-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>TaeL/TaeS saturation curves for both substrates, Glc-1P <bold>(A)</bold> and ATP <bold>(B)</bold>, in presence (dark circles) or absence (open circles) of 3-PGA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01498-g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Kinetic parameters for the recombinant TaeS/TaeL, TaeS/StuL, StuS/TaeL and StuS/StuL heteromeric ADP-Glc PPases.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substrate</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S</italic><sub>0.5</sub>(mM)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>(U.mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TaeS/TaeL</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glc-1P</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glc-1P + 3-PGA<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083 &#x000b1; 0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP + 3-PGA<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">StuS/TaeL</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glc-1P</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093 &#x000b1; 0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.4 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glc-1P + 3-PGA<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072 &#x000b1; 0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.4 &#x000b1; 1.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP + 3-PGA<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6 &#x000b1; 1.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TaeS/StuL</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glc-1P</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14 &#x000b1; 0.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050 &#x000b1; 0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glc-1P + 3-PGA<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11 &#x000b1; 0.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030 &#x000b1; 0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP + 3-PGA<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">StuS/StuL</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glc-1P</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;1.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glc-1P + 3-PGA<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 &#x000b1; 2.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP + 3-PGA<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup>&#x02217;</sup>1 mM 3-PGA.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Kinetic Properties of Hybrid Constructs</title><p>To further understand the properties of the different subunits from plant ADP-Glc PPases with different behavior toward effectors (such the potato tuber and wheat endosperm enzymes), we produced heteromeric S/L hybrid enzymes. For this purpose, we used the same strategy described above to obtain the recombinant wheat ADP-Glc PPase (see section Materials and Methods) by combining pCDFduet and pET28 constructs. We also expressed a recombinant potato tuber ADP-Glc PPase using this system, and the enzyme showed similar kinetic and regulatory properties to those previously reported (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Iglesias et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 1998</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). As shown in <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>, the presence of the respective L subunit from either potato tuber or wheat endosperm gave specific properties to the heteromeric hybrid proteins. Remarkably, the presence of StuL conferred sensitivity to 3-PGA and Fru-6P to the resulting hybrid enzymes, both of which are the main and a secondary activator of many ADP-Glc PPases from plants, respectively (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Iglesias and Preiss, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Iglesias et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Casati and Iglesias, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Kuhn et al., 2013</xref>). Also, TaeS/StuL and StuS/StuL had a higher apparent affinity for 3-PGA than for Fru-6P (about five and threefold higher, respectively). For a more comparative analysis of the kinetic and regulatory properties of the hybrid ADP-Glc PPases, we determined their kinetic parameters in the absence or presence of 3-PGA. As shown in <bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>. TaeS/TaeL and StuS/TaeL enzymes were insensitive to activation, as 3-PGA had neither effect on <italic>S</italic><sub>0.5</sub> values for substrates nor on <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>. Conversely, TaeS/StuL and StuS/StuL exhibited <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> values 9.7- and 42-fold higher (respectively) in presence of 3-PGA that in its absence.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>3-PGA <bold>(A)</bold> and Fru-6P <bold>(B)</bold> activation plots of hybrid ADP-Glc PPases. Saturation curves for 3-PGA and Fru-6P were performed for hybrid proteins TaeS/TaeL (open squares), StuS/TaeL (open circles), TaeS/StuL (dark squares), and StuS/StuL (dark circles). Relative activity was calculated considering the unity of activity as: 6.7, 56.8, 0.25, and 13.8 U/mg (in <bold>A</bold>) or 6.5, 55.2, 0.22, and 15.3 U/mg (in <bold>B</bold>), respectively for TaeS/TaeL, StuS/TaeL, TaeS/StuL, and StuS/StuL.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01498-g003"/></fig><p>Regarding their regulatory properties, the role of the S subunit from wheat endosperm ADP-Glc PPase seemed to be different from the L subunit. It appears that the S subunit may be primarily responsible for the sensitivity (in terms of relative apparent affinity) of the enzyme to P<sub>i</sub> inhibition. For instance, constructs with StuS had a much higher affinity for P<sub>i</sub> than those with TaeS (<bold>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></bold>). StuS/StuL reached maximal inhibition of 4.6-fold and StuS/TaeL was inhibited 4.2-fold. TaeS/TaeL was inhibited 7.4-fold compared to 1.4-fold for TaeS/StuL, however, the apparent affinity for P<sub>i</sub> of TaeS/TaeL was 40-, and 14-fold lower than StuS/StuL and StuS/TaeL, respectively (<bold>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></bold>). The <italic>I</italic><sub>0.5</sub> for the TaeS/TaeL recombinant enzyme was in the millimolar-range, which is similar to the data from the enzyme purified from wheat seeds (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Tuncel and Okita, 2013</xref>). In agreement with the idea that TaeS makes the enzyme less sensitive to P<sub>i</sub> inhibition, the TaeS/StuL hybrid enzyme was unable to be inhibited more than 1.4-fold, even at high concentrations (10 mM) of P<sub>i</sub>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Pi inhibition of the proteins characterized in this work.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>I</italic><sub>0.5</sub> (mM)</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-Fold</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">StuS/StuL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TaeS/StuL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.<sup>&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">StuS/TaeL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TaeS/TaeL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>n.d.<sup>&#x02217;</sup>, not determined, as low inhibition level was observed even at 10 mM P<sub>i</sub></italic>.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Heat Stability</title><p>We noticed that the hybrid proteins were more stable and retained more activity than the wheat endosperm wild-type protein (TaeS/TaeL). As a result, we tested the heat stability of the hybrid constructs to determine the cause of this effect. The hybrids exhibited similar heat stability for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C, but at 55&#x000b0;C, StuS/TaeL retained almost 80% of the original activity, whereas TaeS/StuL retained no more than 10% (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>). TaeS/TaeL could not retain the original activity above 42&#x000b0;C. StuS/StuL was previously shown to remain active until 60&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Yep et al., 2004</xref>). The presence of the StuS subunit seems to be responsible for the increased heat-stability of the StuS/TaeL hybrid construct.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Heat stability of hybrid ADP-Glc PPases. Assays were carried out as described in section Materials and Methods; TaeS/TaeL (open squares), StuS/TaeL (open circles), TaeS/StuL (dark squares), and StuS/StuL (dark circles).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01498-g004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Herein, we report the recombinant production of the wheat endosperm ADP-Glc PPase by a procedure that allowed us to reach a high level of purity and stability of the enzyme. The pure recombinant enzyme exhibited kinetic and regulatory proteins that agree with those previously reported for the enzyme purified from its natural source (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Casati and Iglesias, 2002</xref>). Also, the recombinant procedure was useful to construct chimeric hybrid proteins by combining small and large subunits between the wheat endosperm and the potato tuber heterotetrameric ADP-Glc PPases. Because these latter enzymes have distinctive properties with respect to allosteric regulation and sensitivity to heat treatments (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Iglesias et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 1995</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Casati and Iglesias, 2002</xref>), we could explore specific roles played by the small and large subunits in the regulation and structural stability of plant ADP-Glc PPase.</p><p>Our results support the view that the large subunit in plant ADP-Glc PPase plays a main role in conferring regulatory properties to the enzyme. The TaeL subunit was found inactive, in agreement with homologous proteins from other plants (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Kavakli et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Crevillen et al., 2003</xref>). However, TaeL showed responsibility for a major contribution to the &#x0201c;pre-activation&#x0201d; and insensitivity to activators (either 3-PGA or Fru-6P) for StuS/TaeL and TaeS/TaeL. This is compatible with the idea that L subunits influence the regulatory properties of ADP-Glc PPases. Previous data from hybrid potato-<italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADP-Glc PPases showed that the apparent affinity for 3-PGA was mainly dependent upon the L subunit regardless of the S subunit involved (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Ventriglia et al., 2007</xref>). In the case of the wheat endosperm enzyme, the TaeL causes pre-activation/insensitivity to the activator rather than altering the apparent affinity for it.</p><p>Concerning the small subunit of plant ADP-Glc PPase, results herein suggest a main role of the protein in conferring apparent affinity to P<sub>i</sub> inhibition; the subunit is also critical for the heat stability of the enzyme. Previous studies have shown the heat stability of ADP-Glc PPases may influence yield or seed weight in rice, maize, wheat, and potato tuber (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Krauss and Marschner, 1984</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Wilhelm et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Smidansky et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Morita et al., 2005</xref>). In early controlled studies, heat adversely affected the seed biomass of wheat (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Gibson and Paulsen, 1999</xref>) and the rate of photosynthesis (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Nagai and Makino, 2009</xref>). Many ADP-Glc PPases are heat-stable up to 60&#x000b0;C, whereas the enzymes from endosperm are heat labile (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Preiss et al., 1971</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Kleczkowski et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Casati and Iglesias, 2002</xref>). The heat stability of the potato tuber ADP-Glc PPase enzyme has been attributed to the presence of Cys<sup>12</sup> in StuS, which forms a disulfide bridge in the homotetrameric protein (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2005</xref>). This residue is conserved in all S subunits from plants, with the exception of endosperm enzymes from monocots (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ballicora et al., 1999</xref>). Previously, the heat stability of the maize endosperm was improved by introducing a mutation from methionine to cysteine at the N terminus of the S subunit (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Linebarger et al., 2005</xref>).</p><p>One way to increase yield in a warmer climate may be to engineer a heat stable ADP-Glc PPase (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Giroux et al., 1996</xref>). In our study, the StuS/TaeL enzyme exhibited increased heat stability and similar allosteric properties to the TaeS/TaeL wild-type enzyme. We propose that this hybrid construct may yield a heat stable transgenic wheat plant, without major changes in physiology. Previously, a transgenic wheat plant was constructed using a genetically modified maize ADP-Glc PPase L subunit and a mutant potato-maize mosaic S subunit (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Meyer et al., 2007</xref>). They saw an increased yield, but only in an environment with non-limiting resources. Unlike their work, the potato/wheat hybrid we propose contains unaltered S and L subunit genes from two agriculturally important crops.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Regarding enzymes from storage tissues (e.g., seeds, tubers, etc.), it seems that one main difference in regulation between monocots and dicots is their sensitivity and response to activators. Dicot ADP-Glc PPases are very sensitive to allosteric effectors and can be activated to a high <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>, whereas some monocot forms are in a seemingly insensitive state. In this work we show that the insensitivity in wheat is caused by the L subunit, which drives the heterotetramer to a more active form when compared to the S subunit alone. This unifies the theory that the interaction between L and S subunits of plant ADP-Glc PPases determines their different regulatory properties for adaptation to the needs of different tissues (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Crevillen et al., 2003</xref>). In this case, wheat endosperm is not an exception, but rather an extreme case of how the L subunit affects the heteromer regulatory properties. Rather than improving the affinity of 3-PGA, it activates the heterotetramer and renders it insensitive for further activation.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MK, MA, DF, AI, and MB conceived and designed the experiments and wrote the paper. MK, CF, and DF performed the experiments. MK, MF, CP, MA, AI, and MB analyzed the data. AI and MB contributed reagents, materials, and analysis tools.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by the National Science Foundation (grants MCB 1024945 and MCB 1616851) to MB, the Fourth Year Fellowship Loyola University Chicago to MK, and the Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship American Society of Plant Biologists and Carbon Scholarship University Chicago to CF and by grants from ANPCyT (PICT 2015 1767 to AI), UNL (CAID 2016 to AI). MA and AI are members of the Research Career from CONICET. DF is a doctoral fellow from CONICET.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01498/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01498/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><media xlink:href="Image_1.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Plant biotechnology in the 21st century: the challenges ahead.</article-title>
<source><italic>Electron. J. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2225/vol2-issue2-fulltext-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubay</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devillers</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Resurrecting the ancestral enzymatic role of a modulatory subunit.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>280</volume>
<fpage>10189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10195</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M413540200</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15632142?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15632142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frueauf</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schurmann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Activation of the potato tuber ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase by thioredoxin.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>275</volume>
<fpage>1315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1320</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.2.1315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10625679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frueauf</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Heat stability of the potato tuber ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase: role of Cys residue 12 in the small subunit.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>257</volume>
<fpage>782</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>786</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1999.0469</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10208860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10208860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesbitt</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>ADP-Glucose pyrophosphorylase from potato tubers. Site-directed mutagenesis studies of the regulatory sites.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>274</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.118.1.265</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9733546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9733546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase, a regulatory enzyme for bacterial glycogen synthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.67.2.213-225.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12794190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase: a regulatory enzyme for plant starch synthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Photosynth. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:PRES.0000011916.67519.58</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16228397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laughlin</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okita</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Adenosine 5&#x02019;-diphosphate-glucose pyrophosphorylase from potato tuber. Significance of the N terminus of the small subunit for catalytic properties and heat stability.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>109</volume>
<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>251</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.1.245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7480324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crevillen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merida</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The different large subunit isoforms of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase confer distinct kinetic and regulatory properties to the heterotetrameric enzyme.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>278</volume>
<fpage>28508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28515</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M304280200</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12748181?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12748181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doan</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The allosterically unregulated isoform of ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase from barley endosperm is the most likely source of ADP-glucose incorporated into endosperm starch.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>121</volume>
<fpage>965</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>975</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.121.3.965</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10557246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10557246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fusari</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demonte</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aleanzi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A colorimetric method for the assay of ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anal. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>352</volume>
<fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2006.01.024</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16574055?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16574055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Yield components of wheat grown under high temperature stress during reproductive growth.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>1841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1846</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1999.3961841x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giroux</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okita</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A single mutation that increases maize seed weight.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>5824</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5829</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.12.5824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8650177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez-Casati</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase from wheat endosperm. Purification and characterization of an enzyme with novel regulatory properties.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>214</volume>
<fpage>428</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>434</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250100634</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11855648?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11855648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloksberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Expression of the potato tuber ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>268</volume>
<fpage>1081</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1086</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8380404?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8380404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Bacterial glycogen and plant starch biosynthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biochem. Educ.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0307-4412(92)90191-N</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Crystal structure of potato tuber ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase.</article-title>
<source><italic>EMBO J.</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>694</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>704</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600551</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15692569?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15692569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kavakli</surname><given-names>I. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamone</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Generation, characterization, and heterologous expression of wild-type and up-regulated forms of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> leaf ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>215</volume>
<fpage>430</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>439</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-001-0727-8</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12111225?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12111225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleczkowski</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villand</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luthi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Insensitivity of barley endosperm ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase to 3-phosphoglycerate and orthophosphate regulation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.101.1.179</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 8278493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8278493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marschner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Growth rate and carbohydrate metabolism of potato tubers exposed to high temperatures.</article-title>
<source><italic>Potato Res.</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>303</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02357638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Falaschetti</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title><italic>Ostreococcus tauri</italic> ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase reveals alternative paths for the evolution of subunit roles.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>284</volume>
<fpage>34092</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34102</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.037614</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19737928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19737928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The ancestral activation promiscuity of ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylases from oxygenic photosynthetic organisms.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Evol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>:<issue>51</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-13-51</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23433303?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23433303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laemmli</surname><given-names>U. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>227</volume>
<fpage>680</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>685</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/227680a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5432063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linebarger</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boehlein</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannah</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Heat stability of maize endosperm ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase is enhanced by insertion of a cysteine in the N terminus of the small subunit.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>139</volume>
<fpage>1625</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1634</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.067637</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16299180?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16299180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>F. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbert</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanning</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giroux</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Field evaluation of transgenic wheat expressing a modified ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase large subunit.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>336</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>342</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2006.03.0160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonemaru</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takanashi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Grain growth and endosperm cell size under high night temperatures in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>695</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>701</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mci071</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15655104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15655104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Differences between rice and wheat in temperature responses of photosynthesis and plant growth.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>744</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>755</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcp029</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19251744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19251744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plaxton</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Purification and properties of nonproteolytic degraded ADPglucose pyrophosphorylase from maize endosperm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.83.1.105</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16665182?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16665182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lammel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabraw</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>). <article-title>A unique adenosine diphosphoglucose pyrophosphorylase associated with maize embryo tissue.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>108</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.47.1.104</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16657563?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16657563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smidansky</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clancy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>F. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanning</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbert</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Enhanced ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase activity in wheat endosperm increases seed yield.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>1724</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1729</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.022635299</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11830676?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11830676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smidansky</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannah</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giroux</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Seed yield and plant biomass increases in rice are conferred by deregulation of endosperm ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>216</volume>
<fpage>656</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>664</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12569408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12569408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krohn</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermanson</surname><given-names>G. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallia</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Provenzano</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Measurement of protein using bicinchoninic acid.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anal. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>150</volume>
<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(85)90442-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3843705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuncel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okita</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Improving starch yield in cereals by over-expression of ADPglucose pyrophosphorylase: expectations and unanticipated outcomes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>211</volume>
<fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2013.06.009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23987811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23987811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ventriglia</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crevillen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Regulatory properties of potato-Arabidopsis hybrid ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>875</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>880</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcm047</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17452341?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singletary</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Heat stress during grain filling in maize.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>:<issue>1733</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1999.3961733x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yep</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bejar</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballicora</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubay</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>An assay for adenosine 5&#x02019;-diphosphate (ADP)-glucose pyrophosphorylase that measures the synthesis of radioactive ADP-glucose with glycogen synthase.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anal. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>324</volume>
<fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2003.09.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Grain yield, starch content and activities of key enzymes of waxy and non-waxy wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>4548</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-22587-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29540822?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29540822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list id="DL1"><def-item><term>3-PGA</term><def><p>3-phosphoglycerate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ADP-Glc</term><def><p>ADP-glucose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ADP-Glc PPase</term><def><p>ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Fru-6P</term><def><p>fructose-6-phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P<sub>i</sub></term><def><p>inorganic orthophosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PP<sub>i</sub></term><def><p>inorganic pyrophosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>StuL</term><def><p><italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> tuber L subunit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>StuS</term><def><p><italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> tuber S subunit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TaeL</term><def><p><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> endosperm L subunit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TaeS</term><def><p><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> endosperm S subunit</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>