<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Public Health Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Public Health Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PHN</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Public Health Nutrition</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1368-9800</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2727</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5582405</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1368980017001173</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1368980017001173</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00117</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="section"><subject>Assessment and Methodology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dietary gap assessment: an approach for evaluating whether a country&#x02019;s food
supply can support healthy diets at the population level</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">EM Kuyper <italic>et al</italic>.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Dietary gap assessment</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuyper</surname><given-names>Edye M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Engle-Stone</surname><given-names>Reina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>Joanne E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arimond</surname><given-names>Mary</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>Katherine P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>Kathryn G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<institution>University of California</institution>, <addr-line>Davis</addr-line>,
<addr-line>College of Agricultural and Environmental Sciences</addr-line>,
<addr-line>International Programs Office</addr-line>, <addr-line>Davis</addr-line>,
<addr-line>CA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<institution>University of California</institution>, <addr-line>Davis</addr-line>,
<addr-line>Program in International and Community Nutrition</addr-line>, <addr-line>3253
Meyer Hall</addr-line>, <addr-line>One Shields Avenue</addr-line>,
<addr-line>Davis</addr-line>, <addr-line>CA 95616</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><italic>Corresponding author:</italic> Email <email>kgdewey@ucdavis.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>2277</fpage><lpage>2288</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>06</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Authors 2017</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution licence (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>), which permits unrestricted
re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S1368980017001173a.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="normal"><sec id="abs1" sec-type="general"><title>Objective</title><p>Dietary diversity, and in particular consumption of nutrient-rich foods including
fruits, vegetables, nuts, beans and animal-source foods, is linked to greater nutrient
adequacy. We developed a &#x02018;dietary gap assessment&#x02019; to evaluate the degree to which a
nation&#x02019;s food supply could support healthy diets at the population level.</p></sec><sec id="abs2" sec-type="general"><title>Design/Setting</title><p>In the absence of global food-based dietary guidelines, we selected the Dietary
Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH) diet as an example because there is evidence it
prevents diet-related chronic disease and supports adequate micronutrient intakes. We
used the DASH guidelines to shape a hypothetical &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; diet for the test country of
Cameroon. Food availability was estimated using FAO Food Balance Sheet data on
country-level food supply. For each of the seven food groups in the &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; diet, we
calculated the difference between the estimated national supply (in kcal, edible portion
only) and the target amounts.</p></sec><sec id="abs3" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>In Cameroon, dairy and other animal-source foods were not adequately available to meet
healthy diet recommendations: the deficit was &#x02212;365 kcal (&#x02013;1527 kJ)/capita per d for
dairy products and &#x02212;185 kcal (&#x02013;774 kJ)/capita per d for meat, poultry, fish and eggs.
Adequacy of fruits and vegetables depended on food group categorization. When tubers and
plantains were categorized as vegetables and fruits, respectively, supply nearly met
recommendations. Categorizing tubers and plantains as starchy staples resulted in
pronounced supply shortfalls: &#x02212;109 kcal (&#x02013;457 kJ)/capita per d for fruits and &#x02212;94 kcal
(&#x02013;393 kJ)/capita per d for vegetables.</p></sec><sec id="abs4" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The dietary gap assessment illustrates an approach for better understanding how food
supply patterns need to change to achieve healthier dietary patterns.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Dietary diversity</kwd><kwd>Food supply</kwd><kwd>Food balance sheets</kwd><kwd>Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension diet</kwd><kwd>Agriculture&#x02013;nutrition</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>The need to improve diet quality, particularly among populations most vulnerable to
malnutrition, currently figures prominently in global conversations<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The ability to access a healthy diet is included in the definition of food
security: &#x02018;Food security exists when all people, at all times, have physical and economic
access to sufficient, safe and nutritious food that meets their dietary needs and food
preferences for an active and healthy life&#x02019;<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. At the country level, population access to a high-quality diet depends on the
availability of an adequate supply of diverse nutrient-rich foods<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Availability of such foods is not sufficient to ensure consumption of a healthy
diet by everyone in the population, due to variation in food distribution, access and
utilization attributable to factors such as geographic location, gender, age or socio-economic
status<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Nevertheless, improving the adequacy of a nation&#x02019;s overall food supply is an
essential step in meeting dietary intake goals. The objective of the present paper is to
describe the methodology for a &#x02018;dietary gap assessment&#x02019; approach to evaluating the degree to
which a nation&#x02019;s current food supply could meet the goal of achieving &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; diets. To
demonstrate our methodology, we chose one healthy diet pattern<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and assessed food availability to meet this pattern in one country, Cameroon.</p><p>Adherence to dietary guidance and recommended consumption patterns is associated with
reductions in chronic disease risk and all-cause mortality in adults<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In low-income settings, dietary diversity has been linked to higher
micronutrient density in infant diets and a higher probability of micronutrient adequacy for
adult women<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Diets in low-income countries and communities are often dominated by starchy
staple foods, with much smaller amounts of nutrient-dense foods such as fruits, vegetables,
nuts, beans and animal-source foods<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Compared with most staple foods, these latter foods generally have a higher
nutrient density (amount of critical nutrients per unit of energy). Country-level supply of
starchy cereal and tuber foods is associated with child stunting<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, possibly due to the low micronutrient density of available foods. At the same
time, countries undergoing the &#x02018;nutrition transition&#x02019; are experiencing greater demand for
foods high in fat and sugar, as well as rising rates of obesity and associated chronic
diseases<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Cameroon, the &#x02018;test country&#x02019; used to demonstrate the approach described here, is
among the countries currently experiencing the &#x02018;triple burden&#x02019; of undernutrition,
micronutrient malnutrition and diet-related chronic disease<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. These populations continue to experience undernutrition, including micronutrient
deficiencies, often resulting in the coexistence of over- and undernutrition in the same
households and even at the level of the individual (e.g. a person who is simultaneously obese,
stunted and anaemic)<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Global energy availability per capita is continuing to increase, and is
associated with reduced rates of child stunting and (although non-significant) increased rates
of IHD<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Given that no country to date has reversed its obesity epidemic<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and that rates are growing rapidly even in low-income countries<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref>
<sup>&#x02013;</sup>
<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, addressing obesity-related lifestyle factors, including diet quality, is
necessary in all countries.</p><p>It has been argued that improvements to diet quality offer a sustainable path to addressing
the multiple forms of malnutrition<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Nutrient fortification and supplementation interventions are efficacious in
addressing micronutrient malnutrition, but sustained success at scale depends on external
funding or adequate consumer demand<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Additionally, such interventions do little to address non-communicable diseases
and may even exacerbate non-communicable diseases in instances where the vehicle for
fortification does not support healthy eating patterns (e.g. vitamin A-fortified chocolate
wafers). Dietary improvements similarly require consumer demand and access, but can
simultaneously address the challenges of nutrition-related chronic disease, micronutrient
malnutrition and undernutrition. Dietary change requires contributions from public- and
private-sector actors working in health and agriculture<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and comprehensive policies on health, agriculture and trade that promote healthy
diets in the face of globalization<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>24</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In this context, better understanding of how the current food supply needs to
change may help inform efforts to achieve healthier diets<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Although a universal definition of a healthy diet does not exist, various food-based dietary
guidelines have been issued that translate recommended nutrient intakes into specific
recommendations for foods to consume or avoid for optimal health. Food-based guidelines have
been developed for over 100 countries, including numerous upper- and middle-income countries
but few lower-income countries<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>26</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In developing food-based dietary guidelines, national authorities consider
evidence linking diet and health in the context of national public health issues and
priorities and cultural dietary patterns. Once national health and nutrition priorities have
been identified, locally available, culturally acceptable foods that address nutrient
requirements are identified<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>27</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. While guidelines and particularly specific food items vary across countries,
there are common elements, including recommendations to consume a variety of food groups, to
increase consumption of fruits and vegetables, and to limit consumption of foods associated
with chronic disease risk<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>28</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In addition to national food-based dietary guidelines, other approaches have
included identification of healthful diet patterns at the regional level (e.g. the
Mediterranean diet<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>29</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, the new Nordic diet<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>30</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>) and for reduction in risk of specific non-communicable diseases (e.g. the
Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH) diet<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>31</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>). These diets also include the same elements of diversity, ample fruits and
vegetables, and moderation in consumption of certain foods and ingredients<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>32</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>33</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The global relevance of these common elements is also affirmed in WHO
guidance<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>34</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. For our analysis, we selected the DASH diet pattern as an example because there
is strong evidence (including a randomized trial, albeit in the US context) that it leads to
reductions in multiple biomarkers of chronic disease risk factors<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>35</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> while also meeting nutrient requirements<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>36</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. We selected Cameroon as the &#x02018;test country&#x02019; because we had access to nationally
representative dietary data to guide the categorization of foods commonly consumed in the
local diet into the food groups set forth in the DASH diet, to account for differences in
local food availability and preferences when applying this diet to other contexts.</p><p>The method described in the current paper consists of the following steps: (i) use the DASH
guidelines, which are expressed in numbers of servings per food group, to construct a
reference &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; diet expressed as the average amount of energy to be consumed from each of
seven food groups, per capita, per day; (ii) calculate the quantity of food within each of the
food groups that would be required for all Cameroonians to attain the reference diet; and
(iii) compare the results with national-level data on food supply from FAO Food Balance Sheets
(FBS). This allows us to estimate the &#x02018;gap&#x02019; between the current food supply and that required
to promote health. Although other efforts have focused on global availability of selected
foods<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>37</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and regional<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>38</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and national availability of specific nutrients<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>39</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>40</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, to our knowledge, this is the first attempt to develop an adaptable methodology
that could be used, globally, to identify gaps between national food supplies and an
evidence-based healthy diet pattern. Because our approach uses FAO FBS data to quantify the
food supply, the approach could be extended globally and could incorporate evaluation relative
to other reference diet patterns.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec1-1" sec-type="general"><title>Overview</title><p>To estimate the dietary gap in Cameroon, we: (i) selected energy intake per food group as
the most appropriate metric for comparing the food supply data with the DASH diet
recommendations; (ii) used intake data from Cameroon to select foods commonly consumed in
Cameroon to be included in each of the DASH food groups; (iii) calculated target energy
values for each food group (kcal/capita per d); (iv) used national food supply data to
calculate per capita energy supply for each DASH food group; and (v) compared the national
food supply with target energy values. Each of these steps is described below.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-2" sec-type="general"><title>Rationale for using the DASH diet</title><p>Research preceding the development of the DASH diet assessed the impact of single
nutrients and dietary factors on reducing rates of hypertension. The DASH study was
initiated to evaluate the efficacy of an overall dietary pattern, rather than single
nutrients, for lowering blood pressure<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>31</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The DASH diet was designed to help ensure adequate intakes of both
macronutrients and micronutrients, as described in greater detail elsewhere<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>36</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. It was developed to be consistent with dietary recommendations for the
prevention of cancer, osteoporosis and heart disease<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>41</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, and emphasizes low sodium intake, increased consumption of fruits,
vegetables and wholegrain cereals, and balanced intake of lean meats, poultry, fish, eggs
and low-fat dairy products.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-3" sec-type="general"><title>Rationale for selecting Cameroon as test country</title><p>Like many low- and middle-income countries, Cameroon is experiencing a nutrition
transition, with slightly over half the population now residing in urban areas<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>42</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The <italic>Global Nutrition Report 2015</italic> cites high rates of
stunting in Cameroon among children under the age of 5 years (33 %) and anaemia among
women of reproductive age (41&#x000b7;5 %)<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>43</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, and a nationally representative survey showed that 32 % of women of
reproductive age were overweight (BMI&#x02265;25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) and 11 % were obese (BMI&#x02265;30
kg/m<sup>2</sup>). Overweight and obesity were particularly evident in the two largest
urban areas, where 48 % of women had BMI&#x02265;25 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and 20 % had BMI&#x02265;30
kg/m<sup>2</sup>
<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>44</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Because Cameroon is experiencing the nutrition transition and because data
were available from a 2009 national nutrition survey including dietary intake data that
enabled us to operationalize the DASH diet, Cameroon was a logical choice for a first test
case of the dietary gap approach.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-4" sec-type="general"><title>Selection of energy as the unit of comparison</title><p>The DASH dietary guidelines recommend consuming a specific number of servings of food
from each of seven food groups. To operationalize the DASH recommendations for our
analysis, we chose to convert the recommended number of servings for each food group into
total energy (in kilocalories; 1 kcal=4&#x000b7;184 kJ) from each group, rather than amounts
(grams) per group, to allow for the most appropriate comparison with the data available
from the FBS (described further below). In particular, the FBS data for weight in grams
represent the total amount of food available as it enters the household, including any
non-edible (waste) portion, whereas the values for energy equivalents (kcal from each
food) represent the edible portion only and thus are more appropriate for comparison with
a reference diet that is also based on edible portions.</p><p>We set the target energy content of the reference diet to 2100 kcal (8786 kJ)/capita per
d based on the World Food Programme&#x02019;s estimated energy requirements for populations<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>45</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The World Food Programme&#x02019;s estimate is based on a generic developing-country
profile assuming an adult male weight of 60 kg, an adult female weight of 52 kg and
&#x02018;light&#x02019; physical activity level. Using the World Food Programme&#x02019;s age- and sex-specific
estimates of per capita energy requirements, we calculated a weighted average of daily
energy requirements based on Cameroon&#x02019;s age and sex profile as well as the proportions of
pregnant and lactating women<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>46</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The resulting estimated energy requirement (2040 kcal (8535 kJ)/capita per
d) was similar to the World Food Programme&#x02019;s estimate, so for simplicity we based our
calculations on a 2100 kcal (8786 kJ) reference diet.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-5" sec-type="general"><title>Classification of local foods into reference diet groups</title><p>By presenting a dietary pattern based on food groups, the DASH diet allows flexibility to
select food items within each food group that are preferred based on cultural norms,
tastes, allergies, etc. However, the diversity of foods within each food group complicates
the calculation of a single value for energy content per serving from a food group, which
will depend on the individual food items selected.</p><p>Because the DASH diet was designed based on foods commonly consumed in the USA, assessing
the adequacy of the national food supply in Cameroon to achieve the DASH diet required
populating the DASH food groups with foods consumed in Cameroon. This was accomplished by
first selecting a &#x02018;short list&#x02019; of available and accessible food items in Cameroon to
represent each food group (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>). These items
were identified by examining data from a national survey of dietary intakes of women and
young children in Cameroon<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>47</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Dietary data were collected using an interactive 24 h recall method, with
replicate recalls in a subset of participants. Food items were included in the short list
if they were consumed on at least ~5 % of person-days in the dietary database. Spices,
alcoholic beverages and pastries (from the Grains group) and items in the &#x02018;Sweets and
added sugars&#x02019; food group (refined sugar and chocolate products) were excluded.<table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Description of the reference dietary pattern based on the Dietary Approaches to
Stop Hypertension (DASH) diet and adjusted to include food items that are commonly
consumed in Cameroon</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="S1368980017001173_tab1"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Scenario A, starchy fruits and
vegetables are categorized with other starchy staples</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Scenario B, starchy fruits and
vegetables are categorized with other fruits and vegetables</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DASH food group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated no. of servings/d
recommended by DASH for 2000 kcal (8368 kJ) diet<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tab1fn1">*</xref>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Example serving sizes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;Short list&#x02019; of food items selected
from dietary data set<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tab1fn2">&#x02020;</xref> to represent
food group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of servings/d, adjusted to 2100
kcal (8786 kJ)/capita per d</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average energy content per serving
using Cameroonian food patterns (kcal/serving)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average energy content of food group
per day in Cameroon DASH pattern (kcal/capita per d)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tab1fn3">&#x02021;</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;Short list&#x02019; of food items selected
from dietary data set<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tab1fn2">&#x02020;</xref> to represent
food group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of servings/d, adjusted to 2100
kcal (8786 kJ)/capita per d</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average energy content per serving
using Cameroonian food patterns (kcal/serving)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average energy content of food group
per day in Cameroon DASH pattern, (kcal/d)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tab1fn3">&#x02021;</xref>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dairy</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x000b7;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 cup milk or yoghurt</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh whole cow&#x02019;s milk, powdered cow&#x02019;s
milk, whole yoghurt</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x000b7;5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">162</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">409</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh whole cow&#x02019;s milk, powdered cow&#x02019;s
milk, whole yoghurt</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x000b7;3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">162</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">373</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fats and oils</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x000b7;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 teaspoon of oil or margarine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groundnut, palm, cottonseed and palm
kernel oil; margarine</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x000b7;5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groundnut, palm, cottonseed, and palm
kernel oil; margarine</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x000b7;3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruits</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 medium fruit; &#x000bd; cup fresh fruit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bananas, oranges, lemons/limes, papayas</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bananas, oranges, lemons/limes,
papayas, plantains</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grains (Starchy staples)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x000b7;0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 slice bread; &#x000bd; cup cooked rice, pasta
or cereal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pasta/macaroni, bread, rice, rice
flour, maize, maize flour, millet, millet flour, sorghum, plantains, Irish
potatoes, sweet potatoes, cassava, yam, taro, cocoyam</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x000b7;1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">813</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pasta/macaroni, bread, rice, rice
flour, maize, maize flour, millet, millet flour, sorghum</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x000b7;4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">752</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meat, poultry, fish and eggs</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x000b7;0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 oz (28&#x000b7;35 g) cooked meat or fish; 1
egg</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish (ocean and freshwater),
crustaceans, beef, sheep meat, goat meat, pork, chicken eggs</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x000b7;1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish (ocean and freshwater),
crustaceans, beef, sheep meat, goat meat, pork, chicken eggs</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">273</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuts, seeds and legumes</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000bd; cup cooked legumes, 2 tablespoons
seeds</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beans, cowpeas, groundnuts, groundnut
paste, melon seed</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;7&#x000a7;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beans, cowpeas, groundnuts, groundnut
paste, melon seed</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;7<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tab1fn4">&#x000a7;</xref>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetables</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000bd; cup cooked vegetable</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomatoes, onions, leeks, okra, cassava
leaves, string beans, carrots, other vegetables (green leafy vegetables)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomatoes, onions, leeks, okra, cassava
leaves, string beans, carrots, other vegetables (green leafy vegetables),
Irish potatoes, sweet potatoes, cassava, yam, taro, cocoyam</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b7;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">272</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total kcal/d</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2100</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>1 kcal=4&#x000b7;184 kJ.</p></fn><fn id="tab1fn1"><label>*</label><p>See FAO<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>53</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p></fn><fn id="tab1fn2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>See Engle-Stone <italic>et al</italic>.<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>44</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p></fn><fn id="tab1fn3"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>Some values may differ from the product of the previous two columns due to
rounding of the average kcal/serving.</p></fn><fn id="tab1fn4"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p>Calculated from 5 servings/week. The adjusted (2100 kcal (8786 kJ)) value is
slightly lower but rounds to 0&#x000b7;7 servings/d.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>Then, we classified each food on the short list into one of the seven DASH groups. For
most foods, classification was straightforward (dairy, fats and oils, grains, meat and
nuts/seeds/legumes). However, definitions of fruit and vegetable groups historically have
varied depending on context and objective<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>48</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In the broadest definition, &#x02018;vegetable&#x02019; could refer to any edible plant.
More commonly, grains and legumes/nuts/seeds are grouped separately. Classifications of
roots and tubers such as white potatoes, sweet potatoes and yams have varied depending on
cultural context and the purpose of the classification. Some have advocated excluding all
roots and tubers from the vegetable category<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>49</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and some have also excluded plantains from the fruit category<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>50</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>51</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The rationale for these exclusions is that these foods are different from
other fruits and vegetables in both nutrient content and culinary use, and typically
function as &#x02018;starchy staples&#x02019; in the areas where they are consumed. However, in the DASH
diet, white potatoes are classified as a vegetable. Because the DASH diet was designed to
include only foods commonly consumed in the USA, there is no mention in the original DASH
diet description of other roots and tubers commonly consumed in tropical countries nor is
there mention of plantains<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>52</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. We took two approaches to classifying roots, tubers and plantains in order
to illustrate the impact of these classifications on assessment of the adequacy of the
national supply of fruits and vegetables. In the first scenario, we included plantains and
all roots and tubers (white potato, sweet potato, yam, taro and cocoyam) in the &#x02018;Starchy
staples&#x02019; category (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>, Scenario A). In the
second scenario, plantains were classified as fruits, and all roots and tubers were
classified as vegetables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>, Scenario B).</p><p>We also had to decide how to treat dairy products, as the DASH diet recommends
consumption of low-fat dairy products but these products are scarce in Cameroon. In the
interest of constructing a food list reflective of available products, we retained the
full-fat products in the dairy group.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-6" sec-type="general"><title>Calculation of target energy intake from each food group</title><p>To calculate the target energy intake from each food group, we began by calculating the
serving size in grams of each food item on the short list according to DASH portion sizes,
which differ for different items within a food group. Then, for each food item we
calculated the energy content per serving. Next, we averaged the energy content per
serving for all foods within a food group, and then multiplied this value by the total
number of servings recommended in the DASH pattern to yield the target energy per food
group (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>). Average serving sizes were
extracted from DASH guidance documents<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>53</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and converted into grams using information from the US Department of
Agriculture&#x02019;s nutrient database<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>54</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Energy values were obtained from the West African Food Composition
Tables<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>55</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> where available; remaining values not present in the West African Food
Composition Table were obtained from the US Department of Agriculture&#x02019;s database<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>54</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The target number of servings per food group per day was based on the DASH dietary
pattern for a 2000 kcal (8368 kJ) diet<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>53</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, although these are presented as ranges for many foods and thus require some
interpretation. Specifically, for food groups for which a range was presented, the average
value was used. We used values of 5&#x000b7;0 servings/d for meat (&#x02018;6 or less servings per day&#x02019;)
and 0&#x000b7;7 servings/d for nuts, seeds and legumes (&#x02018;4&#x02013;5 servings per week&#x02019;). The small
serving size for meat should be noted: DASH specifies 1 oz (28&#x000b7;35 g) servings. This number
of servings per day yielded a total energy content of 2079 kcal (8698 kJ)/d for the first
scenario (classifying starchy fruits and vegetables with other starchy staples) and 2280
kcal (9540 kJ)/d for the second scenario (classifying starchy fruits and vegetables with
other fruits and vegetables). Rather than recommend a higher or lower energy intake than
the estimated population requirement of 2100 kcal (8786 kJ)/capita per d (described
above), and to facilitate comparison between the two scenarios for the reference diet, we
adjusted the number of servings by multiplying the number of servings suggested in the
DASH 2000 kcal (8368 kJ)/capita per d plan by the ratio of 2100 kcal (8786 kJ)/2079 kcal
(8698 kJ) and 2100 kcal (8786 kJ)/2280 kcal (9540 kJ), respectively, to achieve a total
energy content of 2100 kcal (8786 kJ)/capita per d for each version of the reference diet
(<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec1-7" sec-type="general"><title>Calculation of per capita energy supply using national data</title><p>For each of the seven DASH food groups, the per capita availability in the national food
supply was estimated based on 2011 country-level data for Cameroon from the FBS<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>56</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The FAO calculates the quantity (metric tons) of food available for human
consumption as the total supply (total quantity produced in country plus total quantity
imported) minus quantities exported, fed to livestock, used for seed, used for industrial
purposes, and lost during storage and transportation<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>57</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Per capita food supply estimates (kg/person) are then calculated by dividing
the quantity of food available for human consumption by the population size. Finally, the
per capita quantity of food available for human consumption is converted to kcal/capita
per d by multiplying the edible portion of the per capita weight by its energy value
indicated in food composition tables.</p><p>To calculate the per capita daily energy supply, we first assigned the food commodities
listed in the 2011 Cameroon FBS to the seven DASH food groups. Next, we summed the energy
supply of each food commodity as reported in the FBS (kcal/capita per d) for each of the
seven food groups and for the total of all seven groups. As for the reference diet, we
constructed separate scenarios with starchy fruits and vegetables categorized along with
grains, or with their respective fruit and vegetable groups. Food commodities reported in
the FBS that were not included in the DASH pattern (e.g. sugar, alcoholic beverages,
coffee and spices) were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-8" sec-type="general"><title>Comparison of the national food supply with the reference diet</title><p>The energy supply (kcal/capita per d) for each food group was then compared with our
calculations of target energy intake for the two scenarios described above. For each food
group, the dietary gap was calculated as the energy available in the food supply minus the
target energy intake.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec2"><title>Results</title><p>The per capita daily energy supply of foods in the Cameroon 2011 food supply is depicted in
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>. The foods that provided the largest amounts
of energy were maize and cassava, providing 324 and 279 kcal (1356 and 1167 kJ)/capita per
d, respectively. Other grains such as sorghum, rice and wheat were also major sources of
energy. Among the fats and oils, palm oil was the predominant item (128 kcal (536 kJ)/capita
per d). Among fruits, plantains provided more energy than all other fruits combined.<fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Per capita daily energy supply of foods in the 2011 Cameroon food supply (1
kcal=4&#x000b7;184 kJ)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S1368980017001173_fig1"/></fig>
</p><p>The Cameroon food supply is compared with the DASH reference diet for the two scenarios on
a per capita daily energy basis in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref> and as a
percentage of the DASH reference diet amounts in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.
2</xref>. For both scenarios, the largest deficit in the food supply was for dairy products:
the deficit was 346&#x02013;382 kcal (1148&#x02013;1598 kJ)/capita per d and the supply provided only ~7 %
of the energy from dairy recommended in the DASH diet. The second largest gap in the food
supply was for meat/poultry/fish/eggs: the deficit was 161&#x02013;188 kcal (674&#x02013;787 kJ)/capita per
d and the supply was 37&#x02013;41 % of recommended in the DASH diet. In Scenario A (with starchy
fruits and vegetables categorized in the starchy staples group) there were deficits of 111
and 96 kcal (464 and 402 kJ)/capita per d for fruits and vegetables, respectively, and an
excess of 679 kcal (2841 kJ)/capita per d for starchy staples. By contrast, in Scenario B
(with starchy fruits and vegetables categorized in their respective fruit and vegetable
groups), the deficit for fruits was only 29 kcal (121 kJ)/capita per d and there was an
excess of 211 kcal (883 kJ)/capita per d for &#x02018;vegetables&#x02019;; the excess of energy for starchy
staples was reduced to 209 kcal (874 kJ)/capita per d. In both scenarios, the largest
excesses in terms of percentage of the recommended DASH reference diet amounts were for the
fats/oils and legumes/nuts/seeds groups, for which the supply was 250&#x02013;300 % of the DASH
reference diet amounts. Although there was an excess of energy available from fats and oils,
53 % came from palm oil. Other major sources of fats and oils included groundnut oil,
cottonseed oil and animal fat. None of these provides a good source of <italic>n</italic>-3
fatty acids, which are important for good health<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>58</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.<fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Gaps in the 2011 Cameroon food supply compared with the Dietary Approaches to Stop
Hypertension (DASH) reference diet pattern: <inline-graphic xlink:href="S1368980017001173_inline1.jpg" mime-subtype="gif"/>, Scenario A;
<inline-graphic xlink:href="S1368980017001173_inline2.jpg" mime-subtype="gif"/>, Scenario B. Gaps are expressed as a
percentage of the DASH reference diet pattern provided by the food supply. Scenario A
categorizes starchy fruit (plantains) and vegetables (potatoes, cassava, etc.) as
starchy staples. Scenario B categorizes starchy fruit and vegetables in their
respective fruit and vegetable groups</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S1368980017001173_fig2"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of daily per capita energy of Cameroon food supply with the Dietary
Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH) reference diet patterns derived for
Cameroon</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="S1368980017001173_tab2"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="2">Scenario A, starchy fruits and
vegetables categorized with starchy staples</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="2">Scenario B, starchy fruits and
vegetables categorized with fruits and vegetables</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Energy supply (kcal/capita per d)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Energy gap<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tab2fn1">*</xref> (kcal/capita per d)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Energy supply (kcal/capita per d)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Energy gap<xref ref-type="fn" rid="tab2fn1">*</xref> (kcal/capita per d)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dairy</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;382</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;346</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fats and oils</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">242</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">242</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruits</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;111</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grains (Starchy staples)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1492</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">679</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">961</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meat, poultry, fish and eggs</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;188</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;161</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuts, seeds and legumes</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">329</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">212</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">329</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">222</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetables</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;96</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">483</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2358</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">258</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2358</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">258</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>1 kcal=4&#x000b7;184 kJ.</p></fn><fn id="tab2fn1"><label>*</label><p>Difference between the food supply and the Cameroon DASH reference diet
pattern.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>In addition to assessing differences in the dietary gap identified by our methods based on
the way roots, tubers and plantains are classified (Scenarios A and B), we also explored the
sensitivity of our methods to the type of dairy products that were selected to populate the
dairy group. In particular, we substituted low-fat dairy products (1&#x000b7;5 % fat milk and
low-fat yoghurt) in place of whole-fat dairy products in the DASH reference diet, given the
limited availability and consumption of low-fat dairy products in Cameroon. If full-fat
dairy foods were replaced with low-fat versions, the deficit in the dairy product supply in
Cameroon would decrease by about 70 kcal (293 kJ)/capita per d, remaining very large
(&#x0003e;200 kcal (&#x0003e;837 kJ)/capita per d). The gaps for the other food groups would
change only slightly because the reduction in energy from dairy products in the low-fat
dairy DASH reference diet pattern would be offset by slight increases in energy from all of
the other food groups (to total to the target of 2100 kcal (8786 kJ)/capita per d).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p>We developed a methodology to assess the adequacy of a national food supply with respect to
a healthy dietary pattern. Application of this method to a test country, Cameroon, revealed
large gaps in availability of animal-source foods, with a deficit of ~350&#x02013;380 kcal
(~1464&#x02013;1590 kJ)/capita per d for dairy products and another ~160&#x02013;190 kcal (~669&#x02013;795
kJ)/capita per d for meat, poultry, fish and eggs. When roots, tubers and plantains were
categorized in the starchy staples group, there were deficits of ~100 kcal (~418 kJ)/capita
per d for vegetables and ~110 kcal (~460 kJ)/capita per d for fruits, and an excess of ~680
kcal (~2845 kJ)/capita per d for starchy staples. When roots and tubers were categorized as
vegetables and plantains were categorized as fruits, the deficit for &#x02018;vegetables&#x02019;
disappeared and the deficit for &#x02018;fruits&#x02019; was reduced to ~30 kcal (~126 kJ)/capita per d.
However, from a dietary perspective, classifying roots, tubers and plantains with grains is
more appropriate because of the way these foods are typically consumed (as starchy staples
rather than as side dishes) and their nutrient profile.</p><p>We selected the DASH diet as our reference diet because its efficacy for health promotion
is based on evidence from a randomized intervention trial (albeit from a single country) and
the recommendations are general enough to allow tailoring of specific foods within each food
group to reflect local food preferences and supply. Similarly rigorous evidence for the
potential health-promoting effects of major adaptations of the DASH diet (e.g. for a
vegetarian version or one that is significantly more plant-based) is not yet available,
making it challenging to identify an alternative to the DASH diet for broader use. It could
be argued that some of the gaps identified for certain food groups may reflect the cultural
context in which the DASH diet was developed (e.g. relatively high suggested intake of dairy
products and lower consumption of nuts, seeds and legumes when compared with a diet more
typical of West Africa), as discussed below. In general, however, our results reveal a food
supply for Cameroon with, on average, adequate energy availability but shortfalls in the
supply of foods that are micronutrient-dense. Because the DASH diet was developed with a
focus on reduction in chronic disease risk, but micronutrient deficiencies are still
prevalent in countries such as Cameroon, we conducted an exploratory analysis (see online
supplementary material) to confirm whether the constructed healthy diet would improve
adequacy of intake of five key micronutrients (vitamin A, vitamin B<sub>12</sub>, folate, Zn
and Fe). We found that the hypothetical diet would greatly reduce the predicted prevalence
of inadequate micronutrient intakes, compared with individual dietary intake data collected
from women in a nationally representative dietary survey in Cameroon. Other analyses of FBS
data suggest inadequate micronutrient density of the available food supply in Cameroon and
elsewhere in sub-Saharan Africa, which is consistent with our observation of gaps in the
supply of fruits, vegetables and animal-source foods<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>38</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>39</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Analyses of available Zn in the food supply conducted by Wessells and
Brown<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>39</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and Arsenault <italic>et al</italic>.<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>40</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> revealed a high prevalence of inadequate Zn availability (33 %) for Cameroon.
FBS analyses by Arsenault <italic>et al</italic>. also predicted a high prevalence of
inadequate vitamin A intakes in Cameroon, but not for folate and several other
micronutrients<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>40</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. However, these analyses assessed nutrient inadequacies rather than the overall
dietary pattern.</p><p>There are several limitations associated with the methodology and data we used to estimate
the dietary gap between a country&#x02019;s food supply and the food that would be required for its
population to achieve a &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; diet. First, recommended food group consumption in the
DASH diet and other food-based dietary guidelines is often expressed as a range of servings.
We used the approximate midpoint of this range to operationalize the diet; future work could
incorporate sensitivity analyses using both low and high values. Second, identifying a
reference diet that is both widely culturally appropriate/adaptable as well as
evidence-based is a challenge. Because the DASH diet was originally developed for
application in the USA and thus reflects the dietary preferences of Americans, the
recommended amounts for each food group (i.e. number of servings and/or serving sizes) may
not be appropriate globally. For example, the DASH diet includes 85&#x02013;170 g of lean meats,
poultry and fish daily. When populated with foods commonly consumed in Cameroon and under
the conservative assumptions that all dairy products are low-fat and all fats and oils are
from plant sources, the DASH diet includes ~33 % of energy from animal-source foods. This is
well above the estimated national availability of energy from animal-source foods in
Cameroon, which is approximately 6 %<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>56</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, and estimated intakes of animal-source foods among women and children (~7&#x02013;9 %
of total energy)<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>59</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In addition, research on the environmental and health impacts of intensive
production and consumption of animal-source foods has sparked global dialogue on sustainable
diets. It is possible that diets with a lower percentage of energy from animal-source foods
may adequately promote health and be more affordable, culturally appropriate and sustainable
in some settings. Another example is that the recommended consumption of nuts, seeds and
legumes in the DASH diet is only three to five servings weekly. Given that there are health
advantages to frequent consumption of legumes<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>60</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and nuts in particular<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>61</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>62</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, a reference &#x02018;healthy diet&#x02019; that incorporates at least one serving daily from
this food group may be more appropriate. This may also make the reference &#x02018;healthy diet&#x02019; a
better fit for countries like Cameroon where legumes and seeds, such as groundnuts and
squash or pumpkin seeds, are frequently consumed.</p><p>To address some of these issues, we made a rough comparison between the hypothetical DASH
diet for Cameroon and the recently published Benin Food Guide, which aimed to contribute to
national efforts to &#x02018;halt the progression of chronic diseases while ensuring adequate intake
to prevent deficiencies&#x02019;<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>63</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The guide was developed using linear programming to identify optimal amounts
of foods per food group that could meet both nutrient requirements and dietary guidelines,
while being consistent with local food habits<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>64</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. These amounts were then expressed as a daily number of servings, giving
serving size examples. Given that the publicly available food guide includes only a few
suggested foods, we were not able to completely translate the recommendations to perform a
quantitative analysis as we did with the DASH diet. However, for a rough comparison we
converted the recommended number of servings in each food group of the Benin Food Guide to
the approximate amount of energy from each food group, and adjusted the resulting diet to
total 2100 kcal (8786 kJ). In terms of dietary gaps, the two patterns result in similar
supply shortfalls of fruits and vegetables. The Benin Food Guide places both plant- and
animal-source protein-rich foods into a single food group and thus allows for meeting
recommendations for that food group without consuming any animal-source foods; this means
that the gap in meat, poultry, fish and eggs identified using DASH would be eliminated.
There would still be a gap in dairy products using the Benin Food Guide, but it would be
about half the size of the gap identified using the DASH diet. Thus, if using the Benin Food
Guide, certain gaps would be less evident or smaller. However, it is not clear whether this
approach would result in similar health benefits as following a DASH-type diet because no
intervention trials have been conducted based on the Benin Food Guide (which is the case for
all national food-based dietary guidelines to date). For example, it is likely that without
requiring any animal-source foods in the &#x02018;protein&#x02019; food group, intakes of certain
micronutrients would be lower (e.g. Ca, Fe, Zn, vitamin B<sub>12</sub>), with potential
implications for some health outcomes. Ideally, intervention studies for dietary patterns
adapted for specific countries would be tested in settings for which they are intended.
However, due to the cost and complexity of such studies, it will be necessary to take steps
to address the growing burden of chronic diseases in low-income settings before such
information is available.</p><p>Several limitations of the FBS data also merit note because of potential implications for
the accuracy and application of our estimates<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>65</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. First, the FAO estimates of the quantity of food available for human
consumption may not fully or accurately capture non-commercial or subsistence production,
which can be substantial in developing countries. Second, the estimates do not account for
wastage at the household level (e.g. losses during household storage or food preparation, as
feed for domestic animals/pets, etc.). Finally, the FBS data do not allow for analysis of
seasonal or geographic differences in the food supply, nor do they account for variability
in access and utilization by gender, age and socio-economic status subgroups<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>66</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Because the data are provided at the country level and at an annual time step,
food distribution, access and utilization issues are not reflected in our analysis, and our
estimates represent the annual average amount of energy available per person per day.
Despite these limitations, the FBS data are of great utility because they are made publicly
available on an annual basis for a very comprehensive set of countries and the methods used
to estimate national-level food supplies are, to the extent possible, fairly consistent
across countries<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>39</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>40</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. While dietary gaps can be assessed using household- or individual-level food
consumption data, which allow for disaggregation, these data are influenced by many factors
such as preferences and economic access and do not directly represent national food
availability.</p><p>The &#x02018;dietary gap assessment&#x02019; approach described herein can be expanded to other countries
using available information on commonly consumed foods to compile appropriate food groupings
for a country-specific DASH pattern. We used Cameroon as a case study because we had access
to recent individual-level nationally representative dietary intake information in order to
populate the DASH food groups with country-specific foods, but this type of information is
not available for most countries. Another potential source of information on commonly
consumed foods are nationally representative household consumption and expenditure surveys
which are conducted in many developing countries by government statistical services or
through the World Bank&#x02019;s Living Standards Measurement Study, usually more widely and
frequently than individual-level consumption studies. Household consumption and expenditure
surveys typically include a list of foods known to be consumed in the country and
respondents are asked how much of each food the household acquired and/or consumed during
some reference period. Other options include more disaggregated data available from FAOSTAT
on production and trade amounts of foods for each country, although these data are somewhat
limited in completeness, or published reports from local dietary intake assessments.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusions and implications</title><p>Many countries are likely to have large gaps in supply of animal-source foods, fruits and
vegetables relative to the amounts needed to achieve &#x02018;healthy diet&#x02019; patterns. Some of these
gaps are evident even in high-income countries. For example, in the USA, analyses of the
food supply conducted over the course of several decades have repeatedly demonstrated
inadequate supply of fruits and vegetables to meet US Government dietary
recommendations<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>67</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>68</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Similarly, Siegel <italic>et al</italic>. documented inadequate supply of
fruits and vegetables at the global level<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>37</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Concern regarding the ability of the food system to nourish a growing population has
precipitated numerous scientific and high-level meetings<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>69</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Although there needs to be continued attention to the overall adequacy of the
global food supply to meet energy needs, a focus on staple food production will not address
the need for greater dietary diversity and healthier dietary patterns<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>70</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The type of analysis presented in the current paper highlights the need for and can help
inform the development of strategies to increase both the supply and demand for the foods
needed for a healthy diet. Action is needed on several fronts, including increased
production, increased demand and reduced post-harvest losses and other wastage, accompanied
by broader strategies aimed at reducing inequity in access to affordable healthy foods.
Country-level dietary gap analysis, as illustrated herein, could provide a useful
contribution to ongoing policy dialogues on agricultural and food system priorities. This
information may be particularly useful in discussions related to policies and investments
that promote improved production of and access to more diverse foods<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, and would complement existing economic and ecological analyses that support
the benefit of greater diversification<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>71</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ref72" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>72</sup>
</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>
<italic>Financial support:</italic> This work was supported by funding provided by a grant
from the Bill &#x00026; Melinda Gates Foundation to the University of California, Davis,
World Food Center. The Bill &#x00026; Melinda Gates Foundation had no role in the design,
analysis or writing of this article. <italic>Conflict of interest:</italic> The authors
declare no known conflicts of interest. <italic>Authorship:</italic> This research was
conceptually initiated by K.G.D. and further designed in collaboration with all of the
co-authors. K.P.A., J.E.A., R.E.-S. and M.A. conducted data analysis. All authors
contributed to writing the manuscript, and E.M.K. and K.G.D. coordinated the process.
<italic>Ethics of human subject participation:</italic> Not applicable.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec5"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1368980017001173sup001"><p>For supplementary material accompanying this paper visit http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S1368980017001173.</p><media xlink:href="S1368980017001173sup001.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1958" position="anchor"><caption><p>click here to view supplementary material</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list id="refs"><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &#x00026; World
Health Organization (2014) Rome Declaration on Nutrition. Second International Conference
on Nutrition, Rome, 19&#x02013;21 November 2014. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/3/a-ml542e.pdf">http://www.fao.org/3/a-ml542e.pdf</uri> (accessed May 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (1996) Rome
Declaration on World Food Security. World Food Summit, 13&#x02013;17 November 1996, Rome, Italy.
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/docrep/003/w3613e/w3613e00.htm">http://www.fao.org/docrep/003/w3613e/w3613e00.htm</uri> (accessed May
2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Herforth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The food environment, its effects on dietary
consumption, and potential for measurement within agricultural-nutrition
interventions</article-title>. <source>Food Secur</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>520</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (2016) Supply
Utilization Accounts and Food Balance Sheets: background information for your better
understanding. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/economic/the-statistics-division-ess/methodology/methodology-systems/supply-utilization-accounts-and-food-balance-sheets-background-information-for-your-better-understanding/en/">http://www.fao.org/economic/the-statistics-division-ess/methodology/methodology-systems/supply-utilization-accounts-and-food-balance-sheets-background-information-for-your-better-understanding/en/</uri>
(accessed September 2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Obarzanek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Dietary Approaches to Stop
Hypertension: rationale, design, and methods. DASH Collaborative Research
Group</article-title>. <source>J Am Diet Assoc</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <issue>Suppl. 8</issue>,
<fpage>S12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10450289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Struijk</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>May</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wezenbeek</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Adherence to dietary guidelines and
cardiovascular disease risk in the EPIC-NL cohort</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source>
<volume>176</volume>, <fpage>354</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>359</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25107447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jankovic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geelen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Streppel</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>WHO guidelines for a healthy diet
and mortality from cardiovascular disease in European and American elderly: the CHANCES
project</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>756</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26354545</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Arimond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiesmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Becquey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Simple food group diversity
indicators predict micronutrient adequacy of women&#x02019;s diets in 5 diverse, resource-poor
settings</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>
<volume>140</volume>, issue <issue>11</issue>,
<fpage>2059S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2069S</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20881077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, International Fund for
Agricultural Development &#x00026; World Food Programme</collab> (<year>2013</year>)
<source>The State of Food Insecurity in the World 2013: The Multiple Dimensions of Food
Security</source>. <publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name>; available at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/docrep/018/i3434e/i3434e.pdf">http://www.fao.org/docrep/018/i3434e/i3434e.pdf</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Montiero</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Stunting is associated with overweight in
children of four nations that are undergoing the nutrition transition</article-title>.
<source>J Nutr</source>
<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>3009</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3016</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9001368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Gordon-Larsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The nutrition transition: worldwide obesity
dynamics and their determinants</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <issue>Suppl. 3</issue>,
<fpage>S2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15543214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Post-green revolution food systems
and the triple burden of malnutrition</article-title>. <source>Food Policy</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vorster</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Margetts</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The nutrition transition in Africa: can it be
steered into a more positive direction?</article-title>
<source>Nutrients</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>441</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22254104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dangour</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Global dietary quality,
undernutrition and non-communicable disease: a longitudinal modelling
study</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e009331</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Roberto</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swinburn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Patchy progress on obesity
prevention: emerging examples, entrenched barriers, and new thinking</article-title>.
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>385</volume>, <fpage>2400</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2409</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25703111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Global, regional, and national
prevalence of overweight and obesity in children and adults during 1980&#x02013;2013: a
systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study</article-title>.
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>384</volume>, <fpage>766</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>781</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>NCD Risk Factor Collaboration</collab> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Trends
in adult body-mass index in 200 countries from 1975 to 2014: a pooled analysis of 1698
population-based measurement studies with 19.2 million participants</article-title>.
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>387</volume>, <fpage>1377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1396</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27115820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>NCD Risk Factor Collaboration</collab> (<year>2016</year>)
<article-title>Worldwide trends in diabetes since 1980: a pooled analysis of 751
population-based studies with 4.4 million participants</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>387</volume>, <fpage>1513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1530</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27061677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jaacks</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slining</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Recent underweight and overweight trends by
rural&#x02013;urban residence among women in low- and middle-income countries</article-title>.
<source>J Nutr</source>
<volume>145</volume>, <fpage>352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>357</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25644358</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Suchdev</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jefferds</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Sustainability of market-based
community distribution of Sprinkles in western Kenya</article-title>. <source>Matern
Child Nutr</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <issue>Suppl. 1</issue>,
<fpage>S78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Darnton-Hill</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Nalubola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Fortification strategies to meet micronutrient
needs: successes and failures</article-title>. <source>Proc Nutr Soc</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12133205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maundu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Agricultural biodiversity as a link
between traditional food systems and contemporary development, social integrity and
ecological health</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric</source>
<volume>93</volume>, <issue>Suppl. 1</issue>,
<fpage>S3433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S3442</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fanzo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Cogill</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Understanding sustainable diets: a descriptive
analysis of the determinants and processes that influence diets and their impact on
health, food security, and environmental sustainability</article-title>. <source>Adv
Nutr</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>418</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>429</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25022991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Uneven dietary development: linking the
policies and processes of globalization with the nutrition transition, obesity and
diet-related chronic diseases</article-title>. <source>Global Health</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16569239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Kantor</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <chapter-title>A comparison of the US food supply with the
Food Guide Pyramid recommendations</chapter-title> In <source><italic>America&#x02019;s Eating Habits: Changes and Consequences</italic>. <italic>Agriculture
Information Bulletin</italic></source>, no. AIB-750, pp. <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage> [E Fraz&#x000e3;o, editor].
<publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>DC: US Department of
Agriculture, Economic Research Service</publisher-name>; available at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.ers.usda.gov/webdocs/publications/42215/5833_aib750d_1_.pdf?v=41055">https://www.ers.usda.gov/webdocs/publications/42215/5833_aib750d_1_.pdf?v=41055</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (2016)
Food-based dietary guidelines. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/nutrition/education/food-dietary-guidelines/home/en/">http://www.fao.org/nutrition/education/food-dietary-guidelines/home/en/</uri> (accessed
July 2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations &#x00026; World
Health Organization (1998) <italic>Preparation and Use of Food-Based Dietary Guidelines.
Report of a Joint FAO/WHO Consultation. WHO Technical Report Series</italic> no. 880.
Geneva: WHO; available at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://whqlibdoc.who.int/trs/WHO_TRS_880.pdf">http://whqlibdoc.who.int/trs/WHO_TRS_880.pdf</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <chapter-title>Dietary standards and guidelines: similarities
and differences among countries</chapter-title> In <source>Present Knowledge in
Nutrition</source>, <edition>10th ed</edition>, pp.
<fpage>1110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1134</lpage> [JW Erdman, editor]. <publisher-loc>Hoboken,
NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sofi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Macchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abbate</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Mediterranean diet and health
status: an updated meta-analysis and a proposal for a literature-based adherence
score</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nutr</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>2769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2782</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24476641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mithril</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dragsted</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Guidelines for the New Nordic
Diet</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nutr</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1941</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1947</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22251407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sacks</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A dietary approach to prevent
hypertension: a review of the Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH)
Study</article-title>. <source>Clin Cardiol</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <issue>Suppl. 3</issue>,
<fpage>S6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boushey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shvetsov</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Associations of key diet-quality
indexes with mortality in the Multiethnic Cohort: the Dietary Patterns Methods
Project</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>597</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25733644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mozaffarian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Dietary and policy priorities for
cardiovascular disease, diabetes, and obesity: a comprehensive review</article-title>.
<source>Circulation</source>
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26746178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
World Health Organization (2015) Healthy diet. Fact sheet no. 394. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs394/en/">http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs394/en/</uri> (accessed July
2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Siervo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Effects of the Dietary Approach to
Stop Hypertension (DASH) diet on cardiovascular risk factors: a systematic review and
meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>
<volume>113</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25430608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karanja</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Validation of diet composition for
the Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension trial. DASH Collaborative Research
Group</article-title>. <source>J Am Diet Assoc</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <issue>Suppl. 8</issue>,
<fpage>S60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S68</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10450296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Srinivasiah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Do we produce enough fruits and
vegetables to meet global health need?</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e104059</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25099121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Joy</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ander</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Dietary mineral supplies in
Africa</article-title>. <source>Physiol Plant</source>
<volume>151</volume>, <fpage>208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24524331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wessells</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Estimating the global prevalence of zinc
deficiency: results based on zinc availability in national food supplies and the
prevalence of stunting</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e50568</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23209782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hijmans</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Improving nutrition security through
agriculture: an analytical framework based on national food balance sheets to estimate
nutrition adequacy of food supplies</article-title>. <source>Food Secur</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>707</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Harsha</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Obarzanek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Dietary Approaches to Stop
Hypertension: a summary of study results. DASH Collaborative Research
Group</article-title>. <source>J Am Diet Assoc</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <issue>Suppl. 8</issue>,
<fpage>S35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10450292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
World Bank (2015) Urban population (% of total). <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.URB.TOTL.IN.ZS?view=chart">http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.URB.TOTL.IN.ZS?view=chart</uri> (accessed
September 2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>International Food Policy Research Institute</collab> (<year>2015</year>)
<source>Global Nutrition Report 2015: Actions and Accountability to Advance Nutrition
and Sustainable Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>IFPRI</publisher-name>; available at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2499/9780896298835">http://dx.doi.org/10.2499/9780896298835</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<name><surname>Engle-Stone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ndjebayi</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nankap</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) Prevalence of obesity and elevated waist-to-hip
ratio among a national sample of women of reproductive age in Cameroon, and change from
2009 to 2012 in urban areas. Poster presented at <italic>Experimental Biology
2015</italic>, Boston, MA, USA, 28 March&#x02013;1 April 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, UNICEF, World Food Programme
<italic>et al</italic>.</collab> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Food and Nutrition Needs
in Emergencies</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>; available at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/nutrition/publications/emergencies/a83743/en/">http://www.who.int/nutrition/publications/emergencies/a83743/en/</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Republic of Cameroon (2010) La population du Cameroun en 2010. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.statistics-cameroon.org/downloads/La_population_du_Cameroun_2010.pdf">http://www.statistics-cameroon.org/downloads/La_population_du_Cameroun_2010.pdf</uri>
(accessed August 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Engle-Stone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ndjebayi</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nankap</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Consumption of potentially
fortifiable foods by women and young children varies by ecological zone and
socio-economic status in Cameroon</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>
<volume>142</volume>, <fpage>555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>565</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22323765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Agudo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Measuring Intake of Fruit and Vegetables</source>.
<publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>; available
at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/dietphysicalactivity/publications/f&#x00026;v_intake_measurement.pdf">http://www.who.int/dietphysicalactivity/publications/f&#x00026;v_intake_measurement.pdf</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Cancer Research Fund &#x00026; American Institute for Cancer
Research</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Food, Nutrition, Physical Activity, and the
Prevention of Cancer: A Global Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington,
DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AICR</publisher-name>; available at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.aicr.org/assets/docs/pdf/reports/Second_Expert_Report.pdf">http://www.aicr.org/assets/docs/pdf/reports/Second_Expert_Report.pdf</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Indicators for
Assessing Infant and Young Child Feeding Practices. Part II: Measurement</source>.
<publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>; available
at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/nutrition/publications/infantfeeding/9789241599290/en/">http://www.who.int/nutrition/publications/infantfeeding/9789241599290/en/</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (2011)
Guidelines for measuring household and individual dietary diversity. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/fileadmin/user_upload/wa_workshop/docs/FAO-guidelines-dietary-diversity2011.pdf">http://www.fao.org/fileadmin/user_upload/wa_workshop/docs/FAO-guidelines-dietary-diversity2011.pdf</uri>
(accessed July 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Karanja</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Obarzanek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Descriptive characteristics of the
dietary patterns used in the Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension Trial. DASH
Collaborative Research Group</article-title>. <source>J Am Diet Assoc</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <issue>Suppl. 8</issue>,
<fpage>S19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10450290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
US Department of Health and Human Services, National Heart, Lung, and
Blood Institute (2006) In Brief: Your guide to lowering your blood pressure with DASH.
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/files/docs/public/heart/dash_brief.pdf">https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/files/docs/public/heart/dash_brief.pdf</uri> (accessed June
2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
US Department of Agriculture (2011) National Nutrient Database for
Standard Reference, Release 27. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ndb.nal.usda.gov/">http://ndb.nal.usda.gov/</uri> (accessed August
2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</collab>
(<year>2012</year>) <source>West African Food Composition Table</source>.
<publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name>; available at
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/docrep/015/i2698b/i2698b00.pdf">http://www.fao.org/docrep/015/i2698b/i2698b00.pdf</uri>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (2011) Food
Balance Sheets. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/faostat/en/#data/FBS">http://www.fao.org/faostat/en/#data/FBS</uri> (accessed July
2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (2001) Food
Balance Sheets: a handbook. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/docrep/003/x9892e/x9892e00.htm">http://www.fao.org/docrep/003/x9892e/x9892e00.htm</uri> (accessed July
2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Calder</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Yaqoob</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids and human
health outcomes</article-title>. <source>Biofactors</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>266</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19391122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shahab-Ferdows</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Engle-Stone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hampel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Regional, socioeconomic, and
dietary risk factors for vitamin B-12 deficiency differ from those for folate deficiency
in Cameroonian women and children</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>
<volume>145</volume>, <fpage>2587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2595</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26446486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rebello</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greenway</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Finley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A review of the nutritional value of legumes
and their effects on obesity and its related co-morbidities</article-title>.
<source>Obes Rev</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>392</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>407</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24433379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Long-term associations of nut consumption with
body weight and obesity</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
<volume>100</volume>, <issue>Suppl. 1</issue>,
<fpage>S408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S411</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Grosso</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marventano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Nut consumption on all-cause,
cardiovascular, and cancer mortality risk: a systematic review and meta-analysis of
epidemiologic studies</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>793</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25833976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Republic of Benin (2015) Benin Food Guide. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://poledfn.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/guide_alimentaire_benin_legal.pdf">http://poledfn.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/guide_alimentaire_benin_legal.pdf</uri>
(accessed November 2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Levesque</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delisle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Agueh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Contribution to the development of a food guide
in Benin: linear programming for the optimization of local diets</article-title>.
<source>Public Health Nutr</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>622</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>631</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24762926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Del Gobbo</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khatibzadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Assessing global dietary habits: a
comparison of national estimates from the FAO and the Global Dietary
Database</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>1038</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1046</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25788002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ngure</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pelto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>What are we assessing when we
measure food security? A compendium and review of current metrics</article-title>.
<source>Adv Nutr</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>505</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24038241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reedy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The United States food supply is
not consistent with dietary guidance: evidence from an evaluation using the Healthy
Eating Index-2010</article-title>. <source>J Acad Nutr Diet</source>
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25441965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Krebs-Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reedy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Bosire</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Healthfulness of the US food supply: little
improvement despite decades of dietary guidance</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>472</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>477</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20153133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Herforth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lidder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Strengthening the links between nutrition and
health outcomes and agricultural research</article-title>. <source>Food Secur</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>461</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pingali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Agricultural policy and nutrition outcomes &#x02013;
getting beyond the preoccupation with staple grains</article-title>. <source>Food Secur</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>591</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kuteya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Sitko</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Creating scarcity from abundance: bumper
harvests, high prices, and the role of state interventions in Zambian maize
markets</article-title>. <source>Afr J Agric Nutr Dev</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>10272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10289</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Remans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flyn</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>DeClerck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Assessing nutritional diversity of cropping
systems in African villages</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e21235</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21698127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>