<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5869696</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3616</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03616-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>GS9</italic> acts as a transcriptional activator to regulate rice grain shape and appearance quality</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Dong-Sheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Qian-Feng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Chang-Quan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Chen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Qing-Qing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Li-Xu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Xin-Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Ming-Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5543-5798</contrib-id><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Qiao-Quan</given-names></name><address><email>qqliu@yzu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.268415.c</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Plant Functional Genomics of the Ministry of Education/Key Laboratory of Crop Genetics and Physiology of Jiangsu Province, College of Agriculture, </institution><institution>Yangzhou University, </institution></institution-wrap>225009 Yangzhou, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.268415.c</institution-id><institution>Co-Innovation Center for Modern Production Technology of Grain Crops of Jiangsu Province/Joint International Research Laboratory of Agriculture and Agri-Product Safety of the Ministry of Education, </institution><institution>Yangzhou University, </institution></institution-wrap>225009 Yangzhou, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1240</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Identification of grain shape determining genes can facilitate breeding of rice cultivars with optimal grain shape and appearance quality. Here, we identify <italic>GS9</italic> (<italic>Grain Shape Gene on Chromosome 9</italic>) gene by map-based cloning. The <italic>gs9</italic> null mutant has slender grains, while overexpression <italic>GS9</italic> results in round grains. <italic>GS9</italic> encodes a protein without known conserved functional domain. It regulates grain shape by altering cell division. The interaction of GS9 and ovate family proteins OsOFP14 and OsOFP8 is modulated by OsGSK2 kinase, a key regulator of the brassinosteroids signaling pathway. Genetic interaction analysis reveals that <italic>GS9</italic> functions independently from other previously identified grain size genes. Introducing the <italic>gs9</italic> allele into elite rice cultivars significantly improves grain shape and appearance quality. It suggests potential application of <italic>gs9</italic>, alone or in combination with other grain size determining genes, in breeding of rice varieties with optimized grain shape.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">Rice grain shape or size is an important trait associated with both yield and appearance quality. Here, the authors identify GS9 as a negative transcription regulator of slender grain and show it can improve grain shape and appearance independently from other previously identified grain size genes.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">In rice, grain morphology, notably grain size or shape (GS), is one of the key determinants of both yield and quality. In general, large grain size is associated with high yield but poor quality, especially the appearance of milled rice, such as chalkiness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. An important goal of rice breeding programs is therefore a high yield plus ideal grain shape. Slender rice grains are highly commercial worldwide due to their transparent appearance and lack of an undesirable chalky texture and taste<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">To date, several genes and major quantitative trait loci (QTLs) controlling grain morphology have been cloned and characterized, most of which play a role in regulating grain size and yield, with counteractive effects on grain appearance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. These cloned genes have provided considerable insight into the individual molecular basis of grain size and shape regulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. For example, <italic>GS3</italic> is known to encode a putative trans-membrane protein involved in the G protein signal pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, while <italic>GW2</italic> encodes a RING-type protein with E3 ubiquitin ligase activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Furthermore, <italic>qSW5</italic>/<italic>GW5</italic> encodes a polyubiquitin-binding protein involved in the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Transcriptional regulatory factors also play important roles in controlling grain size<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. <italic>GLW7</italic> encodes the plant-specific transcription factor OsSPL13, which positively regulates cell size<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, while <italic>GL7</italic> encodes <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homologous protein LONGIFOLIA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. <italic>OsSPL16</italic>/<italic>GW8</italic> encodes a SBP-domain transcription factor that binds directly to the <italic>GW7</italic>/<italic>GL7</italic> promoter and represses expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, while the <italic>OsMKK4</italic>-<italic>OsMAPK5</italic> regulatory module plays an important role in regulating grain size by controlling cell proliferation in spikelet hulls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Plant hormones are also directly or indirectly involved in controlling grain size. <italic>qGL3</italic> encodes the protein phosphatase OsPPKL1, which might participate in brassinosteroids (BR) signaling in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, and <italic>GL3.1</italic> controls grain size by regulating Cyclin-T1-3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Moreover, several other genes, including <italic>GS5</italic>, <italic>GS2</italic>/<italic>GL2</italic>, and <italic>GW5</italic>, are also involved in BR signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. <italic>TGW6</italic> and <italic>BG1</italic>, which encode an IAA-glucose hydrolase activity protein and membrane localized protein, respectively, are thought to be specifically induced by auxin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Although several important genes involved in the regulation of grain size and shape have been cloned in rice, their regulation mechanism and network remain largely unknown<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Functional characterization of additional genes/QTLs involved in determining grain shape is therefore important in furthering our understanding of the molecular mechanisms behind regulation of grain traits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, as well as helping meet the demand for high yield and quality cultivars<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">From a series of chromosome segment substitutional lines (CSSLs) derived from two subspecies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, we identify the CSSL N138, which has a slender grain shape but identical grain weight as its recipient Nipponbare (NPB) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Its target gene, <italic>GS9</italic> (<italic>Grain Shape Gene on Chromosome 9</italic>), is found to encode a transcriptional activator involved in regulation of grain shape. Furthermore, introducing <italic>gs9</italic> null allele produces a slender grain with excellent appearance quality. These findings may facilitate our understanding of the mechanism of grain shape in rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Slender grain shape in N138 line is controlled by <italic>gs9</italic></title><p id="Par7">The CSSL N138 harbors six homozygous chromosomal segments substituted from the donor Qingluzan11 (<italic>indica</italic>) in Nipponbare background (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1b</xref>). It exhibited a more slender grain phenotype than that of Nipponbare. (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a&#x02013;d</xref>), and no obvious difference was observed in grain thickness or any other agronomic traits.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Map-based cloning of <italic>GS9</italic>. The morphology (<bold>a</bold>), length (<bold>b</bold>), width (<bold>c</bold>), and thickness (<bold>d</bold>) of mature grains from CSSL line N138 and its recipient Nipponbare. Scale bar, 3&#x02009;mm. Data are given as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30); ** significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <italic>t</italic>-test). NS not significant difference. <bold>e</bold>
<italic>GS9</italic> was preliminary mapped between markers RM6235 and IN0913 on chromosome 9 using 289 F<sub>2</sub> recessive individuals from the cross of N138 and Nipponbare. <bold>f</bold>
<italic>GS9</italic> was narrowed down to a 5.9-kb genomic DNA region between markers IN0927 and IN0929 using 2400 F<sub>3</sub> recessive individuals. The numbers below the bar in panels <bold>e</bold> and <bold>f</bold> indicate the number of recombinants between <italic>GS9</italic> and the molecular markers shown. <bold>g</bold> Genotype (left) and grain width (right) were shown for recombinant plants and the control plants. Black and gray bars represent chromosomal segments homozygous for Nipponbare and N138 alleles, respectively, while red one indicates heterozygous. <bold>h</bold> Schematic representation of the structure and allelic variation of the candidate gene <italic>LOC_Os09g27590 (GS9)</italic>, the only one predicted open reading frame in the 5.9-kb delimited region, among three CSSLs and their parents. The numbers below the gene bar indicate the number of polymorphic nucleotide(s) located in coding region, where the first nucleotide of start codon is as No. 1. Differential nucleotides are shown in blue and resulting amino acids are in brackets. The grain width of three CSSLs and their recipient Nipponbare is shown on the right</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e599"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">Mature seeds of F<sub>1</sub> plants derived from N138 and Nipponbare exhibited a similar morphology as Nipponbare (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2a</xref>). Among the derived F<sub>2</sub> population, the ratio of normal (Nipponbare) to slender (N138) grains was around 3:1 (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2b</xref>). Linkage analysis revealed that the slender phenotype was tightly co-segregated with the substitutional segment of 5.9&#x02009;Mb long on chromosome 9 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1b</xref>). These findings suggest that the slender grain phenotype in N138 is controlled by a single recessive gene within this substitutional segment. The alleles in N138 and Nipponbare were therefore named <italic>gs9</italic> and <italic>GS9</italic>, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Map-based cloning of <italic>GS9</italic></title><p id="Par9">The <italic>GS9</italic> locus was initially mapped to a region between markers RM6235 and IN0913 using the above F<sub>2</sub> population (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>), and further narrowed to a 5.9-kb genomic DNA region between markers IN0927 and IN0929 using F<sub>3</sub> population (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f, g</xref>). Only one candidate gene, <italic>LOC_Os09g27590</italic>, was subsequently identified as having the predicted open reading frame (ORF) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1e</xref>), hereafter referred to as <italic>GS9</italic>.</p><p id="Par10">Based on the rice annotation database, <italic>LOC_Os09g27590/GS9</italic> contains four exons and three introns (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref>). Sequencing data showed six polymorphic sequences in the coding region of <italic>GS9</italic> between N138 and Nipponbare (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref>), including one 3-bp (GCG) insertion in the first exon (InDel1), four single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the fourth exon (SNP1&#x02013;SNP4), and one 7-kb insertion in the second exon (InDel2) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). Except for InDel2, the remaining five polymorphisms also existed between the two parents, Nipponbare and Qingluzan11, resulting in the insertion of one amino-acid residue and substitution of three residues (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref>). The 7-kb insertion of InDel2 was subsequently amplified from the N138 genome, revealing a relatively complex sequence without the predicted ORF. Partial repeats were observed at both the 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; ends, matching multiple regions in the rice genome thought to have originated from recombination of various repeated sequences (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par11">Two more CSSLs, N107 and N139, were also found to carry the substituted segment covering the <italic>GS9</italic> locus from 9311 and Qingluzan11, respectively (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1c, d</xref>). The <italic>LOC_Os09g27590/GS9</italic> locus in N107 and N139 was identical to that in 9311 and Qingluzan11 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref>). Interestingly, both lines displayed a normal grain phenotype like Nipponbare (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a&#x02013;d</xref>). Additional linkage analysis of the F<sub>2</sub> population revealed that the slender grain phenotype was tightly co-segregated with the 7-kb insertion (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3d, e</xref>). These findings suggest that <italic>LOC_Os09g27590</italic> is the candidate gene for <italic>GS9</italic>, and the 7-kb insertion resulted in the loss-of-function and subsequent slender grain phenotype in N138.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Confirmation of the <italic>GS9</italic> gene</title><p id="Par12">The near-isogenic line (NIL) NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> containing <italic>gs9</italic> allele within the Nipponbare background was developed for complementary and functional tests. NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and Nipponbare showed identical growth, development, and final phenotype (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref>). Mature grains of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> were significantly more slender, causing about 24% increase in the ratio of grain length to width (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c&#x02013;e</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Confirmation of <italic>GS9</italic> in regulating grain shape. <bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>g</bold> Confirmation by using near-isogenic line. Morphology of whole plant (<bold>a</bold>), panicle (<bold>b</bold>), grain shape (<bold>c&#x02013;e</bold>) and weight (<bold>f</bold>), and yield (<bold>g</bold>) of the near-isogenic line NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and Nipponbare during maturation from the same planting condition in the summer of 2014. Scale bar, 20&#x02009;cm (<bold>a</bold>), 3&#x02009;cm (<bold>b</bold>), 3&#x02009;mm (<bold>c</bold>). Data in d and e are given as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30); ** significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <italic>t</italic>-test). NS not significant difference (<italic>t</italic>-test). <bold>h</bold>&#x02013;<bold>k</bold> Complementary test. Grain shape (<bold>h</bold>), length (<bold>i</bold>), width (<bold>j</bold>), and thickness (<bold>k</bold>) of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and its complementary transgenic line NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>-C, and their parent Nipponbare from the same planting condition in 2015. Scale bar, 3&#x02009;mm. Data are given as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30). <bold>l</bold>&#x02013;<bold>o</bold>, CRISPR/Cas9 editing and overexpression of <italic>GS9</italic> in Nipponbare. Comparison of grain shape (<bold>i</bold>), length (<bold>m</bold>), width (<bold>n</bold>), and thickness (<bold>o</bold>) among different lines from the same planting condition in 2016. NPB-cas9-1, a null <italic>gs9</italic> mutant in Nipponbare background created by CRISPR/Cas9 editing system; NPB-OE-1, a <italic>GS9</italic> overexpression line in Nipponbare background. Scale bar, 3&#x02009;mm. Data in <bold>m</bold>&#x02013;<bold>o</bold> are given as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20). The presence of the different lowercase letters in <bold>i</bold>&#x02013;<bold>k</bold> and <bold>m</bold>&#x02013;<bold>o</bold> denotes significant difference between the means (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, one-way ANOVA)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e890"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">As expected, the spikelet hulls of the complementary plants NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>-C perfectly resembled those of Nipponbare (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4a&#x02013;f</xref>), without any obvious morphological differences (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4b</xref>). Mature grains of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>-C also resembled those of Nipponbare, being rounder than those of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2h&#x02013;k</xref>). One homologous mutant NPB-cas9-1, produced in Nipponbare background using CRISPR/cas9 approach, had a 1-bp insertion and subsequent frameshift mutation in the coding region of <italic>LOC_Os09g27590</italic> (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5a</xref>). The NPB-cas9-1 mutant grew normally, (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5b&#x02013;e</xref>), but presented a more slender grain as that of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2l&#x02013;o</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5f&#x02013;i</xref>).</p><p id="Par14">The <italic>GS9</italic> overexpression lines, NPB-OE and NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>-OE, were generated in Nipponbare and NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> background, respectively, and their mature grains were rounder than those of Nipponbare (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2l&#x02013;o</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6a&#x02013;f</xref>). The ectopic expression of <italic>GS9</italic> also caused other phenotypic changes such as a slight decrease in plant height and panicle length, and a shortened leaf (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6g&#x02013;m</xref>). Overall, these results verified that <italic>LOC_Os09g27590</italic> is the target gene of <italic>GS9</italic>, acting as a dominant and specific regulator of grain shape in rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><italic>GS9</italic> regulates grain shape by altering cell division</title><p id="Par15">Dynamic observations during grain filling showed that the caryopsis of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> was significantly more slender than that of Nipponbare from 7 days after fertilization (DAF) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7d</xref>). Interestingly, there was no difference in caryopsis size between Nipponbare and NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> from 1 to 5 DAF (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7d</xref>), suggesting that the slender mature grains in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> were the result of differentiation of the spikelet hull (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7a&#x02013;c</xref>).</p><p id="Par16">As expected, the spikelet hull just before fertilization was also much slender in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> than Nipponbare (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7a&#x02013;c</xref>). Consistently, examination of a cross-section of the spikelet hull showed a significantly shorter spikelet perimeter, and decreased number of lower epidermis cells, both palea and lemma, in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b&#x02013;f</xref>). It suggests that cell division was significantly reduced in a transverse direction in the NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> spikelet hulls. However, an obvious increase in cell size was observed in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>, possibly due to compensation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Although the spikelet perimeter decreased in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>, the number of rows of specialized cells with a rigid wall in the upper epidermis was unchanged (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b, c</xref>). In addition, there is no significant difference in longitudinal cell density on the outer surface of the glume between NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and Nipponbare (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3g, h</xref>). Thus, it suggested that the longer grain length of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> was due to an increase in longitudinal cells in the spikelet hull, while the narrower width was the result of a decrease in transverse cell number. We thus compared the expression of several genes involved in cell cycle, such as <italic>CDKA1</italic>, <italic>H1</italic>, <italic>CYCB2.2</italic>, <italic>CYCIaZm</italic>, <italic>CDKB</italic>, and <italic>MAD2</italic>, and found that they were upregulated in young panicles of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>), suggesting that the altered cell number might result from elevated expression of genes promoting cell proliferation. Overall, it appears that the loss-of-function of <italic>GS9</italic> in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> altered cell division during spikelet development.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Histological comparison of the spikelet hulls between NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and Nipponbare. <bold>a</bold> Spikelet hulls before anthesis. The white dashed line indicates the sites of the cross-sections shown in <bold>b</bold>. Scale bar, 1&#x02009;mm. <bold>b</bold> Cross-sections of spikelet hulls. The right-hand images show close-up views of the boxed region. Scale bar, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. The black arrows indicate the lower epidermis cells. <bold>c</bold> Magnified views of the cross-sections indicated in <bold>b</bold>. The black and blue arrows indicate the rows of specialized cells with rigid walls and the lower epidermis cells, respectively. Scale bar, 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. Spikelet perimeter (<bold>d</bold>), cell number (<bold>e</bold>), and cell area (<bold>f</bold>) of palea and lemma. Data are given in means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD, with three biological replicates. ** significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <italic>t</italic>-test). <bold>g</bold> Scanning electron microscopy of the outer surfaces of the glumes. Scale bar, 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. <bold>h</bold> The cell length in longitude. Data are given as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD; <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;15. NS not significant difference (<italic>t</italic>-test)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1118"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><italic>GS9</italic> encodes a transcriptional activator</title><p id="Par17">In Nipponbare, <italic>GS9</italic> transcript level was preferentially high in young panicles, decreasing gradually during panicle development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, b</xref>). In transgenic rice containing the <italic>GUS</italic> (&#x003b2;-glucuronidase) reporter gene driven by <italic>GS9</italic> promoter, high GUS activity was detected in inflorescences and developing spikelets, with weak activity in developed spikelets (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). This expression pattern was consistent with the role of <italic>GS9</italic> in determining spikelet hull development. In NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>, no <italic>GS9</italic> transcript was detected in any of the tested organs or tissues (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, b</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><italic>GS9</italic> acts as a transcriptional activator. <bold>a</bold>
<italic>GS9</italic> transcript levels in different organs. Sd1 and Sd2, leaf and roots of seedlings, respectively; P1&#x02013;P4, young panicles with the average lengths of about 2&#x02009;cm, 5&#x02009;cm, 10&#x02009;cm, and &#x0003e;10&#x02009;cm, respectively; while P5&#x02013;P6, panicles before heading or 4 days after heading, respectively; St1, L1, and LS1, the stem, leaf, and leaf sheath at panicle differentiation, respectively; St2, L2, and LS2, the stem, leaf, and leaf sheath just before heading; En1 and En2, endosperms 5 and 25 days after fertilization, respectively. Rice <italic>actin</italic> gene was used as a control. Values are shown as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). <bold>b</bold> No <italic>GS9</italic> transcript was detected in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> shown by using semi-quantitative PCR. P1&#x02013;P4, the same as in <bold>a</bold>. <bold>c</bold> Subcellular localization of GS9 (35&#x02009;S::GS9-GFP) and OsOFP14 (35&#x02009;S::OsOFP14-GFP) in rice protoplasts. 35S::GFP was the control containing only the GFP coding region. Scale bar, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. <bold>d</bold> Transcription activity assay of full-length or truncations of GS9 in yeast. BD-GS9-FL, BD-GS9-C1, BD-GS9-C2, and BD-GS9-N1 showed the GAL4 DNA-binding domain in pGBKT7 vector fused with full-length, the regions encoding C-terminal, or N-terminal of GS9, respectively. Numbers below the bar indicate the amino acid residues used for construction. <bold>e</bold> Shape and width of mature grains from overexpression plants and wild-type Nipponbare. NPB-OE-FL, NPB-OE-C1, NPB-OE-C2, and NPB-OE-N1 represented the transformants overexpressed of full-length or truncations of GS9 as shown in <bold>d</bold>. All were driven by the <italic>CaMV 35S</italic> promoter. Scale bar, 4&#x02009;mm. Values are shown as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30). Different letters denote significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, one-way ANOVA)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1211"/></fig></p><p id="Par18"><italic>GS9</italic> encodes an unknown expressed protein with a number of orthologs in higher plants; however, none has been functionally characterized and no known-functional domain has yet been predicted. Phylogenetic analysis classified these proteins into two subgroups, dicots and monocots (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>). GS9-like proteins from rice and seven other Poaceae species formed a small clade with a high bootstrap value and strong similarity in the C-terminal region (265&#x02013;346 residues) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">11</xref>). In addition, no GS9 orthologous proteins were found in any other organism, suggesting that GS9 is a regulator specific to higher plants.</p><p id="Par19">The GS9::GFP fusion protein localized in the nucleus of either rice protoplast (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>) or tobacco epidermal cells (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">12</xref>). Furthermore, transcription activation assay in yeast showed transcriptional activation activity of the full-length <italic>GS9</italic> (BD-GS9-FL) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>). Data from dual-luciferase assays further confirmed that <italic>GS9</italic> functions as a transcription activator (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>). Interestingly, the N-terminal region of the GS9 protein (1&#x02013;237 residues), BD-GS9-N1, was found to be sufficient for activation of the reporter, while its C-terminal truncates, BD-GS9-C1 (238&#x02013;346 residues) and BD-GS9-C2 (265&#x02013;346 residues), were not (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>). These data suggest that the N- and C-terminals of GS9 are involved in transcription activation and DNA-binding activity, respectively.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>OsOFP14 interacts with GS9 and decreases its transcription activity. <bold>a</bold> Analyses of interactions between GS9 and OsOFP14, OsOFP1, OsOFP8, OsGSK2 in yeast two-hybrid assay, respectively. GS9-C1 means the vector containing the C1 terminal of GS9 as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>. OsOFP14, LOC_Os04g33870; OsOFP1, LOC_Os01g12690; OsOFP8, LOC_Os01g64430; OsGSK2, LOC_Os05g11730. <bold>b</bold> Confirmation of the interaction between GS9 and OsOFP14, OsOFP8 in rice protoplasts using BiFC assay. nYFP and cYFP, N-terminal and C-terminal of YFP, respectively. Chl chlorophyll. Scale bar, 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> Transcription activity assay using the pMN6 system. The main structure of vectors is shown in <bold>c</bold>. LUC firefly luciferase; RNL LUC renilla luciferase. <bold>d</bold> shows the transcription activity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> protoplasts by co-transformation of different effector vector(s) with the reporter plasmid pGIL and internal control pRIL. Data are given as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD, with three biological replicates. * or ** significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 or 0.01, <italic>t</italic>-test). <bold>e</bold>, <bold>f</bold> Analyses of interactions among OsOFP14, OsOFP8, OsOFP1, and OsGSK2 in yeast two-hybrid assay</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1295"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Accordingly, four types of transgenic plants with overexpression of different GS9 domains were generated, designated as NPB-OE-FL, NPB-OE-C1, NPB-OE-C2, and NPB-OE-N1, respectively (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13a&#x02013;f</xref>). However, grain shape alteration was only observed in the NPB-OE-FL transgenic plants containing the full-length CDS of <italic>GS9</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13c, g&#x02013;i</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that full-length GS9 is required for the regulation of grain shape in rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>GS9 interacts with OsOFP14 and OsOFP8</title><p id="Par21">To determine the underlying mechanism of GS9 in regulating grain shape, 11 potential <underline>G</underline>S9-<underline>i</underline>nteracting <underline>p</underline>roteins (GIPs) were screened using a yeast two-hybrid (Y2H) assay (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>), including OsOFP14/LOC_Os04g33870, an OVATE family protein (OFP), which usually functions in fruit shape<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The interaction between GS9 and OsOFP14 was further confirmed using full-length cDNA of <italic>OsOFP14</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). Interestingly, OsOFP14 was also localized to the nucleus, as with GS9 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">12</xref>). Moreover, bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) analyses in both epidermal and protoplast cells further confirmed in vivo interaction between GS9 and OsOFP14 in the nucleus of plant cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">14</xref>). Since OsOFP14 is a member of a transcription suppressor family<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, we speculated that OsOFP14 antagonistically or synergistically modulates GS9 activity. The dual-luciferase assays revealed the repression effect of OsOFP14 on GS9 transcriptional activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c, d</xref>), confirming the role of OsOFP14 as a negative regulator of GS9. This modulated activity also implied that the GS9-OFP14 interaction indeed occurred in vivo.</p><p id="Par22">There are several OFP members in rice; therefore, two additional representatives, OsOFP1/LOC_Os01g12690 and OsOFP8/LOC_Os01g64430, were selected for further interaction analysis. The results supported the interaction between OsOFP8, but not OsOFP1, with either GS9 or OsOFP14 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a, e, f</xref>). Recently, OsOFP8 was identified as a regulator of rice development and growth via interaction with OsGSK2/LOC_Os05g11730, a key negative regulator of BR signaling pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Surprisingly, no interaction was detected between OsGSK2 and either GS9 or OsOFP14 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a, e, f</xref>). Thus, these findings suggest that GS9 is able to interact with OsOFP8 and OsOFP14, while OsGSK2 only interacts and phosphorylates OsOFP8 as reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The dual-luciferase assays also revealed the repression effect of OsOFP8 on the transcriptional activity of <italic>GS9</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c, d</xref>), and this repression could be partly recovered by OsGSK2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">15</xref>). As expected, co-expression of OsOFP14 and OsOFP8 had a more serious repression effect on <italic>GS9</italic> transcriptional activity, which could also be attenuated by OsGSK2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>). Overall, these findings suggest that at least three members, GS9, OsOFP14, and OsOFP8, are involved in transcription co-regulation, activity of which seems to be further modulated by OsGSK2 via the bridge of OsOFP8.</p><p id="Par23">With the end to clarify whether <italic>OsOFP8</italic> and <italic>OsGSK2</italic> also regulate grain size, we obtained their transgenic rice lines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the <italic>OsOFP8-</italic>overexpression line (<italic>OsOFP8</italic>-OE7)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> exhibited a more slender grain than that of the wild-type (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">16a&#x02013;c</xref>), while the <italic>OsGSK2</italic> RNA interference (RNAi) line (<italic>OsGSK2</italic>-Gi-2)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> showed a 22% increase in grain length (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">17a&#x02013;c</xref>). No difference was observed in longitudinal cell density on the outer surface of the glume between <italic>OsOFP8</italic>-OE7 or <italic>OsGSK2</italic>-Gi-2 and the wild types (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">16d</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">17d</xref>). Thus, it suggested that the longer grain length of <italic>OsOFP8</italic>-overexpression or <italic>OsGSK2</italic>-RNAi lines was the result from an increase in longitudinal cell numbers of their spikelet hulls. Overall, these results further indicated that the GS9-OsOFP8-OsGSK2 complex participates in regulation of grain shape, at least in part, by modulating cell division.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Effects of <italic>gs9</italic> mutation on transcriptome</title><p id="Par24">To further explore the effects of <italic>gs9</italic> mutation on gene expression, we performed RNA-sequencing analysis with young panicles from NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and Nipponbare. The data showed that the <italic>gs9</italic> null mutation resulted in a number of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) (Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Gene Ontology (GO) assay showed that these DEGs were significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) enriched for cellular component, molecular function, and biological process, including DNA binding activity and cell differentiation (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">18</xref>). Besides, the <italic>gs9</italic> mutation also caused the altered expression of some putative transcripts which preferred to express in rice inflorescence and glumes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ricexpro.dna.affrc.go.jp">http://ricexpro.dna.affrc.go.jp</ext-link>), such as <italic>LOC_Os01g46169</italic>, <italic>LOC_Os02g42950</italic>, and <italic>LOC_Os09g28370</italic> (Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">1</xref>), which was consistent with the fact that <italic>gs9</italic> null mutation altered cell division and inflorescence development.</p><p id="Par25">As shown above, BR signaling was involved in GS9-mediated regulation of grain shape. However, our RNA-sequencing data revealed no significant difference between NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and Nipponbare in the expression of genes involved in BR signaling (Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">2</xref>). More interestingly, although OsOFP8 and OsOFP14 physically interacted with GS9 to suppress its transcriptional activity, the transcription of <italic>OFP</italic> genes was almost not altered in response to <italic>GS9</italic> mutation (Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">2</xref>). In addition, our quantitative RT-PCR data further verified the identical transcription of <italic>OsGSK2</italic> and two <italic>OFP</italic> genes in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">19</xref>). All these data implied that the crosstalk among GS9 and OFPs as well as BR signaling pathway might not occur in the transcriptional level. However, the detailed mechanism still needs further clarification.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><italic>GS9</italic> functions independently from other grain size genes</title><p id="Par26">To further understand the genetic interaction between <italic>GS9</italic> and other known grain size genes, two NILs, NIL-<italic>GW5</italic> and NIL-<italic>gs3</italic>, were constructed in Nipponbare background (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). Subsequently, two pyramiding lines, NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>/<italic>GW5</italic> and NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>/<italic>gs3</italic>, were generated by crossing with NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Genetic interaction between <italic>GS9</italic> and other grain size genes, <italic>GS3</italic> and <italic>GW5</italic>. <bold>a</bold> Comparison of grain shape among Nipponbare and its various near-isogenic lines (NILs) carrying different combinations of the alleles of <italic>GS9</italic>, <italic>GW3</italic>, and <italic>GW5</italic>. Nipponbare (<italic>GS9</italic>/<italic>gw5</italic>/<italic>GS3</italic>) means the wild-type Nipponbare carrying the combination of alleles of <italic>GS9GS9</italic>/<italic>gw5gw5</italic>/<italic>GS3GS3</italic>, and the NILs harbored corresponding alleles as shown in Nipponbare background. NIL-<italic>GW5</italic>, near-isogenic line with the <italic>GW5</italic> allele in Nipponbare; NIL-<italic>gs3</italic>, near-isogenic line with the <italic>gs3</italic> allele in Nipponbare; NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>/<italic>GW5</italic>, pyramiding line from NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and NIL-<italic>GW5</italic>; NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>/<italic>gs3</italic>, pyramiding line from NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and NIL-<italic>gs3</italic>. Scale bar, 2&#x02009;mm. <bold>b&#x02013;i</bold> Grain length (<bold>b</bold> and <bold>f</bold>), width (<bold>c</bold> and <bold>g</bold>), thickness (<bold>g</bold> and <bold>h</bold>), and 1000-grain weight (<bold>e</bold> and <bold>i</bold>) of Nipponbare and NILs. Data are given as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30 in <bold>b&#x02013;d</bold>, <bold>f</bold>, <bold>g</bold>, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 in <bold>e</bold>, <bold>i</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1713"/></fig></p><p id="Par27">The NIL-<italic>GW5</italic> line, which contained the functional <italic>GW5</italic> allele<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> from 9311, showed a slender grain shape (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>) but lower grain weight compared with Nipponbare carrying null <italic>gw5</italic> allele (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b&#x02013;e</xref>). In the pyramiding line NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>/<italic>GW5</italic>, grain shape was much slenderer than that of either NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> or NIL-<italic>GW5</italic>, while grain weight was similar to that of NIL-<italic>GW5</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b&#x02013;e</xref>). In addition, <italic>GS9</italic> transcript levels were similar between NIL-<italic>GW5</italic> and Nipponbare (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">20</xref>). A similar result was presented between <italic>GS3</italic> and <italic>GS9</italic> genes. In the NIL-<italic>gs3</italic> line carrying null <italic>gs3</italic> allele<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> from 9311, the mature grains were much slenderer and heavier than those of Nipponbare (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6f&#x02013;i</xref>), as previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Meanwhile, in the pyramiding line NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>/<italic>gs3</italic>, the grains were much longer and narrower compared with either NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> or NIL-<italic>gs3</italic>, but their weight remained similar to that of NIL-<italic>gs3</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6f&#x02013;i</xref>). These results suggest that <italic>GS9</italic> has an additive effect with <italic>GW5</italic> or <italic>GS3</italic> in determining grain shape.</p><p id="Par28">The effects of <italic>gs9</italic> mutation on the expression of other grain size genes were also examined and no obvious differences were observed between NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and Nipponbare (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">21</xref>), suggesting no direct correlation between the expression of <italic>GS9</italic> and other grain size genes during panicle development in rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Natural variation in the <italic>GS9</italic> gene</title><p id="Par29">To investigate natural variation in <italic>GS9</italic> gene, a total of 114 rice germplasms with abundant diversity in grain size were selected. A total of five polymorphic sites were identified (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), as described above, between 9311/Qingluzan11 and Nipponbare (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref>). Thus, a total of five haplotypes, H1&#x02013;H5, were classified (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). The wild rice samples were clustered into four haplotypes excluding H1, with most identified as H2 (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>), while the cultivar samples were clustered into H1, H2, H4, and H5 haplotypes, with most found in H1 and H5 (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Interestingly, most <italic>japonica</italic> cultivars belonged to H1 haplotype, while most <italic>indica</italic> cultivars belonged to H5 (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). Phylogenetic tree analysis revealed that the largest genetic distance existed between the H1 and H5 haplotypes (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">22</xref>).</p><p id="Par30">The two CSSL lines N107 and N139, both carrying the H5 haplotype, had a similar grain shape to Nipponbare, which belonged to the H1 haplotype. These findings imply that natural variation in <italic>GS9</italic> gene has no direct correlation with the determination of grain shape. For the rare allele of <italic>gs9</italic> from N138, the 7-kb insertion may have occurred spontaneously during CSSL construction.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Null <italic>gs9</italic> allele improves appearance quality of milled rice</title><p id="Par31">Although grain shape was more slender in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> than Nipponbare, the 1000-grain weight and final grain yield were identical (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f, g</xref>). Moreover, similar results were presented within the CRISPR/cas9 mutant NPB-cas9-1 (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5e</xref>).</p><p id="Par32">Milled rice from NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> was more slender than that of Nipponbare (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a&#x02013;e</xref>). More importantly, transparency of the milled rice was greatly improved in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>. Some milled rice from Nipponbare showed an obvious white core or belly area in the endosperm, unlike NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>, which showed no or very little chalkiness (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b, f, g</xref>). In addition, similar to NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>, milled rice of NPB-cas9-1 line was also slender without obvious white spots in the endosperm (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5f&#x02013;i</xref>).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Improved appearance quality of milled rice by introgression of <italic>gs9</italic> allele. <bold>a</bold> The shape of milled rice of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and its recipient Nipponbare. Scale bar, 2&#x02009;mm. <bold>b</bold> Decreased chalkiness in milled rice of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> compared with those of Nipponbare. Blue arrows indicate chalkiness in Nipponbare. Scale bar, 2&#x02009;mm. Scanning electron microscopy of cross-sections of milled rice from Nipponbare and NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> are shown in the upper left and right, respectively. Scale bar, 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. The length (<bold>c</bold>), width (<bold>d</bold>), length&#x02013;width ratio (<bold>e</bold>) of whole milled rice from Nipponbare and NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>. Data are given as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30). The percentage of milled rice with chalkiness (<bold>f</bold>) and the chalkiness degree of milled rice (<bold>g</bold>) from Nipponbare and NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>. Comparison of grain length (<bold>h</bold>) and width (<bold>i</bold>) between the individuals, from the same BC<sub>3</sub>F<sub>2</sub> backcross population but carrying the homozygous <italic>GS9</italic> or <italic>gs9</italic> alleles, respectively, under <italic>japonica</italic> 2661, WYJ27, or WYJ8 background. Data are given as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30 in <bold>c</bold>&#x02013;<bold>e</bold>, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 in <bold>f</bold> and <bold>g</bold>, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20 in <bold>h</bold> and <bold>i</bold>); ** significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <italic>t</italic>-test). <bold>j</bold> Comparison of the appearance of milled rice between Y8-cas9-WT and Y8-cas9-1, carrying the homozygous <italic>GS9</italic> or <italic>gs9</italic> alleles, respectively. Scale bar, 5&#x02009;mm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e2037"/></fig></p><p id="Par33">The rice quality assay showed a similar brown and milled rice percentage, apparent amylose and protein contents, gel consistency, and gelatinization properties between NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and Nipponbare (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">23a&#x02013;f</xref>). Thus, the null <italic>gs9</italic> allele appears to greatly improve the appearance quality of milled rice without affecting any other qualities or properties of rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Improve grain appearance quality by introgressing <italic>gs9</italic></title><p id="Par34">As shown above, the null <italic>gs9</italic> allele is rare and has great potential to improve grain appearance quality. Two recently released <italic>japonica</italic> cultivars, Wuyunjing27 (WYJ27) and Wuyunjing8 (WYJ8), with high yield and widely grown in lower reaches of the Yangtze River in China, were therefore selected as targets for introgression of <italic>gs9</italic> allele. With the assistance of the <italic>gs9</italic>-specific molecular marker (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">24a</xref>), the <italic>gs9</italic> allele was successfully introgressed into WYJ8 and WYJ27 via several rounds of backcross, respectively.</p><p id="Par35">As expected, within the BC<sub>3</sub>F<sub>2</sub> population derived from WYJ27 and N138, mature grains of WYJ27-<italic>gs9</italic> plants, carrying <italic>gs9</italic> allele, were significantly more slender than those of WYJ27-<italic>GS9</italic> with normal <italic>GS9</italic> allele, with a 5.5% increase in length and 4.7% decrease in width but no changes in thickness or weight (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7h, i</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">24b, c</xref>). Similar findings were observed in the WYJ8-<italic>gs9</italic> grains, with a 5.4% increase in length and 3.2% decrease in width (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7h, i</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">24b, c</xref>). Moreover, introgression of the <italic>gs9</italic> allele caused similar improvements in the potential new breeding line 2661, which has a large grain size and high yield. Grains of 2661-<italic>gs9</italic> individuals were 4.6% longer and 7.6% narrower than those of 2661-<italic>GS9</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7h, i</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">24b, c</xref>).</p><p id="Par36">As a convenient method of utilizing the null <italic>gs9</italic> allele, the CRISPR/cas9 editing system was used in Yandao8 (Y8), another high-yield cultivar. One homologous null <italic>gs9</italic> mutant, Y8-cas9-1, was identified with a 1-bp insertion (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">25a</xref>), similar with NPB-cas9-1 mutant in Nipponbare background (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5a</xref>). As expected, the grain shape was significantly more slender than that of the non-mutated control (Y8-cas9-WT), with a 5.5% increase in length and 9.1% decrease in width, and no changes in grain thickness (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">25b&#x02013;e</xref>). More importantly, the milled rice of Y8-cas9-1 was also much more slender than that of Y8-cas9-WT, resulted in significant decrease of chalkiness (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7j</xref>). These findings confirmed the great potential for application of null <italic>gs9</italic> allele to improve grain appearance quality in high-yield but poor appearance rice cultivars.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par37">A number of genes/QTLs are known to control grain size and shape in rice, several of which have been cloned and characterized<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. However, our understanding remains fragmentary, and thus, further efforts to mine elite genes/alleles are required. It is well-known that grain size is controlled by multiple signaling pathways; however, the gaps in these pathways and their interactions in co-regulating grain size are largely unknown<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par38">In the present study, we identified a grain shape regulator, <italic>GS9</italic>, contributing to a slender grain shape (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). <italic>GS9</italic> encodes an unknown expressed protein and its homologs are widespread but specific to higher plants, with only one homolog in rice genome (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>), indicating the irreplaceable role of <italic>GS9</italic> in grain development and shape determination (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>). Overexpression of <italic>GS9</italic> led to changes in the architecture of both vegetative and reproductive organs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>), possibly due to its ectopic expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par39"><italic>GS9</italic> allelic variation had no effect on the expression of other grain size-related genes (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">20</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">21</xref>). In addition, genetic interaction using NIL lines revealed that <italic>GS9</italic> is independent of both <italic>GS3</italic> and <italic>GW5</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Moreover, only full-length GS9 contributes to the regulation of grain shape (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13</xref>). This is quite different from <italic>GS3</italic>, as several domains of which independently regulate grain size<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Taken together, <italic>GS9</italic> functions as a distinct regulator of grain shape, independent of other known grain size genes.</p><p id="Par40">GS9-OsOFP14 interaction was identified and confirmed, resulting in repression of <italic>GS9</italic> transcription activation activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). The OFPs family are transcription repressors, in most cases, functioning in regulation of fruit shape<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, OFPs participate in multiple aspects of plant growth and development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. The rice genome contains 31 putative <italic>OFP</italic> genes; however, little is known about their functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Recently, OsOFP8 was found to regulate plant growth via interacting with OsGSK2, a key negative regulator of BR signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. In this study, GS9 together with OsOFP8 and OsOFP14 form a transcriptional complex (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Correspondingly, the leaves of <italic>GS9</italic>-overexpressing plants were more erect than those of wild-type (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6g</xref>), similar to those of <italic>OsOFP8</italic>-RNAi lines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Moreover, increased leaf angle was also observed in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). These findings suggested that <italic>GS9</italic> might play a role in modulating BR pathway, at least partially through its interaction with OsOFP8, thereby regulating rice spikelet development.</p><p id="Par41">The mechanism underlying BR regulation of grain size is quite complex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, and OFPs are thought to have overlapping and diverse functions in regulating plant growth and development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. But the knowledge of their interaction is still limited. OsBZR1 could bind the promoter of <italic>OsOFP1</italic>, and in turn OsOFP1 interacts with DLT and OsGSK2, suggesting that BR may regulates OFP1 at both transcription and protein levels to modulate rice architecture and grain morphology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Moreover, OsOFP19 could also modulate plant architecture and grain shape via integration of cell division and BR signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Similarly, GW5 interacts with OsGSK2, repressing its kinase activity and thereby leading to an increase in un-phosphorylated OsBZR1 and DLT, subsequently regulating grain hull size by affecting cell number<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. OsGSK2 also directly interacts with OsGRF4/GL2, inhibiting its transcription activation activity, and thereby regulating the grain length<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Overall, BR also plays an important role in modulating rice grain size by interacting with various regulators. In this study, GS9 together with OsOFP8 and OsOFP14 was found to function as a transcription activity regulator, which may be regulated by OsGSK2 via the bridge of OsOFP8 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Our results from both <italic>OsOFP8</italic> and <italic>OsGSK2</italic> transgenic rice further validated their function in regulating grain size (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">16</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">17</xref>). Thus, the molecular mechanism of regulation of grain shape here might rely partially on an OsGSK2-OsOFP8-GS9 signal transduction module, further co-regulating downstream target genes involved in cell division. The transcriptome analysis identified a set of DEGs (Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">1</xref>), some of which might be the candidate genes involved in determination of grain shape. Thus, it is possible that GS9 forms a linkage between transcription factors and BR signaling pathway during spikelet development; however, details of this potential mechanism require further elucidation.</p><p id="Par42">So far, a number of rice grain size genes, including <italic>GL2</italic>, <italic>GL7</italic>, <italic>GLW7</italic>, and <italic>GSE5</italic>, are known to contribute to the diversity of grain size and shape via expression alteration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Although several SNPs were identified in <italic>GS9</italic>, they did not contribute to the changes in grain shape (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). In contrast, null <italic>gs9</italic> mutation caused a slender grain shape, while <italic>GS9</italic> overexpression resulted in a rounder grain shape (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). These findings suggest that expression levels of <italic>GS9</italic> cause grain shape alterations.</p><p id="Par43"><italic>gs9</italic> null allele caused a slender spikelet hull and cell number was altered in both transverse and longitudinal directions in the spikelet hull of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>). Therefore, grain shape differences between NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> and wild type could be attributed to cell division in the rice glume. Similar alterations in grain shape and cell proliferation were observed in <italic>GW7</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. In general, large spikelet hulls are usually accompanied by incomplete grain filling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, but slender hulls provide a shorter milk-filling path, and thus, eliminate chalkiness of milled grains of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> or Y8-cas9-1 line (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Starch granules are loosely packed and spherical in a chalky endosperm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Consistent with this, the starch granules in the chalky area in Nipponbare were spherical and loose, while in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>, the entire area was translucent (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).</p><p id="Par44">Slightly increased leaf angle was observed in NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>), which may affect the performance of population photosynthesis efficiency, yet it did not alter population yield under conventional management in the field (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2g</xref>). It is possible that the NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> population maintains a suitable level of the field spaced arrangement among individuals to capture sunlight and other resources. In addition, <italic>gs9</italic> null allele showed similar performance to <italic>gw8</italic> and upregulation of <italic>GL7</italic>/<italic>GW7</italic> in altering grain shape and appearance quality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. The effect of <italic>gs9</italic> null allele with slender grains and improved appearance quality were also confirmed using genome editing approach (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Overall, the <italic>gs9</italic> null allele seems to be a specific regulator of appearance quality in rice.</p><p id="Par45">Therefore, to mine more <italic>GS9</italic> alleles, we analyzed more than 100 germplasms of both wild and cultivated rice, revealing five haplotypes, but no other loss-of-function allele (Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>). Interestingly, haplotype distribution showed a certain preference among rice subpopulations, and phylogenetic distance among haplotypes well matched the genetic distance between subpopulations (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">22</xref>). However, the common H1 and H5 haplotypes had an equal effect on grain shape (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). This is quite different from the beneficial alleles of <italic>gs3</italic>, <italic>GS5</italic>, <italic>gw5</italic>, and <italic>GW8</italic>, which have been artificially selected in modern rice varieties during domestication<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. Therefore, it implied that sequence variation in the <italic>GS9</italic> locus had been accrued during rice domestication, and they were naturally reserved due to no or limited effects on plant growth and morphology. Besides, it is also possible that the loss-of-function allele of <italic>GS9</italic> may have been escaped during artificial selection, as the <italic>gs9</italic> mutation lacks an effect on grain weight as well as final yields, and high yielding is highly preferred during modern rice-breeding program.</p><p id="Par46">In conclusion, <italic>gs9</italic> is a rare and specific allele involved in regulating grain shape and appearance quality in rice, and its benefits were shown in several high-yield rice cultivars via introgression of <italic>gs9</italic> allele (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">24</xref>). Moreover, several new high-yield breeding lines with same improvements were also generated using the genome editing approach (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">25</xref>). Furthermore, QTL pyramiding based on combinations of <italic>gs9</italic> and <italic>GW5</italic>/<italic>gs3</italic> alleles allowed development of several new rice lines showing improved grain shape (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) and possible better grain quality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. These findings will help studies aimed at understanding the combined effect of multiple alleles on grain size<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, thereby contributing to improving grain quality of rice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Plant materials and trait measurements</title><p id="Par47">The two CSSLs N138 (carrying null <italic>gs9</italic> allele) and N139 (carrying wild-type <italic>GS9</italic> allele) were generated by repetitive backcrossing of progeny derived from a cross between <italic>japonica</italic> rice Nipponbare (recipient) and <italic>indica</italic> rice Qingluzan11 (donor) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Similarly, the CSSL N107 (carrying wild-type <italic>GS9</italic> allele) was generated from repetitive backcross progeny from a cross between Nipponbare (recipient) and <italic>indica</italic> 9311 (donor)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par48">The near-isogenic line NIL-<italic>gs9</italic>, which possessed the <italic>gs9</italic> allele from the N138 line, was derived from a backcross between progeny of the N138 line, which contains only one donor segment on chromosome 9. During this process, recessive individuals were selected for mapping. Two other NILs, NIL-<italic>gs3</italic> and NIL-<italic>GW5</italic>, were also constructed in the background of Nipponbare, in which null <italic>gs3</italic> and functional <italic>GW5</italic> alleles were introgressed from <italic>indica</italic> 9311, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The <italic>OsOFP8-</italic>overexpression line (<italic>OsOFP8</italic>-OE7)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> and the <italic>OsGSK2-</italic>RNAi transgenic line (<italic>OsGSK2</italic>-Gi-2)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> were derived from the <italic>japonica</italic> cultivar Zhonghua11 (ZH11), which were kindly provided by Prof. Jianxiong Li and Prof. Chengcai Chu, respectively.</p><p id="Par49">A set of germplasms, including 83 rice varieties (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) and 31 wild rice samples, were used for genotyping of <italic>GS9</italic> (Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>). To further analyze the effect of the null <italic>gs9</italic> allele on grain shape, four recently released <italic>japonica</italic> cultivars with high yield but poor grain appearance, Wuyunjing27 (WYJ27), Wuyunjing8 (WYJ8), 2661, and Yandao8 (Y8), were selected for introgression of the <italic>gs9</italic> allele and creation of null <italic>gs9</italic> mutants using the CRISPR/cas9 approach.</p><p id="Par50">Rice plants grew in an experimental field in Yangzhou, China, during the natural growing season. Some transgenic plants grew in greenhouse referring to nature condition. Spikelet hulls were harvested before flowering for measurements of length and width. Grain length, width, and thickness as well as the 1000-grain weight were measured using fully filled grains after maturation. For plot yield tests, all plants in 4-m<sup>2</sup> plots were collected in three completely randomized blocks. Plant height, flag leaf length and width, and main panicle length were measured on the main culm. In addition, the percentage of chalky grains and degree of chalkiness of milled rice were measured using a grain appearance analyzer ScanMaker (Microtek, China). The apparent amylose content, gel consistency were measured with the standard of NY/T 593-2013 published by Ministry of Agriculture, China (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zbgb.org/27/StandardDetail1476335.htm">http://www.zbgb.org/27/StandardDetail1476335.htm</ext-link>). Viscosity was tested with a Rapid Visco Analyzer (RVA) (Newport Scientific, Australia) and protein content was estimated by nitrogen combustion with a nitrogen determinator (Kjeltec 8400, FOSS, Denmark)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Genetic analysis and molecular mapping</title><p id="Par51">The genetic background of the <italic>gs9</italic> mutant (N138) was confirmed using reduced whole-genome sequencing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. A total of 289 F<sub>2</sub> plants derived from the cross of N138/Nipponbare were used for genetic analysis and mapping of <italic>GS9</italic> at chromosome 9. An additional 2400 F<sub>3</sub> recessive individuals were then used for fine mapping. The phenotype of grain shape in selected recombinants was confirmed using the self-progeny. Several molecular markers were designed using Primer Premier 5.0 based on the genomic sequences of interest between Nipponbare and 9311, and the primer sequences are listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Microscopy observations</title><p id="Par52">Fresh young spikelet hulls were fixed, dehydrated, and embedded in Paraplast Plus (Sigma) then cut into 10-&#x003bc;m-thick sections. Cross-sections were analyzed by light microscopy (Olympus), and the cell number and cell area in the outer parenchyma cell layer of hulls were measured using ImageJ and Adobe Photoshop CS2 software. For glume cell observation, the outer surfaces of the spikelet glumes were observed by scanning electron microscope (S-4800, Hitachi). For starch granule observation, natural cross sections of mature milled rice were observed by scanning electron microscope (XL30ESEM, Philip).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>RNA extraction and RT-PCR</title><p id="Par53">Total RNA was isolated using an RNeasy Plant mini kit (Qiagen) or TRIzol. RNase-free DNase I was used to remove genomic DNA, and subsequently first-strand cDNA was synthesized using reverse transcriptase (Thermo) with the oligo dT18 primer. The full-length or truncated cDNA of <italic>GS9</italic> from Nipponbare was amplified and sequenced, and the rice housekeeping gene, <italic>Actin</italic> (<italic>LOC_Os03g0718100</italic>), used as an internal control. Real-time PCR analysis was performed on ABI ViiA7 according to the SYBR Green method, and the primers were listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Vector construction and rice transformation</title><p id="Par54">As a complementation test, a 2283-bp genomic fragment upstream of <italic>GS9/ LOC_Os09g27590</italic> was amplified from wild-type Nipponbare using primers p1300-590pro (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). A 1205-bp cDNA fragment containing the entire coding sequence of <italic>GS9/LOC_Os09g27590</italic> was also amplified from the cDNAs of Nipponbare using the primers p1300-590FL (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>) and fused to the upstream promoter region. The fusion fragment was inserted into the binary vector pCAMBIA1300, and the resulting plasmid <italic>pGS9::GS9</italic> was introduced into the callus of NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> by <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par55">The entire coding sequence of <italic>GS9</italic>/<italic>LOC_Os09g27590</italic> used in complementary analysis was also inserted into the binary vector <italic>pCAMBIA1300</italic> under control of the <italic>CaMV 35S</italic> promoter for overexpression analysis (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6a</xref>). The resulting plasmid <italic>p35S::GS9-FL</italic> was introduced into NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> or Nipponbare to generate overexpression lines, respectively.</p><p id="Par56">To genome editing by the CRISPR/Cas9 system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>, a 21-bp target sequence was selected for specific recognition of <italic>GS9</italic>/<italic>LOC_Os09g27590</italic> (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5a</xref>). The fragment was cloned into the vector SK-gRNA digested with <italic>Aar</italic> I, then digested and cloned into the <italic>pC1300-Cas9</italic> vector, and the plasmid was transformed into Nipponbare or Yandao8, respectively, to generate the <italic>gs9</italic> mutants.</p><p id="Par57">In addition, different truncations of <italic>GS9</italic>/<italic>LOC_Os09g27590</italic> based on protein sequence conservation were also amplified and cloned into <italic>pCAMBIA1300</italic> (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>) under control of the <italic>CaMV 35S</italic> promoter (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13a, b</xref>). The resultant plasmids were then transformed into Nipponbare, respectively.</p><p id="Par58">For promoter activity assay, a 2.3-kb <italic>GS9</italic> promoter region from wild-type Nipponbare (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>) was fused to the <italic>GUS</italic> reporter gene with the nopaline synthase terminator and inserted into the <italic>pCAMBIA1301</italic> vector. The constructed plasmid <italic>pGS9::GUS</italic> was then transformed into Nipponbare for GUS activity by the histochemical assay method.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Bioinformatic analyses</title><p id="Par59">Nucleotide and protein sequences of <italic>GS9</italic>/<italic>LOC_Os09g27590</italic> based on the full-length cDNA and the Rice Genome Annotation Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/">http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/</ext-link>) were deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) GenBank database (accession number: MF621928). For phylogenetic analysis of <italic>GS9</italic> homologs, a total of 49 protein sequences were obtained through the NCBI BLAST search. Phylogenetic trees were constructed using MEGA 5.0 based on the neighbor-joining method. Eight protein sequences of Poaceae plants were selected for sequence alignment using GeneDoc software. In addition, the coding region of <italic>GS9</italic> was amplified and sequenced in a set of 114 rice germplasms (Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>), and the phylogenetic trees of <italic>GS9</italic> haplotypes were constructed using MEGA 5.0 software.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Transactivation activity assay in yeast</title><p id="Par60">To construct the necessary serial vectors, full-length coding sequences and their various truncations of <italic>GS9</italic> were amplified and cloned into the <italic>pGBKT7</italic> vector. The truncations of <italic>GS9</italic> for the transactivation activity were the same as those used for rice transformation. The resulting constructs were then transformed into the AH109 yeast strain, and the Matchmaker GAL4-based Two-Hybrid system 3 (Clontech) was used for the transactivation activity assay. Each yeast liquid culture was diluted to an absorbance of 0.5 at OD600, and 3&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of each dilution inoculated onto tryptophan-, histidine-, and adenine-negative synthetic dropout medium. The relevant PCR primer sequences are given in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Y2H screening and confirmation</title><p id="Par61">Y2H screening was performed using Matchmaker Gold Yeast two-hybrid systems (Clontech). The truncated coding region (GS9-C1, without transcription activation activity) was introduced into the <italic>pGBKT7</italic> vector and the truncated protein used as a bait to screen a cDNA library prepared from developing inflorescence (P1 stage) of Nipponbare. Full-length cDNA of the candidate interacting proteins and several additional proteins including OsOFP1, OsOFP8, and OsGSK2 were amplified and cloned into the pGADT7 vector, respectively, for further verification. In addition, the entire coding regions of <italic>OsOFP14/LOC_Os04g33870</italic> and <italic>OsGSK2</italic> were introduced into the <italic>pGBKT7</italic> vector, respectively. Relevant primers are listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Transient expression assays</title><p id="Par62">For subcellular localization analysis, <italic>35S::GS9-GFP</italic> and <italic>35S::OsOFP14-GFP</italic> fusions were constructed by in-frame fusion of full-length <italic>GS9</italic> or <italic>OsOFP14</italic> cDNA with <italic>GFP</italic> (green fluorescent protein) coding region, respectively. The fusion genes were then inserted into the <italic>pCAMBIA2300</italic> or <italic>pJIT163</italic> vectors driven by the <italic>CaMV 35S</italic> promoter, and the constructs were transformed into <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> strain GV3101 and injected into tobacco leaves, or directly transformed into rice protoplasts, respectively. GFP signal was then observed by confocal microscope (Leica). All the primers are listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>.</p><p id="Par63">For BiFC assays, full-length <italic>GS9</italic> or <italic>OsOFP14</italic> cDNA was cloned into pBiFC vectors using the gateway system containing either the N- or C-terminal end of YFP. The resulting constructs (<italic>nYFP-GS9</italic> and <italic>OsOFP14-cCFP</italic>) and corresponding empty vectors were transformed into <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> strain GV3101, respectively. In addition, full-length <italic>GS9</italic>, <italic>OsOFP14</italic>, or <italic>OsOFP8</italic> cDNA was cloned into <italic>pYNE</italic>(R) and <italic>pYCE</italic>(R) containing the N- or C-terminal end of YFP, respectively, and the resulting constructs (<italic>nYFP-GS9</italic>, <italic>cYFP-OsOFP14</italic>, and <italic>cYFP-OsOFP8</italic>) and their corresponding empty vectors were directly transformed into the protoplasts of rice Nipponbare and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Col plants, respectively. Fluorescence was then observed by confocal microscope (Leica)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. All the primers are listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Protoplast transient assays of gene transcription</title><p id="Par64">To determine overall transcriptional activity of GS9, full-length cDNA of <italic>GS9</italic> or <italic>OsOFP8</italic> was cloned into the pMN6 vector, while that of <italic>OsOFP14</italic>, <italic>OsOFP8</italic>, or <italic>OsGSK2</italic> into the pJIT163 vector without the DBD region, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. The resulting vectors, <italic>pMN6-GS9</italic>, <italic>pMN6-OsOFP8</italic>, <italic>pJIT163-OsOFP14</italic>, <italic>pJIT163-OsOFP8</italic>, and <italic>pJIT163-OsGSK2</italic>, were used as effector plasmids, and co-transformed with the reporter plasmid <italic>pGIL</italic> and internal control <italic>pRIL</italic> into protoplasts of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Col plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. After incubation at 22&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;h, the protoplasts were collected for luciferase activity assay (Promega). All the primers are listed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>RNA-sequencing analysis</title><p id="Par65">Young panicles (approximate 5&#x02009;cm in length) of Nipponbare and NIL-<italic>gs9</italic> plants were harvested for total RNA preparation using TRizol method (Invitrogen), and they were further purified using mRNA purification kit (Promega). Three biological replicates were collected and used for RNA sequencing. The library products were ready for sequencing via Illumina HiSeq 2500. The filtered clean reads were aligned to the rice Nipponbare reference genome and genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/">http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/</ext-link>) using TopHat2/Bowtie2 software. The Blast2GO (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.blast2go.org/">http://www.blast2go.org/</ext-link>) program was used to obtain GO annotations of DEGs and finding significantly enriched GO terms with <italic>P-</italic>value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par66">Results are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD. SPSS 16.0 software was used for all statistical tests. Statistical significance was determined by independent-sample <italic>t</italic>-test for comparison of two groups and one-way ANOVA for comparison of three or more groups. Differences were considered statistically significant when <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05. <italic>P</italic>-values are indicated by * when <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 or ** when <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Data availability</title><p id="Par67">The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding authors upon request. The sequence of the <italic>GS9</italic> coding region has been deposited in the GenBank nucleotide database under accession code MF621928 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/MF621928">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/MF621928</ext-link>. RNA-sequencing data has been deposited in the SRA database under accession code SRP132484 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/?term=SRP132484">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/?term=SRP132484</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec29"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Information(DOCX 10228 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Descriptions of Additional Supplementary Files(PDF 25 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Data 1(XLSX 31 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Data 2(XLSX 18 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="41467_2018_3616_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Peer Review File(PDF 120 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>These authors contributed equally: Dong-Sheng Zhao, Qian-Feng Li and Chang-Quan Zhang.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41467-018-03616-y.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology of China (2016YFD0100902 and 2016ZX08009003-004) and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31601275) to Q.-F.L., and China Postdoctoral Science Foundation (2017M610357) to D.S.Z., and Jiangsu PAPD and &#x0201c;333&#x0201d; Projects to Q.Q.L. We thank Dr. Ke-Jian Wang for providing the CRISPR/Cas9 vectors, Prof. Jia-Yang Li for providing the pYNE(R) and pYCE(R) vectors, Prof. Jian-Xiong Li for providing the rice <italic>OsOFP8</italic>-overexpression transgenic rice line, Prof. Cheng-Cai Chu for providing the <italic>OsGSK2</italic>-RNAi transgenic rice line, and Prof. Chen Chen for comments on the article.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Q.Q.L. and D.S.Z. conceived and designed the experiments. D.S.Z., Q.F.L., C.Q.Z, C.Z., Q.Q.Y., X.Y.R., J.L., and L.X.P. performed the experiments. D.S.Z., Q.F.L., Q.Q.L., and M.H.G. analyzed and interpreted the data. D.S.Z., Q.Q.L., and Q.F.L. wrote the paper. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par68">The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying and exploiting grain yield genes in rice</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2008.01.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18343712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18343712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shaping taste: the molecular discovery of rice genes improving grain size, shape and quality</article-title><source>J. Genet. Genom.</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgg.2015.09.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calingacion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diversity of Global rice markets and the science required for consumer-targeted rice breeding</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e85106</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24454799?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24454799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fine mapping of a grain weight quantitative trait locus on rice chromosome 8 using near-isogenic lines derived from a cross between <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> and <italic>Oryza rufipogon</italic></article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2006</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0348-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16850315?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16850315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and molecular bases of rice yield</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>11.1</fpage><lpage>11.22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042809-112209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling pathways of seed size control in plants</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2016.05.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27294659?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27294659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Linking differential domain functions of the GS3 protein to natural variation of grain size in rice</article-title><source>Pro. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>19579</fpage><lpage>19584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1014419107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The novel quantitative trait locus <italic>GL3.1</italic> controls rice grain size and yield by regulating Cyclin-T1;3</article-title><source>Cell Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1666</fpage><lpage>1680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2012.151</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23147796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23147796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rare allele of <italic>OsPPKL1</italic> associated with grain length causes extra-large grain and a significant yield increase in rice</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>21534</fpage><lpage>21539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1219776110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23236132?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23236132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>OsSPL13</italic> controls grain size in cultivated rice</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3518</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26950093?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26950093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A QTL for rice grain width and weight encodes a previously unknown RING-type E3</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng2014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17417637?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17417637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation and initial characterization of <italic>GW5</italic>, a major QTL associated with rice grain width and weight</article-title><source>Cell Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1199</fpage><lpage>1209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2008.307</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19015668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Natural variation in <italic>GS5</italic> plays an important role in regulating grain size and yield in rice</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2011</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1266</fpage><lpage>1269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.977</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22019783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22019783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of grain size, shape and quality by <italic>OsSPL16</italic> in rice</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>950</fpage><lpage>954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2327</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22729225?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22729225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Che</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of grain size and rice yield by GL2-mediated brassinosteroid responses</article-title><source>Nat. Plants</source><year>2015</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>15195</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nplants.2015.195</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27250747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27250747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of <italic>OsGRF4</italic> by <italic>OsmiR396</italic> controls grain size and yield in rice</article-title><source>Nat. Plants</source><year>2015</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>15203</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nplants.2015.203</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27250749?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27250749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A rare allele of <italic>GS2</italic> enhances grain size and grain yield in rice</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1455</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2015.07.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26187814?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26187814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Activation of Big Grain 1 significantly improves grain size by regulating auxin transport in rice</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>11102</fpage><lpage>11107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1512748112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26283354?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26283354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The OsSPL16-GW7 regulatory module determines grain shape and simultaneously improves rice yield and grain quality</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3352</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26147620?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26147620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Copy number variation at the <italic>GL7</italic> locus contributes to grain size diversity in rice</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>944</fpage><lpage>948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3346</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26147619?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26147619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular genetic dissection of quantitative trait loci regulating rice grain size</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Genet.</source><year>2014</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-genet-120213-092138</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25149369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25149369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shomura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deletion in a gene associated with grain size increased yields during rice domestication</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.169</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18604208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18604208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SMALL GRAIN 1, which encodes a mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase 4, influences grain size in rice</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12405</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24320692?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24320692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OsMAPK6, a mitogen-activated protein kinase, influences rice grain size and biomass production</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2015</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26366992?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26366992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GW5 acts in the brassinosteroid signaling pathway to regulate grain width and weight in rice</article-title><source>Nat. Plants</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>17043</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nplants.2017.43</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28394310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28394310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishimaru</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of function of IAA-glucose hydrolase gene <italic>TGW6</italic> enhances rice grain weight and increases yield</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2612</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23583977?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCouch</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Not just a grain of rice: the quest for quality</article-title><source>Trends Plant. Sci.</source><year>2009</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2008.12.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19230745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19230745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of QTLs in the breeding of high-yielding rice</article-title><source>Trends Plant. Sci.</source><year>2011</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2011.02.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21429786?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21429786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic bases of rice grain shape: so many genes, so little known</article-title><source>Trends Plant. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2012.11.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23218902?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23218902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and high-throughput genotyping of substitution lines carrying the chromosome segments of <italic>indica</italic> 9311 in the background of <italic>japonica</italic> Nipponbare</article-title><source>J. Genet. Genom.</source><year>2011</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgg.2011.11.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujikura</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Horiguchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponce</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Micol</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordination of cell proliferation and cell expansion mediated by ribosome-related processes in the leaves of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2009</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03886.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19392710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19392710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eck</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new class of regulatory genes underlying the cause of pear-shaped tomato fruit</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>13302</fpage><lpage>13306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.162485999</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12242331?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression pattern and subcellular localization of the ovate protein family in rice</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0118966</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118966</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25760462?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25760462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OVATE family protein 8 positively mediates brassinosteroid signaling through interacting with the GSK3-like kinase in rice</article-title><source>PLoS Genet.</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e1006118</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006118</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27332964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27332964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DWARF AND LOW-TILLERING acts as a direct downstream target of a GSK3/SHAGGY-like kinase to mediate Brassinosteroid responses in rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2562</fpage><lpage>2577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.097394</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22685166?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22685166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis ovate family protein 1 is a transcriptional repressor that suppresses cell elongation</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2007</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>858</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03096.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17461792?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17461792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OVATE FAMILY PROTEIN 4 (OFP4) interaction with KNAT7 regulates secondary cell wall formation in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04595.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21457372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21457372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagnussat</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaresan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell-fate switch of synergid to egg cell in Arabidopsis eostre mutant embryo sacs arises from misexpression of the BEL1-like homeodomain gene BLH1</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3578</fpage><lpage>3592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.107.054890</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18055603?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18055603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crop seed size: BR matters</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2017.04.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28450180?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28450180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis ovate family proteins, a novel transcriptional repressor family, control multiple aspects of plant growth and development</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e23896</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023896</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21886836?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21886836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brassinosteroids regulate OFP1, a DLT interacting protein, to modulate plant architecture and grain morphology in rice</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1698</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.01698</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29021808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29021808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functions of OsBZR1 and 14-3-3 proteins in brassinosteroid signaling in rice</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>13839</fpage><lpage>13844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0706386104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17699623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17699623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OsOFP19 modulates plant architecture by integrating cell division pattern and brassinosteroid signaling</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2017</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Natural variation in the promoter of <italic>GSE5</italic> contributes to grain size diversity in rice</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>694</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2017.03.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28366824?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fine mapping of the grain chalkiness QTL <italic>qPGWC-7</italic> in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2009</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-008-0922-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19020855?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19020855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel factor FLOURY ENDOSPERM2 is involved in regulation of rice grain size and starch quality</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>3280</fpage><lpage>3294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.070821</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20889913?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20889913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>GS3</italic>, a major QTL for grain length and weight and minor QTL for grain width and thickness in rice, encodes a putative transmembrane protein</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2006</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>1164</fpage><lpage>1171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0218-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16453132?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16453132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovach</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>McCouch</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into the history of rice domestication</article-title><source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2007.08.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17963977?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17963977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influence of multi-gene allele combinations on grain size of rice and development of a regression equation model to predict grain parameters</article-title><source>Rice</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12284-015-0066-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26519289?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26519289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biofortification of rice with the essential amino acid lysine: molecular characterization, nutritional evaluation, and field performance</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2016</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>4285</fpage><lpage>4296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erw209</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27252467?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27252467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A highly efficient transformation system mediated by Agrobacterium tumefaciens in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Acta Phytophysiol. Sinica</source><year>1998</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>271</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple CRISPR/Cas9 system for multiplex genome editing in rice</article-title><source>J. Genet. Genom.</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgg.2015.09.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gampala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An essential role for 14-3-3 proteins in brassinosteroid signal transduction in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Dev. Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2007.06.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17681130?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17681130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A residue substitution in the plastid ribosomal protein L12/AL1 produces defective plastid ribosome and causes early seedling lethality in rice</article-title><source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-016-0453-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26873698?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26873698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PHYTOCHROME-INTERACTING FACTOR 1 is a critical bHLH regulator of chlorophyll biosynthesis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>305</volume><fpage>1937</fpage><lpage>1941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1099728</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15448264?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15448264</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>