<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6298526</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2018.01829</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genetic Diversity and Resistance to Fusarium Head Blight in Synthetic Hexaploid Wheat Derived From <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> and Diverse <italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> Subspecies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Szabo-Hever</surname><given-names>Agnes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Qijun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/650840/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>Timothy L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/476808/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Shaobin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/429305/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>Elias M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/645183/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Xiwen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Yue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/605891/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>Justin D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>Shiaoman</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Steven S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/438291/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Cereal Crops Research Unit, Edward T. Schafer Agricultural Research Center, Agricultural Research Service, United States Department of Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line>Fargo, ND</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Plant Sciences, North Dakota State University</institution>, <addr-line>Fargo, ND</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Plant Pathology, North Dakota State University</institution>, <addr-line>Fargo, ND</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Cereal Disease Laboratory, Agricultural Research Service, United States Department of Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line>St. Paul, MN</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Eva Darko, Hungarian Academy of Sciences (MTA), Hungary</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Paul Nicholson, John Innes Centre (JIC), United Kingdom; Parveen Chhuneja, Punjab Agricultural University, India; Yaxi Liu, Sichuan Agricultural University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Shiaoman Chao, <email>shiaoman1906@gmail.com</email> Steven S. Xu, <email>steven.xu@ars.usda.gov</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Breeding, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1829</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Szabo-Hever, Zhang, Friesen, Zhong, Elias, Cai, Jin, Faris, Chao and Xu.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Szabo-Hever, Zhang, Friesen, Zhong, Elias, Cai, Jin, Faris, Chao and Xu</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Synthetic hexaploid wheat (SHW) can serve as a bridge for the transfer of useful genes from <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> and tetraploid wheat (<italic>Triticum turgidum</italic>) into common wheat (<italic>T. aestivum</italic>). The objective of this study was to evaluate 149 SHW lines and their 74 tetraploid parents for their genetic diversity, breeding values and inter-genomic interactions for resistance to Fusarium head blight (FHB). The genetic diversity analysis was performed based on the population structure established using 4,674 and 3,330 polymorphic SNP markers among the SHW lines and tetraploid parents, respectively. The results showed that all <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> and most <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accessions formed different clusters and subpopulations, respectively, whereas all the <italic>T. durum</italic>, <italic>T. polonicum</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic>, and <italic>T. turanicum</italic> accessions were clustered together, suggesting that <italic>T. durum</italic> was more closely related to <italic>T. polonicum</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic>, and <italic>T. turanicum</italic> than to <italic>T. dicoccum</italic>. The genetic diversity of the SHW lines mainly reflected that of the tetraploid parents. The SHW lines and their tetraploid parents were evaluated for reactions to FHB in two greenhouse seasons and at two field nurseries for 2 years. As expected, most of the SHW lines were more resistant than their tetraploid parents in all environments. The FHB severities of the SHW lines varied greatly depending on the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and tetraploid genotypes involved. Most of the SHW lines with a high level of FHB resistance were generally derived from the tetraploid accessions with a high level of FHB resistance. Among the 149 SHW lines, 140 were developed by using three <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions CIae 26, PI 268210, and RL 5286. These SHW lines showed FHB severities reduced by 21.7%, 17.3%, and 11.5%, respectively, with an average reduction of 18.3%, as compared to the tetraploid parents, suggesting that the D genome may play a major role in reducing disease severity in the SHW lines. Thirteen SHW lines consistently showed a high level of FHB resistance compared to the resistant check, Sumai 3, in each environment. These SHW lines will be useful for the development of FHB-resistant wheat germplasm and populations for discovery of novel FHB resistance genes.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>wheat</kwd><kwd>synthetic hexaploid wheat</kwd><kwd><italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic></kwd><kwd>tetraploid wheat</kwd><kwd><italic>Triticum turgidum</italic></kwd><kwd>Fusarium head blight</kwd><kwd>genetic diversity</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="64"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Fusarium head blight (FHB), also known as scab, is a destructive disease of durum wheat [<italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> L. ssp. <italic>durum</italic> (Desf.) Husn., 2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 28, AABB] and common wheat (<italic>T. aestivum</italic> L. em Thell., 2<italic>n</italic> = 6<italic>x</italic> = 42, AABBDD) in the humid and semi-humid wheat-growing areas of the world (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Schroeder and Christensen, 1963</xref>). This disease, mainly caused by fungal pathogen <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> Schwabe [teleomorph <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic> (Schw.) Petch.] in North America, can lead to severe losses not only in grain yield but also in quality. Mycotoxins, the secondary metabolites of this pathogen, make the harvested grain unsuitable for consumption as food or feed (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Gilbert and Tekauz, 2000</xref>). Since the early 1990s, FHB has become a serious threat to wheat production globally due to its frequent outbreaks in many wheat-growing regions including the United States, Canada, Europe, and China (see review by <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">McMullen et al., 1997</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2012</xref>). The severe epidemics of this disease in North America in the early 1990s resulted in an estimated loss of at least 100 million bushels annually for the years 1991, 1993, and 1994 (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">McMullen et al., 1997</xref>). A recent estimate for the value of yield loss for wheat in the United States was $1.176 billion in 2015 and 2016 (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Wilson et al., 2018</xref>). To confine this threat, an emphasis has been placed on FHB resistance breeding in wheat. Tremendous work had been put into finding new resistance sources with a focus mainly on the resistance present in the exotic wheat germplasm from China and various gene banks. As a result, more than 50 FHB resistance quantitative trait loci (QTL) have been identified, and the most notable QTL were mapped on chromosome arms 3BS (<italic>Fhb1</italic>), 5AS (<italic>Qfhs.ifa-5A</italic>), 5AL (<italic>Qfhb.rwg-5A.2</italic>), and 6BS (<italic>Fhb2</italic>) from common wheat &#x02018;Sumai 3&#x02019; and PI 277012 (see reviewed by <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Buerstmayr et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2018b</xref>).</p><p>To widen the genetic resources of FHB resistance, it is necessary to identify and transfer novel resistance QTL from the germplasms of wheat and its related species that have not been tapped for FHB. Hexaploid wheat is known to originate as a result of hybridization between an AB genome-containing tetraploid wheat (<italic>T. turgidum</italic> spp., 2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 28, AABB) and the diploid goatgrass <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> Cosson (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 14, DD), which contributed the D genome (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Kihara, 1944</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">McFadden and Sears, 1946</xref>). Therefore, the world core collections of eight tetraploid wheat subspecies [<italic>T. turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>carthlicum</italic> (Nevski) &#x000c1;. L&#x000f6;ve &#x00026; D. L&#x000f6;ve, <italic>T. turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>dicoccoides</italic> (K&#x000f6;rn. ex Asch. &#x00026; Graebner) Thell., <italic>T. turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>dicoccum</italic> (Schrank ex Sch&#x000fc;bler) Thell., <italic>T. turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>durum</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>polonicum</italic> (L.) Thell., <italic>T. turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>turanicum</italic> (Jakubz.) &#x000c1;. L&#x000f6;ve &#x00026; D. L&#x000f6;ve, <italic>T. turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>paleocolchicum</italic> (Menabde) &#x000c1;. L&#x000f6;ve &#x00026; D. L&#x000f6;ve, and <italic>T. turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>turgidum</italic>, which are abbreviated as <italic>T. carthlicum</italic>, <italic>T. dicoccoides</italic>, <italic>T. dicoccum</italic>, <italic>T. durum</italic>, <italic>T. polonicum</italic>, <italic>T. turanicum</italic>, <italic>T. paleocolchicum</italic>, and <italic>T. turgidum</italic>, respectively] and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> have been considered as invaluable genetic resources for wheat improvement (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000f6;rner et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Fedak, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Arora et al., 2018</xref>). Many unique genes for resistance to several major wheat diseases and insects, such as rusts, powdery mildew, Hessian fly, and greenbug, have been transferred from tetraploid wheat and/or <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> into common wheat and extensively used in wheat breeding and production globally (see reviews by <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Ogbonnaya et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">B&#x000f6;rner et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Fedak, 2015</xref>).</p><p>Tetraploid wheat and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> have been used less as sources of FHB resistance because tetraploid wheat is generally more susceptible to FHB than hexaploid wheat, and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> plants are not suitable for direct evaluation for FHB resistance in field conditions because of their premature seed shattering nature. <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Buerstmayr et al. (2012)</xref> suggested that tetraploid durum wheat, which is known to be highly susceptible to FHB, does not necessarily lack FHB resistance alleles. Their findings that a resistance QTL introgressed from hexaploid wheat into durum improved resistance in only a few cases supported the hypothesis that either most durum wheat genotypes possess suppressors that silence or reduce the effect of resistance QTL (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Stack et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Garvin et al., 2009</xref>), or the D genome contributes resistance-inducing genes that are absent in durum wheat (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Fakhfakh et al., 2011</xref>). Actually, a number of accessions of <italic>T. dicoccoides</italic> (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Buerstmayr et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Oliver et al., 2007</xref>), <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Oliver et al., 2008</xref>), <italic>T. polonicum</italic> (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Wiwart et al., 2013</xref>), and <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Oliver et al., 2008</xref>) were identified to have moderate to high levels of FHB resistance. Several FHB resistance QTL were identified in durum wheat (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Somers et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2018a</xref>), <italic>T. dicoccoides</italic> (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Otto et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Stack and Faris, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Gladysz et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Buerstmayr et al., 2013</xref>), <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Buerstmayr et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>), and <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Somers et al., 2006</xref>). <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Brisco et al. (2017)</xref> identified five and seven <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions showing resistance and moderate resistance, respectively, suggesting that <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> can be a potential source of novel FHB resistance.</p><p>One way to bring potential new resistance genes from tetraploid wheat and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> germplasm into wheat breeding programs is the development of synthetic hexaploid wheat (SHW) (<italic>xAegilotriticum</italic> spp., 2<italic>n</italic> = 6<italic>x</italic> = 42, AABBDD). Since the 1940s, over 1,500 SHW lines have been developed and a large number of the SHW lines have been identified to exhibit resistance to major wheat diseases (rusts, Septoria, barley yellow dwarf virus, crown rot, tan spot, spot blotch, nematodes, powdery mildew, FHB, etc.) and insects (Hessian fly and greenbug) and tolerance to abiotic stresses (drought, heat, salinity/sodicity, and waterlogging) as well as novel grain yield and quality traits (see review by <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Ogbonnaya et al., 2013</xref>). A large number of adapted wheat germplasms and populations have been developed from elite SHW lines (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Lazar et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Dreisigacker et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Lage and Trethowan, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Jafarzadeh et al., 2016</xref>) and some of SHW-derived germplasms have been successfully utilized to develop common wheat varieties, such as the highly yielding variety &#x02018;Chuanmai 42&#x02019; (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2009</xref>) and greenbug-resistant varieties &#x02018;TAM 110&#x02019; (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Lazar et al., 1997</xref>) and &#x02018;TAM 112&#x02019; (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Rudd et al., 2014</xref>). Previous efforts to develop SHW germplasm for wheat improvement have mostly targeted the genetic diversity of the D genome present in world core collections of <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic>. Noticeably, most of the SHW lines that are currently available were developed from the crosses between durum wheat and diverse <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions by L. R. Joppa at USDA-ARS (Fargo, ND, United States; <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2010</xref>) and <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Mujeeb-Kazi and Delgado (2001)</xref> and <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Mujeeb-Kazi (2003)</xref> at the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center, Mexico (CIMMYT). Therefore, most of the tetraploid wheat germplasm resources other than durum have not been intentionally utilized for SHW production for wheat breeding programs except for a small number of <italic>T. dicoccoides</italic>, <italic>T. carthlicum</italic>, and <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accessions that were sporadically used (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Lange and Jochemsen, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Xu and Dong, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Lage et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>To incorporate the genetic diversity from under-exploited tetraploids into SHW germplasm resource, we recently developed 200 new SHW lines, with 178 lines being developed using six tetraploid subspecies <italic>T. carthlicum</italic>, <italic>T. dicoccum</italic>, <italic>T. dicoccoides</italic>, <italic>T. polonicum</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic>, and <italic>T. turanicum</italic>. These new SHW lines plus durum Langdon-derived SHW lines previously developed by L. R. Joppa (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2010</xref>) represent a unique resource for wheat improvement and for investigating polyploidization and intergenomic interactions in wheat. The objectives of this study were to identify FHB resistant SHW lines and to investigate the effect of the D-genome chromosomes derived from various <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions on FHB resistance by evaluating the genetic diversity and FHB resistance in a subset of 149 SHW lines and their 74 tetraploid parents.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Plant Materials</title><p>A total of 149 SHW lines and their tetraploid wheat (<italic>T. turgidum</italic> L.) parents were used in genetic diversity analysis and evaluation for resistance to FHB. These SHW lines were developed from crossing 10 <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions to 74 tetraploid wheat accessions belonging to durum wheat and five other tetraploid wheat subspecies (<italic>T</italic>. <italic>carthlicum</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>dicoccum</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>polonicum</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic>, and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turanicum</italic>). The accession or line numbers and sources of the tetraploid wheat and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions are listed in Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>, and the line numbers and pedigrees of the SHW lines are listed in Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>. Of the 10 <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions, four (CIae 17, PI 268210, RL 5286, and TA 2377) and six (CIae 19, CIae 22, CIae 25, CIae 26, PI 476874, and TA 1675) were classified as subspecies <italic>strangulata</italic> and <italic>tauschii</italic>, respectively. Three (CIae 26, PI 268210, and RL 5286) of the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions were used as the parents of 140 (94%) SHW lines. Except for seven durum &#x02018;Langdon&#x02019;-derived SHW lines (SW7, SW8, SW9, SW25, SW52, SW53, and SW59) developed by Dr. L. R. Joppa (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2010</xref>), all other lines were recently produced by crossing seven <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions (CI 22, CIae 26, PI 268210, RL 5286, PI 476874, TA 1675, TA 2377) with the 74 tetraploid wheat accessions.</p></sec><sec><title>Genetic Diversity Analysis on the SHW Lines and Their Tetraploid Wheat Parents</title><p>The SHW lines and their tetraploid parents were genotyped with the Illumina iSelect wheat 9K array containing 9,000 gene-derived SNPs (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cavanagh et al., 2013</xref>) using Illumina&#x02019;s Infinium method following the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocols (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA, United States). The SNP genotype calls were performed using the genotyping module implemented in the Illumina&#x02019;s GenomeStudio software v.2011.1. Genotype data were manually inspected for call accuracy before exporting the SNP data file. Heterozygote calls were converted into missing data, markers with poorly separated clusters were excluded, and SNPs with a missing data rate of 10% or higher as well as those with minor allele frequency (MAF) of 0.05 or lower were filtered out. The high-density SNP-based consensus map developed by <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Maccaferri et al. (2015)</xref> for tetraploid wheat and the consensus map previously produced by <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cavanagh et al. (2013)</xref> for hexaploid wheat were used to remove SNPs with no map information. The final SNP data set for molecular analysis consisted of 3,330 and 4,674 markers for tetraploid parents and SHW lines, respectively.</p><p>Polymorphic information content (PIC) was applied to assess genetic diversity and was calculated for single loci as</p><disp-formula><mml:math id="E1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>k</italic> is the total number of alleles detected for a given marker locus and <italic>P<sub>i</sub></italic> is the frequency of the <italic>i</italic>-th allele in the set of genotypes investigated (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Anderson et al., 1993</xref>). In our analysis the PIC = 1 - (<italic>p</italic><sup>2</sup>+ <italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup>) formula was used, where <italic>p</italic> and <italic>q</italic> denote the frequencies of the two alleles (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Ghislain et al., 1999</xref>).</p><p>Genetic diversity present among SHW lines and their tetraploid parents was evaluated using both principle component analysis (PCA) in TASSEL4 (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Bradbury et al., 2007</xref>) and cluster analysis in the R program<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>FHB Resistance Evaluation</title><p>Evaluation experiments were performed for evaluating Type II resistance (resistance to spread in the spike) in both greenhouse condition and field nurseries based on the well-established procedures for plant culture, inoculation, and disease scoring as described by <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2014)</xref>. Out of the 74 tetraploid parents, only one accession (<italic>T. dicoccum</italic> PI 272572) was not evaluated because of the low germination rate. In the field and greenhouse evaluation experiments, common wheat varieties &#x02018;Sumai 3&#x02019; and &#x02018;Grandin&#x02019; were used as resistant and susceptible checks, respectively. In greenhouse experiments, a total of 224 genotypes (149 SHW lines, 73 tetraploid parents, and two checks) were evaluated in two seasons in winter 2015 and 2016, respectively, using a randomized complete block design (RCBD) with three replicates. Each genotype was planted in a plastic pot (16.2 &#x000d7; 18.4 cm) with four seeds for each genotype per replicate. Therefore, a total of 12 plants per genotype were evaluated for most of the lines in each greenhouse experiment. The greenhouse settings for photoperiod and temperature were 16 h and 22&#x000b0;C, respectively. The inoculum was prepared at a concentration of 50,000 spores mL<sup>-1</sup> from three strains of pathogenic <italic>F</italic>. <italic>graminearum</italic>. For inoculation, 10 &#x003bc;L of inoculum was injected into a single central spikelet near the center of each spike at anthesis as described by <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Stack et al. (2002)</xref>. Each inoculated spike was misted and then covered with a misted plastic bag for 72 h. For each genotype, about 10 spikes in each replicate were inoculated. Disease scoring was performed by counting infected spikelets and total spikelets on each spike at 21 days post-inoculation, and disease severity for each line was calculated as the percentage of total infected spikelets in total spikelets from all the scored spikes.</p><p>In the field experiments, the plant materials were planted in mist-irrigated nurseries using a RCBD with three replicates at two locations (Fargo and Prosper, ND, United States) in the summers of 2015 and 2016. Each genotype was planted in a hill plot with 15 seeds. Inoculum was prepared using the grain spawn inoculation method, in which autoclaved corn seeds were infected with a mixture of spores produced separately from 20 <italic>F</italic>. <italic>graminearum</italic> strains, including 10 3ADON (3-acetyl-deoxynivalenol) producers and 10 15ADON (15-acetyl-deoxynivalenol) producers, collected from the field in North Dakota (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Puri and Zhong, 2010</xref>). At the boot stage of the earliest lines, inoculum was evenly applied among plots at a rate of 35.6 g m<sup>-2</sup>. The nursery was misted for 2 min in 1-h intervals for 12 h daily (4:00 p.m. to 4:00 a.m.), until about 14 days after anthesis of most the genotypes. Ten spikes for each line were individually examined at 21 days post anthesis as the number of infected spikelets per spike using a visual scale: 0 = no spikelets infected, 100 = all spikelets infected based on the method of <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Stack and McMullen (1998)</xref>.</p><p>Plant height (PH) data were collected in the field experiments, and days to flowering (DTF) data were collected in the field and greenhouse experiments to determine the correlation of these traits with FHB disease severity. PH was measured from the ground surface to the top of the spike excluding the awns. DTF was calculated from January 1 in the greenhouse experiments, and in the field experiments it was calculated from July 1 in 2015 and from June 20 in 2016 when 50% of spikes in a hill were flowering.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>All the statistical analyses were performed separately using evaluation data from hexaploid entries (SHW lines and checks), the tetraploid wheat parents, and the two groups combined. Descriptive statistics were calculated using the software JMP Genomics 7 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, United States). A normality test for distribution of disease severity was performed using Shapiro-Wilk under the &#x0201c;Goodness of Fit&#x0201d; option using the same program. Bartlett&#x02019;s test under the general linear model (GLM) procedure was used to test homogeneity of disease severity variances among the experiments using SAS program version 9.4 (SAS Institute). The reduction in FHB severity in the SHW lines was calculated as the difference in FHB severity between the SHW lines and their respective tetraploid parents. To determine the significance of the reduction, the least significant difference (LSD) value was used. Correlation coefficients between disease severity and PH or DTF were calculated using the PROC CORR procedure (SAS Institute). The same procedure was used to calculate the correlation coefficients between the disease severity of SHW lines and their tetraploid parents. To test homogeneity of PH and DTF data, Levene&#x02019;s test was used under the GLM procedure (SAS Institute). Broad sense heritability was estimated across environments according to <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Nyquist (1991)</xref> with the following formula: H<sup>2</sup> across environments = 1 - (MS<sub>G</sub>
<sub>&#x000d7;</sub>
<sub>E</sub>/MS<sub>G</sub>), where MS<sub>G</sub>
<sub>&#x000d7;</sub>
<sub>E</sub> was mean square genotype &#x000d7; environment; and MS<sub>G</sub> was mean square genotype.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Genetic Diversity of the SHW Lines and Their Tetraploid Wheat Parents</title><p>A total of 4,674 SNP markers that were polymorphic among the SHW lines were mapped based on the consensus map previously produced by <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cavanagh et al. (2013)</xref> resulting in an average of 223 markers per chromosome. The markers spanned a genetic distance of 3,445 cM with an average density of 0.7 cM per marker. However, the average marker density for the D genome was poor at 24 markers per chromosome. The number of markers ranged between 3 (chromosome 4D) and 504 (chromosome 2B). The PIC value was between 0.1 and 0.5 with an average of 0.38 (data not shown). The consensus map developed by <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Maccaferri et al. (2015)</xref> was used to assign the map positions for 3,330 SNP markers for the tetraploid parents resulting in an average of 238 markers per chromosome. The total genetic distance was 2,532.8 cM with an average density of 0.8 cM per marker. The number of markers ranged between 95 (chromosome 4B) and 386 (chromosome 2B). The PIC value varied between 0.1 and 0.5 with an average of 0.39 (data not shown).</p><p>To evaluate genetic similarity, results from PCA indicated that three subpopulations were likely present in both the SHW lines and the tetraploid parents. Results from cluster analysis further confirmed the presence of three major clusters separating 73 tetraploid parents (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) and 149 SHW lines (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The cluster 1 in tetraploid samples (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, black) consisted of one <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accession (PI 352548-1) and all 21 <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> accessions. Cluster 2 consisted of 50 individuals (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, blue) which were further grouped into two subpopulations with one consisting of only <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accessions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, subpopulation 2a) and another containing all durum, <italic>T. polonicum</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic>, and <italic>T. turanicum</italic> accessions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, subpopulation 2b). Interestingly, <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accession CItr 14133-1 (Entry 21) may be an outlier, as it did not share similarity with any of the tetraploid lines (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, red).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Dendrogram of the 73 tetraploid parents, forming three major clusters. Cluster 1 incluides one <italic>T</italic>. <italic>dicoccum</italic> and 21 <italic>T</italic>. <italic>cathlicum</italic> accesions. Cluster 2a consists of 34 <italic>T</italic>. <italic>dicoccum</italic> accesions. Cluster 2b contains all durum, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>polonicum</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic>, and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turanicum</italic> accessions. Accession <italic>T</italic>. <italic>dicoccum</italic> CItr 14133-1 is an outlier.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01829-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Dendrogram of the 149 SHW lines, forming three major clusters. Cluster 1 consists of 43 SHW lines derived from the accessions in the tetraploid wheat cluster 1. Cluster 2 contains 30 SHW lines corresponding to tetraploid wheat cluster 2b and the outlier <italic>T</italic>. <italic>dicoccum</italic> CItr 14133-1. Cluster 3 contains 76 SHW lines belonging to the tetraploid wheat cluster 2a.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01829-g002"/></fig><p>The three clusters separating 149 SHW lines (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) generally corresponded well with the clustering of the tetraploid parents (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Cluster 1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, black) consisted of the 43 SHW lines derived from all the accessions in the tetraploid wheat cluster 1. Cluster 2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, red) contained 30 SHW lines mainly derived from the accessions belonging to tetraploid wheat cluster 2b. Cluster 3 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, blue) consisted of 76 SHW lines derived from all the <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accessions belonging to tetraploid wheat cluster 2a. Although <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> CItr 14133-1 was separated alone from all other tetraploid parents, its three SHW lines (SW91, SW92, and SW93) were grouped into the SHW cluster 2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, red) with the SHW lines derived from tetraploid wheat cluster 2b. These analyses showed that the genetic diversity of this set of SHW lines obviously reflected that of the tetraploid wheat accessions. The results also clearly indicated that among the tetraploid accessions used, including <italic>T. dicoccum</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic>, <italic>T. turanicum</italic>, <italic>T. durum</italic>, and <italic>T. polonicum</italic> lines, <italic>T. durum</italic> was genetically more similar with <italic>T. polonicum</italic> than with <italic>T. dicoccum</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Reactions to FHB of SHW Lines and Their Tetraploid Wheat Parents</title><p>The 149 SHW lines and their 73 tetraploid parents, together with the two hexaploid checks (Sumai 3 and Grandin), were evaluated for reactions to FHB in two greenhouse seasons and two field nurseries (Fargo and Prosper) in 2 years (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). However, two SHW lines, SW9 and SW52 (Entries 4 and 6), and <italic>T. polonicum</italic> accession PI 272567 (Entry 204) were not evaluated in the field experiments in 2015 due to low germination rate. The Bartlett&#x02019;s test for disease severity variances showed heterogeneity across the two greenhouse seasons and the 2 years of field experiment at two locations (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>df</sub>
<sub>=</sub>
<sub>5</sub> = 205.6, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001). However, the data from the field tests showed homogeneity between the two locations in each year (2015: &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>df</sub>
<sub>=</sub>
<sub>1</sub> = 2.88, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0896; 2016: &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>df</sub>
<sub>=</sub>
<sub>1</sub> = 2.31, <italic>P</italic> = 0.1284), as well as between the two greenhouse experiments (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>df</sub>
<sub>=</sub>
<sub>1</sub> = 2.88, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0895). Therefore, the disease severity data from the two greenhouse experiments (FHBGH) as well as from the field experiments within each year (FHB15 and FHB16) were combined. Thus, these three sets of FHB severity data were used in the subsequent statistical analyses. In addition, the overall mean of disease severity from all the experiments is presented in Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref> to provide general information about the resistance level of each genotype.</p><p>The resistant check Sumai 3 had the expected level of FHB resistance in all environments (FHB severity: 8.6&#x02013;17.1%) (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S1</xref>). The susceptible check Grandin had the expected level of susceptibility only in the greenhouse experiments (55.3%), but it did not exhibit the expected level of susceptibility in the field environments (26.4% in FHB15 and 24.7% in FHB16) (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S1</xref>). Such low FHB severities were probably caused by early flowering dates of Grandin plants. We observed that Grandin was always among a few lines that had the earliest flowering dates, and it flowered at 9.9, 6.2, 14.7, and 12.4 days earlier than the population average in Prosper and Fargo nurseries in 2015 and 2016, respectively. At the early stage of the experiments, the inoculum pressure was likely not adequately built up. The FHB severity of the SHW lines and tetraploid parents, as expected, was highly variable among different environments. The average FHB severities of the entire population (SHW lines, tetraploid parents, and checks) were 29.9%, 49.8%, and 41.9% in FHB15, FHB16, and FHBGH, respectively (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S1</xref>). The tetraploid parents (average FHB severities: FHB15 = 33.8%, FHB16 = 71.3%, FHBGH = 56.9%) had more variable expressions of FHB than SHW lines (FHB15 = 28.2%, FHB16 = 39.7%, FHBGH = 34.6%) in different experiments (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). For FHB severity, the heritability (H<sup>2</sup>) values were 0.70, 0.85 and 0.64 among experiments in FHB15, FHB16 and FHBGH, respectively (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), indicating good reproducibility of the experiments.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Statistical analysis on Fusarium head blight (FHB) severity, days to flowering, and plant height data of a panel of 149 synthetic hexaploid wheat (SHW) lines and their tetraploid wheat parents evaluated in the field and greenhouse experiments.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data set</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sumai 3</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grandin</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHB15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4&#x02013;92.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHB16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1&#x02013;98.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHBGH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5&#x02013;100.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5&#x02013;130.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DTF GH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3&#x02013;60.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DTF15 Pro</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0&#x02013;37.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DTF15 Far</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0&#x02013;29.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DTF16 Pro</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0&#x02013;45.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DTF16 Far</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0&#x02013;45.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>Data set: FHB15 and FHB16 are combined FHB severity data from to field locations (Fargo, Prosper) in 2015 and 2016, respectively; FHBGH is combined FHB severity data from the two greenhouse experiments; PH is combined plant height data from all field experiments (2015, 2016); DTF GH is combined days to flowering data from the two greenhouse experiments; DTF15 Pro and DTF16 Pro are days to flowering data in Prosper in 2015 and 2016, respectively; DTF15 Far and DTF16 Far are days to flowering data in Fargo in 2015 and 2016, respectively. SD, standard deviation; LSD, least significant differences (&#x003b1; &#x0003c; 0.05); H<sup>2</sup>, broad-sense heritability.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Distribution of Fusarium head blight (FHB) disease severities among the tetraploid wheat lines in the three environments (FHB15, FHB16, and FHBGH). Letter &#x0201c;P&#x0201d; represents probability from normality test for distribution of disease severity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01829-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of Fusarium head blight (FHB) disease severities among the SHW lines in the three environments (FHB15, FHB16, and FHBGH). The two checks, Sumai 3 and Grandin, were included in the data set. Letter &#x0201c;P&#x0201d; represents probability from normality test for distribution of disease severity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-09-01829-g004"/></fig><p>Several resistant genotypes were identified in the field as well as in the greenhouse. Among the 25 most FHB-resistant SHW lines listed in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, 13 lines (SW53, SW87, SW91, SW92, SW93, SW157, SW159, SW162, SW188, SW203, SW252, SW253, and SW261) showed a high level of FHB resistance. Their FHB severities were not significantly different (<italic>P</italic> = 0.05) from Sumai 3 in all three environments in which they were successfully evaluated. Among these SHW lines, eight (61.5%) were derived from the crosses involving <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> CIae 26, suggesting that <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> CIae 26 may carry FHB resistance QTL. Three resistant SHW lines SW91, SW92, and SW93 were derived from <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> CItr 14133-1 crossed with three <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions, indicating that CItr 14133-1 may carry FHB resistance QTL. In fact, CItr 14133-1 showed a high level of FHB resistance in the field conditions with 8.1% and 7.1% disease severities in FHB15 and FHB16, respectively. Similarly, two <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accessions PI 191091 and <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> PI 272527 showed a high level of resistance comparable to Sumai 3 in all the environments. In particular, PI 272527 had the highest level of FHB resistance among all the tetraploid accessions and SHW lines evaluated in this study, with disease severities being 3.4%, 9.8%, and 8.5% in FHB15, FHB16, and FHBGH, respectively. The two SHW lines SW187 and SW188 derived from PI 272527 also had low disease severities.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Fusarium head blight (FHB) severity of most resistant synthetic hexaploid wheat (SHW) lines and tetraploid wheat lines.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entry No.</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Line</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Materials/Pedigree</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Average FHB severity<hr/></th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW92</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CItr 14133-1/RL 5286</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW91</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CItr 14133-1/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW93</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CItr 14133-1/PI 268210</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Langdon/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW187</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 272527/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4<sup>*</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW261</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 349052/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0<sup>*</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.7<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW53</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Langdon/PI 268210</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.5<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW162</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 41025/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2<sup>*</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW182</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 190926/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1<sup>**</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW253</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 254215/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW185</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 191390/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7<sup>**</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW186</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 191390/PI 268210</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9<sup>**</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW157</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI 14086/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW159</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI 14135/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW203</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 94753/PI 268210</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6<sup>*</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW156</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI 14085/PI 268210</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.8<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW87</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8155-B2/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW183</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 191091/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW268</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 185192/PI 268210</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW163</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 41025/PI 268210</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW143</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 352548-1/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6<sup>**</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7<sup>*</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW158</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI 14086/PI 268210</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW252</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 225335/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW85</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iumillo/CIae 26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW188</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 272527/RL 5286</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5<sup>*</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.3<sup>**</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 272527</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. dicoccum</italic> PI 272527</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CItr 14133-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. dicoccum</italic> CItr 14133-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 191091</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. dicoccum</italic> PI 191091</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI 14135</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. dicoccum</italic> CI 14135</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI 191390</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. dicoccum</italic> PI 191390</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sumai 3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. aestivum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grandin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. aestivum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup>&#x02217;</sup>, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup>, and <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup> indicate that the SHW lines were significantly different from their respective tetraploid parents at the 0.05, 0.01, and 0.001 probability levels, respectively (LSD test). Line number followed by &#x0201c;-1&#x0201d; (e.g., CItr 14133-1) indicated a single plant selection from the original seed stock.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Effects of Plant Height and Days to Flowering on FHB Severity of SHW Lines and Their Tetraploid Parents</title><p>The Levene&#x02019;s test for PH showed homogeneity of error variances across the field experiments (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.1437, <italic>df</italic> = 3), therefore all the experiments were combined for further analyses. The tetraploid parents showed a wide variation in PH, ranging from 67.5 to 130.0 cm, whereas the SHW lines ranged from 73.8 to 108.9 cm (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). The DTF data from the greenhouse experiments were combined based on the homogeneity test result (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.3242, <italic>df</italic> = 1), whereas the DTF data from field experiments were heterogeneous (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001, <italic>df</italic> = 3) and were analyzed separately in the further analyses. The plants started flowering early in 2016 (30th of June in Fargo, 1st of July in Prosper) due to the warm weather in May and June. However, the flowering period was longer in 2016 (35 days in Fargo, 34 days in Prosper) than in 2015, when the flowering started later (3rd of July in Fargo, 13th of July in Prosper) and took a shorter period (26 in Fargo and 24 days in Prosper) (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). Analyzing the DTF data separately for hexaploid lines and tetraploid parents showed that the two groups started flowering about the same time and flowering lasted for about the same period in both years at both locations (data not shown).</p><p>The Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficients between FHB severity and PH were significant in the field experiments (<italic>r</italic> = -0.273 and -0.226, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), indicating that the shorter plants had higher disease severities (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S4</xref>). However, no significant correlation was detected between the field PH data and the greenhouse FHB data (<italic>r</italic> = 0.072; <italic>P</italic> = 0.282). Also, the plants that flowered later showed lower disease severity in the field experiments, except in the experiment at the Fargo location in 2016. The PH and DTF did not influence the FHB severity in the greenhouse experiments. Significant correlations were detected among DTF and FHB data collected in various environmental conditions (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Decreases of FHB Disease Severities in SHW Lines Compared With Their Tetraploid Parents</title><p>Correlation analysis of the FHB severities between SHW lines and their tetraploid parents showed that both the overall data set and the 2016 field data of tetraploids were significantly correlated with the FHB severity data of their SHW lines in all environments (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The FHB severity of SHW lines in the greenhouse (SHWGH) was significantly correlated with the data of tetraploids in all environments except in 2015 (Tetr15), suggesting that FHB resistance in the tetraploid parents can be expressed at the hexaploid level.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Pair-wise correlation coefficients between synthetic hexaploid wheat (SHW) lines and their tetraploid parents for Fusarium head blight (FHB) severity.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data set</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SHW15</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SHW16</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SHWGH</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SHWALL</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetr15</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetr16</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TetrGH</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SHW16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SHWGH</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.363<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SHWALL</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.605<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.795<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.758<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetr15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetr16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.289<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.412<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.348<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.490<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TetrGH</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.039</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263<sup>**</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.505<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.507<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TetrALL</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.183<sup>*</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.180<sup>*</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.290<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.290<sup>***</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815<sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup>&#x02217;</sup>, <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup>, and <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup> indicate significant at 0.05, 0.01, and 0.001 probability levels, respectively. Data set: SHW15 and SHW16 are combined FHB severity data of SHW lines from both experimental locations (Fargo, Prosper) in 2015 and 2016, respectively; SHWGH and TetrGH are combined FHB severity data of SHW and tetraploid lines, respectively, from the two greenhouse experiments; SHWALL and TetrALL are combined overall FHB severity data of SHW and tetraploid lines, respectively; Tetr15 and Tetr16 are combined FHB severity data of tetraploid lines from both experimental locations (Fargo, Prosper) in 2015 and 2016, respectively.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A comparison of FHB severities between individual SHW lines and their respective tetraploid parents showed that most SHW lines had lower FHB disease severities than their tetraploid wheat parents, especially under environments with high disease pressures (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). The total numbers of the SHW lines with lower FHB disease severities than their tetraploid wheat parents were 80 (55.2%), 135 (91.2%), and 134 (90.5%) in FHB15, FHB16, and FHBGH, respectively. The total numbers of the SHW lines with significant FHB reduction (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) over their tetraploid wheat parents were 24 (16.6%), 108 (73.0%), and 98 (66.2%) in FHB15, FHB16, and FHBGH, respectively. On the contrary, there were only 14 (9.7%), 1 (0.7%), and 1 (0.7%) SHW lines having significant increases (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) of FHB severities over their tetraploid parents in FHB15, FHB16, and FHBGH, respectively. Because most of these SHW lines were derived from FHB-susceptible tetraploid parents, the significantly higher FHB severities of these SHW lines were mainly caused by unusually low FHB severities of their tetraploid parents. For example, <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> PI 94751 had FHB severities 72.6% in FHB16 and 56.8% in FHBGH, however, it had FHB severity only 13.7% in FHB15. An FHB-susceptible genotype can occasionally exhibit a resistant reaction with low FHB severity, which might result from unfavorable environmental conditions for disease development or escape of inoculation. This phenomenon commonly occurs in the field FHB evaluation, especially in highly variable weather conditions.</p><p>To analyze the effects of the tetraploid subspecies and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> genotypes on the FHB resistance of the SHW lines, the percentages of FHB severity reductions in the 140 SHW lines derived from three <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions (CIae 26, PI 268210, and RL 5286) were grouped by their tetraploid subspecies and <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The high levels of FHB severity reductions were largely observed in the SHW lines derived from <italic>T. durum</italic> (27.6%), <italic>T. polonicum</italic> (55.5%), <italic>T. turgidum</italic> (45.2%), and <italic>T. turanicum</italic> (51.4%), whereas low levels of FHB severity reductions were observed in the SHW lines derived from <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> (16.0%) and <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> (11.0%). Similarly, different <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> genotypes also affected the FHB severities of the SHW lines. Across the six tetraploid subspecies, the three <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions CIae 26, PI 268210, and RL 5286 resulted in 21.7%, 17.3%, and 11.5% of the FHB severity reduction in their SHW lines, respectively (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). We observed that the highest levels of FHB severity reduction occurred in the SHW lines from the hybrids of <italic>T. turanicum</italic> accessions crossed with <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> PI 268210 (69.0%) and CIae 26 (67.4%), and <italic>T. polonicum</italic> (66.7%) and <italic>T. durum</italic> (65.1%) accessions crossed with <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> CIae 26 (data not shown). For all the SHW lines, there was an overall average of 18.3% FHB severity reduction compared with their tetraploid wheat parents (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>), indicating that the D genome may play an important role in FHB resistance in wheat.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Average reductions in Fusarium head blight (FHB) severity calculated from 140 synthetic hexaploid wheat (SHW) lines derived from crosses of six tetraploid wheat subspecies (<italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum</italic> ssp.) with three <italic>Ae</italic>. <italic>tauschii</italic> accessions (CIae 26, PI 268210, and RL 5286).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetraploid subspecies</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">CIae 26</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">PI 268210</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">RL 5286</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall Avg</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avg</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avg</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avg</th><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. durum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-29.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-56.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-56.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-49.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-34.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-44.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-25.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-21.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-27.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. dicoccum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-25.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-20.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-16.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-31.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-17.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-18.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-25.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-10.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-12.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-16.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. carthlicum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-24.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-15.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-23.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-15.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-10.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-37.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-10.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. polonicum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-47.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-58.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-59.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-55.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-55.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. turgidum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-14.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-50.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-64.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-41.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-24.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-59.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-57.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-44.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-45.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. turanicum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-39.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-63.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-57.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-59.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-49.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-37.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-61.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-51.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-51.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avg</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-6.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-31.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-26.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-21.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-29.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-19.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-17.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-26.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-10.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-18.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>2015: Average FHB severity decrease in field experiments (Fargo and Prosper, ND, United States) in 2015. 2016: Average FHB severity decrease in field experiments (Fargo and Prosper, ND, United States) in 2016. GH: Average FHB severity decrease in two greenhouse experiments. Avg: Data were calculated from the average FHB severity data of the individual lines in each environment.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Synthetic hexaploid wheat has been considered as a valuable germplasm resource for introducing unique genes of agronomically important traits into bread wheat from its closely related or progenitor species in the primary gene pool (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Ogbonnaya et al., 2013</xref>). For resistance to FHB, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Mujeeb-Kazi et al. (2001a</xref>,<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>) evaluated a large number of the SHW lines targeting <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> genetic diversity developed at CIMMYT and identified 16 SHW lines having a level of resistance as good as the resistant check Sumai 3. <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Mujeeb-Kazi et al. (2001a)</xref> incorporated the FHB-resistant SHW lines into wheat breeding at CIMMYT. Our present study reveals that the SHW lines we recently developed and investigated in our program are also good sources of FHB resistance. Among 149 SHW lines evaluated, many lines showed a high level of FHB resistance in different experiments with 13 lines, namely SW53, SW87, SW91, SW92, SW93, SW157, SW159, SW162, SW188, SW203, SW252, SW253, and SW261, showing FHB severity comparable to the level of Sumai 3 in all experiments. Some of these lines should serve as useful genetic stocks that can be used for development of adapted wheat germplasm and varieties in breeding programs.</p><p>It is well known that cultivated tetraploid wheat is more susceptible to FHB than hexaploid wheat (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Stack et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Oliver et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>). As expected, most of the SHW lines evaluated in our study were more resistant than their tetraploid wheat parents in all environments (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). On average, 140 SHW lines derived from three <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions (CIae 26, PI 268210, and RL 5286) decreased their disease severities by 18.3%, suggesting that either the D genome or the increased ploidy level reduced the disease severity in the SHW lines. The data from our experiment provide some evidence to support the hypothesis (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Fakhfakh et al., 2011</xref>) that the D genome may play an important role in FHB resistance. Conceivably, the D genome may be necessary for expression or increased expression of some FHB resistance QTL located on the A- and/or B-genome chromosomes. It is also possible that the silencing of suppressors present on the A and/or B genome of tetraploids by D genome may lead to expression of resistance.</p><p>The evaluation data showed that the FHB severities of the SHW lines varied greatly with different <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and tetraploid wheat genotypes involved. The three <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions, CIae 26, PI 268210, and RL 5286, resulted in 21.7%, 17.3%, and 11.5% of the FHB severity reduction in their SHW lines, respectively (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Because <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> CIae 26 and PI 268210 caused the large reduction of FHB severities, they may carry FHB resistance QTL. Therefore, we inferred that the increased FHB resistance in the SHW lines derived from CIae 26 and PI 268210 might be the result of mutual or additive effects from the D genome and its FHB resistance QTL. The two <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions may have different QTL because they had different effects on the FHB severity reduction in their SHW lines. <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Brisco et al. (2017)</xref> recently evaluated 109 <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions in the greenhouse and detected significant variation in FHB severity. Among the 10 <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions in the present study, two accessions, namely CIae 25 (TA1703) and TA 2377, were evaluated for FHB resistance by <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Brisco et al. (2017)</xref> and they were identified as moderately susceptible-moderately resistant and susceptible, respectively. However, in our experiment, their SHW lines (SW8 and SW62) had significant reductions in FHB severities over their durum parent Langdon in two (FHB16 and FHBGH) and three environments, respectively. Because the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> parents were not evaluated in our study, we cannot determine if the FHB severities of the SHW lines were associated with those of their <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> parents. Therefore, further studies are needed to elucidate the relationships of FHB resistance between SHW lines and their <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> parents by evaluating the SHW lines along with their <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> parents.</p><p>Regarding the effect of tetraploid wheat genotypes on the FHB resistance of the SHW lines, we found that there were positive correlations between the tetraploids and their SHW lines under the environments with high FHB disease pressures in the field nurseries in 2016 (<italic>r</italic> = 0.412, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and greenhouse (<italic>r</italic> = 0.263, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) (Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Most of the SHW lines with a high level of FHB resistance were derived from tetraploid wheat accessions with a high level of FHB resistance. For example, most of <italic>T. polonicum</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic>, and <italic>T. turanicum</italic> accessions evaluated in our study had high disease severities 83.2%, 78.3%, 81.5%, respectively, whereas most <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> and <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> had relatively low disease severities (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). The SHW lines derived from these <italic>T. polonicum</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic> and <italic>T. turanicum</italic> accessions had high levels of reductions in FHB severity (55.5%, 45.2%, 51.4%, respectively), whereas those SHW lines derived from the <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> and <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> had low levels of reductions in FHB severity (16.0% and 11.0%, respectively) (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Noticeably, two <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accessions PI 272527 and PI 191091 exhibited high levels of FHB resistance in all the environments, suggesting that they may carry major FHB resistance QTL (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The SHW lines derived from the crosses between these FHB-resistant <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accessions and different <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions also consistently showed high levels of FHB resistance across different environments. The lower levels of reductions in FHB severity in the SHW lines involving <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> and <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> is supported by the previous findings that some <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> and <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> accessions have FHB resistance QTL (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Gagkaeva, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Clarke et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Gladysz et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Somers et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Buerstmayr et al., 2012</xref>). We previously conducted QTL analysis on FHB resistance in two <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accessions, PI 41025 and PI 272527, and identified two QTL on chromosomes 3A and 5A from PI 41025 and four QTL on chromosomes 1A, 3A, 5A, and 7B, derived from PI 272527 (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).</p><p>In addition to <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> and tetraploid wheat genotypes, the levels of FHB severity decrease in the SHW lines varied among the environments. On average, there were 29.8% and 21.0% reductions under the environments with high FHB pressures in the field nurseries in 2016 (FHB16) and greenhouse (FHBGH), respectively. However, only a 3.3% reduction was observed under low FHB pressure in the field nurseries in 2015 (FHB15), mostly because the low FHB severities in the field conditions in 2015 reduced the differences between the tetraploids and the SHW lines. This observation is in line with the fact that modern durum crop is more susceptible than bread wheat under the environments with high FHB pressures.</p><p><xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2006)</xref> investigated the genetic diversity and genetic relationships among 48 tetraploid wheat accessions belonging to <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turgidum, T</italic>. <italic>durum</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>carthlicum</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>paleocolchicum</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turanicum</italic>, and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>polonicum</italic> using simple sequence repeat (SSR) markers and grouped <italic>T. durum</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic> and <italic>T. polonicum</italic> into the same cluster in their experiment. <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Dreisigacker et al. (2008)</xref> genotyped a set of 348 accessions from five different tetraploid subspecies using 21 SSR markers and separated <italic>T</italic>. <italic>dicoccum</italic> accessions from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>durum</italic> accessions by principal coordinate analyses. In our study, we found that accessions from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>durum</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>polonicum</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>turanicum</italic>, and <italic>T. turgidum</italic> formed a subpopulation, whereas all <italic>T. carthlicum</italic> and most <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> accessions formed two different clusters. Genetic diversity of the SHW lines in our study clearly reflected that of the tetraploid wheat parents. Therefore, these SHW lines represent a unique genetic resource by preserving the high level of genetic diversity from their tetraploid parents.</p><p><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Lage et al. (2003)</xref> analyzed 54 SHW lines derived from 21 <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> and 15 <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> parental accessions using amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) markers. They also found that the genetic diversity of the SHW lines was associated with the <italic>T. dicoccum</italic> parents rather than their <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> parents. <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Dreisigacker et al. (2008)</xref> suggested that &#x0201c;SHW diversity would be expected to preferably reflect the diversity of the tetraploid parent&#x0201d; because the tetraploid wheat parent contributed two-thirds of the SHW genome. When genotyping a set of 56 SHW lines derived from durum wheat with only D-genome SSR markers, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Dreisigacker et al. (2008)</xref> found that the genetic diversity of the SHW lines was closely associated with the subspecies and geographic origin of the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> parents. Among the 10 <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> accessions used in our study, four and six belong to the subspecies <italic>strangulata</italic> and <italic>tauschii</italic>, respectively. The fact that genetic diversity of the SHW lines was not related to the <italic>Ae. tauschii</italic> parents in our study is likely due to the paucity of molecular markers on the D genome because there are approximately ninefold less markers for the D genome than for the A and B genomes.</p><p>Use of association mapping analysis to identify FHB resistance genes/QTL in both SHW and tetraploid populations was attempted. However, no associations of markers with significant effects on FHB resistance were detected in either the SHW population or the tetraploid genotypes. This is likely due to the low number of SHW lines used and/or the low frequency of resistance genes and alleles present in the populations. Nonetheless, the results from this study might provide guidance in selecting SHW lines for development of mapping populations to identify FHB resistance genes/QTL using linkage analysis. The SHW lines showing high levels of resistance in all environments, such as SW87, SW162, SW252, SW253, and SW261, might be suitable parents for future development of mapping populations for QTL analysis of FHB resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>SX and SC initiated and planned this study. AS-H, SC, SX, QZ, SZ, TF, and EE conducted the FHB evaluations in field nurseries and greenhouse. AS-H and SC conducted marker analysis and association mapping. AS-H and SX analyzed the FHB data. SX and YJ conceived and planned the research on development of the SHW lines. QZ, SX, YJ, XC, and JF developed the SHW lines. AS-H, SX, and SC wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed and edited the manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This material was based upon work supported by the United States Department of Agriculture, under Agreement No. FY16-SP-007 and the CRIS Project No. 5442-22000-080-037-00D. This is a cooperative project with the US Wheat and Barley Scab Initiative. This research was supported in part by an appointment to the Agricultural Research Service (ARS) Research Participation Program administered by the Oak Ridge Institute for Science and Education (ORISE) through an interagency agreement between the United States Department of Energy (DOE) and the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA). ORISE is managed by Oak Ridge Associated Universities (ORAU) under DOE contract number DE-SC0014664.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank Terrance Peterson, Mary Osenga, and Joseph Mullins for assistance with field disease evaluations, Danielle Holmes and Joseph Mullins for preparing inoculum for greenhouse and field disease evaluations, respectively. All opinions expressed in this paper are the author&#x02019;s and do not necessarily reflect the policies and views of USDA, ARS, DOE, or ORAU/ORISE. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this article was solely for the purpose of providing specific information and does not imply recommendation or endorsement by the United States Department of Agriculture. USDA was an equal opportunity provider and employer.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01829/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2018.01829/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Table_1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Table_2.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><media xlink:href="Table_3.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><media xlink:href="Table_4.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5"><media xlink:href="Presentation_1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Autrique</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Optimizing parental selection for genetic linkage maps.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g93-024</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18469981?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steuernagel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandramohan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matny</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Resistance gene discovery and cloning by sequence capture and association genetics.</article-title>
<source><italic>bioRxiv</italic></source> [Preprint]. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/248146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;rner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogbonnaya</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;der</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Periyannan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagudah</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). &#x0201c;<source><italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> introgressions in wheat,&#x0201d; in <italic>Alien Introgression in Wheat: Cytogenetics, Molecular Biology, and Genomics</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Moln&#x000e1;r-L&#x000e1;ng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceoloni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolezel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casstevens</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramdoss</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckler</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>TASSEL: software for association mapping of complex traits in diverse samples.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>2633</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2635</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm308</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17586829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brisco</surname><given-names>E. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Fusarium head blight resistance in <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genet. Resour. Crop Evol.</italic></source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>2049</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2058</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10722-017-0495-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buerstmayr</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>QTL mapping and marker-assisted selection for Fusarium head blight resistance in wheat: a review.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Breed.</italic></source>
<volume>128</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0523.2008.01550.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buerstmayr</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stierschneider</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemmens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griesser</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nevo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Variation for resistance to head blight caused by <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> in wild emmer (<italic>Triticum dicoccoides</italic>) originating from Israel.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>130</volume>
<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1022324727780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buerstmayr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alimari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buerstmayr</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Genetic mapping of QTL for resistance to Fusarium head blight spread (type 2 resistance) in a <italic>Triticum dicoccoides</italic> &#x000d7; <italic>Triticum durum</italic> backcross-derived population.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>126</volume>
<fpage>2825</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2834</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-013-2174-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23921957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23921957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buerstmayr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buerstmayr</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Mapping of QTL for Fusarium head blight resistance and morphological and developmental traits in three backcross populations derived from <italic>Triticum dicoccum</italic> &#x000d7;<italic>Triticum durum</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>125</volume>
<fpage>1751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1765</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-1951-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22926291?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22926291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide comparative diversity uncovers multiple targets of selection for improvement in hexaploid wheat landrace and cultivars.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>8057</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8062</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1217133110</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23630259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23630259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Saturation and comparative mapping of a major Fusarium head blight resistance QTL in tetraploid wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Breed.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>124</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-006-9049-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Identification and molecular mapping of two QTLs with major effects for resistance to Fusarium head blight in wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet</italic></source>
<volume>123</volume>
<fpage>1107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1119</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-011-1652-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21833554?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21833554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedak</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozniak</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Progress in improvement of Fusarium resistance of durum wheat,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Proceedings of the 2nd Int. Symp. Fusarium Head Blight</italic></source>, <role>ed.</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Canty</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Orlando, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Michigan State Univ</publisher-name>), 43.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dreisigacker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishii</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lage</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Use of synthetic hexaploid wheat to increase diversity for CIMMYT bread wheat improvement.</article-title>
<source><italic>Aust. J. Agric. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>59</volume>
<fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>420</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR07225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fakhfakh</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahyaoui</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezgui</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daaloul</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Inheritances of Fusarium head blight resistance in a cross involving local and exotic durum wheat cultivars.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>2517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2524</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2011.03.0140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedak</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Alien introgressions from wild <italic>Triticum</italic> species, <italic>T. monococcum</italic>, <italic>T. urartu</italic>, <italic>T. turgidum</italic>, <italic>T. dicoccum</italic>, <italic>T. dicoccoides</italic>, <italic>T. carthlicum</italic>, <italic>T. araraticum</italic>, <italic>T. timopheevii</italic>, and <italic>T. miguschovae</italic>,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Alien Introgression in Wheat: Cytogenetics, Molecular Biology, and Genomics</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Moln&#x000e1;r-L&#x000e1;ng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceoloni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolezel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-23494-6_8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gagkaeva</surname><given-names>T. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Importance of Fusarium head blight in Russia and the search for new sources of genetic resistance in wheat and barley,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Proceedings of the National Fusarium Head Blight Forum</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Canty</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siler</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Bloomington, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Michigan State Univ</publisher-name>), <fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garvin</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Quantitative trait locus mapping of increased Fusarium head blight susceptibility associated with a wild emmer wheat chromosome.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytopathology</italic></source>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>452</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-99-4-0447</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19271987?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19271987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghislain</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fajardo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huam&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hijmans</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Marker-assisted sampling of the cultivated Andean potato <italic>Solanum phureja</italic> collection using RAPD markers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genet. Resour. Crop. Evol.</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>555</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008724007888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tekauz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Review: recent developments in research on Fusarium head blight of wheat in Canada.</article-title>
<source><italic>Can. J. Plant. Pathol.</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07060660009501155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gladysz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemmens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buerstmayr</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;QTL mapping of novel resistance sources in tetraploid wheat,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Proceedings of the 2nd International Symposium on Fusarium Head Blight</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Canty</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boring</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wardwell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Orlando, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Michigan State Univ), 63</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gladysz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemmens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buerstmayr</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Evaluation and genetic mapping of resistance to Fusarium head blight in <italic>Triticum dicoccoides</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Isr. J. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>266</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 19271987?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19271987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jafarzadeh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnett</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jannink</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akdemir</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreisigacker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrells</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Breeding value of primary synthetic wheat genotypes for grain yield.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<issue>e0162860</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162860</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27656893?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27656893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1944</year>). <article-title>Discovery of the DD-analyser, one of the ancestors of vulgare wheats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Agriculture and Horticulture (Tokyo)</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>890</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Identification of a novel Fusarium head blight resistance quantitative trait locus on chromosome 7A in tetraploid wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytopathology</italic></source>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>592</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>597</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-97-5-0592</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18943578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lage</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skovmand</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Grain quality of emmer wheat derived synthetic hexaploid wheats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genet. Resour. Crop Evol.</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>955</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>962</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10722-004-7066-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lage</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trethowan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>CIMMYT&#x02019;s use of synthetic hexaploid wheat in breeding for adaptation to rainfed environments globally.</article-title>
<source><italic>Aust. J. Agr. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>59</volume>
<fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>469</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR07223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lage</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossa</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skovmand</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Assessment of genetic diversity in synthetic hexaploid wheats and their <italic>Triticum dicoccum</italic> and <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> parents using AFLPs and agronomic traits.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>134</volume>
<fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:EUPH.0000004953.85283.f4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jochemsen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Use of the gene pools of <italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> ssp. <italic>dicoccoides</italic> and <italic>Aegilops squarrosa</italic> for the breeding of common wheat (<italic>T. aestivum</italic>), through chromosome-doubled hybrids. I. Two strategies for the production of the amphiploids.</article-title>
<source><italic>Euphytica</italic></source>
<volume>59</volume>
<fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00041273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Worrall</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rooney</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thuleen</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Registration of &#x02018;TAM 110&#x02019; wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>1978</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1979</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1997.0011183X003700060055x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Worrall</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuleen</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Registration of eight closely related germplasm lines differing in biotype E greenbug resistance.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>:<issue>1419</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1996.0011183X003600050073x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Z. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Genetic diversity of <italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> L. based on microsatellite markers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Russ. J. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>316</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1134/S1022795406030124</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16649667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16649667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maccaferri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martelli</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>A high-density, SNP-based consensus map of tetraploid wheat as a bridge to integrated durum and bread wheat genomics and breeding.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Biotechnol. J.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>648</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>663</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12288</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25424506?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25424506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1946</year>). <article-title>The origin of Triticum spelta and its free-threshing hexaploid relatives.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Hered.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a105594</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20985728?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20985728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergstrom</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Wolf</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dill-Macky</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hershman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A unified effort to fight an enemy of wheat and barley: Fusarium head blight.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Dis.</italic></source>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>1712</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1728</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-03-12-0291-FE</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallenberg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Scab of wheat and barley: a re-emerging disease of devastating impact.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Dis.</italic></source>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>1340</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1348</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS.1997.81.12.1340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joppa</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). &#x0201c;<article-title>Evaluation of <italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> L. var. dicoccoides for resistance to Fusarium head blight and stem rust</article-title>,&#x0201d; in <source><italic>Proc. 9th Int. Wheat Genetics Symp</italic></source>, <role>ed.</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Slinkard</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Saskatoon, SK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Saskatoon</publisher-name>), <fpage>292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>293</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mujeeb-Kazi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;New genetic stocks for durum and bread wheat improvement,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc 10th Intl. Wheat Genet. Symp</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pogna</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pogna</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galterio</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Paestum</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>S.I.M.I</publisher-name>), <fpage>772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>774</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mujeeb-Kazi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A second, elite set of synthetic hexaploid wheats based upon multiple disease resistance.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Wheat Newslett.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mujeeb-Kazi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juarez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001a</year>). <article-title>Scab resistance in bread wheat/synthetic hexaploid derivatives.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Wheat Newslett.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mujeeb-Kazi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juarez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001b</year>). <article-title>Scab resistance (type II: spread) in synthetic hexaploid germplasm.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Wheat Newslett.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyquist</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Estimation of heritability and prediction of selection response in plant populations.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crit. Rev. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07352689109382313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogbonnaya</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdalla</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mujeeb-Kazi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazi</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosman</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Synthetic hexaploids: harnessing species of the primary gene pool for wheat improvement.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Breed. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9781118497869.ch2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of Fusarium head blight resistance in tetraploid wheat (<italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2007.03.0129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Reaction of wild emmer wheat accessions to Fusarium head blight.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>899</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2006.08.0531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kianian</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joppa</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Genetic dissection of a major Fusarium head blight QTL in tetraploid wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>625</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>632</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1014821929830</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11999839?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11999839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The 3ADON population of Fusarium graminearum found in North Dakota is more aggressive and produces a higher level of DON than the prevalent 15ADON population in spring wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytopathology</italic></source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>1007</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1014</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-12-09-0332</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20839936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20839936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devkota</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>&#x02018;TAM 112&#x02019; wheat, resistant to greenbug and wheat curl mite and adapted to the dryland production system in the southern high plains.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Plant Regist.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3198/jpr2014.03.0016crc</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>). <article-title>Factors affecting resistance of wheat to scab caused by <italic>Gibberella zeae</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytopathology</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>831</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>838</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedak</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Mapping of FHB resistance QTLs in tetraploid wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>1586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1593</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g06-127</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17426773?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17426773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetch</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joppa</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Fusarium head blight reaction of Langdon durum-<italic>Triticum dicoccoides</italic> chromosome substitution lines.</article-title>
<source><italic>Crop Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>637</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>642</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2002.6370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Identification of a Fusarium head blight resistance QTL on chromosome 6B in tetraploid wheat,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Abstracts of Plant and Animal Genome XIV Conference</italic></source>, (San Diego, CA: Scherago International), 172.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source><italic>A Visual Scale to Estimate Severity of Fusarium Head Blight in Wheat, NDSU 1095</italic>.</source>
<publisher-loc>Fargo, ND</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NDSU Extension Service</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nganje</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Economic costs of <italic>Fusarium</italic> head blight, scab and deoxynivalenol.</article-title>
<source><italic>World Mycotoxin J.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3920/WMJ2017.2204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiwart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchowilska</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandler</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulyok</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Groenwald</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krska</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Can Polish wheat (<italic>Triticum polonicum</italic> L.) be an interesting gene source for breeding wheat cultivars with increased resistance to Fusarium head blight?.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genet. Resour. Crop Evol.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>2359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2373</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10722-013-0004-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Fertility and meiotic mechanisms of hybrids between chromosome autoduplication tetraploid wheats and <italic>Aegilops species</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome</italic></source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>384</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g92-057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klindworth</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nygard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Evaluation and characterization of high-molecular weight 1D glutenin subunits from <italic>Aegilops tauschii</italic> in synthetic hexaploid wheats.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Cereal Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>52</volume>
<fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>336</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcs.2010.05.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23341752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23341752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Improving wheat disease resistance and yield potential by using CIMMYT synthetic germplasm in Sichuan, China,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Abstract Book 1st Synthetic Wheat Symp. Synthetics for Wheat Improvement</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Imtiaz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogbonnaya</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Ginkel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Horsham, VIC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Dept of Primary Industries), 8</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Synthetic hexaploid wheat and its utilization for wheat genetic improvement in China.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Genet. Genomics</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>546</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1673-8527(08)60145-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19782955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Lee</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waalwijk</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Population analysis of the <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic> species complex from wheat in China show a shift to more aggressive isolates.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>e31722</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0031722</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22363714?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22363714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Axtman</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Identification and molecular mapping of quantitative trait loci for Fusarium head blight resistance in emmer and durum wheat using a single nucleotide polymorphism-based linkage map.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Breed.</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>1677</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1687</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-014-0180-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Identification and molecular mapping of quantitative trait loci for resistance to Fusarium head blight in cultivated emmer PI 272527,&#x0201d; in</article-title>
<source><italic>Proceedings of the National Fusarium Head Blight Forum</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Canty</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiermer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanford</surname><given-names>D. Van</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Milwaukee, WI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wheat &#x00026; Barley Scab Initiative), 97</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018a</year>). <article-title>Molecular mapping of QTL for Fusarium head blight resistance introgressed into durum wheat.</article-title>
<source><italic>Theor. Appl. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>131</volume>
<fpage>1939</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1951</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-018-3124-4</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29869075?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29869075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanjugi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosz</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018b</year>). <article-title>Molecular mapping of Fusarium head blight resistance in the spring wheat line ND2710.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytopathology</italic></source>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>972</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>979</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-12-17-0392-R</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29561710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29561710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>