<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Med. Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5797868</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29199245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">17-0171</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.17-0171</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pathology</subject><subj-group><subject>Note</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Primary renal mixed tumor characterized by marked proliferation of osteoblast-like cells with osteoid formation in a swine</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>OSHIMA</surname><given-names>Yuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>NAKAGAWA</surname><given-names>Yuri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>KASHIMA</surname><given-names>Tsutae</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>MATSUNAGA</surname><given-names>Masako</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>KUSHIMA</surname><given-names>Shohei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>TANAKA</surname><given-names>Yukichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Meat Inspection Station, Kanagawa Prefectural Government, 892-1 Sakai, Atsugi, Kanagawa 243-0022, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>Kanagawa Prefectural Hospital Organization Kanagawa Childrens Medical Center, 2-138-4 Mutsukawa, Minami-ku, Yokohama, Kanagawa 232-8555, Japan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Oshima, Y.: <email xlink:href="oshima.nbw@pref.kanagawa.jp">oshima.nbw@pref.kanagawa.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>80</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2018 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. (CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"> https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Renal mixed tumor characterized by the absence of nephrogenic blastema and the presence of predominant osteoid-producing osteoblast-like cells occurred in the kidney of a 6-month-old, hybrid, female pig. At the
post-mortem examination, the tumor was found as a calcified grayish-white mass at the cranial end of the left kidney. Histologically the tumor consisted of 3 growth areas of poorly differentiated spindle cells,
osteoid-producing osteoblast-like cells, and luminal epithelial cells. Transition from the spindle cells to the osteoblast-like cells or the luminal epithelial cells was observed. Immunohistochemically, the spindle cells
and the osteoblast-like cells were consistently positive for &#x003b2;-catenin. Although the luminal epithelial cells and adjacent spindle cells were positive for cytokeratin, these 3 types of tumor cells were consistently
negative for WT1. The tumor was diagnosed as primary renal mixed tumor characterized by marked proliferation of osteoblast-like cells with osteoid formation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>kidney</kwd><kwd>mixed tumor</kwd><kwd>osteoid</kwd><kwd>swine</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Mixed tumors contain two or more neoplastic tissue components and are considered to be derived from pluripotential cells that have the ability to differentiate into multiple directions [<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In pigs, nephroblastoma is known as the most common primary renal tumors, however, little is known of mixed tumor other than nephroblastoma [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. We encountered a rare case
of mixed tumor characterized by mesenchymal cell growth with osteoid and epithelial cell growth with luminal structure. In humans, ossifying renal tumor of infancy (ORTI), a rare benign pediatric renal tumor, has been
described by the histological characteristics of marked osteoid formation, osteoblast-like cells and spindle cells, which resembled the present case closely [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In dogs, sarcomatoid renal cell carcinoma (SRCC) also showed similar histological future of sarcomatoid tissue with
osteogenic differentiation [<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In this report, a rare case of swine mixed tumor we encountered is distinguished from swine ordinary nephroblastoma at the histological and
immunohistochemical aspects, and discussed about the histological similarity with ORTI and SRCC.</p><p>A 6-month-old, hybrid, female pig was slaughtered at the Kanagawa meat center. No abnormalities were observed at the ante-mortem inspection. At the carcass inspection, a grayish-white mass, 5.0 &#x000d7; 3.5 &#x000d7; 2.0 cm, which was
odd-shaped with multiple millet seed-sized, calcified nodules on the surface or cross-section, was found at the cranial end of the left kidney (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Gross finding of the tumor: Grayish-white, medullary lesion with calcified core (arrow) and staghone-like lesion with largely calcified areas (arrowhead) are seen.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-80-112-g001"/></fig>). The tumor lacked a capsule but the border between the mass and adjacent renal tissue was relatively clear. Small hemorrhagic foci were dispersed in the mass. No neoplastic lesion was recognized in the other
organs.</p><p>Tissue samples were fixed in 10% neutral-buffered formalin and were embedded in paraffin wax. A portion of calcified samples was decalcified in 10% Na2EDTA for several days before embedding. Four-<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m
sections were cut and stained with hematoxylin and eosin (HE). For immunohistochemical examination, a polymer method (EnVision System-HRP; Dako, Tokyo, Japan) was used on deparaffinized sections with primary antibodies,
including mouse monoclonal anti-human cytokeratin (clone AE1/AE3; Dako), mouse monoclonal anti-human epithelial membrane antigen (EMA, clone E29; Dako), mouse monoclonal anti-human &#x003b2;-catenin (clone 14/&#x003b2;-catenin; BD
Transduction Laboratories, Lexington, KY, U.S.A.) and rabbit polyclonal anti-human WT1 (clone C-19; Santa Cruze Biotechnology, Dallas, TX, U.S.A.). Before incubation with primary antibodies, deparaffinized sections were
pretreated with microwave heating in Tris/EDTA buffer (pH9.0) for 20 min at 90&#x000b0;C. Polymer reagent (Peroxidase-labeled polymer-conjugated to goat anti-mouse and anti-rabbit IgG) was used as secondary antibodies. The reaction
products were visualized by 3,3&#x02032;-diaminobenzidine tetrahydrochloride (Dako) and the sections were counter-stained with hematoxylin. As a positive control for immunostaining of WT1, we used paraffin sections of a swine
nephroblastoma.</p><p>Histologically, the mass was mainly composed of 3 growth areas of poorly differentiated tumor cells, osteoblast-like cells with osteoid of varying size, and epithelial cells forming the luminal structures. Although the
proportion of these components varied by site, the area of osteoblast-like cells with osteoid accounted for the largest portion of the tumor, whereas the epithelial cells occupied the smallest area. The poorly differentiated
tumor cells were round to spindle shaped with round to oval nuclei containing distinct nucleoli, and small amount of eosinophilic cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2a</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>a) The tumor basically consists of fairly uniform and round to spindle shaped poorly differentiated tumor cells with round to oval nuclei containing distinct nucleoli and small amount of eosinophilic cytoplasm. HE.
Bar, 50 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m. b) The atypical osteoblast-like cells are polygonal shaped, and had abundant basophilic cytoplasm. They proliferate in insular or dense reticular pattern and surround the osteoid. HE. Bar,
50 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m. c) The luminal epithelium are cuboidal to columnar with anisokaryosis, karyomitosis. HE. Bar, 50 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-80-112-g002"/></fig>). Mitotic figures were noted often in the poorly differentiated tumor cells (12 mitoses in 10 consecutive high power fields). The atypical osteoblast-like cells were polygonal shaped, and had abundant basophilic
cytoplasm. They proliferated in insular or dense reticular pattern and surrounded the osteoid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2b</xref>). The form and amount of osteoid was highly variable. Transition from the
poorly differentiated tumor cells to the osteoblast-like cells was observed.</p><p>The epithelial cells of the luminal structures were cuboidal to columnar and showed anisokaryosis, karyomitosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2c</xref>). The luminal epithelial cells were scattered among the
dense sheet of poorly differentiated tumor cells, or predominated in some areas. They were apparently distinguished from the pre-existing glomeruli and renal tubules involved by the presence of their cytological atypia.
Transition from the poorly differentiated tumor cells to the luminal epithelial cells was also observed.</p><p>Immunohistochemical examination showed that the poorly differentiated tumor cells and osteoblast-like cells expressed &#x003b2;-catenin in the cytoplasm and the nuclei, and the renal tubular epithelium showed positive reaction to
the &#x003b2;-catenin in the cytoplasmic membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3a</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>a) The poorly differentiated tumor cells and osteoblast-like cells express &#x003b2;-catenin in the cytoplasm and the nuclei. IHC. Bar, 100 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m. b) The luminal epithelium and some poorly differentiated tumor
cells are positive for cytokeratin. IHC. Bar, 50 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m. c) EMA is only expressed in the cytoplasm of the osteoblast-like cells but in the other tumor components. IHC. Bar, 50 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m. Inset;
The adjacent renal tubular epithelium show positive reaction for EMA in the cytoplasmic membrane. IHC. Bar, 50 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m. d) Nuclear staining for WT1 is absent in any of the tumor cells. IHC. Bar, 100
<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m. Inset; The blastemal cells of nephroblastoma used as positive control are positive for WT1. IHC. Bar, 50 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-80-112-g003"/></fig>). The luminal epithelial cells and some of poorly differentiated tumor cells were positive for cytokeratin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3b</xref>). EMA was expressed in the cytoplasm of the osteoblast-like
cells but not in the luminal epithelial cells and the poorly differentiated tumor cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3c</xref>), while adjacent renal tubular epithelium showed positive reaction in the cytoplasmic
membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3c</xref>; inset). On the other hand, any of the tumor cells were consistently negative for WT1 although the nuclei of some pre-existing podocytes were positive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3d</xref>). In one case of nephroblastoma used as a positive control, the nuclei of neoplastic blastemal cells were often positive for WT1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig.
3d</xref>; inset). Immunoreactivity of individual components in tumor tissue is summarized in <xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table1.</label><caption><title>Immunoreactivity of individual components in tumor tissue</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor components</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytokeratin</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta-catenin</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT1</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poorly defferentiated tumor cell</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;/+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoblast-like cell</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luminal epithelial cell</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>+: positive, &#x02013;: negative, &#x02013;/+: partially positive.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>.</p><p>Histological and immunohistochemical findings showed that the 3 types of neoplastic cells as poorly differentiated tumor cells, osteoid-producing osteoblast-like cells and atypical luminal epithelial cells, the present case
was diagnosed as primary renal mixed tumor. The differential diagnosis included nephroblastoma, SRCC and ORTI.</p><p>Nephroblastoma is the most frequently observed renal neoplasms of the pig, accounting for approximately 40% of all porcine neoplasia [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The tumor is a triphasic mixture of embryonic
epithelium (glomerular buds and tubules), metanephric blastema and myxomatous mesenchyme in various amounts [<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Nephroblastoma appeared similar to the present case in that both tumors
contain the cellular components of both epithelial and mesenchymal origin [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. However, this case was lack of blastemal cells that represent
their characteristic morphology with oval or round, hyperchromatic nuclei and scant cytoplasm [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and their positive staining for WT1 [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. These results indicate that the poorly differentiated tumor cells are clearly distinct from the metanephric blastemal cells included in
nephroblastoma.</p><p>Renal cell carcinoma (RCC) is a malignant epithelial tumor without embryonal differentiation. Histologic types of RCC seen in animals are solid, tubular, papillary or cystic (multilocular cystic) and one of the most common
histologic characteristics is a mixture of these various cell types. Sarcomatoid features can be found rarely in RCC and when seen there is an obvious transition from one of the epithelial patterns into a spindle cell tumor
with high cellular and nuclear density [<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In dogs, SRCC with osteogenic differentiation was reported and closely similar to the present case in that both tumors were composed of
sarcomatoid tissue made up of spindle cells, polygonal cells with an abundant osteoid matrix and atypical epithelial cells [<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In the report, neoplastic epithelial cells were
organized to form papillae and the same degree of reactivity was observed for cytokeratin in papillary structures, as well as in mesenchymal tumor cells, indicated the transition from epithelial neoplastic cells to
mesenchymal tumor cells. Likewise, in the present case, the positive reaction to the cytokeratin shown in some poorly differentiated tumor cells represented the epithelial origin of this tumor cells and the mesenchymal
components such as the poorly defferentiated tumor cells were considered to be generate from neoplastic epithelial cells, presumably as a consequence of dedifferentiation. Hence, the present case is likely to be SRCC.</p><p>Marked osteoid formation by the osteoblast-like tumor cells was a notable histological feature of the present case. Ossifying lesion is rarely seen in nephroblastoma [<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], but little
is known of the description of osteoid formation as much as seen in the present case. Meanwhile, ORTI, defined as an intracalyceal mass composed of osteoid trabeculae, osteoblast-like cells and a spindle cell component,
arising from, and attached to the medullary pyramid, also shows marked osteoid formation, and transition of spindle cells to osteoblast-like cells with osteoid which expressed EMA [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], as seen in the present case. However, the luminal epithelial cells present in ORTI are not
considered to be neoplastic cells. Since the present case is composed of malignant epithelial component and osteosarcoma-like mesenchymal component, it is considered different from ORTI.</p><p>Beta-catenin plays an important role in cell adhesion as a cadherin lining protein in the cell membrane and is an essential effector of the Wnt signaling pathway [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The Wnt signaling
pathway is not only widely involved in the control of embryogenesis, it is also involved in the hereditary deseases and development of tumors [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Recently, &#x003b2;-catenin is known to
promote transformation of mesenchymal cell into osteogenic cells [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], and to be deeply involved in tumorigenesis [<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In the present case, also,
&#x003b2;-catenin may play a role in marked osteoid formation and development of this tumor. In fact, the poorly differentiated tumor cells were positive for &#x003b2;-catenin and showed morphological transformation ino the osteoblast-like
cells.</p><p>Although, the malignant features such as high mitotic index and atypia in the luminal epithelium were seen in the present case, it was difficult to assert that this tumor is malignant because there were no metastasis and
invasion.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year>. <article-title>Signal transduction by the Wnt family of ligands</article-title>. <source><italic>Biochem. J.</italic></source><volume>329</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>223</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/bj3290209</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9425102?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9425102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Grieco</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riccardi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belotti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanziani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>. <article-title>Immunohistochemical study of porcine nephroblastoma</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Comp. Pathol.</italic></source><volume>134</volume>:
<fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>151</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcpa.2005.09.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16540114?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16540114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Grubb</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeve</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year>. <article-title>Expression of WT1 protein in fetal kidneys and Wilms tumors</article-title>. <source><italic>Lab. Invest.</italic></source><volume>71</volume>:
<fpage>472</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>479</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7967503?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7967503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hard</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year>. <article-title>Histologic characterization of renal tumors (nephroblastomas) induced transplacentally in IIIVO/J and WH/J rabbits by N-ethylnitrosourea</article-title>.
<source><italic>Am. J. Pathol.</italic></source><volume>113</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 6312804?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6312804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyanagi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanioka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year>. <article-title>Ossifying renal tumor of infancy: the first Japanese case with long-term follow-up</article-title>. <source><italic>Pathol. Int.</italic></source><volume>48</volume>:
<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1827.1998.tb03885.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9589480?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9589480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kashima</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year>
<article-title>Detection of porcine tumor cases at the meet inspection office of Kanagawa Prefecture in 1970&#x02013;1990</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Jpn. Vet. Med.
Assoc.</italic></source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>436</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>440</lpage><comment> (in Japanese with English summary)</comment>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12935/jvma1951.48.436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Keen</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year> Ossifying renal tumor of infancy. p. 62. <italic>In</italic>: Pathology and Genetics of Tumours of the Urinary System and Male Genital Organs, World Health Organization Classification of
Tumors. (John, N. E., Guido, S., Jonathan, I. E. and Isabell, A. S. eds.), IARC Press, Lyon.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>. <article-title>Tumor formation by genetic mutations in the components of the Wnt signaling pathway</article-title>. <source><italic>Cancer Sci.</italic></source><volume>94</volume>:
<fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2003.tb01424.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12824913?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Kusewitt</surname><given-names>F. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year> Neoplasia and tumor biology. pp. 253&#x02013;298. <italic>In:</italic> Pathologic Basis of Veterinary Desease 4th ed. (McGavin, D. M. and Zachary, F. J. eds.), Mosby, St. Louis.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Mbalaviele</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stains</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>V. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Civitelli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year>. <article-title>&#x003b2;-catenin and BMP-2 synergize to promote osteoblast differentiation and new bone formation</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Cell.
Biochem.</italic></source><volume>94</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.20253</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15526274?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15526274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Meuten</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meuten</surname><given-names>T. L. K.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year> Tumor of the Urinary System. pp. 632&#x02013;688. <italic>In</italic>: Tumors in Domestic Animals 5th ed. (Donald, J. M. ed.), Wiley Blackwell.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Misdorp</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1976</year>. <article-title>Tumors of the kidney</article-title>. <source><italic>Bull. World Health Organ.</italic></source><volume>53</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1086154?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1086154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Polakis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year>. <article-title>Wnt signaling and cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>Genes Dev.</italic></source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1837</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1851</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10921899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10921899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sotelo-Avila</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year>. <article-title>Ossifying renal tumor of infancy: a clinicopathologic study of nine cases</article-title>. <source><italic>Pediatr. Pathol. Lab. Med.</italic></source><volume>15</volume>:
<fpage>745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>762</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/15513819509027010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8597860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8597860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">The Committee on Histological Classification of Childhood Tumors, The Japanese Society of Pathology. <year>2008</year>. Histological Classification and Color
Atlas of Tumors in Infancy and Childhood vol 4., Kinbara Publishing Co., Tokyo (in Japanese).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Zini</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bovero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nigrisoli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rampazzo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zatelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>. <article-title>Sarcomatoid renal cell carcinoma with osteogenic differentiation and paraneoplastic hepatopathy in a dog, possibly related to human Stauffer&#x02019;s syndrome</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Comp. Pathol.</italic></source><volume>129</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9975(03)00038-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14554128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14554128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>