<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bot Stud</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bot Stud</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Botanical Studies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1817-406X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1999-3110</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6203701</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">240</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40529-018-0240-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Grain width 2 (GW2) and its interacting proteins regulate seed development in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Kyu Ho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Sang Woo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Yeon Jeong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>Yeon Jong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Jong Tae</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Hak Soo</given-names></name><address><phone>+82-2-880-4548</phone><email>seohs@snu.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0470 5905</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.31501.36</institution-id><institution>Department of Plant Science, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Research Institute of Agriculture and Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Seoul National University, </institution></institution-wrap>Gwanakro 200, Gwanak-gu, Seoul, 151-921 South Korea </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0356 9399</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.14005.30</institution-id><institution>Department of Biological Chemistry, </institution><institution>Chonnam National University, </institution></institution-wrap>Gwangju, 61186 South Korea </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0661 1556</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.258803.4</institution-id><institution>School of Applied Biosciences, </institution><institution>Kyungpook National University, </institution></institution-wrap>Daegu, 41566 South Korea </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>59</volume><elocation-id>23</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Seed size has been extensively studied in crop plants, as it determines crop yield. However, the mechanism of seed development remains elusive. In this study, we explored the mechanism of seed development in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.), and identified proteins affecting seed size.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">Proteomic analysis showed that glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase, chitinase 14 (CHT14), and phosphoglycerate kinase (PGK) accumulated to high levels in the seeds of the natural <italic>japonica</italic> rice mutant Oochikara, which carries a loss-of-function mutation in the <italic>grain width 2</italic> (<italic>GW2</italic>) gene; <italic>GW2</italic> encodes a RING-type E3 ubiquitin ligase. In vitro pull-down and ubiquitination assays showed that CHT14 and PGK directly interacted with GW2 but were not ubiquitinated by GW2. Immunoblot analysis revealed that protein disulfide isomerase-like 1-1 accumulated to high levels in young developing seeds of the <italic>gw2</italic> mutant compared with the wild type. Histochemical <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>glucuronidase</italic> staining showed strong expression of <italic>GW2</italic> in leaf and root tissues but weak expression in leaf sheaths and internodes. In addition, transformation of the <italic>green fluorescent protein</italic> (<italic>GFP</italic>) gene under the control of the <italic>GW2</italic> promoter in rice revealed <italic>GFP</italic> expression in the aleurone layer of seeds.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">Collectively, these results suggest that GW2 regulates seed size through direct interactions with proteins involved in carbohydrate metabolism by modulating their activity or stability and controlling disulfide bond formation in various proteins during seed development. Additionally, GW2 participates in vegetative as well as reproductive growth, and protects the seed from pathogen attack.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Aleurone layer</kwd><kwd>CHT14</kwd><kwd>E3 ubiquitin ligase</kwd><kwd>GW2</kwd><kwd>PDIL1-1</kwd><kwd>PGK</kwd><kwd>Rice</kwd><kwd>Seed size</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Next-Generation BioGreen 21 Program</institution></funding-source><award-id>PJ01327601</award-id><award-id>PJ01330802</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Hak Soo</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par20">Post-translational modification of proteins involves the covalent addition of functional molecules of proteins, cleavage of protein subunits, or complete degradation of proteins. Ubiquitination is a type of post-translational modification in which the ubiquitin protein is covalently conjugated to the target protein (Ciechanover <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1994</xref>). Ubiquitination involves three sequential reactions, each catalyzed by three unique enzymes: an ubiquitin-activating enzyme E1, an ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme E2, and a specific ligase E3 (Vierstra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2009</xref>; Bie and Ciechanover <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2011</xref>; Kelley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2018</xref>). Ubiquitination is involved in the regulation of protein localization, stability, and activity (Kelley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2018</xref>). Target proteins undergo either monoubiquitination or polyubiquitination. The 26S proteasome complex degrades polyubiquitinated proteins but not monoubiquitinated proteins. Monoubiquitination affects the localization and function of the modified protein (Bie and Ciechanover <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2011</xref>). Ubiquitination is emerging as a key process in the regulation of seed size in crop plants (Song et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>; Choi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par21">Seed size is a major factor affecting grain yield in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) (Fan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR200">2006</xref>; Bai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR201">2010</xref>; Song et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>) and is controlled by the hull. Rice grain width 2 (GW2) is an E3 ubiquitin ligase, which contains a RING finger motif and shows both auto-ubiquitination and substrate ubiquitination activities (Song et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>; Choi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>). GW2 homologs have been identified in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>; TaGW2) and maize (Zea mays; ZmGW2); these are involved in the regulation of kernel size, weight, width, and maturity (Su et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2011</xref>; Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2010</xref>). Although progress has been made towards the cloning and characterization of seed size-related quantitative trait loci and genes, mechanisms determining seed size remain unclear. Recently, it was reported that GW2 directly interacts with and ubiquitinates EXPANSIN-LIKE 1 (EXPLA1), thus inactivating it.</p><p id="Par22">Here, we showed that GW2 strongly interacted with chitinase 14 (CHT14) and phosphoglycerate kinase (PGK) but did not ubiquitinate these proteins, suggesting that GW2 regulates seed size control via its interacting partners, CHT14 and PGK. Additionally, the level of protein disulfide isomerase-like 1-1 (PDIL1-1) was higher in young developing seeds of the <italic>gw2</italic> mutant than in the wild-type. Moreover, GW2 was specifically expressed in the aleurone layer. These data suggest that GW2 controls the development of the aleurone layer and the activity or stability of various proteins by regulating disulfide bond formation during seed development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Proteomic analysis of gw2 seeds</title><p id="Par23">Because GW2 protein contains a RING finger domain and has auto-ubiquitination activity, we hypothesized that it functions as an E3 ubiquitin ligase of target proteins involved in GW2-mediated seed development. We used a proteomics approach to identify GW2-interacting proteins. Proteomics is a useful method to identify proteins that accumulate in an organ- or development-specific manner (Cho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR202">2006</xref>). Soluble proteins were extracted from the seeds of the wild-type rice cultivar Norin 22 and those of the <italic>japonica</italic> rice <italic>gw2</italic> mutant, Oochikara. These proteins were separated in the first dimension via isoelectric focusing (IEF) on a pH gradient ranging from 4 to 7 and in the second dimension by sodium dodecyl sulfate&#x02013;polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) using 10% polyacrylamide gels (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Protein spots in parallel gels were cross-matched, demonstrating reproducibility. After electrophoresis, gels were analyzed using PDQuest software, and two-dimensional (2-D) gels were systematically compared. Three protein spots showing significant accumulation in <italic>gw2</italic> seeds were selected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b). Proteins in these spots were identified via Ettan matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS), followed by a homology search. The three proteins were identified as glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH), CHT14, and PGK.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Proteomic analysis of seed proteins in the <italic>grain width 2</italic> (<italic>gw2</italic>) mutant of rice, Oochikara. Total proteins were extracted from whole seeds and subjected to isoelectric focusing (IEF) in the first dimension, using immobilized pH gradient dry strips (pH 4&#x02013;7 nonlinear, 24&#x000a0;cm in length), and SDS-PAGE in the second dimension, using 10&#x02013;16% gradient polyacrylamide gels. Gels were stained with silver nitrate. Three independent biological replicates were performed. <bold>a</bold> 2D gels showing protein spots in wild-type and <italic>gw2</italic> mutant rice. Arrowheads indicate highly accumulated proteins in the <italic>gw2</italic> mutant compared with the wild type. Boxed regions shown in <bold>a</bold> are magnified in <bold>b</bold>. Spot #1, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH); spot #2, chitinase 14 (CHT14); spot #3, phosphoglycerate kinase (PGK)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40529_2018_240_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>GW2 interacts with but does not ubiquitinate PGK and CHT14</title><p id="Par24">To characterize GAPDH, PGK, and CHT14, we isolated the corresponding cDNAs using reverse transcriptase PCR (RT-PCR). Gene-specific primers were designed on the basis of sequences present in the nucleotide database of the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). Results of proteomic analysis showed the accumulation of these proteins in <italic>gw2</italic> seeds, implying that GW2 directly interacts with and possibly ubiquitinates these proteins, thus rendering them liable to degradation by the 26S proteasome complex. Next, we examined the possible interaction of GW2 with each of the three proteins using in vitro pull-down assay. Three recombinant plasmids encoding the maltose-binding protein (MBP) fused with GW2 (MBP-GW2) and glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase (GST) fused with CHT14 (GST-CHT14) and PGK (GST-PGK) were constructed and expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) cells. Recombinant proteins were then affinity purified (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a), and GST-CHT14 and GST-PGK were pulled down with either MBP or MBP-GW2. In vitro pull-down assay using MBP-GW2 confirmed that GW2 interacted with CHT14 and PGK (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). However, no interaction was detected between GW2 and GAPDH.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>GW2 interacts with PGK and CHT14. <bold>a</bold> Recombinant fusion proteins MBP-GW2, GST-PGK, and GST-CHT14 were overexpressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> and purified using amylose or glutathione resins. Arrowheads indicate MBP-GW2, GST-PGK, and GST-CHT14. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> In vitro pull-down assay showing the proteins GST-PGK (<bold>b</bold>) and GST-CHT14 (<bold>c</bold>) pulled down with MBP-GW2, separated on 10% SDS&#x02013;polyacrylamide gels, and detected by western blotting using anti-GST antibody. <italic>GST</italic> glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase, <italic>MBP</italic> maltose-binding protein, <italic>GW2</italic> grain width 2, <italic>PGK</italic> phosphoglycerate kinase, <italic>CHT14</italic> chitinase 14</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40529_2018_240_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par25">Direct interaction of GW2 with CHT14 and PGK raised the possibility that GW2 may ubiquitinate CHT14 and PGK. However, in vitro ubiquitination assays showed that both CHT14 and PGK were not ubiquitinated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, b), indicating that GW2 does not ubiquitinate CHT14 and PGK.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>GW2 does not ubiquitinate PGK and CHT14 in vitro. MBP-GW2, GST-PGK, and GST-CHT14 were overexpressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> and purified with amylose or glutathione affinity columns. Ubiquitination of GST-PGK (<bold>a</bold>) or GST-CHT14 (<bold>b</bold>) was examined in the presence or absence of rabbit E1, UbcH5b (E2), MBP-GW2 (E3), and His<sub>6</sub>-ubiquitin. PGK and CHT14 proteins were detected by western blotting using anti-GST antibody</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40529_2018_240_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>PDIL1-1 accumulates during early seed development in gw2 mutants</title><p id="Par26">PDIL1-1 regulates the amounts of various seed proteins, which in turn influence the development of endosperm and the aleurone layer (Kim et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2012</xref>). In addition, seeds of <italic>PDIL1</italic>-<italic>1&#x00394;</italic> exhibit a floury phenotype due to the production of irregular starch granules and protein bodies (Kim et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2012</xref>). Seeds of the <italic>gw2</italic> mutant also display a floury phenotype (Choi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>). Therefore, we examined the level of PDIL1-1 during seed development in the <italic>gw2</italic> mutant. Results showed that PDIL1-1 accumulated to high levels in <italic>gw2</italic> seeds at 5 and 10&#x000a0;days after flowering (DAF), whereas its level remained very low in wild-type seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a, b), suggesting that GW2 affects the level of PDIL1-1 protein.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Accumulation of PDIL1-1 protein in <italic>gw2</italic> mutant (Oochikara) and wild-type (Norin 22) seeds during development. Total proteins were extracted from Norin 22 and Oochikara seeds at the indicated time points. After SDS-PAGE, proteins were transferred onto a nitrocellulose membrane. <bold>a</bold> Immunodetection of PDIL1-1 protein using anti-PDIL1-1 antibody. <bold>b</bold> SDS&#x02013;polyacrylamide gel stained with Coomassie brilliant blue after blotting. PDIL1-1, protein disulfide isomerase-like 1-1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40529_2018_240_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>GW2 is highly expressed in panicles and anthers</title><p id="Par27">Previous studies showed that <italic>GW2</italic> is expressed in anthers, stamens, pistil, panicles, hull, and endosperm (Song et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>; Choi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>). To further examine the expression of <italic>GW2</italic>, we generated transgenic rice lines overexpressing <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-<italic>glucuronidase</italic> (<italic>GUS</italic>) and <italic>green fluorescent protein</italic> (<italic>GFP</italic>) reporter genes under the control of the <italic>GW2</italic> promoter. Histochemical staining of <italic>GW2</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub>-<italic>GUS</italic> plants showed that <italic>GUS</italic> was strongly expressed in leaves and roots but weakly in leaf sheaths and internodes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). Additionally, fluorescence detection in <italic>GW2</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub>-<italic>GFP</italic> plants revealed a strong GFP signal in the seed aleurone layer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>GFP</italic> reporter genes under the control of the <italic>GW2</italic> promoter. <bold>a</bold> Examination of <italic>GUS</italic> expression in <italic>GW2</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub>-<italic>GUS</italic> transgenic rice. <bold>b</bold> Detection of GFP fluorescence in <italic>GW2</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub>-<italic>GFP</italic> transgenic rice. GFP imaging was performed using a LAS 4000 imager. <italic>GW2</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub>
<italic>GW2</italic> promoter, <italic>GUS</italic> &#x003b2;-glucuronidase, <italic>GFP</italic> green fluorescent protein</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40529_2018_240_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par28">In this study, we show that GW2-interacting proteins, CHT14 and PGK, regulate GW2-mediated seed development. Additionally, GW2 participates in vegetative as well as reproductive growth. Previously, auto-ubiquitination and substrate ubiquitination activities of GW2 have been reported in vitro (Song et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>; Choi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>), suggesting that the E3 ligase activity of GW2 is required for the regulation of cell size in the spikelet hull. To further study the role of GW2 during seed development, we isolated GW2-interacting proteins whose level and stability were regulated by GW2 activity. Proteomic analysis of <italic>gw2</italic> mutant and wild-type seeds revealed that the levels of several proteins were higher in <italic>gw2</italic> mutant seeds than in wild-type seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b). Determination of amino acid sequences revealed that GAPDH, CHT14, and PGK proteins accumulated to high levels in <italic>gw2</italic> mutant seeds, suggesting that these proteins are destabilized by the E3 ubiquitin ligase activity of GW2. In vitro pull-down assay showed interaction of GW2 with CHT14 and PGK but not with GAPDH (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, b). Moreover, in vitro ubiquitination assay revealed that GW2 did not ubiquitinate CHT14 and PGK (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, b). CHT enzymes, which are encoded by a multigene family, degrade chitins and repress pathogen growth (Nakahara and Masuta <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2014</xref>). This suggests that CHTs play a pivotal role in plant immunity. Direct interaction between GW2 and CHT14 suggests that GW2 can be involved in the protection of the seeds from pathogen attack during development. PGK converts 1,3-bisphosphoglycerate into 3-phosphoglycerate during glycolysis but also participates in the reverse reaction during gluconeogenesis and the Calvin&#x02013;Benson cycle, indicating that PGK provides the building blocks for carbohydrate biosynthesis (Watson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1982</xref>; Brinkmann and Martin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">1996</xref>). Therefore, direct interaction between GW2 and PGK suggests that GW2 regulates carbohydrate biosynthesis during seed development. Together, these results suggest that the levels of CHT14 and PGK are not directly regulated by the E3 ligase activity of GW2. Nevertheless, direct interactions between GW2 and CHT14 or PGK suggest that GW2 can regulate the activity and level of CHT14 and PGK or, that CHT14 and PGK can control the activity of GW2.</p><p id="Par29">The natural <italic>gw2</italic> mutant Oochikara has a floury endosperm due to small, spherical, and loosely packed starch granules (Song et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>; Choi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>). This endosperm phenotype of Oochikara is similar to that of the <italic>PDIL1</italic>-<italic>1&#x00394;</italic> mutant; the floury endosperm phenotype of the <italic>pdil1</italic>-<italic>1</italic> deletion mutant is caused by the production of irregular starch granules and protein bodies (Kim et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2012</xref>). However, in Oochikara, PDIL1-1 accumulated to high levels during the early stages of seed development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). PDIL ensures proper protein folding through the formation and breakage of intramolecular disulfide bonds (Wilkinson and Gilbert <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR203">2004</xref>). How a high level of PDIL1-1 protein leads to the production of a floury endosperm is currently unknown. It is possible that PDIL1-1 stabilizes the enzymes involved in branching and debranching of carbohydrates or those involved in formation of protein bodies during early seed development in Oochikara. Failure to degrade these enzymes in a timely manner may lead to their stabilization, thus increasing their activity. Another possibility is that the loss-of-function of <italic>GW2</italic> changes the stability or activity of target proteins involved in endosperm development, including those involved in the formation of starch granules and protein bodies, leading to a floury endosperm. Further in vitro and in vivo analyses are required to elucidate whether PDIL1-1 level and activity are regulated by GW2 through direct interaction between PDIL1-1 and GW2. In addition, the effect of PDIL1-1 on seed phenotypes using transgenic Norin 22 and Oochikara plants overexpressing <italic>PDIL1</italic>-<italic>1</italic> also needs to be investigated.</p><p id="Par30">Investigation of gene expression in <italic>GW2</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub>-<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>GW2</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub>-<italic>GFP</italic> transgenic rice plants showed that <italic>GUS</italic> was highly expressed in leaves and roots but weakly in leaf sheaths and internodes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). Notably, <italic>GFP</italic> was highly expressed in the aleurone layer of seeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). Additionally, <italic>GW2</italic> expression has been previously demonstrated in various floral organs and seeds (Song et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>; Choi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>). All of these data strongly indicate that <italic>GW2</italic> regulates rice growth and development during vegetative as well as reproductive growth.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par31">Overall, we conclude that GW2 strongly interacts with CHT14 and PGK but does not ubiquitinate these proteins. Our data also suggest that CHT14 and PGK can participate in the regulation of the function of GW2, and that GW2 controls seed size through the regulation of CHT14 and PGK levels or activities as well as its E3 ubiquitin ligase activity. Further analysis of transgenic plants will provide insights into how CHT14, PGK, and PDIL1-1 participate in GW2-mediated regulation of vegetative and reproductive growth of rice plants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Plant material and growth conditions</title><p id="Par32">The natural <italic>japonica</italic> rice <italic>gw2</italic> mutant Oochikara (Accession No. 54075) was obtained from the National Institute of Agrobiological Sciences (NIAS), Japan, and the wild-type rice cultivar Norin 22 was kindly provided by Dr. Hee Jong Koh, Seoul National University. Rice plants were grown at 26&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under long day conditions (16&#x000a0;h light/8&#x000a0;h dark) in the greenhouse or field.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>2D PAGE and MALDI-TOF MS</title><p id="Par33">Total proteins were extracted from the seeds of &#x02018;Norin 22&#x02019; and &#x02018;Oochikara&#x02019; using homogenizing buffer (7&#x000a0;M urea, 2&#x000a0;M thiourea, 4% CHAPS, 1% DTT, 2% pharmalyte, and 1&#x000a0;mM benzamidine). Protein concentrations were determined using the Bradford assay (Bio-Rad, Bradford <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1976</xref>), and proteins were subjected to 2D PAGE as described previously (Yeu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2007</xref>). The signal intensity of each spot was normalized relative to the total spot intensity. Three protein spots, which accumulated to high levels in <italic>gw2</italic> mutant seeds, were subjected to in-gel digestion using modified porcine trypsin. Proteins were identified using an Ettan MALDI-TOF (Amersham Biosciences) as described previously (Yeu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Construction of recombinant plasmids</title><p id="Par34">To produce MBP-GW2, GST-CHT14, GST-GAPDH, and GST-PGK fusion proteins, cDNA sequences encoding full-length GW2, CHT14, GAPDH, and PGK were PCR amplified using gene-specific primers and cloned into pMALc2 (New England Biolabs) or pGEX4T-1 (Amersham Biosciences) vectors. Recombinant plasmids were transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> strain BL21 (DE3) pLysS, and the expression of recombinant proteins was induced with the addition of 5&#x000a0;mM isopropyl-&#x003b2;-<sc>d</sc>-thiogalactoside (IPTG).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Purification of recombinant proteins</title><p id="Par35">Recombinant proteins expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 cells were purified according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Cells expressing MBP or MBP-GW2 were resuspended and sonicated in a buffer containing 20&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.4), 200&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 1&#x000a0;mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, 2&#x000a0;mM PMSF, and proteinase inhibitor cocktail (Roche). Total protein extracts were loaded onto a column packed with amylose resin (New England Biolabs). Columns were washed with buffer containing 20&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.4), 200&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 1&#x000a0;mM EDTA, and 1% Triton X-100, and MBP and MBP-GW2 recombinant proteins were eluted with 10&#x000a0;mM maltose.</p><p id="Par36">To purify GST fusion proteins, <italic>E. coli</italic> cells expressing GST-CHT14, GST-GAPDH, and GST-PGK were resuspended and sonicated in buffer containing 50&#x000a0;mM Tris, 50&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 1&#x000a0;mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, 2&#x000a0;mM PMSF, and proteinase inhibitor cocktail (Roche). Total protein extracts were loaded onto a column packed with glutathione resin (Pharmacia), and columns were washed with buffer containing 50&#x000a0;mM Tris, 50&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 1&#x000a0;mM EDTA, and 1% Triton X-100. The recombinant proteins GST-CHT14, GST-GAPDH, and GST-PGK were eluted using 10&#x000a0;mM glutathione. All protein concentrations were determined using the Bradford assay (Bio-Rad).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>In vitro pull-down assays</title><p id="Par37">Interactions of MBP-GW2 with GST-CHT14, GST-PGK, and GST-GAPDH were examined using in vitro pull-down assay. Two micrograms of MBP-GW2 was mixed with 2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g of GST-PGK, GST-CHT14, or GST-GAPDH, and this mixture was added to the reaction buffer containing 50&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 100&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 1% Triton X-100, 0.2% glycerol, and 0.5&#x000a0;mM 2-mercaptoethanol. Reaction mixtures were incubated at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;h and then purified using the amylose resin. Resins were washed with buffer containing 50&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 100&#x000a0;mM NaCl, and 1% Triton X-100 five times. Proteins were eluted using 10&#x000a0;mM glutathione and separated by 10% SDS-PAGE. The GST fusion proteins were detected by immunoblotting using anti-GST antibody (0.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g&#x000a0;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; Santa Cruz Biotechnology).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>In vitro ubiquitination assay</title><p id="Par38">In vitro ubiquitination reactions were carried out in reaction buffer containing 50&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.4), 5&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 2&#x000a0;mM ATP, and 1&#x000a0;mM DTT. Each reaction mixture contained 50&#x000a0;ng of E1 (Boston Biochem), 100&#x000a0;ng of E2 (Boston Biochem), 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g of His<sub>6</sub>-ubiquitin (Sigma), 200&#x000a0;ng of MBP-GW2, and 100&#x000a0;ng of GST-CHT14 or GST-PGK. Reactions were incubated at 30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x000a0;h, and proteins were separated by 10% SDS-PAGE. Ubiquitination of GST-CHT14 and GST-PGK was examined by immunoblotting with anti-GST antibody (0.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g&#x000a0;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; Santa Cruz Biotechnology).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Promoter activity analysis</title><p id="Par39">Transgenic rice lines overexpressing <italic>GW2</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub>-<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>GW2</italic><sub><italic>pro</italic></sub>-<italic>GFP</italic> were generated as described previously (Choi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2018</xref>). Histochemical GUS staining assays were carried out as described previously (Shomura et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2008</xref>). Specimens were photographed using the OLYMPUS SZX7 microscope. GFP fluorescence in flowers and immature seeds of transgenic and wild-type rice plants was observed using a fluorescence microscope (LAS 4000 imager, GE Life Sciences).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p id="Par40">The level of PDIL1-1 protein during seed development was examined in wild-type and <italic>gw2</italic> mutant rice seeds harvested at 5, 10, 20, and 30 DAF. Total proteins were extracted from whole grains using buffer containing 50&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;Cl (pH 7.5), 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 1% Triton X-100, and 1&#x000a0;mM PMSF, and then separated by 10% SDS-PAGE. The PDIL1-1 protein was detected by immunoblotting with anti-PDIL1-1 antibody as described previously (Kim et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2012</xref>).</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CHT14</term><def><p id="Par4">chitinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>E. coli</italic></term><def><p id="Par5">
<italic>Escherichia coli</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EXPLA1</term><def><p id="Par6">EXPANSIN-LIKE 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GAPDH</term><def><p id="Par7">glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GFP</term><def><p id="Par8">green fluorescence protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GST</term><def><p id="Par9">glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GUS</term><def><p id="Par10">&#x003b2;-glucuronidase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GW2</term><def><p id="Par11">grain width 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MALDI-TOF</term><def><p id="Par12">matrix assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MBP</term><def><p id="Par13">maltose binding protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PAGE</term><def><p id="Par14">polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PDIL1-1</term><def><p id="Par15">protein disulfide isomerase-like 1-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PGK</term><def><p id="Par16">phosphoglycerate kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RING</term><def><p id="Par17">real interesting new gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RT-PCR</term><def><p id="Par18">real time polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDS</term><def><p id="Par19">sodium dodecyl sulfate</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>HSS designed the project. YJK and MK carried out experiments. KHL, SWP, YJK, JTS and HSS analyzed and interpreted the data. KHL, SWP and HSS wrote the manuscript. All authors commented on the results and the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par41">We appreciate Dr. Hee Jong Koh for providing wild-type Norin 22 rice.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par42">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par43">No applicable for that section.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par44">No applicable for that section.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par45">No applicable for that section.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par46">This work was supported by a grant from the Next-Generation BioGreen 21 Program (Plant Molecular Breeding Center No. PJ01327601), Rural Development Administration, Republic of Korea. This work was also supported by a grant from the Next-Generation BioGreen 21 Program (Plant Molecular Breeding Center No. PJ01330802), Rural Development Administration, Republic of Korea and supported by Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education (Grant Number: 2015057573).</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par47">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR201"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic dissection of rice grain shape using a recombinant inbred line population derived from two contrasting parents and fine mapping a pleiotropic quantitative trait locus qGL7</article-title><source>BMC Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-11-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20184774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciechanover</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitination of E3 ligases: self-regulation of the ubiquitin system via proteolytic and non-proteolytic mechanisms</article-title><source>Cell Death Differ</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1393</fpage><lpage>1402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cdd.2011.16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21372847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1976</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(76)90527-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brinkmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Higher-plant chloroplast and cytosolic 3-phosphoglycerate kinases: a case of endosymbiotic gene replacement</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00017803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8616244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR202"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Subbramanyam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Deepak</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sardesai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein extraction/solubilization protocol for monocot and dicot plant gel-based proteomics</article-title><source>J Plant Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03031120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Markkandan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GW2 functions as an E3 ubiquitin ligase for rice expansin-like 1</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>E1904</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms19071904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29958473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciechanover</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ubiquitin-proteasome proteolytic pathway</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>79</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(94)90396-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7923371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR200"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GS3, a major QTL for grain length andweight and minor QTL for grain width and thickness in rice, encodes a putative transmembrane protein</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1164</fpage><lpage>1171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0218-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>E3&#x000a0;ubiquitin&#x000a0;ligases: key regulators of hormone signaling in plants</article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.MR117.000476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29514858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhoo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rice protein disulfide isomerase (OsPDI) and rice chaperone binding protein (OsBiP) levels are not directly correlated with the eating quality of rice</article-title><source>J Korean Soc Appl Biol Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3839/jksabc.2010.077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahuku</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and characterization of a putative GS3 ortholog involved in maize kernel development</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-009-1196-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19898828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakahara</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction between viral RNA silencing suppressors and host factors in plant immunity</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2014.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24875766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shomura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Izawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebitani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanegae</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deletion in a gene associated with grain size increased yields during rice domestication</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18604208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A QTL for rice grain width and weight encodes a previously unknown RING-type E3 ubiquitin ligase</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17417637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and development of a functional marker of TaGW2 associated with grain weight in bread wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>122</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-010-1437-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20838758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ubiquitin-26S proteasome system at the nexus of plant biology</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19424292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendell</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fothergill</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Conroy</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuite</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence and structure of yeast phosphoglycerate kinase</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1982</year><volume>1</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>4160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1982.tb01366.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6765200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR203"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein disulfide isomerase</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2004</year><volume>1699</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1570-9639(04)00063-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15158710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeu</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The serine proteinase inhibitor OsSerpin is a potent tillering regulator in rice</article-title><source>J Plant Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>50</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03030715</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>