<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6345851</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">36777</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-36777-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The effects of drought and nutrient addition on soil organisms vary across taxonomic groups, but are constant across seasons</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9720-4146</contrib-id><name><surname>Siebert</surname><given-names>Julia</given-names></name><address><email>julia.siebert@idiv.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>S&#x000fc;nnemann</surname><given-names>Marie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7432-8453</contrib-id><name><surname>Auge</surname><given-names>Harald</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>Sigrid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cesarz</surname><given-names>Simone</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ciobanu</surname><given-names>Marcel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guerrero-Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>Nathaly R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0371-6720</contrib-id><name><surname>Eisenhauer</surname><given-names>Nico</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.421064.5</institution-id><institution>German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research (iDiv) Halle-Jena-Leipzig, Deutscher Platz 5e, </institution></institution-wrap>04103 Leipzig, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2230 9752</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9647.c</institution-id><institution>Institute of Biology, </institution><institution>Leipzig University, Deutscher Platz 5e, </institution></institution-wrap>04103 Leipzig, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0493 728X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.425084.f</institution-id><institution>Martin-Luther-University Halle-Wittenberg, </institution><institution>Leibniz Institute of Plant Biochemistry, </institution></institution-wrap>Weinberg 3, 06120 Halle, Saale Germany </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0492 3830</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7492.8</institution-id><institution>Department of Community Ecology, </institution><institution>Helmholtz-Centre for Environmental Research &#x02013; UFZ, </institution></institution-wrap>Theodor-Lieser-Str. 4, 06120 Halle, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Institute of Biological Research, Branch of the National Institute of Research and Development for Biological Sciences, 48 Republicii Street, 400015 Cluj Napoca, Romania </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>639</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Anthropogenic global change alters the activity and functional composition of soil communities that are responsible for crucial ecosystem functions and services. Two of the most pervasive global change drivers are drought and nutrient enrichment. However, the responses of soil organisms to interacting global change drivers remain widely unknown. We tested the interactive effects of extreme drought and fertilization on soil biota ranging from microbes to invertebrates across seasons. We expected drought to reduce the activity of soil organisms and fertilization to induce positive bottom-up effects <italic>via</italic> increased plant productivity. Furthermore, we hypothesized fertilization to reinforce drought effects through enhanced plant growth, resulting in even drier soil conditions. Our results revealed that drought had detrimental effects on soil invertebrate feeding activity and simplified nematode community structure, whereas soil microbial activity and biomass were unaffected. Microbial biomass increased in response to fertilization, whereas invertebrate feeding activity substantially declined. Notably, these effects were consistent across seasons. The dissimilar responses suggest that soil biota differ vastly in their vulnerability to global change drivers. Thus, important ecosystem processes like decomposition and nutrient cycling, which are driven by the interdependent activity of soil microorganisms and invertebrates, may be disrupted under future conditions.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001659</institution-id><institution>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (German Research Foundation)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>FZT 118</award-id><award-id>FZT 118</award-id><award-id>FZT 118</award-id><award-id>FZT 118</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Siebert</surname><given-names>Julia</given-names></name><name><surname>Auge</surname><given-names>Harald</given-names></name><name><surname>Cesarz</surname><given-names>Simone</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenhauer</surname><given-names>Nico</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Anthropogenic global environmental change affects ecosystem properties worldwide and threatens important ecosystem functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Climate change is predicted to alter precipitation regimes towards more frequent and severe drought events in the future<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Simultaneously, human activities, such as fossil fuel combustion and fertilization, are causing an acceleration of the turnover rates of the nitrogen cycle and will double nitrogen deposition in the future<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. The same is true for phosphorous inputs, which also increased at a global scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Thus, multiple global change drivers are occurring side by side, and their effects are not necessarily additive or antagonistic. Our knowledge on their interactive effects, however, is still highly limited<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. This is particularly true for the responses of soil organisms, which mediate crucial ecosystem functions and services, such as nutrient cycling and decomposition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Their significant role is not adequately reflected in the body of global change literature yet. Therefore, a more comprehensive understanding of above- and belowground dynamics is key to predict the responses of terrestrial ecosystems in a changing world<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Many soil organisms are dependent on a water-saturated atmosphere or on water films on soil aggregates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Altered precipitation patterns will result in drought periods, which are likely to have substantial effects on their abundances and community structure, thus affecting important soil organism-mediated ecosystem processes. Previous studies reported detrimental effects of drought on soil microbial respiration and biomass as well as a reduction of the diversity of microbial communities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Furthermore, drought was shown to cause a decline in soil microarthropod abundances<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. In contrast, drought seems to have only marginal effects on nematode community composition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Yet, a reduction of soil moisture content can induce community shifts <italic>via</italic> lower trophic levels, often favouring fungal-feeding nematodes over bacteria-feeders, as fungi perform relatively better under dry conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Nutrient enrichment is another key factor that affects the soil community by altering the physical and chemical properties of the soil, e.g., by influencing pH, soil porosity, and organic fractions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Nitrogen addition has been identified to decrease soil microbial respiration and biomass, often leading to shifts in the soil microbial community composition under the use of mineral fertilizer (NPK)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. On the other hand, fertilization treatments were shown to increase soil microbial catabolic and functional diversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Furthermore, nitrogen addition alters the nematode community structure towards bacterivores, thus promoting the bacterial-dominated decomposition pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, and was shown to simplify communities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Similarly, nitrogen was reported to create unfavourable conditions for soil microarthropods, leading to declines in abundance as well as diversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. At the same time, nitrogen enrichment is one of the major drivers determining aboveground primary production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Nitrogen and phosphorous addition are known to increase total aboveground biomass and consequently the quantity and quality of plant litter input to the soil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. In addition, nitrogen also affects plant rhizodeposition by altering the amount and quality of substrates released from roots<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Both mechanisms can potentially enhance resource availability <italic>via</italic> bottom-up effects and can therefore increase soil microarthropod abundances<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Concurrently, the fertilization-induced increase in aboveground biomass may cause higher transpiration rates, which are likely to reinforce drought effects on soil organisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">To investigate the interactive effects of extreme drought events and fertilization (NPK), we established a field experiment at the UFZ Experimental Research Station (Bad Lauchst&#x000e4;dt, Germany), which combines the treatments of two globally distributed networks &#x02013; the Drought-Network and the Nutrient Network<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Here, we tested the responses of soil microorganisms, nematodes, and overall soil invertebrate activity to the interactive effects of extreme drought and fertilization (NPK) across all seasons. Based on prior research, we hypothesized that (1) drought will reduce the activity of soil organisms, whereas (2) fertilization will increase their activity, owing to enhanced plant litter input that subsequently increases resource availability for soil organisms. Furthermore, we predicted that (3) the interactive effects of drought and fertilization will result in detrimental conditions for soil organisms as the negative effects of drought were expected to be further enhanced by increased plant growth under fertilization, resulting in reduced soil water availability for soil organisms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Research site</title><p id="Par6">The study site is located at the Experimental Research Station of the Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research (UFZ), which is situated in Bad Lauchst&#x000e4;dt, Germany. The field site is located in the central German dry area with a mean annual precipitation of 487&#x02009;mm and an average annual daily temperature of 8.9&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Meteorological data of Bad Lauchst&#x000e4;dt, Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research GmbH - UFZ, Department of Soil System Science, 1896&#x02013;2017). The area represents an anthropogenic grassland, which is maintained by moderate mowing (twice a year since 2012). It is a successional plant community dominated by <italic>Vulpia myuros</italic> (L.) C. C. Gmel., <italic>Picris hieracioides</italic> (L.) and <italic>Taraxacum officinale</italic> (F. H. Wigg.) with <italic>Apera spica-venti</italic> (L.) P. Beauv. and <italic>Cirsium arvense</italic> (L.) Scop. being very common. The soil is classified as a haplic chernozem, developed upon carbonatic loess substrates, distinguished by a composition of 70% silt and 20% clay<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Within the upper 30&#x02009;cm, the soil contains 0.18% total nitrogen, 1&#x02009;g&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> total phosphorus, and 20&#x02009;g&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> total potassium. For more details see Altermann <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Weather conditions</title><p id="Par7">Weather conditions within the two-year sampling period of this study were in line with the long-term average (2005&#x02013;2015) despite some exceptions (Meteorological data of Bad Lauchst&#x000e4;dt, Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research GmbH - UFZ, Department of Soil System Science): precipitation patterns deviated from the long-term average in 2016 with a dry May (21.2&#x02009;mm compared to an average of 62.3&#x02009;mm) and a wet June (80.2&#x02009;mm compared to an average of 41.2). September tended to be drier than usual in both years (19.5&#x02009;mm in 2016 and 22.1&#x02009;mm in 2017 compared to an average of 51.8&#x02009;mm).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Experimental design and treatments</title><p id="Par8">The experimental site was established in March 2015. The experimental design consists of five blocks with five plots each. The plots have a size of 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2&#x02009;m and are arranged at a distance of 3&#x02009;m from each other (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The experiment includes two treatments with two levels each (first applied in March 2016): drought (control/drought) and fertilization (no NPK/NPK addition), as well as their interaction (drought &#x000d7; fertilization). Notably, this experiment crosses treatments of two globally distributed experimental networks: the full NPK fertilization treatment of the Nutrient Network<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> and the drought treatment of the Drought-Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drought-net.colostate.edu/">http://www.drought-net.colostate.edu/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par9">In order to simulate drought, a rainfall manipulation system was established<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> using corrugated acrylic strips. The roofs have a size of 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3&#x02009;m and reduce precipitation by 55% throughout the year, simulating a severe long-term reduction in precipitation. Roofs were built with a slope of 20&#x000b0; to ensure water runoff and account for the expected snow load in the region. Exclusion of potential artefacts was realized by equal roof constructions using inverted acrylic strips intended to let rainfall pass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). To control for possible infrastructure effects of the roof constructions itself, a fifth plot was added to each block without any roof construction (ambient plots), thus receiving ambient precipitation (not crossed with the fertilization treatment and thus only used to assess if the roof construction itself affected soil water content, see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). To validate the drought treatment, soil water content was quantified on all plots in every sampling campaign. All three precipitation levels differed significantly in their soil water content (Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05): as intended, the lowest soil water content was found for the drought treatment (&#x02212;19.4% compared to the ambient plots). Also the infrastructure control plots (with concave roof constructions) differed significantly from the ambient plots (without roof construction), indicating that there were effects of the roof construction itself (&#x02212;13.4%). Furthermore, soil water content varied significantly between seasons (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).</p><p id="Par10">The fertilization treatment was realized by annual addition of a mixture of separate fertilizers for nitrogen (N), phosphorus (P) and potassium (K) (i.e. NPK fertilization; applied at 10&#x02009;g&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> y<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> by elemental mass for each of the three main fertilizer elements) before each growing season. Following the protocol of the Nutrient Network<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, we used coated urea (CO(NH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>) as nitrogen fertilizer (Multicote, Haifa &#x02013; Pioneering the Future Haifa, Matam-Haifa, Israel), P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> as phosphorus fertilizer (Triple Super Phosphate, Delitzscher Landhandels- und Dienste GmbH, Delitzsch, Germany), and K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> as potassium fertilizer (KaliSOP gran. max. 1.0% Cl, K&#x02009;+&#x02009;S KALI GmbH, Kassel, Germany). In addition, the micronutrient mix &#x0201c;Micromax Premium&#x0201d; (Everris, Geldermalsen, The Netherlands) was applied in the first treatment year<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Specifically, we applied 25&#x02009;g&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x000b2; Multicote, 50.9&#x02009;g&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x000b2; Triple Super Phosphate, and 22.3&#x02009;g&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x000b2; KaliSOP per year, and 100&#x02009;g&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x000b2; Micromax Premium in the first year.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Soil sampling</title><p id="Par11">The first soil sampling took place in March 2016. Sampling campaigns were repeated every three months to cover every season (spring, summer, fall, winter) from March 2016 to December 2017 (i.e., eight samplings across two years). Samples were taken on all plots with roof construction (drought and control) with a steel core sampler (1&#x02009;cm in diameter; 15&#x02009;cm deep). Seven subsamples per plot were homogenized, sieved at 2&#x02009;mm, and stored at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Soil samples were used to determine soil water content and microbial respiration. In addition, nematodes were extracted from the soil samples in spring and summer of 2017, and pH was measured for all four seasons in 2017.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>The Bait Lamina Test</title><p id="Par12">Feeding activity of soil invertebrates was surveyed using the bait lamina test (Terra Protecta GmbH, Berlin, Germany), which presents a commonly used rapid ecosystem function assessment method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The test uses rigid PVC sticks (1&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;6&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;120&#x02009;mm) with 16 holes of 1.5&#x02009;mm diameter in 5&#x02009;mm distance. Original sticks were filled with a bait substrate consisting of 70% cellulose powder, 27% wheat bran, and 3% activated carbon, which was prepared according to the recommendations of Terra Protecta. The bait substrate is primarily consumed by mites, collembolans, nematodes, enchytraeids, millipedes, and earthworms, whereas microbial activity plays a minor role in bait loss<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. The bait strips were inserted vertically into the soil with the topmost hole just below the ground surface. To avoid damaging the strips, a steel knife was used to prepare the ground prior to insertion. Five strips were used per plot to account for spatial heterogeneity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. For each sampling campaign, the bait lamina strips were removed from the soil after three weeks of exposure and evaluated directly in the field. Bait consumption was recorded for each of the 16 holes per strip as empty (1), partly empty (0.5), or filled (0). Thus, soil invertebrate feeding activity per bait strip could range from 0 to 16 (maximum feeding activity). Mean bait consumption per plot (averaged among the five strips) was calculated prior to statistical analyses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Microbial biomass and activity</title><p id="Par13">An O<sub>2</sub>-microcompensation system was used to measure the respiratory response of soil microorganisms in two separated steps using approximately 6.5&#x02009;g of fresh soil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. First, basal respiration was determined as a measure of soil microbial activity (&#x000b5;l O<sub>2</sub> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> soil dry weight) without the addition of any substrate. Second, the maximal respiratory response to a single addition of glucose (4&#x02009;mg&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry weight soil, solved in 1.5&#x02009;ml distilled water) allowed us to determine soil microbial biomass (&#x003bc;g Cmic g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> soil dry weight)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. For an overview of the experimental setup see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Nematode analysis</title><p id="Par14">Nematode extraction was conducted with a modified Baermann method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Approximately 25&#x02009;g of soil per plot were transferred to plastic vessels with a milk filter and a fine gauze (200&#x02009;&#x000b5;m) at the bottom and placed in water-filled funnels. More water was added to saturate the soil samples and to ensure a connected water column throughout the sample and the funnel. Hence, nematodes migrated from the soil through the milk filter and the gauze into the water column and gravitationally-settled at the bottom of a closed tube connected to the funnel. After 72&#x02009;h at 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, the nematodes were transferred to a 4% formaldehyde solution. Nematodes were counted at 100x magnification using a Leica DMI 4000B light microscope. Identification was conducted at 400x magnification. For identification, sediment material from the bottom of each sample vial was extracted with a 2&#x02009;ml plastic pipette and examined in temporary mounted microscope slides. At least 100 well-preserved specimens (if available in the sample) were randomly selected and identified to genus (adults and most of the juveniles) or family level (juveniles), following Bongers (1988)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Nematode taxa were then arranged into trophic groups (bacteria-, fungal- and plant-feeders, omnivores and predators)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. Due to low densities, omnivorous and predatory nematodes were grouped into a combined feeding type for most analyses, which was based on the fact that both groups often share similar traits, like being carnivores (i.e. representing higher trophic levels) and being persisters rather than colonizers on the c-p scale (see explanation below), thus responding similarly to environmental disturbances<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Nematodes were ordered according to the colonization-persistence gradient (c-p values)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>, which classifies nematode taxa based on their life history strategy (i.e. r or K strategists). Cp-1 taxa are distinguished by their short generation cycles and high fecundity. They mainly feed on bacteria. Cp-2 taxa have longer generation times, lower fecundity and consist of bacterivores and fungivores<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Both are categorized as r-strategists. Cp-3 to cp-5 are classified as K-strategist nematodes with longer generation times, higher trophic feeding levels and increasing sensitivity against disturbances<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. The c-p-values can be used to calculate the Maturity Index (MI) as weighted means of nematode families assigned to c-p-values. It is used to describe soil health and as an indicator of overall food web complexity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>.<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$MI=\sum _{i=1}^{n}\,(\begin{array}{c}n\\ k\end{array})\,v(i)\,\ast \,f(i)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36777_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>with <italic>v(i)</italic> being the c-p-value of a taxon i and <italic>f(i</italic>) being the frequency of that taxon in a sample.</p><p id="Par15">Furthermore, nematode taxa were assigned to functional guilds according to Ferris <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>, which then served as a basis to calculate additional indices. Functional guilds refer to the following trophic groups: bacterial feeders (Ba<sub>X</sub>), fungal feeders (Fu<sub>X</sub>), omnivores (Om<sub>X</sub>), and carnivores (Ca<sub>X</sub>). Associated numbers (i.e., the x of the respective trophic group) are again referring to the c-p values described above. The Enrichment Index (EI) indicates the responsiveness of the opportunistic bacterial (Ba<sub>1</sub> and Ba<sub>2</sub>) and fungal feeders (Fu<sub>2</sub>) to food web enrichment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> and is calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{EI}}=100\times [\frac{{\rm{e}}}{{\rm{e}}+{\rm{b}}}]$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">EI</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36777_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>with <italic>e</italic> as weighted frequencies of Ba<sub>1</sub> and Fu<sub>2</sub> and <italic>b</italic> as weighted frequencies of Ba<sub>2</sub> and Fu<sub>2</sub> nematodes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. The Channel Index (CI) reflects the nature of decomposition channels through the soil food web. High values indicate a predominant decomposition pathway of organic matter dominated by fungal-feeding nematodes, whereas low values refer to bacterial-dominated decomposition pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>.<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{CI}}=100\times [0.8\times \frac{{\rm{Fu}}2}{3.2\times {\rm{Ba}}1+0.8\times {\rm{Fu}}2}]$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CI</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Fu</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ba</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Fu</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36777_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>with 0.8 and 3.2 representing enrichment weightings for Fu<sub>2</sub> and Ba<sub>1</sub> nematodes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. The Structure Index (SI) provides information about the complexity of the soil food web. A highly structured food web with a high SI suggests ecosystem stability, while low values imply environmental disturbance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>.<disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{SI}}=100\times [\frac{{\rm{s}}}{{\rm{s}}+{\rm{b}}}]$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">SI</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36777_Article_Equd.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>with <italic>s</italic> calculated as the weighted frequencies of Ba<sub>3</sub>-Ba<sub>4</sub>, Fu<sub>3</sub>-Fu<sub>4</sub>, Ca<sub>3</sub>-Ca<sub>5</sub> and Om<sub>3</sub>-Om<sub>5</sub> nematodes, and <italic>b</italic> representing the weighted frequencies of Ba<sub>2</sub> and Fu<sub>2</sub> nematodes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Statistical analyses</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Soil microorganisms and invertebrates</title><p id="Par16">Linear mixed-effects models (LMM) were used to analyse the effects of drought, NPK fertilization, season, and their interactions on invertebrate feeding activity, microbial activity, and microbial biomass using the R-package &#x0201c;<italic>nlme</italic>&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. The random intercept of the model was structured with plots nested within blocks, nested within year (year as a categorical factor). To account for repeated measurements within plots, we compared first-order autoregressive and compound symmetry covariance structures based on the Akaike information criterion (AIC). As differences between AIC values were lower than 2, the simplest covariance structure (i.e. compound symmetry) was used. Based on the importance of soil water content for microbial activity and biomass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>, soil water content was added as an additional explanatory variable to the LMMs (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>, Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). As we were expecting a strong relation between aboveground plant biomass and microbial biomass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>, additional LMMs were used to test the influence of plant biomass on microbial biomass (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). To evaluate model variation explained by fixed and random effects, marginal and conditional R<sup>2</sup> were calculated using the &#x0201c;<italic>MuMIn</italic>&#x0201d; package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>; marginal R<sup>2</sup> represents model variation explained by fixed effects in the final model and conditional R<sup>2</sup> represents model variation explained by both random and fixed effects.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Nematode community indices</title><p id="Par17">LMMs were also used to assess the effects of drought, NPK fertilization, season (spring and summer 2017), and their interactions on nematode indices, i.e. Enrichment Index, Structure Index, Channel Index, and Maturity Index. A random intercept with plots nested within block was included in the models. We accounted for repeated measurements within plots by using a compound symmetry covariance structure, which fitted the data better than a first-order autoregressive covariance structure based on the AIC. To evaluate model variation explained by fixed and random effects, marginal and conditional R<sup>2</sup> were calculated using the &#x0201c;<italic>MuMIn</italic>&#x0201d; package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Soil pH</title><p id="Par18">We also used LMMs to assess the effects of drought, NPK fertilization, and their interaction on soil pH for all seasons in 2017. Additionally, we tested the influence of soil pH on invertebrate feeding activity. A random intercept with blocks nested within season was included in the models. We accounted for repeated measurements within plots by using a compound symmetry covariance structure, which fitted the data better than a first-order autoregressive covariance structure based on the AIC. To evaluate model variation explained by fixed and random effects, marginal and conditional R<sup>2</sup> were calculated using the &#x0201c;<italic>MuMIn</italic>&#x0201d; package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Nematode density, richness, and trophic groups</title><p id="Par19">Generalized mixed-effects models (GLMM) were used to assess the effects of drought, NPK fertilization, season (spring and summer 2017), and their interactions on nematode richness, total density (i.e. total number of individuals in the nematodes community) and the abundance of each trophic group (i.e. percentage of individuals in each trophic group). Nematode richness and total density of nematodes were modelled with Poisson distribution (link&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x0201c;log&#x0201d;), while the trophic groups were modelled with Binomial distribution (link&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x0201c;logit&#x0201d;). The random intercept of the model was structured with plots nested within blocks. To account for over-dispersion, an observation-level random effect was used in the model with omnivorous and predatory nematodes as a response variable.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Nematode functional guilds and cp groups</title><p id="Par20">GLMMs were also used to assess the effects of drought, NPK fertilization, and their interactions on nematode functional guilds and cp-groups (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>) using Binomial distribution (link&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x0201c;logit&#x0201d;). The random intercept of the model was structured with plots nested within blocks, nested within sampling (sampling as a categorical factor). GLMMs were performed using the &#x0201c;<italic>lme4</italic>&#x0201d; package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par21">Model assumptions of the LMMs and the GLMMs were checked by visually inspecting residual plots for homogeneity and quantile-quantile plots for normality (i.e. no correlation between the residuals and the fitted parameters of the model). To meet the assumptions of the model, invertebrate feeding activity and microbial activity were log-transformed (log(x&#x02009;+&#x02009;1)). Figures are based on mixed-effects model fits extracted using the package &#x0201c;<italic>ggeffects</italic>&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. All statistical analyses were conducted using R version 3.4.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Soil microbial responses</title><p id="Par22">Soil microbial activity ranged from 0.7 to 5.1&#x02009;&#x000b5;l O<sub>2</sub> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry weight soil with an average of 1.7&#x02009;&#x000b5;l O<sub>2</sub> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> per g dry weight soil across all measurements. We could not detect a significant effect of the drought or the fertilization treatment on soil microbial activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). However, microbial respiration was significantly affected by season, with lowest activity in summer and highest activity in winter (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). In addition, we found a positive relation between microbial activity and soil water content (F<sub>1, 111</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;170.83, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>) that was independent of the drought and fertilization treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The effects of drought, fertilization, and season on soil microbial variables based on mixed effects model fits for each treatment. (<bold>a</bold>) Combined treatment effects across all seasons and (<bold>b</bold>) seasonal effects on soil microbial activity (log-scaled). (<bold>c</bold>) Combined treatment effects across all seasons and (<bold>d</bold>) seasonal effects on soil microbial biomass. Error bars indicate 95% confidence intervals. Grey&#x02009;=&#x02009;no NPK fertilization; green&#x02009;=&#x02009;NPK fertilization. n.s.&#x02009;=&#x02009;not significant; *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; ***p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36777_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1236"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Results of linear mixed-effects models for the effects of drought, NPK fertilization, season, and their interactions on soil invertebrate feeding activity, soil microbial activity, and soil microbial biomass.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Response Variables</th><th>Drought</th><th>NPK</th><th>Season</th><th>Drought&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;NPK</th><th>Drought&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Season</th><th>NPK&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Season</th><th>Drought&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;NPK&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Season</th><th colspan="2">R&#x000b2; %</th></tr><tr><th>F-value<break/>(1,27)</th><th>F-value<break/>(1,27)</th><th>F-value<break/>(3,108)</th><th>F-value<break/>(1,27)</th><th>F-value<break/>(3,108)</th><th>F-value<break/>(3,108)</th><th>F-value<break/>(3,108)</th><th>Marginal</th><th>Conditional</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Microbial Activity</td><td>0.78</td><td>2.71</td><td>31.02***</td><td>0.02</td><td>1.07</td><td>0.30</td><td>0.28</td><td>37</td><td>49</td></tr><tr><td>Microbial Biomass</td><td>2.25</td><td>35.48***</td><td>3.95*</td><td>0.22</td><td>1.55</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.36</td><td>8.4</td><td>80</td></tr><tr><td>Invertebrate Feeding Activity</td><td>22.65***</td><td>22.60***</td><td>22.78***</td><td>9.17**</td><td>0.19</td><td>0.36</td><td>0.38</td><td>44</td><td>49</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>A random intercept with plots nested within blocks, which were nested within year was added to the model. A compound symmetry covariance structure was used to account for repeated measurements within plots. Marginal R<sup>2</sup>: model variation explained by fixed effects; conditional R<sup>2</sup>: model variation explained by both fixed and random effects. Logarithmic transformations were used for soil invertebrate feeding activity and soil microbial activity. NPK&#x02009;=&#x02009;NPK fertilization. *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; ***p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">Soil microbial biomass ranged from 168.0 to 979.8&#x02009;&#x000b5;g Cmic g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry weight soil with an average of 530.6&#x02009;&#x000b5;g Cmic g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry weight soil across all measurements. Overall, soil microbial biomass increased significantly with NPK fertilization (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). Microbial biomass was also significantly affected by season with lowest biomass in summer and highest biomass in fall (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Furthermore, fertilization and soil water content interactively affected microbial biomass (F<sub>1, 111</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.60, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>); while microbial biomass increased with higher soil water content under ambient conditions, it slightly decreased with higher soil water content on plots with NPK fertilization (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). In addition, soil microbial biomass increased significantly with aboveground plant biomass (F<sub>1, 59</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.81, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.004; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Nematode responses</title><p id="Par24">Neither total nematode density nor richness were significantly affected by any of the experimental treatments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a,b</xref>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>); we could only detect significant differences between spring and summer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7a,b</xref>). Among the nematode trophic groups, only bacteria-feeders were significantly increased by the fertilization treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>), which was mainly due to a significant increase of the r-strategic Ba<sub>1</sub>-nematodes (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.57, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.032; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8a</xref>). In addition, bacteria-feeders were highly abundant in summer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9c</xref>). Plant-feeders were affected by the interactive effects of fertilization and season: while fertilization favoured plant-feeding nematodes in spring, it had a negative effect in summer (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9d</xref>). The combined group of omnivorous and predatory nematodes marginally significantly decreased under drought and NPK fertilization (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>), with a stronger negative effect of fertilization in spring (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9e</xref>). Fungal-feeders were not significantly affected by any of the treatments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f</xref>). A closer look at changes in the nematode community composition revealed that cp2 plant-feeding nematodes increased with drought (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.65, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0099; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10c</xref>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>), whereas nematodes with higher c-p values, in detail Fu<sub>3</sub>-nematodes (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.97, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.026; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10e</xref>), Om<sub>4</sub>-nematodes (marginally; &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.80, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.051; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10g</xref>), cp3 (marginally; &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.74, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.098; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10d</xref>), and cp4-nematodes (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.83, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0051; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10f</xref>) decreased significantly in response to fertilization.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Chi-squared values (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>) of the generalized mixed-effects models for the effects of drought, fertilization, season (spring and summer 2017), and their interaction on soil nematode density and richness using Poisson distribution and percentage of each nematode trophic group using Binomial distribution.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Nematode response variable</th><th>Drought</th><th>NPK</th><th>Season</th><th>Drought&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;NPK</th><th>Drought&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Season</th><th>NPK&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Season</th><th>Drought&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;NPK&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Season</th></tr><tr><th>&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup></th><th>&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup></th><th>&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup></th><th>&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup></th><th>&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup></th><th>&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup></th><th>&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Total Density</td><td>0.51</td><td>2.51</td><td>118.15***</td><td>0.66</td><td>0.80</td><td>0.47</td><td>0.79</td></tr><tr><td>Richness</td><td>0.14</td><td>0.38</td><td>21.47***</td><td>0.13</td><td>0.05</td><td>0.06</td><td>0.01</td></tr><tr><td>Plant-feeders</td><td>0.24</td><td>1.22</td><td>12.53***</td><td>0.53</td><td>3.24<sup>(*)</sup></td><td>11.17***</td><td>1.10</td></tr><tr><td>Fungal-feeders</td><td>1.15</td><td>0.74</td><td>0.57</td><td>0.06</td><td>3.24<sup>(*)</sup></td><td>1.87</td><td>0.61</td></tr><tr><td>Bacteria-feeders</td><td>0.26</td><td>4.76*</td><td>15.64***</td><td>0.71</td><td>2.05</td><td>0.25</td><td>0.95</td></tr><tr><td>Predators/Omnivores</td><td>3.53<sup>(*)</sup></td><td>3.50<sup>(*)</sup></td><td>0.80</td><td>2.16</td><td>1.53</td><td>5.63*</td><td>0.07</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Plots nested within blocks served as a random intercept in the model. NPK&#x02009;=&#x02009;annual NPK fertilization. <sup>(*)</sup>p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1; *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; ***p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The effects of drought and fertilization on nematode response variables based on mixed effects model fits for each treatment. (<bold>a</bold>) Total nematode density per g dry weight soil; (<bold>b</bold>) nematode taxon richness; percentage of (<bold>c</bold>) bacteria-feeding nematodes; (<bold>d</bold>) plant-feeding nematodes; (<bold>e</bold>) fungal-feeding nematodes; and (<bold>f</bold>) predatory- and omnivorous nematodes. Error bars indicate 95% confidence intervals. Grey&#x02009;=&#x02009;no NPK fertilization; green&#x02009;=&#x02009;NPK fertilization. Both seasons (spring and summer 2017) are included (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref> for seasonal effects). n.s.&#x02009;=&#x02009;not significant;&#x000a0;<sup>(*)</sup>p &#x0003c; 0.1; *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36777_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1832"/></fig></p><p id="Par25">While the increase in the Enrichment Index was marginally significant under drought conditions (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>), drought led to a marginally significant decrease of the Structure Index and the Maturity Index (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b,c</xref>). Fertilization increased the importance of the bacterial decomposition channel as indicated by a marginally significant decrease of the Channel Index (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). In addition, fertilization decreased nematode complexity as indicated by a significant decrease of the Structure Index and Maturity Index. (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b,c</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Results of linear mixed effects models for the effects of drought, fertilization, season (spring and summer 2017), and their interaction on soil nematode indices.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Nematode response variable</th><th>Drought</th><th>NPK</th><th>Season</th><th>Drought &#x000d7; NPK</th><th>Drought &#x000d7; Season</th><th>NPK &#x000d7; Season</th><th>Drought &#x000d7; NPK &#x000d7; Season</th><th colspan="2">R&#x000b2; %</th></tr><tr><th>F-value<break/>(1,12)</th><th>F-value<break/>(1,12)</th><th>F-value<break/>(1,16)</th><th>F-value<break/>(1,12)</th><th>F-value<break/>(1,16)</th><th>F-value<break/>(1,16)</th><th>F-value<break/>(1,16)</th><th>Marginal</th><th>Conditional</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Enrichment Index</td><td>3.30<sup>(*)</sup></td><td>0.84</td><td>0.07</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.03</td><td>0.05</td><td>0.17</td><td>9.4</td><td>18</td></tr><tr><td>Structure Index</td><td>4.95<sup>(*)</sup></td><td>6.65*</td><td>0.02</td><td>0.32</td><td>1.70</td><td>0.51</td><td>0.53</td><td>23</td><td>29</td></tr><tr><td>Channel Index</td><td>1.60</td><td>3.98<sup>(*)</sup></td><td>1.42</td><td>0.04</td><td>1.62</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.11</td><td>19</td><td>50</td></tr><tr><td>Maturity Index</td><td>5.07<sup>(*)</sup></td><td>10.18**</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.52</td><td>1.99</td><td>0.21</td><td>0.72</td><td>28</td><td>34</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Plots nested within blocks served as a random intercept in the model. A compound symmetry covariance structure was used to account for repeated measurements within plots. Marginal R<sup>2</sup>: model variation explained by fixed effects; conditional R<sup>2</sup>: model variation explained by both fixed and random effects. NPK&#x02009;=&#x02009;annual NPK fertilization. <sup>(*)</sup>p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1; *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; ***p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The effects of drought and fertilization on soil nematode indices based on mixed effects model fits for each treatment. (<bold>a</bold>) Enrichment Index; (<bold>b</bold>) Structure Index; (<bold>c</bold>) Maturity Index, and (<bold>d</bold>) Channel Index. Error bars indicate 95% confidence intervals. Grey&#x02009;=&#x02009;no NPK fertilization; green&#x02009;=&#x02009;NPK fertilization. Two seasons (spring and summer 2017) were included. <sup>(*)</sup>p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1; *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **p &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36777_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e2109"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Soil invertebrate feeding responses</title><p id="Par26">Mean soil invertebrate feeding activity per plot ranged from 0 to 60% of consumed bait substrate with an average of 11% bait consumption. Feeding activity was significantly affected by an interactive effect of drought x fertilization; overall, fertilization decreased invertebrate feeding activity at ambient precipitation, but had no significant effect under drought conditions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). These treatment effects were consistent across seasons (no treatment x season interaction), however, the level of soil invertebrate feeding activity varied strongly between seasons and tended to be highest in summer and strongly decreased in winter (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The effects of drought, NPK fertilization, and season on soil invertebrate feeding activity (log-scaled) based on mixed-effects model fits for each treatment. (<bold>a</bold>) Combined treatment effects across all seasons and (<bold>b</bold>) seasonal effects. Error bars indicate 95% confidence intervals. Grey&#x02009;=&#x02009;no NPK fertilization; green&#x02009;=&#x02009;NPK fertilization. **p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; ***p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36777_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2138"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Soil pH</title><p id="Par27">Soil pH was significantly reduced by NPK fertilization across all seasons in 2017 (F<sub>1,56</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.11; p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S11a</xref>). In addition, we could show that an decrease in soil pH led to a marginally significant decrease in invertebrate feeding activity across all seasons in 2017 (F<sub>1,58</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.07; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S11b</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par28">We studied the impacts of two major global change drivers, namely drought and fertilization, and their interactive effects on soil communities and functions. By investigating the responses of a wide range of soil organisms across all seasons within a two-year timeframe, we gained a comprehensive picture of how soil ecosystem functions may be altered in a changing world. Intriguingly, we saw vastly different responses among trophic levels that were constant across seasons.</p><p id="Par29">Our first hypothesis, predicting detrimental effects of drought on soil organisms, was confirmed to some extent: drought reduced soil invertebrate feeding activity and led to a more disturbed soil nematode community structure, whereas soil microbial activity and biomass were not significantly affected. The dependency of soil invertebrates on soil moisture content is well documented<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup> as is the fact that soil microfauna is more prone to water stress than bacteria and fungi<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. The detrimental drought effects on faunal activity are thus in line with previous studies, which claim that abiotic conditions shape the performance of the soil faunal community<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. Microarthropods (mites and collembolans), enchytraeids, and earthworms are some of the most relevant groups found in the upper soil layer in temperate regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> and are likely to account for most of the feeding activity leading to bait perforation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>. Extreme drought not only forces them to migrate to deeper soil layers, but also interferes with their reproduction and development success, which is possibly the reason why they are highly susceptible to drought<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup>. Furthermore, drought conditions entail drier food sources for detritivores, which are more difficult to digest<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par30">In line with our expectations, drought was also responsible for (moderate) shifts in nematode indices. The environmental conditions were changed towards an enriched, more disturbed, less structured system, with a higher proportion of opportunistic nematodes. Already at ambient precipitation levels, the guilds of the opportunistic Fu<sub>2</sub>- and Ba<sub>2</sub>-nematodes accounted for the highest shares at our experimental site, indicating a basal food web that is capable to cover a wide ecological amplitude and is already adapted to some environmental stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. The positive response of the Enrichment Index to drought suggests mortality at higher trophic levels, which subsequently promoted nutrient enrichment and gave further rise to opportunistic nematodes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Thus, overall, drought led to simplified trophic structures of the nematode community.</p><p id="Par31">In contrast to our initial hypothesis, soil microbial activity and biomass were not affected by the drought treatment. This was unexpected given the intensity of the drought treatment applied in the experiment (precipitation was reduced by 55% during the entire study period) and the fact that most soil microbes are strongly dependent on soil moisture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>. However, this finding is in line with Pailler <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>, who also found little soil microbial functional responses to drought. In addition, we observed distinct variation of microbial activity and biomass across seasons and could reveal that soil water content explained a significant proportion of the variability in microbial activity, yet irrespective of the treatments. Notably, soil water content itself was strongly varying among seasons (more than in response to the drought treatment; Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>). This suggests that microorganisms residing in the top soil are in general highly dependent on soil moisture levels, which are fluctuating across the year. Therefore, they must be able to sustain drought periods, for instance, through physiological modifications. Such adaptations may comprise an adjustment of internal water potential, sporulation, or production of exopolysaccharides that provide protection against exsiccation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup>. This provides evidence that temporal environmental variability is a strong predictor of species activity and emphasizes the dependency of soil organisms on seasonal patterns<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref></sup>. We therefore infer that seasonal fluctuations in natural precipitation at our site (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>) may have led to acclimatization of the microbial communities to natural drought periods as they are part of their climatic history<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>. We speculate that this may explain the negligible responses to the experimentally induced drought, which may still be within the adaptive range of the community (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>).</p><p id="Par32">The responses of soil biota were again ambiguous with regard to our second hypothesis, in which we expected fertilization to promote the activity of soil biota. Consistent with our hypothesis, soil microbial biomass increased under fertilization. Soil invertebrate feeding activity, however, substantially declined under elevated nutrient supply, questioning the universal validity of our initial hypothesis. Notably, in a recent meta-analysis, Yian <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref></sup> reported negative effects of nitrogen fertilization on soil microbial biomass, which may be attributable to changes in the community composition, but this requires further investigation, because microbe-mediated activity markers were, on the other hand, increased. The pronounced responsiveness of soil microbial biomass to NPK fertilization that we found in our study is in line with similar studies reporting positive effects of nitrogen fertilization on microbial biomass and changes in microbial community structure and function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref></sup>. Fertilization certainly enhanced nutrient availability, resulting in higher yields of aboveground plant biomass (Berger <italic>et al</italic>., in prep.), which is often accompanied by an expanded root system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Subsequently, this increases the release of organic compounds into the soil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref></sup>, providing substrates that support the growth of microbial communities towards higher population densities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par33">Also nematode indices were highly responsive to NPK fertilization, resulting in a less structured and more disturbed system with an enhanced bacteria-driven decomposition pathway. The latter was additionally supported by a strong increase in bacteria-feeding nematodes (especially Ba<sub>1</sub>) and an equally strong decrease in fungal-feeding nematodes (Fu<sub>3</sub>) under fertilization, indicating that fertilization had detrimental effects on soil fungi. This is in line with the general notion that fertilization favours bacteria-dominated decomposition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref></sup>. The simplification of the nutrient-enriched soil food web is also reflected by declines of the omnivorous nematodes (Om<sub>4</sub>) and the cp3 and cp4 nematodes, which consist of long-living, pollutant sensitive, rather immobile organisms that are prone to environmental stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. When linking these changes reported for the nematode indices to the responses of the microbial community, our results suggest that fertilization promoted the growth of bacteria, which then accounted for a strong increase in microbial biomass. As a result, this restructuring of the microbial community may thus have provided the basis for the observed increase in bacteria-feeding nematodes and some of the shifts in nematode indices.</p><p id="Par34">Current evidence for soil invertebrate responses to fertilization is equivocal. Several studies reported an enhancing effect of fertilization on soil invertebrate activity and diversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref></sup>, whereas others revealed no such effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref></sup>, or recorded declines in soil fauna abundances and diversity after fertilizer application<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Most likely, the diminished feeding activity of soil invertebrates can be explained by alterations of soil physicochemical properties. In our study, we found that fertilization decreased soil pH, which can serve as one potential explanation of the reported decline of invertebrate feeding activity. This is in line with previous studies showing that reduced soil pH as a result of mineral fertilization was negatively correlated with the abundance of most soil invertebrates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref></sup>. Especially earthworms, which represent a significant part of soil invertebrate biomass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref></sup>, are known to decline noticeably in numbers under reduced soil pH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref></sup>. Overall, environmental constraints, such as altered energy channels, simplified food web structures, and reduced soil pH outweighed potential positive bottom-up effects through enhanced plant growth, which we expected to find.</p><p id="Par35">Prior studies emphasized the importance of interactive effects of global change drivers as they will profoundly alter ecosystem functions and services<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref></sup>. Accordingly, our third hypothesis predicted fertilization to reinforce drought effects, resulting in reduced soil water content and thus aggravated living conditions for soil organisms. Indeed, drought and fertilization interacted significantly in restraining soil invertebrate feeding activity, partially supporting our hypothesis. However, as discussed above, fertilization obviously created an unfavourable environment for most soil invertebrates at our site. Although both global change drivers individually decreased soil invertebrate feeding activity, the interaction, however, did not result in further declines. We therefore conclude that the combined effects may have led to a distinct restructuring of the soil faunal community by promoting species better adapted to adverse conditions, and thus revealing no measurable change in net effects. Since the combined global change drivers are likely to modify aboveground plant communities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref></sup>, alterations in the quality of aboveground litter inputs can be expected. Leaf litter quality, in turn, affects soil fauna and might therefore be responsible for reshaping the faunal community<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref></sup>. With the methods applied in our study, however, we can only speculate about potential changes in the soil faunal community composition. This highlights the need for future research to detect which specific groups are responsible for bait perforation. This could be done, for instance, by exposing bait lamina strips with a labelled substrate under controlled laboratory conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref></sup>. Building on that, the abundances of the most important groups of soil organisms could be monitored in the field, while being exposed to different global change drivers.</p><p id="Par36">In contrast to the invertebrate feeding activity, microbial activity was not significantly affected by the interaction of the two global change drivers. Moreover, we could not detect any interactive effects on nematode indices or nematode groups. This illustrates the robustness of a large portion of the soil community to interactive global change effects, which might therefore be able to buffer prospective global change effects to a certain extent.</p><p id="Par37">In conclusion, the main groups of soil organisms investigated in the present study responded differently to the individual and interacting effects of global change drivers. Soil invertebrate activity was strongly impaired by both global change drivers and their interaction, while microbial biomass benefited from enhanced nutrient availability, and microbial activity was surprisingly unaffected by all treatments. Despite the strong seasonal dynamics of temperate regions, these treatment effects remained constant across all seasons within two years. Notably, nematode indices pointed to changes in the state of the ecosystem, shifting towards simplified and more disturbed systems under drought and especially under fertilization that mostly facilitated opportunistic species. We could show that soil biota differ considerably in their sensitivity to global change drivers and in their seasonal dynamics &#x02013; also highlighting the importance of integrating seasonal effects into experimental frameworks. This may lead to far-reaching alterations of crucial ecosystem processes, since decomposition and nutrient cycling are driven by the interdependent concurrence of soil microbial and faunal activities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. By covering a range of different taxonomic and trophic levels of soil organisms, we could therefore show that single as well interacting global change drivers induce complex changes in soil food webs and functions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec22"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_36777_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Julia Siebert and Marie S&#x000fc;nnemann contributed equally.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-36777-3.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the staff of the Bad Lauchst&#x000e4;dt Experimental Research Station for their help in maintaining the experimental site, and Alla Kavtea, Tom K&#x000fc;nne, and Ulrich Pruschitzki for their support with lab and field work. Furthermore, we thank the coordination of the International Drought-Net Experiment for providing protocols and support. Financial support came from the German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research Halle&#x02013;Jena&#x02013;Leipzig, funded by the German Research Foundation (FZT 118).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>N.E. conceived the study. J.S. and M.S. collected the data on soil microbes and invertebrates, M.C. identified the nematodes and computed nematode indices, H.A. and S.B. provided plant data. J.S. and N.R.G. analysed the data. J.S. wrote the manuscript with contributions from N.E., M.S., H.A., S.B., S.C., M.C. and N.R.G.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The datasets analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vitousek</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond global warming: ecology and global change</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1994</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1861</fpage><lpage>1876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1941591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Steffen, W. <italic>et al</italic>. <italic>Global change and the earth system: a planet under pressure</italic>. (Springer Science &#x00026; Business Media, 2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IPCC, T. P. S. B. 2007. <italic>Climate Change 2007. The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fourth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</italic> [<italic>Solomon, S., D. Qin, M.o Manning, Z. Chen, M. Marquis, K.B. Averyt, M. Tignor and H.L. Miller (eds)</italic>]. Vol. 4 (Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA., 2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transformation of the nitrogen cycle: recent trends, questions, and potential solutions</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1136674</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18487183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18487183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lamarque, J. F. <italic>et al</italic>. Assessing future nitrogen deposition and carbon cycle feedback using a multimodel approach: Analysis of nitrogen deposition. <italic>Journal of Geophysical Research: Atmospheres</italic><bold>110</bold> (2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Significant contribution of combustion-related emissions to the atmospheric phosphorus budget</article-title><source>Nature Geoscience</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>48</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ngeo2324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenhauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cesarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Worm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global change belowground: impacts of elevated CO2, nitrogen, and summer drought on soil food webs and biodiversity</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2011.02555.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Vries</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Land use alters the resistance and resilience of soil food webs to drought</article-title><source>Nature Climate Change</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate1368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bardgett</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Putten</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Belowground biodiversity and ecosystem functioning</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2014</year><volume>515</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13855</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25428498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25428498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brussaard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decomposition and nitrogen mineralization in natural and agroecosystems: the contribution of soil animals</article-title><source>Biogeochemistry</source><year>1990</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00004496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between soil respiration and soil moisture</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>1983</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0038-0717(83)90010-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldrian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Merhautov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Petr&#x000e1;nkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cajthaml</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;najdr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of microbial biomass and activity of extracellular enzymes in a hardwood forest soil reflect soil moisture content</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2010.08.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riutta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Clack</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Crockatt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Landscape-scale implications of the edge effect on soil fauna activity in a temperate forest</article-title><source>Ecosystems</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>534</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10021-015-9939-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blankinship</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Niklaus</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hungate</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A meta-analysis of responses of soil biota to global change</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2011</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-011-1909-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21274573?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21274573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hueso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe drought conditions modify the microbial community structure, size and activity in amended and unamended soils</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>2012</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2012.03.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Engtsson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of experimental irrigation and drought on the composition and diversity of soil fauna in a coniferous stand</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source><year>2002</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2664.2002.00769.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cesarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nematode functional guilds, not trophic groups, reflect shifts in soil food webs and processes in response to interacting global change factors</article-title><source>Pedobiologia</source><year>2015</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedobi.2015.01.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kardol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cregger</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Campany</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Classen</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil ecosystem functioning under climate change: plant species and community effects</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>767</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/09-0135.1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20426335?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20426335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galantini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term fertilization effects on soil organic matter quality and dynamics under different production systems in semiarid Pampean soils</article-title><source>Soil and Tillage Research</source><year>2006</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.still.2005.02.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term effect of chemical fertilizer, straw, and manure on soil chemical and biological properties in northwest China</article-title><source>Geoderma</source><year>2010</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2010.04.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marinari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Masciandaro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceccanti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grego</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of organic and mineral fertilisers on soil biological and physical properties</article-title><source>Bioresource Technology</source><year>2000</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-8524(99)00094-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of long-term N, P, K, and NPK fertilization on the composition and potential functions of the bacterial community in grassland soil</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiology Ecology</source><year>2014</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6941.12384</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25046442?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25046442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treseder</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen additions and microbial biomass: A meta&#x02010;analysis of ecosystem studies</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1111</fpage><lpage>1120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2008.01230.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18673384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18673384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Craine</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fierer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen fertilization inhibits soil microbial respiration regardless of the form of nitrogen applied</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>2336</fpage><lpage>2338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2010.08.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bacterial community structure and diversity in a black soil as affected by long-term fertilization</article-title><source>Pedosphere</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>582</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1002-0160(08)60052-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of nitrogen and phosphorus fertilization on soil carbon fractions in alpine meadows on the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau</article-title><source>PLOS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e103266</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103266</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25075624?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25075624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Responses of soil nematodes to water and nitrogen additions in an old-field grassland</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>2016</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2016.02.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gardi, C., Menta, C., Montanarella, L. &#x00026; Cenci, R. Main threats on soil biodiversity: The case of agricultural activities impacts on soil microarthropods. <italic>Threats to Soil Quality in Europe</italic>, 101&#x02013;112 (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fertilizer regime impacts on abundance and diversity of soil fauna across a poplar plantation chronosequence in coastal Eastern China</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>20816</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep20816</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26857390?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26857390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anthropogenic nitrogen deposition predicts local grassland primary production worldwide</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2015</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/14-1902.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaver</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A global perspective on belowground carbon dynamics under nitrogen enrichment</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2010.01482.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20482580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20482580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rice rhizodeposition and its utilization by microbial groups depends on N fertilization</article-title><source>Biology and Fertility of Soils</source><year>2017</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00374-016-1155-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wichern</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberhardt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Joergensen</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen rhizodeposition in agricultural crops: methods, estimates and future prospects</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2007.08.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sjursen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Michelsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonasson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of long-term soil warming and fertilisation on microarthropod abundances in three sub-arctic ecosystems</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>2005</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2005.02.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craven</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plant diversity effects on grassland productivity are robust to both nutrient enrichment and drought</article-title><source>Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</source><year>2016</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>20150277</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2015.0277</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27114579?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27114579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borer</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Finding generality in ecology: a model for globally distributed experiments</article-title><source>Methods in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210X.12125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chernozem&#x02014;Soil of the Year 2005</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Nutrition and Soil Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jpln.200521814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheffield</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dukes</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terrestrial Precipitation Analysis (TPA): A resource for characterizing long&#x02010;term precipitation regimes and extremes</article-title><source>Methods in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1396</fpage><lpage>1401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210X.12582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yahdjian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rainout shelter design for intercepting different amounts of rainfall</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2002</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-002-1024-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28547315?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28547315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gherardi</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated rainfall manipulation system: a reliable and inexpensive tool for ecologists</article-title><source>Ecosphere</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/ES12-00371.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Separating drought effects from roof artifacts on ecosystem processes in a grassland drought experiment</article-title><source>PLOS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e70997</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0070997</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23936480?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23936480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kratz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The bait-lamina test</article-title><source>Environmental Science and Pollution Research</source><year>1998</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02986394</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19005818?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19005818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Soil biodiversity monitoring in Europe: ongoing activities and challenges</article-title><source>European Journal of Soil Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2389.2009.01177.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schellenberg</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the &#x0201c;bait-lamina test&#x0201d; to assess soil microfauna feeding activity in mixed grassland</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>2007</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2007.02.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ro&#x0017c;en</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobczyk</surname><given-names>&#x00141;</given-names></name><name><surname>Liszka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil faunal activity as measured by the bait-lamina test in monocultures of 14 tree species in the Siemianice common-garden experiment, Poland</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2010.03.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Riutta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting soil fauna feeding activity in a fragmented lowland temperate deciduous woodland</article-title><source>PLOS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e29616</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029616</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22235311?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22235311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduced feeding activity of soil detritivores under warmer and drier conditions</article-title><source>Nature Climate Change</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41558-017-0032-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29375673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29375673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated measurement of the respiratory response of soil microcompartments: active microbial biomass in earthworm faeces</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>1992</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>1118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0038-0717(92)90061-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Domsch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A physiological method for the quantitative measurement of microbial biomass in soils</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>1978</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0038-0717(78)90099-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruess</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the nematode fauna of an acid forest soil: spatial distribution and extraction</article-title><source>Nematologica</source><year>1995</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/003925995X00198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bongers, T. The Nematodes of the Netherlands. <italic>The Nematodes of the Netherlands</italic>. (1988).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>De Goede</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Freckman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgieva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feeding habits in soil nematode families and genera&#x02014;an outline for soil ecologists</article-title><source>Journal of Nematology</source><year>1993</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>315</fpage><?supplied-pmid 19279775?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19279775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadota</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal-feeding habits of six nematode isolates in the genus Filenchus</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>1120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2004.11.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bongers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nematode community structure as a bioindicator in environmental monitoring</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology &#x00026; Evolution</source><year>1999</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(98)01583-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10354624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bongers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The maturity index: an ecological measure of environmental disturbance based on nematode species composition</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1990</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00324627</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28313236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28313236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bongers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional diversity of nematodes</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0929-1393(98)00123-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>De Goede</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A framework for soil food web diagnostics: extension of the nematode faunal analysis concept</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>2001</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0929-1393(01)00152-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pinheiro, J., Bates, D., DebRoy, S., Sarkar, D. &#x00026; Team, R. C. Nlme: Linear and nonlinear mixed effects models (R package version 3.1&#x02013;128, 2016). <italic>R Software</italic> (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Norby</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weltzin</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responses of soil respiration to elevated CO2, air warming, and changing soil water availability in a model old&#x02010;field grassland</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2411</fpage><lpage>2424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2007.01433.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Triplett</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial communities and their interactions in soil and rhizosphere ecosystems</article-title><source>Annual Reviews in Microbiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.micro.56.012302.161120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barton, K. Package &#x02018;MuMIn&#x02019;. R package version 1.40. 4. (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bates, D., M&#x000e4;chler, M., Bolker, B. &#x00026; Walker, S. Fitting linear mixed-effects models usinglme4. <italic>ArXiv preprint arXiv:1406.5823</italic> (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">L&#x000fc;decke, D. Ggeffects: Create Tidy Data Frames of Marginal Effects for ggplot (Version 0.3.4). <italic>R Software</italic> (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team, R. C. T. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. Vienna, Austria; 2014 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Coleman, D. C., Crossley, D. A. Jr. &#x00026; Hendrix, P. F. <italic>Fundamentals of Soil Ecology</italic>. (Academic press, 2004).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manzoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schimel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Porporato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responses of soil microbial communities to water stress: results from a meta&#x02010;analysis</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2012</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>930</fpage><lpage>938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/11-0026.1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22690643?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22690643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>MJI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ineson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Piearce</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of climate change on soil fauna; responses of enchytraeids, Diptera larvae and tardigrades in a transplant experiment</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0929-1393(97)00004-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gongalsky</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pokarzhevskii</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of soil temperature and moisture on the feeding activity of soil animals as determined by the bait-lamina test</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>2008</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2007.11.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Larink</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of feeding activity of collembolan and enchytraeid in laboratory studies using the bait-lamina test</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0929-1393(97)00065-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frampton</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Brink</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of spring drought and irrigation on farmland arthropods in southern Britain</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source><year>2000</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>883</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2664.2000.00541.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maraldo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmstrup</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enchytraeids in a changing climate: a mini-review</article-title><source>Pedobiologia</source><year>2010</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedobi.2009.10.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siepel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity of soil microarthropods: the filtering of species</article-title><source>Biodiversity &#x00026; Conservation</source><year>1996</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00055834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wever</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lysyk</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapperton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of soil moisture and temperature on the survival, aestivation, growth and development of juvenile Aporrectodea tuberculata (Eisen)(Lumbricidae)</article-title><source>Pedobiologia</source><year>2001</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1078/0031-4056-00074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Donnell</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological and community responses of established grassland bacterial populations to water stress</article-title><source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>6961</fpage><lpage>6968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.12.6961-6968.2003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14660337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14660337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pailler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vennetier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiral</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forest soil microbial functional patterns and response to a drought and warming event: Key role of climate&#x02013;plant&#x02013;soil interactions at a regional scale</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>2014</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2013.12.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Harris, R. Effect of water potential on microbial growth and activity. <italic>Water Potential Relations in Soil Microbiology</italic>, 23&#x02013;95 (1981).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberson</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Firestone</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between desiccation and exopolysaccharide production in a soil Pseudomonas sp</article-title><source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source><year>1992</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1284</fpage><lpage>1291</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16348695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16348695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Responses of soil respiration to elevated carbon dioxide and nitrogen addition in young subtropical forest ecosystems in China</article-title><source>Biogeosciences</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/bg-7-315-2010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Germino</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Feris</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial community responses to 17 years of altered precipitation are seasonally dependent and coupled to co-varying effects of water content on vegetation and soil C</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>2013</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2013.04.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tonkin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rios&#x02010;Touma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lytle</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonality and predictability shape temporal species diversity</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2017</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ecy.1761</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28144975?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28144975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cruz-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Despite strong seasonal responses, soil microbial consortia are more resilient to long-term changes in rainfall than overlying grassland</article-title><source>The ISME Journal</source><year>2009</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>738</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2009.16</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19279669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19279669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waldrop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Firestone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal dynamics of microbial community composition and function in oak canopy and open grassland soils</article-title><source>Microbial Ecology</source><year>2006</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-006-9100-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16909344?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16909344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Soil extracellular enzyme activities, soil carbon and nitrogen storage under nitrogen fertilization: A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>2016</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2016.07.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Polson</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuur</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of nutrient deposition on bacterial communities in Arctic tundra soil</article-title><source>Environmental Microbiology</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1842</fpage><lpage>1854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2010.02189.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20236166?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20236166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cusack</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Torn</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Firestone</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in microbial community characteristics and soil organic matter with nitrogen additions in two tropical forests</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2011</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/10-0459.1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21608471?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21608471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bais</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilroy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivanco</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of root exudates in rhizosphere interactions with plants and other organisms</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.57.032905.105159</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16669762?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16669762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dual importance of competition and predation as regulatory forces in terrestrial ecosystems: evidence from decomposer food-webs</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1993</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00317685</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28313621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28313621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graenitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of fertilization and crop rotation on biological activity in a 90 year long-term experiment</article-title><source>Bodenkultur-wien and munchen-</source><year>2000</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>106</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van der Wal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dissimilar response of plant and soil biota communities to long-term nutrient addition in grasslands</article-title><source>Biology and Fertility of Soils</source><year>2009</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00374-009-0371-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maraun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Indirect effects of carbon and nutrient amendments on the soil meso-and microfauna of a beechwood</article-title><source>Biology and Fertility of Soils</source><year>2001</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>229</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kofuji</surname><given-names>R-I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of soil pH gradient caused by stemflow acidification on soil microarthropod community structure in a Japanese red cedar plantation: an evaluation of ecological risk on decomposition</article-title><source>Journal of Forest Research</source><year>2000</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02762395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responses of soil microarthropods to inorganic and organic fertilizers in a poplar plantation in a coastal area of eastern China</article-title><source>Applied Soil Ecology</source><year>2015</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2015.01.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fierer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liptzin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global patterns in belowground communities</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2009</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1238</fpage><lpage>1249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2009.01360.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19674041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19674041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gudleifsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of long term use of fertilizer on surface invertebrates in experimental plots in a permanent hayfield in Northern-Iceland</article-title><source>Agric. Soc. Iceland</source><year>2002</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interactive effects of global change factors on soil respiration and its components: a meta&#x02010;analysis</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>3157</fpage><lpage>3169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.13253</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26896336?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26896336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Osenberg</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fertilization effects on species density and primary productivity in herbaceous plant communities</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>2000</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0706.2000.890302.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bobbink</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global assessment of nitrogen deposition effects on terrestrial plant diversity: a synthesis</article-title><source>Ecological Applications</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/08-1140.1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20349829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20349829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thuiller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavorel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change threats to plant diversity in Europe</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>8245</fpage><lpage>8250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0409902102</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15919825?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15919825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Legacies of plant litter on carbon and nitrogen dynamics and the role of the soil community</article-title><source>Pedobiologia</source><year>2012</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedobi.2012.02.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornwell</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plant species traits are the predominant control on litter decomposition rates within biomes worldwide</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1065</fpage><lpage>1071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2008.01219.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18627410?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18627410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bol</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleep</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampedro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatio-temporal variation of stable isotope ratios in earthworms under grassland and maize cropping systems</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>2001</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1673</fpage><lpage>1682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0038-0717(01)00088-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyckmans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scrimgeour</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple and rapid method for labelling earthworms with 15N and 13C</article-title><source>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2004.10.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>